<div id="p003r_3" categories="varnish" continued="yes">

<head><m>Thick varnish</m> for planks</head>

<ab>There is a <m>varnish</m> that takes a long time to dry &amp;
drips more than two <tmp>months</tmp> after it has been applied to the
planks. But this one does not drip like that of <tmp>times
past</tmp>, which was made of <m>linseed oil</m>, <m>garlic</m> boiled in it
to extinguish it &amp; rid it of grease, 
&amp; with <m>wheat</m>. And this one yellowed &amp;
rendered greenish the blue color of paintings. This one is made like the
other one except that one puts <m>coarse common turpentine</m></ab>

</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p003r_3" categories="varnish">



<ab>instead of <m>fine turpentine</m>. And you can put into two
<ms>lb</ms> of <del><fr>tou</fr></del> <m>common turpentine</m> one <ms>lb</ms>
of <m>fine turpentine oil</m> &amp; do everything as with the other one. This one
will cost you no more than five or six <cn>sous</cn> per
<ms>lb</ms> &amp; is sold for 40 <cn>sous</cn> per
<ms>lb</ms>.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p003v_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5ZUY4SkZBblA5MjA">



</figure>

<ab>This <tl>vessel</tl> is for making large quantities of
<m>turpentine oil</m>, that is to say a <ms><ms>bucket</ms> an
<tmp>hour</tmp></ms>, and no matter which <m>turpentine it may be,
whether fine or crude</m>. One needs to give, as you know, a little
fire at the beginning and always keep <m>cold water</m> in the cooler
on the top. The <ms>lb</ms> is sold at xii <cn>sous</cn>, &amp;
at the bottom of the <tl>vessel</tl> remains the <m>colophony</m>, or
<m><la>pix græca</la></m>.<comment rid="c_003v_01"/> In this <tl>vessel</tl>, <m>eau-de-vie</m> is also made well,
and there is no need to distill it again. You
do not need a <tl>oven</tl> for this <tl><m>copper</m> vessel</tl>, but
only <m>charcoal</m> around it if it has a flat bottom, but if it is
round, you will place it on a <tl>trivet</tl>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

 It is better to heat the <m>varnish</m> a little bit, rather than to
put it out <env>in the sun</env>, because this makes the panel
<po>warp</po>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

 Some say it is not good to distil in this <tl><m>copper</m>
vessel</tl> because it makes things green. However, when <m>tinned</m>, it is
good.</ab>

</div>