<div id="p021r_2" categories="arms and armor;practical optics" continued="yes">


<head>For firing a <wp>cannon</wp> at night</head>

<ab>Some keep their <wp>pieces</wp> loaded <del>and</del> from the day. Then, in
order that the <pro>gunner</pro> can fire into the breach where the
assailed are perhaps making repairs, the besiegers raise a false alarm
in order that the besieged throw <tl>torches</tl> &amp; <tl>artificial
fire</tl> into the moats or around the breach, at which the
<pro>gunner</pro> aims. Sometimes, by using the reflection of
<tl>mirrors</tl> or <tl>flasks</tl> full of <m>water</m>, the assailants
light up the breach. The method you know, with a <tl>quadrant</tl> &amp;
<tl><m>plumb</m> line</tl>, is very good. Others nail two or three rows
of boards with <m>strong iron pegs</m> on the <m>wooden</m> platform
made for mounting the <wp>cannon</wp>, and leave empty notches into which the
wheels of the <wp>cannon</wp> can just fit. And by such means you will always
<del><fr>te</fr></del> place it at a similar <del><fr>q</fr></del>
point, that it will not incline more to the right than to the left. And
in order that it be neither too high nor too low, when you fire during
the day, you place a <tl>ruler</tl> fixed well in the ground, which
comes just to touch the the bottom of the edge of the <wp>cannon</wp> after it
has been pointed &amp; adjusted for firing.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">If the
platform, the wheels, or the
wedges break or are disturbed, this
invention is of no profit.</ab>


</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p021r_2" categories="arms and armor;practical optics">



<ab>Others place two poles fixed well into
the earth such that one is <del>equally</del> as far from the edge
<del>and</del>of<comment rid="c_021v_03"/> <add>the</add> muzzle of the 
<wp>cannon</wp> as the other. And underneath they place the above-mentioned
<tl>ruler</tl>. Then when they want to fire at
night, they push their <wp>cannon</wp> straight toward the above-mentioned
<tl>ruler</tl> &amp; make it so that the edge of the mouth rests on the
end of the aforesaid <tl>ruler</tl>. Next, they measure with a
<tl>ruler</tl> or similar thing cut to measure, from one pole to the
side of the <wp>cannon</wp> &amp; if it is too close or too far from it, they
adjust it &amp; do thus from the side of the other pole.</ab></div>