<div id="p094r_1" categories="arms and armor" continued="yes">

<head><pro>Furbisher</pro></head>

<ab>The parts of a sword are <add>the rivet</add>,
the tail of the sword, what comes next is the ricasso, the rest is
the <del><fr>c</fr></del>blade. The sides are the edge
&amp; the point. Some blades have a sharp ridge<del><fr>r</fr></del>,<comment rid="c_094r_03"/>
which has one single elevated ridge in the middle &amp; along the whole
length, and are easy to break.<comment rid="c_094r_05"/> The other
<df>blades</df> are called of three edges or three slopes, which do have
a rise in the middle, but it is flat as if it were a sharp ridge, but
flattened,<comment rid="c_094r_06"/> and <del><fr>s</fr></del> these
ones are the safest. The others <del>are</del> are called fluted, which
are notched in the middle,<comment rid="c_094r_07"/> &amp; when it is
along the whole length, they are just as easy to break as those with
sharp ridges &amp; are more troublesome to furbish because the
<tl><fr>fustée</fr></tl> cannot get in. But one makes one in particular which is
narrow.</ab>

<ab>Of the guard<comment rid="c_094r_08"/> of the sword are the
pommel, the branches of the guard &amp; the
<df><fr>pontet</fr></df>,<comment rid="c_094r_11"/> which is this
<m>iron</m> strip which closes off the branch which is at the end of the
ricasso to stop thrusts from sliding into the guard. The
<df>rings</df><comment rid="c_094r_10"/> are these two branches in
half-round which start from the eye<comment rid="c_094r_11"/> of the
guard up to the branch of the <fr>pontet</fr>. The branch that crosses
the guard is called the <df>body</df>. And this
quillon block,<comment rid="c_018v_02"/> by which the sword
tail<comment rid="c_094r_13"/> enters and to which all the branches
return &amp; are held, is called the <df>eye of the guard</df>.</ab>

<ab>Then follows the <m>wood</m> of the grip, which one <m>glues</m>, or
according to the most competent, with <m>gummed wax</m>,<comment rid="c_094r_04"/> which is of
<m>wax</m> &amp; <m>pitch</m>, because <m>rosin</m> would be too hard.
They heat it lightly, then rub the <m>wood</m> of the grip with it in
order that the tang or the <m>thread</m> takes hold there. Otherwise, if a
<m>thread</m> were to come loose, it would all <del><fr>d</fr></del>
break immediately. On <tl><m>iron wire</m></tl> or <tl><m><al>dog</al>
skin</m></tl>,<comment rid="c_094r_14"/> one also puts <m>glue</m> on
it. The garnishment <del>of</del> which is put on the <m>wood</m>
<del>of</del>, which is of <m>silk</m> or <m>thread</m>, is called the
<df>cord</df>, which is made from two <del>thr</del> or three
<m>threads</m> <del>turned</del> twisted on the <tl>spinning wheel</tl>,
or 4 if the <m>silk</m> is thin. The slightly thicker cord holds better.
The binding, which is also made of <m>silk</m> at both ends of the
handle, are called the
<df>buttons</df>.<comment rid="c_094r_15"/></ab>

<ab>Some grips are made of <m>silk</m>, <m><al>dogfish</al>
skin</m>, <m>annealed iron wire</m>,
<m>threads of gold &amp; of fine &amp; false silve</m>r &amp; of
<m>velvet</m>. <m>Iron wire</m> has a lower price &amp; is the most
durable. Next is the grip of <m>silk</m>, if one does not have the
convenience of being close to the <env>sea</env> to procure some
<m><al>dog</al> skin</m>, which is quite
convenient. <del>To</del> The beautiful <m>skin</m> costs fifty or lx
<ms><cn>sous</cn></ms> &amp; 4 or five <ms>dozen</ms> grips are
made from it. This kind gives a good grip even if the <bp>hand</bp> is
<bp>sweating</bp>. To work it, if it is too hard, one soaks it for one
or two <ms><tmp>hours</tmp></ms> in <m>not quite lukewarm
aquafortis</m>, for if it were too hot, it would cook &amp; spoil the
<m>skin</m>. It is sewn with <m>black thread</m>.</ab>

    <ab margin="left-middle"><figure size="small" id="fig_p094r_1" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5YTlFNHRBSVRrOEU">
</figure><comment rid="c_094r_09"/></ab>


</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p094r_1" categories="arms and armor" continued="yes">



<ab>The <m>gold</m> grips are made by putting underneath <m>thin yellow
canvas</m> or a different <m>canvas yellowed with chalk</m>. And this
<m>canvas</m> is set with <m>glue</m> or the aforesaid <m>gum</m>, this
is in order that the <m>thread</m> holds better on it. These are made of
cords like the <m>silk</m> ones, &amp; between two cords one sets one or
two <m>threads</m> to make it show up better. The <m>silver</m> kind is
made similarly, and there is not as much trouble as with <m>silk</m>,
and even less because it takes more to twist <m>silk</m>, because one
needs to twist it twice. A grip of <m>fine gold</m> is worth 18 or 20
<ms><cn>sous</cn></ms>.</ab>

<ab>The best sword point is the <m><pa>sage</pa> leaf</m> form.</ab>

<ab>This long plank on which the sword is attached &amp; laid down to
furbish it is called the
<tl><df><fr>chameau</fr></df></tl>, it is
commonly of <m><pa>rowan</pa>,</m><comment rid="c_094v_05"/> which is
hard &amp; even.</ab>

<ab>The lower stick, which is folded like a bow, is called the
<tl><df><fr>arson</fr></df></tl>.</ab>

<ab>The upper is called the <tl><df>stick of the
<fr>fustée</fr></df></tl>.</ab>

<ab>And this small square piece, which is pu<del><ill/></del>t
<del><fr>l</fr></del>on the sword to burnish it, is called the
<tl><df><fr>fustée</fr></df></tl>.</ab>

<ab>There are two horns: one is called the <df><tl><m>oil</m> horn</tl></df> and
the other the <df><tl><m>emery</m> horn</tl>.</df><comment rid="c_094v_06"/>
</ab>

<ab>There is an <m>iron</m> which is made like a <tl>halberd point</tl>,
square, &amp; of <m>very even steel, &amp; well <tl>filed</tl></m>,
which is called the
<tl><df><fr>grateau</fr></df></tl>,<comment rid="c_094v_07"/> which
serves to <corr><del>to</del></corr> soften the traces of the
<tl>file</tl> on sword guards &amp; to give an edge to swords after they
have been ground, which is better than with a <tl><m>stone</m></tl> or a
<tl><m>sharpening stone</m></tl>, which quite often makes scratches.</ab>

<ab>To make <del><fr>coupp</fr></del> swords cut better, one gives them
the edge by pulling upward from the point.</ab>

<ab><pro>Those who create sword guards</pro> are <pro>artisans</pro>
separate from the <pro>furbisher</pro>.</ab>

<ab> A is the
<fr>bruisson</fr><comment rid="c_094v_08"/><lb/>

B is the <m>bloodstone</m><comment rid="c_094v_09"/></ab>

<ab>The <tl><df><fr>fustée</fr></df></tl> is a square piece of wood
three <ms><bp>fingers</bp> in thickness</ms>, of
<m><pa>boxwood</pa></m>, which is fitted in the middle of the stick
<add>of the <tl>fustée</tl> to furbish</add>.</ab>

<ab>The <tl><m><fr>fresil</fr></m> stick</tl> is of <m><pa>willow</pa>
wood</m>, which is to clean the rust off weapons with
<df><m><fr>fresil</fr></m></df>, which is the <m>iron scale</m> falling
at the <tl><pro>farriers</pro>’ forge</tl>.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p094v_1" margin="left-top" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Q29MTEVLUGE5RGs">





<caption><tl>scabbard bench</tl></caption>

</figure>
<figure id="fig_p094v_2" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5OEQ3OEFSNnEzeE0">





</figure>

<ab margin="left-middle">

    <figure size="small" id="fig_p094v_8" link="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1Hsga43MIuoLIOrj7I5IKQCRAEEXW75uv"/>
    <figure size="small" id="fig_p094v_4" link="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1cE1kYyCx4GXgsYAIEb9Mp1ppcOGYyK_m"><caption>a</caption></figure>
    <figure size="small" id="fig_p094v_5" link="https://drive.google.com/file/d/17W0Rwiq0U0501jXvYvO8kF_FYjeiNtcx"><caption>b</caption></figure>   
        
<lb/>
        
    <figure size="x-small" id="fig_p094v_7" link="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1HhpPaiH0I9np_aklEzw8tpDV12AM3zD1">
<caption>
D<lb/>
the <tl><fr>baston<lb/>
a <m>felinder</m></fr></tl></caption></figure>
        
    <figure size="x-small" id="fig_p094v_6" link="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1TAYIJ3T-ElLyUZO0P0CX8t0BPIupl1hP">
<caption>
c<lb/>
the <tl><m><fr>flin</fr></m></tl> or <tl><m>thunder<lb/>
stone</m></tl></caption></figure></ab><ab margin="left-middle">

</ab>


</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p094r_1" categories="arms and armor" continued="yes">



<ab>The <pro>furbisher</pro> buys his blades by the <ms>dozen</ms>, which
are not fully drawn by the tang because he does this himself to adjust
them well to the <del><fr>l</fr></del> pommel &amp; <wp>guards</wp>.</ab>

<ab><pl>Spanish</pl> ones are deemed better for being of <m>better steel
&amp; iron</m>, but they are not as <tl>well-forged</tl> as <wp>swords</wp> from
<pl>Vienne</pl> in <del><fr>pro</fr></del> <pl>Dauphiné</pl>. The
<pl>Spanish</pl> ones are not as well ground coming from the
<tl>forge</tl>, because they grind them with the
<tl><bp>foot</bp></tl>,<comment rid="c_095r_05"/> &amp; this is what
makes them wavy.</ab>

<ab>Blades from <pl>Vienne</pl> commonly cost xviii or 19
<ms><cn>lb</cn> a dozen</ms>.</ab>

<ab>The first thing the <pro>furbisher</pro> does when he gets his new
blades is to draw out their tang, which he does himself or has done by
<pro>locksmiths</pro> or <pro>farriers</pro>, giving him some
<cn>liard</cn> for his charcoal. Next, they
pass it over a <tl>grindstone</tl> to make it
cut,<comment rid="c_095r_07"/> then lay it down on the
<tl><fr>chameau</fr></tl>, and <add>with</add> some <tl><m>pulverized
emery</m></tl>, fine &amp; soft as <m>flour</m>, &amp; mixed with <m>oil</m>
to make it hold, they furbish the <wp>sword</wp> with the <tl>stick</tl> used to
remove the traces of the <tl>grindstone</tl>, and then <del>the</del>
clean the <wp>sword</wp> <del><fr>po</fr></del>well<comment rid="c_095r_03"/> with the
<tl><m>emery</m></tl> and give it a <ms>drop</ms> or two of <m>oil</m>, which
they spread with the <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl> to give it luster. Having
put the <m>oil</m>, they furbish the <wp>sword</wp> again on the
<tl><fr>chameau</fr></tl> with the
<tl><m><df><fr>felin</fr></df></m></tl>, which is a
<tl><m>thunderstone</m></tl> mounted in the middle of a stick like the
<tl><fr>fustée</fr></tl>, and this stick is called the <tl><df><fr>baton à
<m>felinder</m></fr></df></tl>. Next, having passed it on the
<tl><m><fr>felin</fr></m></tl>, they furbish it with <tl><m>chalk</m></tl> &amp;
the <m>oil</m> which is on the <wp>sword</wp>. Next, they wipe it &amp; go over
it again, &amp; furbish with <tl><m>dry chalk</m></tl>. And at the end, when they
are ready mounted, one gives them the edge with the
<tl><fr>gratteau</fr></tl>.<comment rid="c_094v_07"/>
<del><fr>Ai</fr></del></ab>

<ab>Once furbished, one mounts it on the <wp>guards</wp> which one presents to
know if they are quite suitable. And taking hold of a blade such that
the whole ricasso is held in the <tl><bp>hand</bp></tl>, one conjectures
that it will be just as heavy once mounted.</ab>

<ab>One puts the blade in a <tl><oc>vise</oc></tl> between two pieces of
<m>wood</m>, then with a <tl>file</tl>, they enlarge the opening of the
<wp>guard</wp><comment rid="c_095r_09"/> if it is necessary. Then, to rivet it,
one places on the rivet<comment rid="c_095r_12"/> <del>a piece of</del>
&amp; the pommel a piece of <m>wood</m>, &amp; with a <tl>hammer</tl>,
one beats on it to align &amp; secure the pommel well. Then, with the
<tl>hammer</tl>, one finishes the rivet when the pommel is well secured
&amp; does not wobble. The <m>wood</m> is put there so as not to spoil
the pommel. Next, one finishes the rivet with a <tl>file</tl> or
<tl>chisel</tl>. And some make <del>the <fr>b</fr></del> the rivet in a
square diamond-shape,<comment rid="c_095r_11"/> but it is not as good
as the round one, for, when faceted, the rivet breaks.</ab>

</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p094r_1" categories="arms and armor" continued="yes">



<ab>The end<comment rid="c_095v_03"/> is bought ready-made by the
<ms>dozen</ms>, which costs six <ms><cn>sous</cn></ms> for
the small ones, but for the the big ones 2
<ms><cn><la>carolus</la></cn></ms>. The end <del>this</del> is put either
with <tl>nails</tl>, which are put on the sides of the cutting edge, but
this only spoils the <wp>sword</wp> &amp; destroys the scabbard because the
<m>water</m> enters through the joint of the <tl>nail</tl>. It is best to
apply some <m>rosin</m> or <m>glue</m> on it, but <m>rosin</m> is better.
And it is best when the end is well adjusted &amp; set so hot that the
<m>pulverized rosin</m> melts on the end. In this way, it does not fall
and cannot be undone unless it is put in the fire.</ab>

<ab>Guards are of several kinds:<lb/>

Worked<comment rid="c_095v_04"/><lb/>

Guttered, which is with round moldings<lb/>

<m>Pearled</m><lb/>

Scarfed, when the bands are crosswise<lb/>

Onioned, which is with a flat head<comment rid="c_095v_05"/><lb/>

In the <pro>King</pro>’s manner, which are plain</ab>

<ab>The <pro>furbishers</pro> buy them by <ms>dozens</ms>, the
<ms>dozen</ms> of plain ones commonly costs x <ms><cn>lb</cn></ms>. The
worked piece, 30 <ms><cn>sous</cn></ms> or depending on its
fashion.</ab>

<ab>The first thing the <pro>apprentice</pro> does is to furbish as
said.</ab>

<ab>And next, to garnish the <wp>sword</wp> &amp; make a scabbard, which is the
height of the art.</ab>

<ab>They buy the <m>wood</m> pieces of
<m><pa>beech</pa> wood</m> for scabbards which are ready made, a hundred for xv or xx or 30
<ms><cn>sous</cn></ms>, depending on the distance from the place
where they are made.</ab>

<ab>These <m>wood</m> pieces are thus called
<df><fr>estelles</fr>,</df><comment rid="c_095v_06"/> and have to be
very neat &amp; without any knots &amp; are one <ms><bp>finger</bp>’s
thickness across</ms>.</ab>

<ab>Then the <pro>furbisher</pro> puts them on a small bench, called a
<df><tl>scabbard bench</tl></df>, and with a <del><fr>e</fr></del>
<add><fr>g</fr></add> <del><tl>plane</tl></del> <tl>small <m>iron</m>
tool</tl> similar to that of the <tl><pro>joiners</pro>’ bench</tl>,
they make it hold firmly. Then, with a<del><fr>e</fr></del><comment rid="c_093v_01"/> <del><tl>plane</tl></del>
<tl>plane</tl> which is like a <tl>knife with two
handles</tl>,<comment rid="c_095v_07"/> one works the <m>wood</m>
roughly from the top, next one passes the <tl><pro>joiner</pro>’s
plane</tl> on it the better to even it. Next, one scours it on the
inside with a</ab>


</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p094r_1" categories="arms and armor">



<ab>

<tl>round plane, also mounted with two handles</tl>, then with a
<tl>small narrow plane</tl>, one hollows &amp; scrapes it <ms>half a
<bp>foot</bp></ms> toward the end of the
<fr>talan</fr>,<comment rid="c_096r_02"/> and the shorter the better.
Without this scraping, the <wp>sword</wp> would always cut the scabbard.</ab>

<ab>

The opening of the scabbard is called the mouth, &amp; on top is the
shape of the blade.<comment rid="c_096r_03"/></ab>

<ab>

The stop, which is a <m>leather</m> rim set on the edge of the blade
shape, is made to stop the hangers.</ab>

<ab>

When the <fr>estelles</fr> are well levelled, one lays the <wp>sword</wp> on top,
&amp; with a <tl><m>black stone</m></tl>, one marks the width of the
blade &amp; the length, &amp; then with a <tl>chisel</tl>, one cuts the
excess. And one passes a <tl><pro>joiner</pro>’s plane</tl> to even it
well, according to the mark.</ab>

<ab>

Next, one glues the two <fr>estoilles</fr> edge to edge <add>and all
around</add>, only as far as the shape of the blade extends &amp; not
elsewhere. And this is to make the <m>leather</m> or <m>velvet</m> of
the scabbard hold.</ab>

<ab>

Then one puts the <wp>sword</wp> into the <fr>estelles</fr>. And precisely thus,
they set it in the scabbard, which is all sewn, and rub what is
<m>glued</m> along the shape of the blade<comment rid="c_096r_04"/>
with <m>tallow</m> to make it run into the scabbard.</ab>

<ab>

The scabbard is made of <m><al>calf</al> or <al>sheep</al> leather</m>,
the <al>calf</al> ones are all in one piece, but not the <al>sheep</al>
ones. But, when the <wp>swords</wp> are long, one makes them in pieces which are
sewn between <m>leather</m> &amp; <m>flesh</m>, &amp; then they rub the
stitching thoroughly with a piece of <tl><m><pa>boxwood</pa></m></tl> to
cover &amp; even it. From a <m>good <al>calf</al> skin</m>, viii or 9 or
x scabbards can be taken.<comment rid="c_096r_01"/> A
<pro>workman</pro> can easily make vi <ms>a <tmp>day</tmp></ms>. If they
are too thick, one thins them a little with a <tl>plane</tl>. If the
<m>skin</m> is hard, one wets it in <m>lightly lukewarm water</m>, and
one does not leave it there for long. Next, the same
<pro>worker who made the <m>wood</m> piece</pro> has to adjust the
scabbard to be well made. It is true that for <pro>common people</pro>,
one may well get ones which are ready made, but they are never carried
as well. When the scabbard is made &amp; sewn with <m>black thread</m>,
one rubs it with a piece of <tl><m><pa>boxwood</pa></m></tl> or with a
<tl>cloth</tl>, having daubed it a little in <m>oil</m>. The scabbard of
a good <al>cow</al> is better than any and also costs more, except the
<m>velvet</m> kind. Under the <m>velvet</m>, one commonly puts <m>plain
canvas</m> or a <al>sheep</al> scabbard or a <m>parchment</m> cover. But
the best scabbard of all is a <m>waxed</m> scabbard, of either
<m>velvet</m> or <al>calf</al>. It is because one covers the <m>wood</m>
with <m>thin canvas</m>, which one next <m>waxes</m>, then one covers it
in <m>velvet</m> or <al>calf</al>. A <m>waxed</m> scabbard is worth at
least xxx <ms><cn>sous</cn></ms>, a <al>cow</al> one xx
<ms><cn>sous</cn></ms>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">


<add>From a <m><al>sheep</al> skin</m>, v or vi.</add></ab>

</div>