<div id="p089v_1" categories="casting">

<head><m>Sal ammoniac</m> and <m>alabaster</m></head>

<ab> <m>Sal ammoniac, well pulverized</m> <del><fr>mou</fr></del> &amp;
ground dry on <tl><m>marble</m></tl>, molds very neatly &amp; is of a very beautiful release, &amp; once mixed with <m>alabaster, pulverized</m>
similarly, ii <ms>℥</ms> per <ms>lb</ms> of
<m>alabaster</m> makes it release well. It suffices to moisten it in
a <env>cave</env> or <env>in the <tmp><fr>serain</fr></tmp></env> or, to
be done more quickly, in a <tl>piece of <m>paper</m></tl> between a wet
<tl>napkin</tl>. Take heed that it does not stay for too long, for it
would become so wet that it would not be good for molding
in a <tl>frame</tl>, but rather <fr>en noyau</fr>, in which you will be
able to use it well as long as it dries well at ease &amp; far from the
fire. Otherwise the heat makes it swell &amp; pushes the <m>salt</m> onto
the surface, which renders it lumpy. You can <del>in</del> anoint the
medal with <m><pa>spike lavender</pa> oil</m>, molding 
<fr>en noyau</fr>. It is better to put in 4 <ms>℥</ms> of
<m>sal ammoniac</m> per <ms>lb</ms>, and moisten it <env>in a damp
place</env> for two or three <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms>, &amp; so that
when you take <bp>fistfuls</bp>, it holds together, without, however,
attaching itself &amp; being pasted to your <tl><bp>hand</bp></tl>. You
will mold very neatly with it. But let it dry &amp; reheat very thoroughly,
leaving the <tl>mold</tl> inside so that it acquires strength by
reheating, for it becomes hard as <m>stone</m> &amp;, in this way, is
more certain to release well. Otherwise if you release before having
reheated it, there would be danger of it crumbling in some <comment rid="c_089v_01"/>place
because of its delicateness &amp; fineness, even if the medal has a high
relief. Once you have molded with it, pulverize it as before and put it
back <env>in the damp</env>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

All <m>sand that releases well</m> has body &amp; gives a good hold. <m>Ammoniac</m>
is fatty and <del><fr>a va</fr></del> is nevertheless sandy,
which makes it release well. There is no better bond than <m>salts
appropriate for metals</m>, for once mixed in powder, they get moistened
together &amp; dry &amp; reheat together.</ab>

</div>