<div id="p085v_4" categories="casting" continued="yes">

<head><m>Experimented sands</m></head>

<ab><mark>X</mark><comment rid="c_084v_02"/> I have experimented with <m>sand from
<pl>Th<exp>oulous</exp>e</pl></m>, &amp; after reheating it well
twice, in a <tl>skillet</tl>, I passed it through a <tl>fine sieve</tl>,
like <tl>the <pro>apothecaries</pro>’ double</tl>, without finely
grinding it further on the <tl><m>porphyry</m></tl>, as I have done
previously. I moistened it with <m>wine boiled with <pa>elm</pa>
root</m> and molded with it a large piece of a portrait of
<pn>Jesus</pn>.<comment rid="c_085v_01"/> I found it easy to release, without having it to knock
on it, <del><fr>Jen</fr></del> &amp; molded neatly with one side in
relief &amp; on the other in hollow, &amp; of the <ms>thickness of a
coin of forty <cn>sous</cn></ms>. I cast very hot</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">
<m>Sand from the <env>mine</env></m>, well chosen &amp; well reheated, is the most
excellent of all, without looking for any other mixtures, because it
receives all <m>metals</m>. It does not want to be used hot, because it
makes things porous. The most finely ground for big works is not the
best, because it does have enough body to sustain.</ab>


</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p085v_4" categories="casting">



<ab>with the <m>material of a skillet</m> mixed with a knob that is
<m>potin</m>. And before that, I had so reheated my molded
<tl>frame</tl>, now with the flame of my <tl>furnace</tl>, now putting
lit <m>charcoals</m> on top of it, that it became as if red. I let it
cool and cast. It came out very neatly in relief on one side &amp; in
hollow on the other, as well for the figure as the letters. It is true
that the material was whitish, almost like <m><fr>metalline</fr></m>, but this was because
of the <m>potin</m>. I made another cast with only the <m>material of
a skillet</m> in the same <m>sand</m>, but not so reheated; it did not
come out well.</ab>
</div>

<div id="p085v_4" part="y" continued="yes">
<ab>Since then I have molded the <m>bone of <al>oxen</al> feet, burned,
pulverized</m> &amp; <tl>sieved</tl> through a <tl>double sieve</tl>
&amp; <del><fr>hum</fr></del> <del>very</del> moistened with
<m>glair of egg</m> or <m>wine boiled with <pa>elm</pa> root</m>. I knocked
on it moderately while molding. Having <del>undone the</del> opened the
<tl>frame</tl>, I found that the figures had not released neatly &amp;
left the <tl>molds</tl> floury &amp; crumbling. I
<del>them</del> moistened the <m>bone sand</m> further, so that
it gave a good hold <del>in the</del> between the
<tl><bp>fingers</bp></tl>, and in this way, I molded neatly with a good
release. And even though it seemed to me that the <m>pulverized bone</m>
was coarse, if there is some <m>material of a skillet</m> thrown in, my
figures came out very neatly. It is true that I had very very reheated
my <tl>frame</tl>; it withstood only <underline>one cast. <emph>I find</emph> that</underline>
when a <m>sand</m> is so finely ground that it renders itself dense as
<m>ceruse</m> &amp; even, <del>like</del> without knowing it to be arid,
rarefied, sandy &amp; rather spongy, that it molds
very neatly, but it does not receive <m>metal</m> so well as if it were
porous to absorb the substance. But rather, once fatty &amp; even, it
becomes porous &amp; does not receive fine features. <emph>I believe that
the secret</emph> to cast well lies in finding a <m>sand</m> that receives the
<m>metal</m> well, one for <m>lead</m>, the other for another, for each
one has its particular one. Let it be molded slowly &amp; carefully, and
leave it for a few days to become compact by itself, if you have the
time for this. And next, reheat it very well, not all at once nor 
with a large fire, but little by little, otherwise it crumbles &amp;
always has some fault. Finally, you ought to cast <m>copper</m> or
<m>latten</m> or other <m>great metals</m> very hot &amp;, if it is
possible, in large quantities of substance, which contain more heat than
small quantities. It is necessary that the <tl>frame</tl> be cold, &amp;
that you cast all at once. Always <m><tl>lute</tl></m> the entrance of your
<tl>frame</tl>, for the <m>metal</m>, touching <m>iron</m> or
<m><fr>metal</fr></m>,<comment rid="c_016v_05"/> </ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

This <m>bone</m> wants to be well <tl>pestled</tl> in a <tl>mortar</tl> and does
not want be reheated because it crumbles.</ab>


</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p085v_4" categories="casting">



<ab>becomes porous. Most importantly, make it so that the cast is always
higher than the molded thing, because usually the <m>sand</m>, being reheated,
swells <del>&amp; if the</del> <del>by this</del> in the middle,
&amp; in this way, the molded thing remaining higher than the cast, the
<m>metal</m> cannot run into it easily or enter at all. Also, make sure
that the <tl>mold</tl> &amp; the cast are well reheated. Cast also all
at once &amp; <env>out of the wind</env>. And if your medal is really
thin, put a <tl><m>card</m></tl> or two or three <ms>thicknesses of
<tl><m>paper</m></tl></ms> underneath, when you want to mold it. In
this way the <tl>mold</tl> will be lower than the cast. Cast also at the
place where your medal will be <del>more <fr>es</fr></del> the least
thick &amp; where there will be less relief.</ab>

</div>