<div id="p020r_1" categories="household and daily life">


<head><comment rid="c_020r_01"/>For making <m><oc>millas</oc></m> <figure size="x-small" id="fig_p020r_1" 
link="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1hyCXz2KOCrpNwqiDiCzKp4Tg4YGawMYm"></figure></head>

<ab>It is necessary to have <m><pa>millet</pa></m> pilled to remove the
<m>husks</m> and then you will clean it well. Next one needs to
grind it again quite finely and pass it through a <oc><tl>hair sieve</tl></oc>
quite finely. This done, it is necessary to mix the <m>flour</m> with
<m>melted fresh butter</m> and <m>milk</m>, and that there be
<ms>as much of one as the other</ms>, in such a manner that it is very light in color,
like the <m>dough to make fritters</m>. And you will put in <m>egg
yolks</m> according to the quantity of <m>flour</m>, so that it amounts
to two <m>egg yolks</m> for each <m><oc>millas</oc></m>.
Then you will put in some <m><pa>saffron</pa></m>, if you like, to give
them a little color.</ab>

<ab>Next, you need to have <tl>molds</tl>, and it is
necessary that they be <m>earthenware</m>, in the fashion of the crown of
a catholic hat, but it is necessary that they be open at both ends. And
then, having made a good fire, you will clean the place in the
<tl><env>hearth</env></tl> where you want to put your
<m><oc>millas</oc></m>, and then you will take your <tl>molds</tl> and
grease them quite heavily in order that the <m>dough</m> does not stick when it is
cooked. Having done that, you will put your said <tl>molds</tl> on the
well-cleaned place in the <tl><env>hearth</env></tl> and will put a
little <m>flour</m> at the bottom and fill them with the aforementioned
<m>dough</m>. Next you will cover the said <tl>molds</tl> with
<tl>lids</tl> which will be made like the <tl>molds</tl>, but it is
necessary that they be larger and not be open at the top. Then having
done that, you will put a little <m>hay</m> on the said <tl>lids</tl>
and plenty of <tl>embers</tl>, and make a good charcoal fire all around.
That done, you will uncover one of them soon thereafter and see when it
is cooked. It should be hard.</ab>

</div>