<div id="p115v_3" categories="casting" continued="yes">

<head>Reheating the <tl><fr>noyau</fr> molds</tl></head>

<ab>After your <tl>molds</tl> have their gate, vents &amp;
<tl>clamps</tl>, as is said, make at the end of the <tl>forge</tl>
<del>in</del>, or in some clean place, a surrounding of
<m>bricks</m>, and fill it with large half-lit charcoals. And place your
<tl>molds</tl> on top, and leave the charcoals thus to kindle by
themselves for a <ms><tmp>half hour</tmp></ms>, so that they heat little
by little and not all at once. Finally, as they will begin to become white,
beat <del>little by little</del> the thus half-lit large charcoals
on top &amp; blow with your <tl>little bellows</tl> until they are
warmed. And thus, little <add>by little</add>, invigorate the fire,
without haste, until your <tl>molds</tl> are quite red on the outside
&amp; the inside. If it is for casting some plant or some animal which
does not release well, &amp; if, for this reason, one needs to burn
<add>it</add> in the <tl>mold</tl>, &amp; when you look through the gate, &amp; through it, you see the <tl>molds</tl> are very red &amp; inflamed
inside, this will be your signal that they are reheated enough. But if
you do not see this signal, increase &amp; continue the fire until it is
the case. If there is nothing in the <tl>mold</tl> that needs burning,
it will be enough that they are dried well on the same fire, if it is
for casting <m>tin</m>. They reheat better in a <tl>reverberatory
furnace</tl>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top" render="wide">
<hr/>
Do not pull out<lb/>
your <tl>reheated molds</tl><lb/>
from the fire before they<lb/>
have cooled<lb/>
themselves, &amp; take care<lb/>
that the <env>wind or the
cold</env> does not hit them while very hot, for this would make them burst.<lb/>
One must not reheat them before they<lb/>
are dry and firmed up, for they would<lb/>
cast in a different way, and<lb/>
it is necessary beforehand to make<lb/>
gates &amp; vents<lb/>
&amp; place <tl>clamps</tl>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">
<figure id="fig_p115v_1" size="small" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dHVja3NnV0dmMlk">
</figure><lb/>
Take care not to heat the fire in one go, for fear <del><fr>f</fr></del>
that your <tl>molds</tl> crack inside.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

They are reheated enough when the entire hole of the gate is red. When
it is black, it is not enough.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle" continued="yes">

For casting in <m>silver</m>, one must not reheat two times
<del>&amp;</del>, if there is nothing in the <tl>mold</tl> that needs
<del>releasing</del> burning, simply because it does not
release well. All the <tl>molds</tl> of flowers are reheated
two times, first for <figure size="x-small" id="fig_p115v_2" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bXhqSkVQbkgwYjQ">            
</figure><comment rid="c_115v_01"/></ab>

</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p115v_3" categories="casting">

<ab margin="left-top" continues="yes">

<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p116r_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SEdPVDdsS2dEUmM">
</figure><comment rid="c_116r_03"/>

burning the plants, flowers, and animal parts which are left inside. Next, one
needs to clean them &amp; remove the <m>ashes</m>. Second, reheat them
&amp; render them red for casting. At the beginning, reheat with some
charcoals, gently lit, and put your <tl><fr>noyau</fr> molds</tl> flat
on the charcoals surrounded by <m>bricks</m>. <tl>Frame molds</tl> are
reheated on a <tl>grate</tl>.

</ab>

</div>