<div id="p135v_1" categories="casting" continued="yes">

<head>Casting in <m>☀</m><comment rid="c_135v_01"/></head>

<ab>Take a <tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl> with a capacity suitable for what you want
to put in it, coarsely pestle a little <m>borax</m> &amp; put it at the
bottom, then the <m>☼</m> on top. Arrange the <tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl> on the <m>charcoals</m> of the <tl>forge</tl> in such a
way that the wind of the <tl>bellows</tl> blows on it from underneath
and not at the side, for this would cool it &amp; would not heat it enough.
Make sure also that it is distanced three <ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> from
the wall of the <tl>forge</tl>, in order that it can be surrounded with
<m>charcoal</m>. Let the said <tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl> reheat until it is quite
red. Then, make your <pro>boy</pro> blow on it with long and strong
pushes, for in this way it heats <del>well</del> better. And
nevertheless, <del>blow by</del> when the <m>gold</m> is melted, blow on
top with <tl>small bellows</tl>, for the <m>gold</m> will become
brittle &amp; take on a crust. And as long as it makes
swirling fumes as you blow thus, it means that is not soft
enough for the cast. Uncover therefore the <tl>crucible</tl>, &amp;
without moving <del><fr>ch</fr></del><comment rid="c_135v_03"/> it from its place and without
interrupting the blowing, make it lean toward you in order to see well
inside. Throw in it the <ms>size of a <pa>bean</pa></ms> of <m>borax</m>,
&amp; blow inside in jolts with the <tl>small bellows</tl>. But if
there is <m>charcoal</m> inside, blow a little stronger to make it go
out. And if the <m>gold</m> <m>smokes</m> &amp; swirls, put some more
<m>borax</m> in and <del>note</del> blow on top, making sure that, if it
is still brittle &amp; not softened<comment rid="c_015r_01"/> enough, it does not cover itself<comment rid="c_135v_02"/>
when you blow, as if it had cooled. But if it does not make this sign,
it is soft enough. At that point, blow very strongly in order
to heat it well, and as you think it is hot enough, throw in on top, in
the <tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl>, the <df><m><fr>couleur</fr></m></df>,<comment rid="c_135r_01"/>
composed, as said before, of <m>verdet</m>, <m>saltpeter</m>,
<m>sal ammoniac</m> &amp; <m>borax</m>, <add>a little</add>. And
<del>let rest</del> blow always with the <tl>small bellows</tl>, and the
<m>gold</m> will become shiny like</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

If you cast in <m>gold</m> some important piece, <m><tl>lute</tl></m> your
<tl>mold</tl> with the same <m>sand</m> where <del>there is</del> there is some
<m><la>crocum</la></m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

If you want to cast some large work in <m>gold</m> or which is
important, make at the foot of the <tl>forge</tl>, or at one end of it,
<add>a <tl><fr>four à vent</fr></tl></add>, where you can hold your
<tl>mold</tl> in the completely <del><fr>n</fr></del><comment rid="c_135v_04"/> red <m>sand</m>. </ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

One can cast two or three <ms>lb</ms> of <m>gold</m>.</ab>


</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p135v_1" categories="casting">



<ab>a mirror. And when you want to <ill/><comment rid="c_136r_01"/> cast, put again a
little of the <m><fr>couleur</fr></m><comment rid="c_135r_01"/> &amp; let rest a little, always
blowing with the <tl>small &amp; large bellows</tl>. Finally, arrange
your very red <tl>mold</tl> between the <tl><fr>moulets</fr></tl><comment rid="c_136r_03"/> or in a

<tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl> full of very hot <m>sand</m>, &amp; cast. And when it has set,
throw, if you want, in <m>water</m>. For <m>gold</m> does not get
damaged like <m>tin</m>, which jumps.</ab>

<ab>To melt <m>gold</m> in ingots, it is of no importance to
<del><fr>gec</fr></del> blow on top with the <tl>little bellows</tl>.</ab>

<ab>For large works, the <tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl> of <m>sand</m> needs to be put in a
<tl><fr>fourneau à vent</fr></tl>, to become entirely red at the end of
the <tl><fr>fournaise</fr></tl>.</ab>

<ab>The <m>gold</m> that the <env>wind</env> hits or that one forges becomes
black. But a little <m>aquafortis</m> uncovers it immediately.</ab>

<ab>If you have some work to forge of <del><m>latten</m></del>
<add><m><la>sol</la></m></add><comment rid="c_136r_02"/> on <m>latten</m>, as one does small
statues, put between the <m>gold</m> &amp; the <m>latten</m> a <m>plate
of lead</m>. And before reheating the <m>gold</m> &amp; putting it again
in the fire, soak in <m>aquafortis</m> &amp; it will be
soft.</ab>

<ab>It is enough that the gate be of the thickness <del><ill/></del> of
the medal, that is to say from the middle of the gate to the medal. But
if the medal is very thick, one ought not, for this reason, to thicken
the gate, for a very thick gate never comes out well.
<del><fr>Mai</fr></del> Also, it could be made wide, as much as can
be done, to embrace the medal.</ab>

</div>