<div id="p133v_3" categories="casting" continued="yes">


<head>Various animals entwined</head>

<ab>

You can entwine a <al>snake</al> <del>entwined</del> with a
<al>lizard</al>, one biting the other, or a <al>snake</al> that eats a
<al>frog</al> or a <al><po>wall lizard</po></al> <del><fr>s</fr></del><comment rid="c_133v_01"/> &amp;
suchlike. But because these entwinings can in no way make a good
release, cut what you can &amp; leave the rest to burn. And to keep a
<al>wall lizard</al>, which is small, in the mouth of the
<al>snake</al>, which is raised &amp; needs to be supported in the air
<del><fr>po</fr></del> because the head of the <al>snake</al> is posed
    raised, put underneath the <al>wall lizard</al> <del><fr>se</fr></del><comment rid="c_133v_02"/>
an elevation of <m>earth</m> suited to support it. And if you put your
<tl>mold</tl> in the <tl>oven</tl>, the animal, drying promptly, will retract
&amp; will burn better afterward. <del>if you see</del> These entwinings are
also made to cover a wound or fault in the animals, which one usually
wounds when one catches them. Also, do not forget to attach &amp; join
with some <m>wax</m> <del><fr>s</fr></del>, finely applied with <tl>hot
<m>iron wire</m></tl>, all the parts of the animal which pass one on top
of the other or those that you notice are not well fixed on the 
<del><m>wax</m></del> <tl><m>earthen</m> slab</tl>, in order that the <m>tempered sand</m>
does not remove it. And it is to</ab>


</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p133v_3" categories="casting">



<ab>

avoid putting <tl>points</tl>, which should not be put except at the
raising of the head, at the thickest places of the body &amp; the simple
&amp; delicate parts in the middle of the <al>lizard</al>’s feet, the
nails of which you will enter into the <tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl>, in
order that they remain secure. When you have made the first cast &amp;
uncovered the belly of the animal, do not forget to put small thin
<del><fr>s</fr></del><comment rid="c_133r_01"/> <tl>slabs of <m>wax</m></tl> at the end of the
<al>lizard</al>’s legs. But, if it is a <al>small wall lizard</al>,
lightly cover with <m>wax</m> the entire bottom of the foot,
<del>and</del> and <del>this</del> the <m>wax</m>, being removed after
the second cast, leaves a cavity which fills these small fingers with
<m>metal</m>, &amp; then one repairs them. Take heed therefore to attach
well with <m>wax</m> the parts of the animal which pass one over the
other, in order that the <m>wetted sand</m> entering between two does not take it
away. <del>And if</del> For if this were to happen, the <del><tl>mold</tl>
would spoil</del> shape <del>in the first place</del> would
<del>spoil</del> corrupt &amp; your <tl>mold</tl> also because it would
not have the thickness that <del><fr>il</fr></del><comment rid="c_128r_02"/> you think &amp; would be
pierced &amp; spoiled. And, even though to avoid this you can make the
<tl>mold</tl> thicker, however, should <del><fr>l</fr></del><comment rid="c_123v_01"/> this mishap
happen, you will be able to repair it in this way.</ab>

</div>