<entry><div id="p129v_4" categories="casting">

<head><al>Spider</al> molded on a leaf</head>

<ab>

The <add>very</add> big ones usually have hairy feet, which are
vexing to mold if you do not lay them flat, or burn them with a
<tl>candle</tl>, or stiffen them &amp; lay them flat <del>with
some</del>, anointing them with <m><pa>wheat</pa> oil</m>. Kill
them in <m>vinegar</m> &amp; <m><bp>urine</bp></m>, like <al>snakes</al>
<del>&amp;</del>, or in <m>eau-de-vie</m>, and then shape them on a
well-made <pa>vine</pa> leaf or other thing. Next, you can give them back their
capricious hair with <del><fr>bourr</fr></del> the <m><tl>sieved</tl>
fine hair of cloth waste</m>, having anointed them <del>with a</del> with
<m><al>fish</al> glue</m> or similar. Their true color is of
<m>vinegar</m> &amp; <m>verdet</m>, &amp; then fumigate them in various
places with <m>sulfur</m>. Having made your <del><fr>tourt</fr></del>
<tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl>, place on it your <pa>vine</pa> leaf, and the
dead <al>spider</al> in the middle, &amp; pierce with a <tl>point of
<m>iron or latten wire</m></tl> the middle of the <al>spider</al>’s body
&amp; the leaf together. Next, place diagonally <tl>small points of
<m>latten wire</m></tl> around the <pa>vine</pa> leaf to secure it well.
Then fix, with a little <m>melted wax</m> and the <tl>point of a hot
<m>iron wire</m></tl>, the end of the legs, adapting them with the end
of <tl>small pincers</tl>. Do the same thing with the end of the
small cornicles of the <al>spider</al>. Return <mark>🜊</mark><comment rid="c_112r_02"/></ab>

    <ab margin="left-top" render="wide">

<add>To make the gate<lb/>
for the <al>spider</al> on the<lb/>
leaf and to prevent<lb/>
the <m>sand</m> from covering the <al>spider</al> from underneath the
belly, furnish the end of the<lb/>
tail &amp; the bottom of the body with a
little <m>wax, melted</m> &amp; applied with the <tl>hot <m>iron
wire</m></tl>, as you know. In<lb/>
this way, when the leaf burns &amp; the<lb/>
<m>wax</m> is melted, there will remain<lb/>
two little holes in the leaf
which will be the gate of the <al>spider</al>.</add></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">
<mark>🜊</mark><comment rid="c_112r_03"/><lb/>
Once the <m>wax</m> is cool, scrape the excess with the point of a
<tl>penknife</tl> in order that the end of the legs stay neat. Next,
place the <tl>circle of <m>earth</m></tl> around &amp; cast your <m>tempered
sand</m>, like for other things. In this manner, you will need to burn the
<pa>vine</pa> leaf in the <tl>mold</tl>, otherwise not. And to cast more
easily, let the animal die fully, in order that, when struggling, it does
not mix up its legs. Having made your first cast, uncover the reverse of
the leaf and make the second cast.</ab>

</div>
</entry>