<div id="p105r_4" categories="cultivation" continued="yes">


<head>Gardening</head>

<ab>For shield grafting, one needs to take the new issue
that the tree that you want to graft has made <add><tmp>in that year</tmp></add>, &amp;
there cut a branch on which you see that next to
<del><fr>raci</fr></del> the sprouting of leaves there are little
buttons that one calls <df><fr>œillets</fr></df>, which are the beginnings of
sprouts. One needs to nimbly, with a <tl>very sharp penknife</tl>, cut
in the shape of a shield a little bit of the skin <del>with</del> which
contains an <fr>œillet</fr> or sprout with the leaf, thus marked B.<comment rid="c_105r_01"/>
<del>But</del> <del><fr>plusto</fr></del> Then, carefully make on the
tender wood, <del><fr>s</fr></del> which is in sap, on which you
want to graft, two lines thus <del><fr>de</fr></del> cut 
<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p105r_3" link="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1Yg3owXGn8wEALDW6I2jZxJzcQs2UURt6"></figure>, then
make in the middle a cleft thus <figure size="x-small" id="fig_p105r_2" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5T1FZYTdOT1U4Qzg"></figure>.
Next, separate, with the point of the <tl>penknife</tl>, the bark &amp;
open it from the cleft in the middle, and having neatly lodged your
shield so that nothing comes out but the sprout, bind it well &amp; wrap
it entirely with a <tl><m>slip of <pa>linen</pa></m></tl> or <tl><m>very
soft thread</m></tl>, so that there is nothing uncovered but the leaf,
which in three or 4 <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms> will give you an indication
whether the shield should take, accordingly it will be green. Leave your
graft seven or eight <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms> thus, then unbind it &amp;
join it well to the bark, especially at the sprout, &amp; then rebind
all gently but not as strongly as before; &amp; if there is any output
or growth, leave it space to go out, &amp; do thus three or 4
times.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p105r_1" size="small" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5UWpzdGVweGVvQTg">
</figure>


</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p105r_4" categories="cultivation">

<ab render="wide">Next, when it is well <del><fr>b</fr></del> taken, cut the top
of the tree that exceeds your tree, <del><fr>ne</fr></del> three or 4
<ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> above the shield for the first time, and
<del><fr>apr</fr></del> then, at the closest point, in order that it
closes. But heed well that when you make your shield no small hole
remains at the back of the sprout, for this would signify to you that
its root would be broken, &amp; your graft would never take; but make it
so that the back is intact. This type of grafting is practiced
<ms><tmp>from mid-May</tmp></ms>, so that the trees have already budded
&amp; made new</ab></div>

<div id="p105r_4" part="y">
        
<ab render="wide">issue, <ms><tmp>until the beginning of
August</tmp></ms>, and so that the trees are in sap. <pa>Almond
trees</pa>, which by their nature are drier, lose their sap earlier, therefore
those who want to graft onto them <pa><fr>mericotons</fr></pa>,
<pa>apricots</pa> &amp; grafts of trees with pitted fruit, which are the
best there, they are grafted <ms><tmp>in the month of
January</tmp></ms>. Generally trees with pitted fruit, like
<pa><fr>mericoton</fr> peaches</pa>, are grafted in clefts. One says
that trees <del><fr>de</fr></del> grafted <fr>en piolet</fr><comment rid="c_105v_06"/> or by
shield are later in bearing fruit than those by cleft.</ab>

</div>