<entry><div id="p100v_2" categories="stones" continued="yes">



<head>For <m>ruby</m> take <m>gold leaf</m></head>

<ab>Raise your <tl>furnace</tl> <ms>by two <tl>tiles</tl></ms> all
around, because one needs more heat for making <m>rubies</m> than for
<m>emeralds</m>. And take one <ms>℥</ms> of <m>white
calcined pebbles</m> and put it in a <tl>mortar of <m>glass</m></tl>, &amp; having ground it coarsely with the <tl>pestle</tl> of the same,
mix in <del>a <ms>grain</ms></del> the <ms>weight of a
grain</ms> of <m>gold leaf</m> of what the <pro>painters</pro>
<m>gild</m>, &amp; grind</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



Some say that, mixing the <m>gold</m> with the <m>pebbles</m> and the
<m>saltpeter</m>, it makes the color of a <pa>peach tree</pa></ab>.

<ab margin="left-middle">



Others say that it is necessary that the <m>gold</m> be cemented several
times, then beaten into leaf.</ab>



</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p100v_2" categories="stones">





<ab>again very well, then add in iii <ms>℥</ms> of
<m>minium</m>, &amp; <tl>pestle</tl> well again all together, &amp; put
it in the <tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl>, which you will cover with an appropriate
<tl>tile</tl>, a bit thick, in order that heat reverberates better
there. Then, set it on the <tl>grate</tl> of your <tl>furnace</tl>,
having put under a few <tl>thick rounded squares</tl>. Next, fill your
<tl>furnace</tl> to the opening with <tl>charcoal</tl>, so that it will
be heaped, and let it kindle, and always maintain the heat evenly
without letting the <tl>charcoal</tl> decrease. And for this effect,
always make it so that the <tl>furnace</tl> is heaped &amp; full of
<tl>charcoal</tl>, and maintain it thus for one <ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms>.
The first experience that I made of it, it only returned a yellow mass,
as is <m>vitrified minium</m> alone, &amp; some <ms>grains of
<m>gold</m></ms> in a mass at the bottom. <emph>Try cemented <m>gold</m>
and accompanied with <m>antimony</m>.</emph></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



If you need greater heat, <del><fr>plie</fr></del> put, on the edge of
the opening of the glowing <tl>furnace</tl>, <tl>tiles</tl>, one against
the other, for making the heat reverberate.</ab>

    <figure size="small" id="fig_p101r_1" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dnlodmJvNkRMaWM">
</figure>

</div>

</entry>