<div id="p119v_1" categories="casting">


<head>Fashion of preparing <del><fr>a spalt</fr></del><comment rid="c_119v_04"/>
<add><m><de>spat</de></m></add><comment rid="c_108r_02"/></head>

<ab>It is found in earth in <pl>Germany</pl>, the color of <m>cooked
plaster</m>, made of long filaments, very soft to handle. And because it
is mixed with <m>earth</m> and <m>filth</m>, one <tl>pestles</tl> it coarsely
&amp; one makes little balls, having for this purpose soaked it in
<m>sal ammoniac water</m> of such a composition that you were told
above. One places these balls to reheat in the fire of the <tl><fr>fornaise</fr>
of the <pro>potters</pro></tl>, then one soaks it again in the same
<m>water</m>. The <m>earth</m> and <add>the</add> coarseness and
<m>filth</m> go to the bottom, and the <m>pure <fr>aspalte</fr></m>,
which is light &amp; soft, and handleable as <m>wet flour</m>, adheres
with the <m>water</m> and goes to the surface, clouding the
<m>water</m>, which murkiness is emptied into a separate <tl>vase</tl>.
When it has settled, one empties the <m>water</m> by tilting or by taking
it away with a <tl>sponge</tl>, and the <m>pure <fr>aspalte</fr></m>
remains at the bottom. Dry it &amp; employ it in a <tl>frame</tl> that has
been moistened with <m>sal ammoniac water</m>. And try it in the
<tl>frame</tl>, in which it shrinks when reheated or dried, that is to
say that one needs to reheat it again on a good fire and redden it.
Thus, for medals and flat things, you should use this one, because it is
the most perfect of all for <m>gold</m>, <m>silver</m>, <m>copper</m>,
<m>lead</m>, <m>latten</m>, &amp; <m>tin</m>, for it withstands the fire
&amp; reddens whenever need be, without corrupting. The more it is used,
the <del><fr>b</fr></del> better it is, &amp; it does not spoil. At the beginning
it is white, &amp; being used, it becomes grey. However, make sure to put
aside the one that served for casting <m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m> &amp;
<m>latten</m>, for <m>gold</m> would sour in it, &amp; would not come
out of it well. And to do this better, you could put it aside to be used
for each <m>metal</m>. </ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

See <pn>Gesnerus</pn>,<comment rid="c_119v_02"/> <la>De lapidibus</la><comment rid="c_119v_03"/>

</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

It endures ten or twelve castings without corrupting, it withstands the
fire &amp; reddens, it is suitable for all <m>metals</m>. It is so
tenacious that should the <tl>frame</tl> be furrowed, it holds.

</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

The <m><de>spat</de></m> almost does not set, even though it is reheated &amp; is
a kind of <m>plaster</m>. Raw, it breaks easily with the
<tl><bp>fingers</bp></tl>.</ab>

</div>