<div id="p114r_1" categories="casting" continued="yes">


<head>Second cast</head>

<ab>When you have well molded the first part of the animal, that is the
back, the backbone, and the entire top part, and the
<del><fr>len</fr></del> half-<tl>mold</tl> where it is enclosed has set
and is hard enough, <figure size="x-small" id="fig_p114r_2" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SWVndzB0aEk5MWs">
</figure> <mark>+</mark><comment rid="c_114r_03"/>  uncover the whole bottom part &amp; side of the belly,
<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p114r_3" link="https://drive.google.com/file/d/11xMXPBFXeustBAj4WfX983gOeRBgM92R">
</figure> now with a <tl>knife</tl> <del>&amp; <fr>tant</fr></del>
at the thickest places, &amp; then with a <tl>penknife</tl>, where the
most delicate parts are enclosed, such as the legs, the tail, &amp;
similar things, and because the head is higher, you will also need to
look for it &amp; uncover deeper, and make a deeper notch there which
ought to release easily. That is to say, widening on the outside, in order that
the second <tl>mold</tl> that you will cast on it can come out well,
which even the animal can help with, which is malleable and obedient,
being natural. However, <del><fr>ad</fr></del> be more careful
when uncovering the throat of the <al>lizard</al> than with the
<al>snake</al>, for the <al>lizard</al> has large jaws &amp; large bones
that are not malleable and has hollow ears, where, if the <m>wet sand</m> has
entered, it is not <del><fr>aff</fr></del> easy to release. But you will
avoid all of this, if you uncover half of the head and those things that
you know do not release well. Once everything is uncovered well, blow
on top &amp; wipe each part, by wiping with <tl>tiny <m><al>hog</al> 
bristle</m> brushes</tl>, slightly moistened by the end with a
little <m>saliva</m>, <add>or with <m>clear water</m>, as you uncover
it</add>, in order that <del>your</del> the uncovered lower part of your
animal will be very neat. <add><mark>#</mark></add>
<add>🝋</add><comment rid="c_114r_03"/> With this done, dip <del>the
<fr>rev</fr></del> <del>your mold</del>, for the <ms><tmp>length
of a paternoster</tmp></ms>,<comment rid="c_114r_05"/> your <tl>mold</tl> in <m>water</m>, not
<del>from the</del> <add>the</add> uncovered side but
opposite &amp; the reverse of the uncovered thing. And this is in order that,
by sucking the <m>water</m> <add>inside</add>, the <m>oil</m> with which
you next anoint the other side <del>to avoid</del>, is not
imbibed at all, but remains on the surface &amp; prevents the second
cast that you will cast on it from attaching to it. Having therefore
thus dipped <add>the reverse of</add> your <tl>mold</tl> in the
<m>water</m>, take a <tl>paintbrush</tl> especially dedicated to
this &amp; <del>anoint it</del> with it, anoint with <m>oil</m>
the whole surface of the <tl>mold</tl>, except the animal, which must in
no way touch the <m>oil</m>, &amp; take heed to retrace well &amp; to anoint
with the point of a <tl>paintbrush</tl> between the parts &amp;
through all the delicate parts. And if by chance the <m>oil</m> is
imbibed, dip the <del><fr>mo</fr></del> reverse of the <tl>mold</tl>, as
mentioned, in <m>water</m>, &amp; you will see the <m>oil</m> return to
the surface in little drops.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

Mold small animals like big ones, except that you need to make
<tl>delicate points of <del><fr>fil</fr></del> <corr><del>of</del></corr> <del><fr>cist</fr></del>
<m><mu>cittern</mu> strings</m></tl>, both long &amp; short.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<comment rid="c_114r_04"/><figure size="x-small" id="fig_p114r_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NVR5Y2FtZHM0ck0">
        
</figure><lb/>

remove with your <tl>small flat pincers</tl>, all the <tl>points</tl>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p114r_4" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=17F847nLWSWShsQsXGUlruIM-6qZBHWkw">
</figure>

And then

<mark>+</mark> <del>now with</del></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p114r_7" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=1E6KtaMUmbjA5oNRc2Rzq23yjVIA5n_GV">
</figure><lb/>

However, leave the <tl>point</tl> of the throat, so that it serves as a
clue to find the head, which is deeper down than any other part, because
when making the arrangement you disposed it higher. It is also at the
level of the head that you should make the biggest notch, &amp; start
with this one to uncover, and follow the rest through the trace of the
<tl>points</tl>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<comment rid="c_114r_04"/><mark>#</mark><lb/>

And if some bit of nail from a leg, or from a tail, or from another
should separate from the <tl>mold</tl>, put <del>there</del>
between the two a small grain of <m>wax</m>, &amp; with the <tl>point of a
hot <m>iron wire</m></tl>, join it, then adapt your <tl>mold</tl> with a
<tl>knife</tl>, &amp; make notches on its sides so that the other
half binds to it. 🝋<lb/>

<figure size="small" id="fig_p114r_6" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5TTRuWU8yVktnc3M">

</figure>

</ab>


</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p114r_1" categories="casting" continued="yes">

<ab>This thus prepared, place your <del><fr>de</fr></del> first
half-<tl>mold</tl> on the <po>cake</po> of <del><m>earth</m></del>
<m>clay</m>, &amp; put the circle also around, &amp; make the mark for
the thickness similar to the first. Then, with another rather thickish
<tl>paintbrush</tl>, moisten well everywhere the uncovered half
<del>&amp; the belly</del> of your animal
<del>And</del> <add>with <m>eau-de-vie</m></add>,
without leaving anything, if it is possible, which is not moistened, for
this is the secret which makes it come out neat. And next, as promptly
as will be possible for you, before the <m>eau-de-vie</m>
<del>not</del> evaporates, wet your <m>sand</m> and cast it in thrusts and by blowing &amp; moving the <tl>mold</tl> as you did
for the first one, making sure that the <del>first <fr>q</fr></del>
beginning of that which you pour on the animal should be a little lighter than the
next one so that it moistens everywhere &amp; closely follows the more delicate
parts. So, leave it for a <ms><tmp>quarter of an hour</tmp></ms> to set, then
remove the circle &amp; the <m>clay</m> <po>cake</po>. And, with a
<tl>knife</tl>, arrange your two <tl>molds</tl> uniformly together in a
long shape of a <mu>mandore</mu>, as mentioned, because of the cast.
Then, dip a little the whole <tl>mold</tl> evenly, at the level of the
joints, in <m>water</m>, for this is another secret to unjoin them,
otherwise you will break everything. Separate them nimbly, therefore, by
this means, and next, extract gently &amp; with patience and method
the half of the animal remaining in one of the <tl>molds</tl>,
<del>for</del> pulling it sometimes from one side &amp; sometimes from
the other, to avoid breaking any of it, or also spoiling something from
the <tl>mold</tl>. <del>And</del> The latter being empty,
<del>extract</del> rejoin the two halves so that no dust
enters it, &amp; put them aside until you want to reheat them, make the
gate &amp; vents, &amp; place the <tl>clamps</tl>. As for the animal, so
that it does not dry &amp; that you might be able to mold it four of
five times, put it in <m>water</m>. And I think that it would keep even
better in <m>eau-de-vie</m>. However, the best would be to mold
in the same <tmp>day</tmp> the 4 or 5 <tl>molds</tl> that you can do,
because these corrupt animals in themselves <sn>stink</sn> within one <ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms>. Having left your <tl>molds</tl> one or two
<del><fr>es</fr></del> <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms> to dry, for they stay
humid for a good <ms><tmp>month</tmp></ms>, make the vents on one
half <figure size="x-small" id="fig_p114v_3" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dkk3MW10YzNIbDg">
</figure><comment rid="c_114v_01"/></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">
<figure size="small" id="fig_p114v_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dmlRQm1lTjc4aXc">
</figure><lb/>
<mark>+</mark><lb/> Note that when you have made your second
<add>cast</add>, were you to leave your <tl>mold</tl> for one
<ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms> or a <ms><tmp>night</tmp></ms> without opening
it, you would need to then dip it in <m>hot water</m> or else reheat it
before opening it, as for <al>crabs</al>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

If, after both halves of the <fr>noyau</fr> have made a strong &amp; hard set, you
would not dip your <tl>mold</tl> in <m>water</m>, it would not unjoin at
all. But as you dip the reverse of the <tl>mold</tl> in <m>water</m>,
the imbibed <m>oil</m> collects at the top &amp; at the level of the
joints &amp; makes it separate.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

However, take heed your second <tl>mold</tl> is of good thickness &amp;
that it is hard enough because if it is lacking in this, after having
dipped it in <m>water</m>, &amp; you want to open it, there is a risk
that it breaks. Take heed therefore to avoid this, and wanting to open
it, dip all of it in <m>water</m> <add>and rub it everywhere</add>,
where it will harden if it has set well. Then, take your two
<tl>molds</tl>, joined with a <tl>rough <m>linen</m> cloth</tl> in
order to have a better grip, and separate them with strength as if you
wanted to tear apart a loaf of <m>bread</m>. But if it happens to break, join
it &amp; on the reverse, strengthen the joints with <tl>clamps</tl>.

<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p114v_4" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NmZxVUxKTmhYSXM">
</figure>

</ab>

<ab margin="bottom" render="wide">

Next, you can repair the faults with small <tl>chisels</tl>.

</ab>

</div>

<div id="p114r_1" part="y">
<ab margin="left-middle" render="wide">
to cast by the tail or from the back of the animal,<lb/>
make it so that the vents come from<lb/>
the head &amp; the middle of the body to join<lb/>
to the said tail,<lb/>
where the<lb/>
gate is done, which is the<lb/>
end of the<lb/>
mandore.</ab> 

</div>

<div  id="p114r_1" part="y">   
<ab margin="left-top" render="tall"><del><fr>N</fr></del><comment rid="c_115r_03"/> And having done your cast, do not forget to make in
it some holes and <del><ill/></del>notches<comment rid="c_115r_02"/> because the metal will run more neatly thus than if
the cast were even, for it gets corrupted in its notches &amp; holes,
&amp; does not go so much at once, &amp; does not become as porous. This
done, <del>put</del> join <del><fr>t</fr></del><comment rid="c_115r_04"/> the two halves of your <tl>mold</tl> &amp; strengthen the joints,
putting around these some small <tl>clamps</tl> of iron wire of this shape<lb/>
<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p115r_2" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5aVlsV1BuajVVejQ">
</figure>. They
prevent<lb/> 
the <tl>molds</tl> from deforming &amp; corrupting while reheating.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p115r_3" size="small" margin="left-top" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5aS1ZeHc2dGxJTE0">
</figure>
    
<figure id="fig_p115r_4" size="small" margin="left-top" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Xzg4WTZ2NFNkOHM">
<caption>This is the shape of the <tl>clamps</tl></caption>
</figure>

</div>