<entry><div id="p012v_3" categories="stones" continued="yes">



<head>For whitening <m>enilanroc</m><comment rid="c_012v_02"/></head>

<ab>Some think that the <m>ceruse</m>-colored crust which is on top
is natural, others say that it is a secret of <pro>ancient lapidaries</pro>
that is lost, others say that it is <m>refired enamel</m>. And by means
of the said crust, several ciphers, letters, circles
<del><fr>st</fr></del> &amp; other bizarre things can be formed. As for
the method, I have practiced it thus. Once I wished to give it a layer of
<m>arsenic</m> ground on <tl><m>marble</m></tl>. However, I experimented
without this, and I put the aforesaid thing, <m>enilanroc</m>, in a
small <tl><m>iron</m> casket</tl> on the fire of my
<tl><pro>goldsmith</pro>’s forge</tl> with three or four small
half-burnt <m>charcoals</m>, and blew only with my <bp>mouth</bp>. And
nonetheless the thing came to <del>redden &amp;</del> ignition &amp; turned
completely white, not only on its surface but also inside, &amp; then I
let it cool on its own <env>near the fire</env>, for otherwise, exposing
it suddenly to cold air, it would have burst. Once all white, I passed
it through my <tl><add><m>lead</m></add><comment rid="c_012v_01"/> <del><m>tin</m></del> wheel</tl>, 
where I found it as hard as before, &amp; uncovering the white
a little, I found it a fair flesh color. Finally, I polished it &amp;
saw that it took a very beautiful polish &amp; could paragon a
very beautiful <m>agate</m> for cutting some beautiful face on it &amp;
bringing it on <del>the</del> a table of

</ab>



</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p012v_3" categories="stones">





<ab>

<m>agate</m> of various color. But because this total whiteness did not
respond to make this white crust on the surface that I was seeking,
leaving the rest of the thing of its natural color, I made a opening in
a <m>brick</m> of the exact size of the thing &amp; put it inside. Then
I reddened two <tl><pro>glassworkers’</pro>
solders</tl>, &amp; as they were red, I
presented them one after the other onto the surface of the thing until I
had the white crust that I required, on which I made such drawing as I
wanted, uncovering up to the red base with a <tl><m>diamond</m>
point</tl>, and I polished it with <tl>small <m><al>hog</al> bristle</m> brushes</tl>
and <tl><m>tripoli</m></tl>. I do not know if it would be better to
reheat it under hot <m>ashes</m>, &amp; if it would be good to encase it
in <m>alabaster</m>, which is very cold, as I encased it in the
<m>brick</m>.</ab>

</div>

</entry>