<entry><div id="p107r_1" categories="casting" continued="yes">

<head>Catching <al>lizards</al> and <al>snakes</al></head>

<ab>Take a <tl>stick</tl> and attach a <tl>string</tl> at the end which
has a <del>knot</del> <del><add>eyelet</add></del> slip
<add>eyelet</add> at the end. And there being two or three to distract the
<al>lizard</al> by whistling, approach the eyelet toward its neck,
and when its head <corr><del><fr>l</fr></del></corr> is inside, pull. <add>The <al>lizard</al> is more
tedious to catch by <tl><bp>hand</bp></tl> than the <al>snake</al> &amp;
bites without letting go &amp; grips like <tl>pincers</tl>.</add></ab>

<ab><al>Snakes</al> can be caught by <tl><bp>hand</bp></tl>, provided
that it is covered by a thick <tl><m>woollen</m> cloth</tl>, for the
teeth of the <al>snake</al> stay in the <tl>cloth</tl> &amp; cannot
pierce like they would with a <m>linen</m>. The dangerous ones are
recognized by their blue &amp; <del><fr>asses</fr></del> <fr>aseures</fr><comment rid="c_107r_03"/>
<add>azure</add> eyes. They hardly ever bite <env>in
water</env>, which <pro><al>crayfish</al> catchers</pro>
experience.</ab>

<ab>The <m>sand</m> mixture is of two <ms>parts</ms> of <m>plaster, pulverized
&amp; reheated</m> as said, &amp; of one <ms>part</ms> of <m>tile</m>,
reddened <del>and <fr>p</fr></del> <del><fr>pre</fr></del> <add>in a good
fire</add> after the first cooking &amp; then finely pulverized, and of
<m>feather alum</m>, <ms>half</ms> as much as of the <m>brick</m>, namely two
full <ms><tl>crucibles</tl></ms> of <m>plaster</m>, one of <m>brick</m>
&amp; a half of <m>feather alum</m>. There can never be too
much <m>feather alum</m>, for <del><fr>s</fr></del> this is
what gives bond to the <m>sand</m>, and because it does not burn, it makes <m>sand</m>
withstand the fire without cracking &amp; bursting. Otherwise, without
it, the <m>sand</m> would not withstand it. This <m>sand</m>, thus composed, is proper
for all <m>metals</m>, but if you want to use it for <m>gold</m>, one
needs more <m>feather alum</m> <del>&amp;</del> than the aforesaid 
composition, and mix in some <m><la>crocum ferri</la></m>. For it is this one that attracts <m>gold</m>.</ab>

<ab>It is necessary that all <m>sand</m> with which you want to cast well,
withstands the fire well, that is to say that it withstands
<del><fr>abon</fr></del> <del><fr>c</fr></del> a great firing without
getting spoiled.</ab>

<ab><m>Feather alum</m> is awkward to <tl>pestle</tl>, and it does not
pass through the <tl>sieve</tl>. Thus, one needs to grind it finely on
<tl><m>marble</m></tl>. And <m>the white one <del>that <fr>v</fr></del>
in powder that <pro>apothecaries</pro> sell</m> is good.<add> It is
ground better <del><fr>su</fr></del> in the <tl>mortar</tl> by <tl>pestling</tl>
&amp; dragging the <tl>pestle</tl>,<comment rid="c_107r_06"/> thus you will render it very
fine.</add></ab>

<ab><m><la>Crocum ferri</la></m> must be set ablaze in a
<tl><pro>glassmaker’s</pro> <fr>fournaise</fr></tl> for four
<ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms>.</ab>

</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p107r_1" categories="casting">

<ab>

<tl>Molds</tl> can only be used once because for
delicate things, like <pa>wormwood</pa> &amp; others, one needs to break
them, but before one <corr><del>them</del></corr> needs to dip them well into <m>water</m> in which
the twice reheated things dissolve easily. Otherwise, you would not be
able <del><fr>f</fr></del> to release your work without danger of
spoiling it.</ab></div>
    
<div id="p107r_1" part="y" continued="yes">

<ab><m><df>Good feather alum</df></m> is white and has a luster as
<add>of</add> <m>white <del><fr>c</fr></del> silk</m>. It is in pieces
long as a <ms><bp>finger</bp></ms>, &amp; is very breakable &amp; wooly
as <m>down</m>. The one made of <m>stone</m> is harder &amp; not so
good. <del>It</del> The best of the aforesaid quality is
fetched in <pl>France</pl>, near <pl>Rouan</pl>. The <m>feather alum</m> for our <m>sand</m> is <tl>pestled</tl> in a <tl>mortar</tl> and is
further ground on <tl><m>marble</m></tl>, especially since one
cannot think of passing it finely through the <tl>sieve</tl>, for it is
so fat &amp; wooly that it would not pass through it. It is this, with
its small soft <del>which</del> &amp; thin filaments, which gives
binding to the <m>sand</m> in a much more excellent fashion than
<m>cloth shearings</m> in the <m>founder’s earth of the <pro>founders
of great works</pro></m>, because these <m>cloth shearings</m> &amp;
<m>cloth waste</m> burn and <m>feather alum</m> <del>not</del> resists the
fire.</ab>

<ab>To enclose the <tl>molds</tl>, when you <del><fr>em</fr></del> throw
onto the things to mold your <m>liquid sand</m>, make <del>your</del> a circle
&amp; surround with well beaten <m>fatty earth</m>.<comment rid="c_107v_03"/></ab>

<ab><la>Archanum omnibus fere reconditum est in re fusoria,<lb/>

<del>ut</del>v<exp>idelicet</exp><comment rid="c_107v_05"/> res exprimenda formis, sive herba sit sive
<al><m>animal</m></al><lb/>
    
ut <al><m>lucerta</m></al>, <del>in</del> <del>af</del> <del>inting</del><comment rid="c_107v_06"/>
inmergatur primum in <m><pa>vini</pa> spiritum</m><lb/>

aprime rectificatum, deinde pulvere composito aspergatur<lb/>

sive illinatur (si pulvis in formam pultis redactus sit, ut<lb/>

assolet).</la><comment rid="c_107v_11"/></ab>

<ab>When you want to mold hollow, it is necessary that the
core be of the same material. And if the <al>snake</al> or
the animal is curved or folded, one ought to make the core of
several pieces.</ab>

<ab><emph>Test whether <m>distilled vinegar</m></emph> is
appropriate for eating away &amp; dissolving what will be in the animal
molded hollow.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

If you know that your <m>plaster</m> is not strong enough to withstand
the fire without cracking, do not be so scrupulous an observer of the
mixture put here that sometimes you <del><fr>mecties</fr></del> would
not diminish the quantity of <m>feather alum</m>
<del><fr>l</fr></del><comment rid="c_107v_12"/> a little bit, for it softens the
<tl>molds</tl> with its softness. Once reheated, do not pulverize it on
this occasion as fine as said, but leave it as the
<pro>apothecaries</pro> have ground it, for it does not hinder the
neatness of the cast &amp; gives more binding. When the <del><m>sand</m></del>
<tl>mold</tl>, <del>being</del> having set, retains the color of <m>brick</m> and is reddish, it is firmer.</ab>

</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p107r_1" categories="casting">



<ab>To hold the cores, some use <tl><m>wire of the same
metal</m> that they cast</tl> because it reduces <del>with</del> &amp;
melts with its counterpart, but because when melting or folding, the
core changes, some find it better to <del><fr>r</fr></del> use
<tl><m>iron wire</m></tl>, sharpened at the ends, because it holds
firmer &amp; having delicate ends, it appears as no more than a point of
a needle. And one can apply <m>gold</m> or <m>silver</m> before using
it for a work. If it makes a hole, one covers it with a small
<tl>chisel</tl>.</ab>

<ab><m>Eau-de-vie</m> prevents the <m>sand</m> from becoming porous &amp; does
not make little holes on the edges of the <tl>mold</tl> if the thing to
mold is well moistened with it. The holes &amp; blisters &amp; bubbles
are not made on the side of the <tl>mold</tl>, which is thick, but at
the edges, which are thinner.</ab>

<ab>One casts with <m>common silver</m>, with which <pro>goldsmiths</pro>
commonly work, which alloys <del>And <fr>qua</fr></del> indifferently.
And when one were to cast with <m>solder</m>, it would run even
better.</ab>

<ab><emph><df><m><de>Spat</de></m></df><comment rid="c_108r_02"/></emph> is a <m>whitish stone</m> which can
be found in <pl>Germany</pl>, &amp; mainly in <pl>Augsburg</pl>, which
one uses for <m>the most excellent sand that can be found for <m>lead</m></m>,
<m>tin</m>, <m>copper</m>, <m>silver</m> &amp; <m>gold</m>. And the more
it is used, the better it is. It is appropriate for casting flat things
in a <tl>frame</tl>. For round things, it is not as fitting nor does
it hold in the fire as well as the aforesaid one made with
<m>plaster</m>.</ab>

<ab>The shreds of <del><fr>cui</fr></del> thick, <m>greasy leather</m>
are <del><fr>p</fr></del>good<comment rid="c_108r_01"/> to cast in the <m>molten
copper and latten</m>, for it cleans it &amp; removes from it all its
<m>filth</m>. </ab>

</div>

</entry>