<entry><div continues="yes" id="p128r_1" categories="casting">





<ab>

You will see that it will torment it &amp; heat it very well and soon
render it very liquid &amp; ready to cast and be clarified, as it should
be. When it is in this state &amp; when it is very white and polished,
shining like <m>quicksilver</m>, prepare yourself to cast. And to this
effect, have some <m>lean delicate sand</m>, in a
<tl><fr>terrine</fr></tl> or another <tl>vessel</tl>, that you would
like to help yourself to. Make a pit in your <m>sand</m>, then, with your
<tl>pincers</tl>, take your <tl>well-reddened mold</tl> &amp; place it
in this pit of <m>sand</m>. Cover immediately the opening of your <tl>mold
</tl>in order that no <m>ash</m> &amp; dust enters inside, &amp; then
enclose it with <m>sand</m> up to the edge of the gate &amp; the vents. This done,
uncover your <tl>mold </tl>&amp; throw on top of your <m>well-melted
silver</m>, the <ms>size of a <pa>pea</pa></ms> or thereabouts, some
of this metallic grain, which will immediately spread through
all your <m>silver</m> &amp; make it boil &amp; turn. Cast as soon as
you have put in this substance, for it is this that is the secret to
making the <m>silver </m>run, since its crust heats it &amp; clarifies
it. You can cast <m>silver finer than the alloy from the <pl>capital
</pl>and like that of the <cn>real</cn></m>, but you must add this
grain in.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



With all of this, do not let yourself forget to put, before all things,
a little <m>borax </m>in the <m>melted silver</m>, for even though
<pro>goldsmiths</pro> do not put any in, nevertheless it is good, and I have
seen it practiced well. Next, one puts in the crust of the substance at
two different times &amp; then the metallic thing. Then make sure <ill/> that
it be placed at the end of your <tl>forge</tl>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



If you want to blow the <m>ash</m> that is around your <tl>mold</tl> when
you hold it between the <tl>pincers</tl>, hold it with the opening at
the bottom, &amp; blow.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



When <m>silver</m> is well melted, you can uncover it and blow with the
<tl>small bellows</tl>, not continually like with <m>gold</m>, but only
to cast out the <m>charcoals</m> in order to put in the substances that
make it run.</ab>

</div>

</entry>