<entry><div continues="yes" id="p141r_1" categories="casting" continued="yes">





<ab>Having therefore let your <al>crayfish</al> dry a little <env>in the
sun</env> or on its own, if it has eggs, they will shrink while drying
and will only be more beautiful. Therefore, make your <tl>slab of
<m>yellow <pro>potter</pro>’s earth</m></tl>, like for other figures,
lay your <al>crayfish</al> on top, the <del><fr>s</fr></del> back
<del>on top</del> <add>on the bottom</add>, &amp; the legs, belly &amp;
eggs, which are all the most fanciful parts to mold, on the other side
and on the top. Push the back down in the <tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl>,
up to near the legs, which is about halfway. And fix the body with an
<tl><m>iron wire</m> point</tl> in the middle &amp;, if it seems
necessary, another at the end of the tail. And in order that the
<add>big</add> legs show themselves lower than the head, which is
<del><fr>enf</fr></del> half sunken, extend them &amp;, from
underneath, add to them a little <m>clay</m> to raise them. Hide also the
horns in the <m>clay</m>, under the big legs, to arrange them afterward
as you like. As for the small legs, extend them on the <m>clay</m>
until the joint, and the other half of the legs remain above, curved,
for the first cast. However, in order that they do not move &amp;
detach, secure them well, not only on the <m>clay</m>, but
<del><fr>att</fr></del> fix them with <m>wax</m> &amp; a <tl>little hot
<m>iron</m></tl> right in the joints. And if you want to find the
most fanciful cast, you can attach the end of one of the legs with the
same <m>wax</m> on the body, or on one of the big legs, and also make, if
it has eggs, the tail to be half folded on the eggs, &amp; fix it in
this form with an <tl><m>iron wire</m> point</tl>. Above all special heed,
since the thing is <del><fr>s</fr></del> thus arranged, that it can be
well cleaned. Lastly, having rubbed the <al>crayfish</al> with
<m>eau-de-vie</m>, cast your <m>sand</m>. Having set, uncover the back of the
<al>crayfish</al>, the head &amp; the eyes &amp; its little pincers, the
big legs, and the small legs all along, for one needs to uncover the most
that one can, both the long horns &amp; the tail, except if you have
folded &amp; curved it to hold the eggs. Other animals</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">Secure what will  detach itself,
like the hairy brows near the mouth, with some <m>melted
wax</m> underneath.</ab>

<figure size="small" id="fig_p141v_1" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5R0NIbHoyNTNQRlk">
</figure>

<ab margin="left-middle">Uncover the most that you can, but take
heed that the notching that you make in the <tl>mold</tl> will release
well.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">Make the <tl>mold</tl> lean on the side
that will be the thickest of the animal.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">To paint it, one does the middle of the
back <del>mixed</del> with <m>vermilion</m> mixed with a little
<m>lake</m>, and the sides &amp; the belly &amp; underneath the legs is
with a flesh color made of <m>vermilion</m>, <m>white of ceruse</m>, a
little <m>yellow ocher</m>. As in this &amp; all other things, have
always the natural one in front of you to imitate it.<hr/></ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">Lay the horns on the big legs,
<del>&amp;</del><comment rid="c_156v_06"/> or make with <m>whitened latten wire</m> &amp;
<m>solder</m> them.</ab>

<ab margin="bottom" render="wide">Take heed <del><fr>d</fr></del><comment rid="c_082r_02"/> when
modeling to arrange the legs in such a way that they do not pass the
belly of the <al>crayfish</al>, <del><fr>Aultr</fr></del> and that,
placing them, they sit well on the belly, otherwise the legs would
break from the weight of the body, which is massive.</ab>


</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p141r_1" categories="casting">





<ab>are not uncovered as much. But because the <al>crayfish</al> is
awkward to burn &amp; clean, one needs to uncover as much as one can,
especially the little legs until the end, for these are awkward &amp; if
they were not to be uncovered and you were to have to pull them, you
could break something in the <tl>mold</tl>. While uncovering with the
<tl>point of a knife</tl>, or even a <tl>burin</tl> or other<tl> appropriate
thing</tl>, clean very carefully the <m>sand</m> which will be in the joints
&amp; elsewhere with your <tl>little brushes</tl>. And if something gets
detached, attach it with <m>wax</m>, as said. And attach also the horns
in the same way. And make also the gate, along the end of the little
legs, with some <m>wax</m>. And fill the holes made by the <tl><m>iron
wire</m> point</tl> with it. And once everything is quite neat &amp; more
than half is uncovered, <m>oil</m> your <del><fr>ut</fr></del><comment rid="c_142r_03"/> <tl>mold</tl>
<del>&amp; <fr>n’oubli</fr></del>, after having dipped the reverse in
<m>water</m>, &amp; do not forget to <m>oil</m> all the delicate parts
which are between the legs and the little pincers. Then, rub the
<al>crayfish</al> with <m>eau-de-vie</m>. And make your second cast,
having flattened the first <tl>mold</tl>, in order that the
<tl>clamps</tl> join better. Your <tl>mold</tl> must be wider on the
side that is imprinted than on the back. Do not open your <tl>mold</tl>
after the second cast unless it has been <m><tl>luted</tl></m> &amp; reheated
&amp; unless what is inside is burned. Do not forget to put
<m><la>crocum</la></m> among your <m>sand</m> when you mold <al>crayfish</al>,
for one needs to reheat strongly, &amp; the <m><la>crocum</la></m>
withstands marvelously. Molding a <al>crab</al> &amp; a
<al>crayfish</al>, it is<comment rid="c_142r_01"/> all the same. When you have uncovered
your <al>crayfish</al> on one side, only delay making the second cast as little you can, for <del><fr>el</fr></del> <al>crayfish</al> dry
<del><fr>se</fr></del> out. It is not just about uncovering the
<al>crayfish</al> well, in such a way that you see an entire half, but
take heed that your <tl>mold</tl> itself, in which you uncover, releases
well, for even if the <al>crayfish</al> were well burned, you
<del><fr>despoui</fr></del> would not be able to open your <tl>mold</tl>
without breaking.</ab>

<ab margin="top" render="wide">Repair with
<tl>penknives</tl>, <del><ill/></del><comment rid="c_142r_02"/> <tl>files</tl>, <tl>little
<fr>chaples</fr></tl>, or <tl>burins</tl>, &amp;c.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

Make all around them, as you see, a gate of <m>wax</m>, &amp; at the end
of the tail, also two or three, from which you make the principal
gate.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p142r_1" size="small" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Qkh2MDhvUkFnUW8">
</figure>

<ab margin="left-middle">Make a gate of <m>wax</m>, elongated in
a line like a <m>thick thread</m>, all along the end of the legs &amp;
at <del><fr>u</fr></del> the extremity of the tail. If there is also
some piece of leg or other part that is further away from the line of
the others, or raised above, or folded on its own, give it a gate of
<m>wax</m>, which from its extremity joins either at the body or at one
of the big legs or at some other place which receives a lot of
<m>metal</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">Having uncovered it, attach &amp; secure
with <m>wax</m> the two little hairy horns of the <al>crayfish</al>
&amp; other things which are not <corr><del><fr>en</fr></del></corr>
<del><fr>despoui</fr></del> secured at all.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p141r_1" categories="casting">

<head>Molding a <al>crayfish</al></head>


<ab margin="left-middle">The gate is made by the tail, very
thin.</ab>
    
</div>
    
    
<div id="p141r_1" part="y">
<ab margin="right-top">
If some little thing is missing from it, you<lb/>
can reattach it or else fill it with <m><pro>goldsmith</pro>’s<lb/>
cement</m>,<lb/>
because<lb/>
it<lb/>
can be<lb/>
painted.<comment rid="c_141r_01"/><hr/></ab>
    
</div>

<div id="p141r_1" part="y" continued="yes">
<ab render="wide">The <al>crayfish</al> is one of the most fanciful to mold, but also
provides an example for casting many other very difficult things. Males
are distinguished by the eggs that females carry and by the four
<del>legs</del> little white leglets at the back that males
<del><fr>ap</fr></del> have inside their tail, after the
eight main legs. It is only a good thing to dry them out a little,
because the lumps only come out <del>hard</del> rougher &amp; more
beautiful, for everything that is of shell does not diminish. It is true
that if you let them dry too much, these little inside leglets diminish
&amp; become more slender &amp; do not have as much body. If also they
are too dry, the flesh separates from the scales. Take heed, therefore,
to use moderation. They have some hair between the legs &amp; at the end
of the tail. And because all hair is vexing to mold, because it
gets mixed up with the <m>sand</m> &amp; is not released, you can burn it with
a <tl>hot <m>iron</m></tl> on the <al>crayfish</al>, so that no one sees
it. As for animals that have hair or feathers, it is necessary that you
anoint them with <m><add><pa>olive</pa></add> <pa>wheat</pa> oil</m>, which
is quickly dry &amp; which will keep the hair flat &amp; spread out.
Thus, you will have the form of your animal and the hair will also show,
but made wavy, and this is something which can be repaired. If your
<al>crayfish</al> has eggs, which are delicate and which
would be awkward to uncover without breaking, you would do better to
make the first cast on the belly &amp; eggs, in order that
<del>you</del> you only need to uncover the back, which is hard &amp;
easy to handle. And the belly &amp; the eggs will remain in the
<tl>mold</tl>, and one will need to burn them inside before opening your
<tl>mold</tl> <del>&amp; <fr>en</fr></del> for the second time. Thus,
<del>all</del> it will open easily, for what is burned will no longer be
attached. Thus, the second cast, which is made on the first one, which
has set well, separates easily from the first after having been
reheated, which is a singular secret for similar <tl>molds</tl>.</ab>


<ab margin="left-middle" render="tall">Do not forget to rub with
<m>eau-de-vie</m> before molding.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle"><al>Stag beetles</al>, <al>crayfish</al>
&amp; <al>crabs</al> are molded in the same fashion.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">If your <al>crayfish</al> <del><fr>a
d</fr></del> has no eggs, mold the back on top &amp; the belly on the
bottom. You can give it some.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">It can be molded hollow as for the body,
but the legs cannot. And to do it well, <al>crayfish</al> are already
fanciful enough to mold without looking for the hollow; this ought to be
reserved for <al>turtles</al>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">When you open your <tl>mold</tl>, you
will find the <al>crayfish</al> with <m>white bones</m>, but not in
powder. And without opening it, the <m>☿</m> will have
done nothing.</ab>

<ab margin="bottom"><hr/>Layer these <m>oil</m> colors very
transparently.</ab>

<ab margin="right-bottom"><hr/>To paint it, boil it with <m>wine</m> &amp; a
little <m>salt</m>, in order that they become very red, &amp; take this as
a model. Paint the back with <m>vermilion</m> mixed with <m>lake</m>,
&amp; the sides &amp; underneath<comment rid="c_141r_02"/> the belly &amp; the legs with
<m>vermilion</m>, &amp; <m>yellow ocher</m>, and <m>white</m>.</ab>



</div>
</entry>