<entry><div id="p003r_1" categories="stones">

<head><m>Counterfeit coral</m><comment rid="c_003r_02"/></head>

    <ab>
                  
                  
        <mark>+</mark>
    </ab>

<ab>One needs to first make the branches of <m>wood</m> or take a
bizarre <m>thorn branch</m>, then melt a <ms>lb</ms> of the most
beautiful <m>clear pitch resin</m> and put in one <ms>ounce</ms> of
<m>subtly ground vermilion</m> with <m><pa>walnut</pa> oil</m>, and if
you add in a little <m><pl>Venice</pl> <fr>laque platte</fr></m>,<comment rid="c_039v_02"/> the
color will be more vivid, and stir everything in the <m>resin</m> melted
over a <m>charcoal</m> fire and not of flame, for fear that it catches fire. 
Next dip in your branches while turning, &amp; if any filaments
should remain on it, turn the branch over the heat of the
<m>charcoal</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top" render="tall">

<df><m>Colophony</m></df> is nothing other than recooked <m>rosin</m>. To do
it well, take a <tl><m>leaded</m> pot</tl> &amp; melt the <m>resin</m>,
&amp; boil it over the <tl>brazier</tl> a good <ms><tmp>hour</tmp></ms>,
&amp; until it appears not to be thick, but clear &amp; liquid like
<m>water</m>, &amp; easily runs &amp; flows from the tip of a
<tl>stick</tl> with which you grind it, &amp; test it. Then pour it
through a <tl><m>coarse canvas</m></tl> or a <tl><m>very light tammy
cloth</m></tl>, such that when pouring it falls into the
strongest <m>vinegar</m> that you can find, for the <m>vinegar</m> gives
it strength &amp; prevents it from being so fragile. Reiterate this two
or three times &amp; it will be beautiful &amp; well purified. For
counterfeiting your <m>coral</m>, you can mix a <ms>quarter part</ms> of
<m>mastic</m> into your <m>purified rosin</m> to render it more firm
and more beautiful, &amp; if you were to take a single tear of
<m>mastic</m>, it would be all the better, but it would be too long.

</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">

<m>Sulfur</m> &amp; <m>vermilion</m> makes the same effect.</ab>

<ab margin="top">

The <m>coral</m> made of <m>gules red enamel</m> endures the
<tl>file</tl> and polishing.</ab>

<ab margin="right-top">

It is made like <m>cement</m> that is stronger mixed with <m><tl>pestled</tl>
<del>than of</del> glass</m> rather than with <m>brick</m>. Thus, here one
mixes well <tl>pestled</tl> <m>gules red enamel</m>, which
is red in body, with the <m>vermilion</m>. Thus with all colors of
<m>enamels</m>.</ab>

</div>

</entry>