<entry><div id="p118v_1" categories="casting" continued="yes">


<head>Casting in <tl>frames</tl></head>

<ab>The same <m>sand that was used in the cooked <fr>noyaulx</fr></m>,
composed, as is said, of <m>plaster</m>, <m>brick</m> &amp; <m>feather alum</m>, is excellent for casting in <tl>frames</tl>, and I
have experienced it thus: I <tl>pestled</tl> the pieces which had come out of
<tl><fr>noyau</fr> molds</tl> in a <tl>mortar</tl>, dragging the
<tl>pestle</tl> because this <m>sand</m> is very soft. I did not
pass it through the <tl>sieve</tl> because the <m>feather alum</m> mixed throughout, which binds it, would not pass, but I
ground finely upon <tl><m>marble</m></tl> what seemed to me too coarse.
And having prepared it thus, I moistened it with <df><m>sal ammoniac
water</m></df>, made of <m>sal ammoniac</m>, <ms>as much as two
<pa>walnuts</pa></ms>, in a <tl>bottle of <m>common water</m></tl>, <ms>the
same size as a <tl>bottle in which one boils <m>tisane</m></tl></ms>,<comment rid="c_118v_02"/> or in a
<tl>good pot of <m>water</m></tl>, so that you find <del><fr>d</fr></del>
the <m>water moderately salty</m>.<comment rid="c_118v_01"/> I mixed throughout <del><m>water</m>
of</del> <ms>half a <m>glass</m> </ms> of <m>sal ammoniac</m>, <del>two
<fr>ault</fr></del> two <del><fr>au t</fr></del> <tl><ms><m>silver</m>
spoonfuls</ms></tl> of <m>eau-de-vie</m>.
<del><fr>J’a</fr></del><comment rid="c_118v_03"/> Having thus moistened the <m>sand</m> in such a fashion
that it gives a good hold, nevertheless coming apart easily, I sprinkled my
medal with <m>charcoal pulverized</m> with a <tl>file</tl>, to rid it of
<m>oil</m> and all other <m>grease</m>, which are necessary to avoid,
for they would <del>make</del> hinder a good release. I blew on my medal
&amp; molded it, <add>and the female part of the <tl>frame</tl> once
filled</add>, I marked &amp; made a line on the reverse <del>of
the</del> &amp; edge of the medal &amp; on the nearby <m>sand</m> as well. In
order that the second <tl>frame</tl> <del><fr>s’em</fr></del> take the
imprint thereupon to denote the place for making the cast, <del>having
filled</del> <del>the female part of the <tl>frame</tl> being filled</del> I
uncovered the outline of the medal and pounced the whole side with
<m>pulverized charcoal</m>, and then filled the male part with <m>sand</m>.
<del>Once <fr>fai</fr></del> I separated the <tl>frame</tl> and did not hit the
corners of the <del><fr>d</fr></del> medal to make it release, because
that knocks the <m>sand</m> &amp; makes it <del><fr>esp</fr></del> crumble.
Rather, I struck the back of the <tl>frame</tl>, retaining the obverse of
the medal on the bottom, and it molded very neatly. If it had not
released thus, I would have waited to remove it until the
<tl>frames</tl> had been dried out over fire. I lit <del>the</del> a row
of charcoals between two little <tl>trivets of <m>iron</m></tl> in the
form that you see, and put the back <del>the</del> &amp; reverse of the
<tl>frames</tl> thereupon &amp; the imprint on top, because in this
way, they dry out gently. And if, by chance, from
being too moistened they should crack, it is on the back, which <del><fr>pr</fr></del>
takes the harshest fire, &amp; the imprint remains safe &amp;
whole.</ab>
<ab margin="left-middle">
For better, one needs to reheat the <m>sand used for the <fr>noyau</fr></m>
before using it in <tl>frame</tl>, until it no longer
contracts.</ab>


<ab margin="left-middle">
<emph><m>Excellent sand</m></emph></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">
Take a little of the same <m>sand, the finest that you can</m>, to cover
the medal with. <hr/></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

For medals &amp; flat things, the true heat of <m>lead</m> &amp;
<m>tin</m> is when it is melted gently.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

Note that I filled the <tl>frame</tl> before pressing it and did not
hit it at all, but rather pressed it only with the strength of my
<tl><bp>hands</bp></tl>, because hitting it makes it go awry. Secure
your <tl>frame</tl> that it does not shift at all, &amp; if you put some
<m>wetted sand</m> under it, it will only hold in place more firmly.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

Make the gate so that it is not too thick, so as not to overcharge the
medal, but wide enough near the medal that it embraces a third part. Do
not forget the vents.</ab>
    

    <ab margin="left-middle"><figure size="small" id="fig_p118v_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Rm5qaUJCNWVFWlk">
</figure></ab>
    
<ab margin="left-middle">

<df>To dry <tl>frames</tl></df> is to rid them of humidity so that they no
longer <m>smoke</m>, being nevertheless very hot.</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom" render="wide">


<df>Reheating</df> is to redden the <tl>frame</tl>, which is done for
<m>gold</m> and for <m>silver</m>.</ab>



</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p118v_1" categories="casting">





<ab> As I saw that they did not <m>smoke</m> anymore &amp; that, scratching
the back &amp; the front of the cast &amp; having found that they are
rough &amp; firm &amp; hard on one side and the other, which is a good
sign of their being quite dry, I left them to cool. I took some <m>fine
tin</m> <del><fr>f</fr></del>, one <ms>lb</ms>, &amp; one <ms>ounce</ms>
of <m>lead, fine &amp; new</m>. I melted it in a <tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl> until
it was, <del>a little</del> as it were, a little red. Being in this way quite hot
<del>I <m>smoked</m> &amp; not <fr>p</fr></del> &amp; being ready to cast, &amp; not
before, I <m>smoked</m> with the <m>smoke of a <tl>tallow candle</tl></m> all
sides of my <tl>frames</tl> &amp; imprint &amp; cast &amp; everything.
I set my <tl>frame</tl>, well joined, in the <tl>press</tl>. I drew my
<tl>crucible</tl> from the fire. I left it a little so that
the redness at the bottom of the <tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl> could <del>pass</del> <add>die
down</add>. And wanting to cast, I threw in two or three
<ms>grains</ms> of something like <m>pitch rosin</m>, &amp; at the same time the
<ms>size of a <pa>bean</pa></ms> of <m>looking-glass tin</m>, &amp; I
mixed, &amp; stirred the <tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl> a little, and I cast. And the
medal came out as neat as the principal.<comment rid="c_137r_03"/> I <m>smoked</m> it with the
<tl><m>candle</m></tl> &amp; cleaned it with <tl>small
brushes</tl>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">

Always cast through the foot of the medal because the head, which is
lower, will come out better &amp; make the cast longish. And when you
cast several medals in a <tl>large frame</tl>, they will come out
better.</ab>

</div>

</entry>