<entry><div id="p069r_2" categories="casting" continued="yes">

<head><m>Sand</m></head>

<ab>You should not choose for casting the one that is in any way so lean
&amp; arid that it does not have bond, like <m>the one from the
<env>sea</env></m> or <del><fr>desei</fr></del> <m>from <env>sandy
paths</env> dried out by the <env>sun</env></m>. But <add>choose</add>
them <del>or in <fr>t</fr></del> in the first place from
<env>quar<del><fr>reries</fr></del>ries</env> or <env>rock caves</env>,
because that one is best, provided that it is very fine. You will recognize the
vein of it if, among the greyish <env>rocks</env> or <env>quarries</env>
<del><fr>qu</fr></del> that seem to be made of <m><fr>arene</fr></m>,
you see, <tmp><env>after rainy weather</env></tmp>, certain small
patches like dust attached to the said <env>rocks</env>, or if due to the
humidity, a small piece of it flakes off, which easily crushes between your 
<tl><bp>hands</bp></tl>. You will also find in <m>lean soils</m> some which comes
off in <del><fr>lop</fr></del> large lumps like <m>stones of
<fr>tuf</fr></m> <del>and not</del>, or among <m><fr>terres
<pl>bolvenes</pl></fr></m>, which are much better than those in
<m>fatty &amp; strong earths</m>. And one ought not to take it from the
surface, for fear that it be mixed with <m>common earth</m>, but three
or 4 <ms><bp>feet</bp></ms> below &amp; the closest to the
<m><fr>tuf</fr></m> or <m>stone</m>. Since it comes out in large lumps one would say that it starts to take shape as a stone. But when it is wet, it
comes apart easily. One needs to make sure that when breaking it up it is quite granular, &amp; that when crushed between the
<tl><bp>fingers</bp></tl>, it renders itself into very great subtlety, <del>like 
impalpable</del>, keeping nevertheless its sandy asperity, without <m>muddying</m> the
<tl><bp>fingers</bp></tl> like <m>clay</m>. It is dried slightly on the
<del><ill/></del> fire,<comment rid="c_069r_05"/> then it is <tl>pestled</tl> &amp; passed finely through a <tl>double
sieve</tl> or a <tl><m>linen</m> sleeve</tl>, then is moistened with
<m>wine</m> or <m><fr>magistra</fr></m> &amp;c / <emph><la>Verte</la></emph><comment rid="c_069r_02"/></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

The <pl>Toulouse</pl> <pro>molder</pro> reheats it strongly then grinds
it finely on <tl><m>marble</m></tl> and passes it through a
<tl><m>linen</m></tl> &amp; moistens <del>pass</del> it with
<m>wine</m>. He makes the cast very broad &amp; <del>not</del>
flat &amp; barely deep. He casts <m>pure latton used for <fr>trebuschets</fr></m>
&amp; similar thin things. He casts very hot.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

Try <m>calcined vitriol</m>.</ab>



</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p069r_2" categories="casting">





<ab>The <m>sand <env>near my area</env></m> is very excellent. But one ought
to, in order to make an excellent work, take it fresh, which has been hardly
put to work. For it dries out after having been cast several times &amp; is
lean &amp; has no body. If you cast some fine work which has hardly any
thickness, it is necessary that your substance of <m>copper</m> be very
hot so that it penetrates &amp; runs. Some mix <m>lead</m> in this
melt, but it is for large works &amp; not for small ones.</ab></div>

<div id="p069r_2" part="y" continued="yes">
<ab><m>Sand from <al>oxen</al> feet, burned twice &amp; finely ground</m>,
melts more neatly with <m>copper</m> than <m>sand</m> that I have seen,
&amp; without crust. I have cast a high relief medal with it, and
<del><fr>f</fr></del> with a thickness as delicate as a <tl>knife</tl>
blade or a <tl>card</tl>. And it was hollow on one side, opposite the
relief, which was on other side.</ab>

<ab>It is necessary that <m>lean sands</m> be more moistened than
others, namely with <m><fr>magistra</fr></m> or good <m>pure wine</m> or
<m>boiled wine with <pa>elm tree</pa> roots</m> &amp; similar things.
But <m>very fine sands</m>, like <m>burned linen</m>, which is fatty &amp;
soft on its own, want to be applied dry.</ab>

<ab>All <m>moistened sand</m> wants to be strongly beaten &amp; stirred, to
be ground finely &amp; to flatten out the clods that it makes in itself
when it is bathed.</ab>

<ab>The <m><pa>olive</pa> oil</m> that some mix in with <m>beaten egg
glair</m> makes it become porous.</ab>

<ab><m>Sand of calcined glass</m> withstands several fusions, but there
is nothing like the first ones. It also becomes porous.</ab>

<ab><m>Latten</m> comes out well on its own, but it runs too quickly. It is
good to mix it with a little <m>copper</m>, like a <ms>quarter
part</ms>, with the <m>substance of skillets</m>.</ab>

<ab><pro>Founders</pro> do cast <tl>frames</tl> up to 30 or 40 <ms>lb</ms>,
but not more.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

It is good for big work, but for small ones it is troublesome for
releasing <del>It</del> because it crumbles. It is good that
it be alloyed with some fatty thing which has bond such as <m>molded
tripoli</m> or <del><fr>ab</fr></del> <m>burned felt</m> or <m>sal
ammoniac</m> or <m>tripoli</m> &amp; similar things.</ab>



</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p069r_2" categories="casting" continued="yes">





<ab>When you have molded, it is good to reheat your mold on the fumes of
the substance you are melting, because the cast is imprinted with the quality
<del><fr>e</fr></del>of<comment rid="c_070r_03"/> the <m>metal</m>, which afterward runs more easily in something that comes from it.</ab>

<ab> <m><al>Human</al> bones</m> are the best for casting once
calcined.</ab>

<ab>To cast neatly, it is necessary that your substance be quite hot
&amp; to achieve this, when your substance is melted, throw in some
<m>iron scales</m>, either in powder or otherwise, <del><fr>E</fr></del> for
it heats <m>copper</m> a lot &amp; cleanses it of its <m>grease</m>. At the
end, when you want to cast, add some <m>saltpeter</m>, by folding your
additions in a <tl><m>paper</m></tl> in order that everyone may not know what you
mix in.</ab>

<ab><m><al>Sheep</al> foot bones</m> are even better than <m>those of <al>oxen</al>
foot</m>.</ab>

<ab><m>Oil</m> &amp; <m>tallow</m> make it very porous, &amp;
    <m><tl>pestled</tl> glass</m>, &amp; <m>copper</m> alone.<comment rid="c_070r_02"/></ab>

<ab><m><fr>Cendrée</fr><comment rid="c_040v_01"/> earth</m> molds very neatly.</ab>

<ab><m>Ash</m> does not have enough body to withstand
<m>copper</m>.</ab>

<ab>It is better not to mix the <m>sands</m>, but to fill the <tl>frame</tl> with
one only.</ab>

<ab><m>Latten</m> is always fatty, &amp; does not mold neatly. One finds
that it comes out better alloyed with a <ms>quarter</ms> of
<m>copper</m>, but let it be cast very hot.</ab>

    <ab><m>Copper</m> comes out well with a bit of <m><fr>metal</fr></m>.<comment rid="c_016v_05"/> If you mix
in <m><fr>metal</fr></m> within <m>latten</m>, it will be more brittle &amp; more
troublesome.</ab>

<ab><m>Slightly coarser sand</m> has more body.</ab>

<ab><m>Sand from <del><fr>corp</fr></del> rock</m> is always better,
which seems like <m><fr>tuf</fr></m> in lumps, which has a beautiful
&amp; very fine grain, &amp; a little fatty. One <tl>pestles</tl> it, then one
dries it in a <tl>skillet</tl> on the fire, until it <del>is</del> no longer
<m>smokes</m>, then one passes it through a fine &amp; <tl>double sieve</tl>,
&amp; one molds with it.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<m>Copper</m> or <m>latten</m> cannot come out well if the medal does
not sufficient thickness, &amp; if it does not have it, give it some
with <m>wax</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

Some cast through a hole made in the middle of the reverse side of the
medal.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

Some, wanting to cast large works in <m>latten</m>, <del>in it</del>
mix in the <m>sand</m> some <m><tl>pestled</tl> glass</m> to give the <m>earth</m>
bond. But it makes it porous, and the work needs to be repaired.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

One puts in <m>lead</m> for a large work to make it run, but not
<del>not<lb/>
for</del> in a small one because it would leave <m>filth</m> all around
the work.</ab>



</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p069r_2" categories="casting">





<ab><m>Copper</m> <del>is <fr>meil</fr></del> and <m>latten</m> are proper to
cast &amp; at the right heat when they throw off, while stirring them in the
<tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl>, a very white flame &amp; that the bath is very
liquid.</ab>

<ab>Some cast in <m>well ground ceruse</m> <del>for
the</del>, others in <m>flour</m> moistened several times with
<m>oil</m> <del>&amp; <fr>g</fr></del> &amp; dried <env>in the
sun</env>.</ab>

<ab>Others, for casting in <m>lead</m>, <m>old
<pro>printers</pro>' type</m> or the <m>composition thereof</m>.</ab>

<ab>Others put into the <m>tin</m> or <m>lead</m> a substance of
<m>fixed quicksilver</m> which makes it run.<comment rid="c_070v_01"/></ab>

</div>
</entry>