<entry><div id="p132r_2" categories="casting" continued="yes">

<head>Method for reheating the <tl>molds</tl></head>

<ab>Light <m>charcoals</m> in the <tl>forge</tl>, &amp; then arrange
them in rows in a corner of it, according to the size of your
<tl>mold</tl>, in such a way that it can be furnished with three or 4
<ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> all around, and especially at the bottom of
the <tl>mold</tl>, which is the thickest <del>and which</del>. Your
<m>charcoals</m> thus arranged, place your <tl>molds</tl> on top of
them, &amp; not on a <tl>grate</tl>, as some do, because they
would take the fire too harshly. And leave for some time thus, &amp;
little &amp; by little, warm your <tl>oven</tl>, always adding some lit
<m>charcoal</m>. And as long as the <tl>mold</tl> is humid, the
<m>charcoals</m> will be as if died down from below. But as it dries,
they will kindle by themselves. And when it is dry on one side, turn it to
the other. And when it is dry on both, &amp; it will no longer <m>smoke</m>. At
that moment, invigorate the fire &amp; cover it with lit
<m>charcoals</m>. And as it will begin to redden, do not blow the
<m>charcoals</m> with the <tl>little bellows</tl>, for this would make it
<del>blow</del> burst. And similarly, when it is red, keep it well
covered with lit <m>charcoals</m> &amp; do not uncover it, for it would
crack. Make sure <env>wind from a window</env> does not beat upon it. Let
cool</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

When you want to reheat your <tl>molds</tl>, <del>&amp;</del> be they
<m><tl>luted</tl></m> or not, mark on the belly the place to put at the bottom,
against the lit <m>charcoals</m>, <del>that</del> because if the
ardor of the fire were to make them crack, it would be better that this be
at the belly &amp; from underneath than on the back.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

If your <tl>mold</tl> is small, one ought not to leave it
<del>rest</del> so much in the fire, for it corrupts and cracks there,
for it reheats more quickly than a big one.</ab>



</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p132r_2" categories="casting">





<ab>by itself. When it begins to redden, it is soon red everywhere.
But make sure, through the gate, that it is red at the bottom &amp; that
nothing appears black.</ab>

</div></entry>