<entry><div id="p056v_1" categories="painting;varnish" continued="yes">



<head>Painter</head>

<ab>The <m>lake</m> &amp; <del><m>florey</m></del> <m>rosette of
<pl>Ghent</pl></m> &amp; others lose their color &amp; die in the
air.</ab>

<ab>All <tl><m>marble</m></tl> on which a <tl>knife</tl> can <po>prick</po> is
worth nothing for grinding fine colors.</ab>

<ab><m>Chalk</m> has no body in <m>oil</m>. <m>Ceruse</m> is
appropriate. But <m>lead white</m> more excellent. <m>Ceruse</m> is the
whitest, when ground first in <m>water</m>, the <m>lead white</m>
grayish. But <del>the white</del> it takes on its perfect whiteness in
<m>oil</m>.</ab>

<ab>When you grind your colors, first clean your <env>workshop</env>
well, for when walking, if you stir up dust, this will damage your
colors, which will never be beautiful if they are not very
<del><fr>be</fr></del> clean.</ab>

<ab><m>Florey</m> must not be mixed with <m><fr>azur d'esmail</fr></m>
or another, for it makes it green.</ab>

<ab>For <tl>palettes</tl> to paint, <m>ivory</m> is excellent, <m>knots
of the <pa>fir tree</pa></m>, the <m><pa>pear tree</pa></m>, &amp; if it
is a <m><pa>walnut tree</pa></m>, make sure the grain of the <m>wood</m>
runs lengthwise.</ab>

<ab><del><fr>L</fr></del> One always needs to apply imprimatura
<del><fr>d</fr></del>on<comment rid="c_056v_01"/> <m>wood</m> to paint there in <m>oil</m> in
order to fill the holes &amp; unevenness, and make imprimatura with some <m>stil de
grain yellow</m> &amp; <m>ceruse</m> tempered in <m>oil</m>, then soften
with a <tl>feather</tl>, which flattens better than a
<tl>paintbrush</tl>. Or when the imprimatura is dry, scrape strongly
with a <tl>knife</tl>.</ab>

<ab>To use <m><fr>azur d'esmail</fr></m> in <m>oil</m>, one needs to
choose the most delicate. And to render it subtle, one ought not to grind it,
for this makes it whiten. But one needs to wash it, &amp; the coarsest
going to the bottom, choose the one that is above in the
<m>water</m> or, by inclination, pour out the cloudy <m>water</m>, then
gather the <m>azure</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



    <comment rid="c_056v_02"/><pro>The one who <add>makes a profession of</add> working in
<m>oil</m></pro> will hardly work well in <m>distemper</m> if he has not
been trained well from adolescence. For the way of working is different,
because when washing the <tl>paintbrush</tl> for <m>distemper</m>,
one always leaves it humid. And on the contrary, when one cleans the
<tl>paintbrush</tl> in <m>oil</m> to soften, one wipes the
<tl>paintbrush</tl> well. Otherwise, the work would run &amp;
would soon be all disfigured.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



The <pl>Italians</pl> soften by hatching with a large flattened
<tl>paintbrush</tl> which makes serrations.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



And they do not lay their shadow all at once like the <pl>Flemish</pl>,
but make them hatching lightest toward the light then a little darker
next &amp; finally a little blacker to better make project &amp; come
out.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



In <m>distemper</m> do not mix your different colors together
<del>But</del>, for this makes them die, but use each separately. And in
order that they do not dry &amp; that you have time to soften, moisten
the back of the <m>canvas</m>.</ab>



</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p056v_1" categories="painting;varnish">





<ab>

<m>Lake</m> takes long to dry in <m>oil</m> and for that reason one must
grind some <m>glass</m> with it. But one needs to choose <m><fr>cristallin</fr></m>
because it is cleaner. And because it would be too difficult to grind by
itself, one must redden it on the fire, then when entirely red throw it
into <m>cold water</m>, &amp; it will crumble &amp; pulverize
easily for grinding it afterward. Being well ground <del>it</del> with a lot of
<m>water</m>, it resembles ground <m>lead white</m>, but for all this it has
no body. I think it would be good for casting.</ab>

<ab hand="handd">

<comment rid="c_057r_02"/><m>Lead white</m> is made with <m>plate lead</m>, beaten thin &amp; put
under the <env><tl><m>dung</m> heap</tl></env>.</ab>

<ab hand="handd">

<m>White varnish of <m>turpentine</m> or of <m><pa>spike lavender</pa>
oil</m> and <m>turpentine</m></m> is colored with <m>pulverized
<fr>terra emerita</fr></m>, making it boil together. It gives a gold
color on <m>silver</m> and more beautiful if it is burnished. It is dry
in a <tmp>quarter of an hour</tmp>. <pa><m>Aloe</m></pa> would make brighter
color still, but it takes long to dry &amp; the other is dry in <tmp>a quarter
of an hour</tmp>, <tmp>in winter</tmp> as well as
<tmp>summer</tmp>.</ab>

<ab hand="handd">

Good <m>lake</m> moistened with <m>saliva</m> is promptly rendered dark.
That from <pl>Florence</pl> is too gummed.</ab>

<ab hand="handd">

If you make a layer of <m><pro>printers</pro>' ink</m> on <m>velvet</m>
and there apply <m>gold leaf</m> and then stretch the <m>velvet</m>, it
will appear grainy as if there were <m>gold powder</m> disseminated on
it.</ab>

<ab>

<comment rid="c_057r_01"/><m>Vermilion</m> ground by itself is wan and pale, but ground after
<m>lake</m>, it is more beautiful.</ab>

<ab>For ridding <tl><m>marbles</m></tl> of grease, one grinds
<m>common ashes</m> on it, which is good afterward to make the first
imprimatura of a panel that is prepared in <m>oil</m> in order to seal
the cracks &amp; chinks of the <m>wood</m>. It has more body than
<m>chalk</m> &amp; it has <del><m>chalk</m></del> a certain fattiness.
One mixes it with the said <m>chalk</m> or <del><fr>ra</fr></del>
with the colors collected from the <tl>vessel</tl> where one cleans the
<tl>paintbrush</tl>. It is desiccative and spares the color.
<del>On</del> Once this first imprimatura is made on the <m>wood</m>, one
scrapes with a <tl>knife</tl> to even it. Next, one makes there a second imprimatura
of <m>ceruse</m> or of the <add>meanest</add> colors mixed together. In
a painting in <m>oil</m> <add>on <m>canvas</m></add>, one applies only
one imprimatura, and the same <m>ashes</m> can be used there. Also, after one
has ground a color, one grinds some <m>pith of coarse bread</m> on it to
rid the <tl><m>marble</m></tl> of grease.</ab>

</div>
</entry>