<entry><div id="p126v_3" categories="casting" continued="yes">



<head>Plants difficult to burn in the <fr>noyau</fr></head>

<ab>Any plant which has a hard stem &amp; like <m>wood</m> is very
difficult to burn in the <fr>noyau</fr>, such as <pa>asparagus</pa>,
<pa>thyme</pa>, &amp; similar things, because they stay as <m>charcoal</m>
in the small conduits, &amp; if they do not reduce well into
<m>ashes</m>, it is not possible to empty them from the <tl>mold</tl>.
Some reheat them, to do this, two or <del><fr>d</fr></del> three
times. Others, putting several plants together in the <tl>mold</tl>,
pass through <del>threads</del> the plants &amp; the <del><fr>es</fr></del><comment rid="c_126v_01"/>
<del><tl>molds</tl></del> <tl>circle of <m>earth</m></tl>,
which is to receive the <m>tempered sand</m>, <del><fr>plusi</fr></del></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

This does not proceed from plants that have a stem with lines, because
<pa>rosemary</pa> burns well, but it is in the nature of certain
plants.</ab>



</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p126v_3" categories="casting">

<ab>some threads, as much to secure the plants, in order that they do not
rise <del>by</del> when you throw in your <m>clear sand</m>, as to
give them venting when the <tl>mold</tl> is reheated. For, in doing this,
the <del><tl>mold</tl></del> <add>thread</add> burns &amp; leaves some
empty space around the plants, which serves as vents &amp; places for
evacuating, &amp; to give air to the plants so that they burn better.
For what makes them stay as <m>charcoal</m> is that they burn in a
closed fire &amp; without empty space because of their fine sprigs. Try,
therefore, to thicken the main stem with a little <m>melted wax</m>,
&amp; let it cool, then mold it. And when the <m>wax</m> melts, it airs
it, the principal stem, with space &amp; as if loose so that it burns
better. Or else, anoint them with <m>oil of <fr>petrol</fr> or
sulfur</m>, <add>of</add> <m>turpentine</m>, <m>oil of
brick</m> &amp; similar things, or <m>aquafortis</m> or
<m>eau-de-vie</m>, or make <m>sands</m> with <m><la>crocum</la></m>, <m>iron
scales</m>, loops of <m>iron</m>, <m>emery</m> &amp; things that
withstand several <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms> of great firing.</ab>
</div>




<div id="p126v_3" part="y">
<ab><m>Animal bones</m> are not so difficult to burn &amp; reduce to
<m>ashes</m>, because once the <m>flesh</m> is burnt, the <m>bones</m>
remain loose &amp; the weight of the <m>quicksilver</m> makes them break
&amp; disintegrate, once calcined &amp; burnt.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle" render="tall">
<pa>Asparagus</pa> always stays as <m>charcoal</m>, like little pins.
Try to take it, and <pa>thyme</pa>, at the beginning, when they are
growing, so that their stem is still thin.</ab>

</div></entry>