<entry><div id="p112v_1" categories="casting" continued="yes">



<head><del>Molding</del> Making the arrangement and disposition
of the animal</head>

<ab continued="yes">Having made provision of <m><df>fatty earth</df></m> called
<m>clay</m>, that should be grey because that commonly is the best, or
another which has good binding &amp; which should be well prepared &amp;
beaten, such that it is handleable without attaching to the
<tl><bp>hands</bp></tl> nor the work, make a lasagna or like a

cake of this <m>earth</m> equally flattened with a <tl>round

stick which <pro>pastry makers</pro></tl> use, which should be a little
thicker than a <ms><bp>thumb</bp></ms>. And on this
<po>cake</po>, arrange your animal, <del><fr>aya</fr></del>
imitating in that its nature &amp; <del><fr>fa</fr></del> the fashion in
which it commonly turns itself. And first, with a good <tl>needle</tl>,
pierce it from underneath in the middle of the throat &amp; up to
<del><fr>u<ill/></fr></del> the top bone of the head. Retract the
<tl>needle</tl>, &amp; in its place &amp; its hole, put the <tl>point of
an <m>iron wire</m></tl> of such a length that it suffices to hold the
head of the animal as <del><fr>q</fr></del><comment rid="c_112v_05"/> high as it must be, &amp; if
the skin moves into the inside <del>&amp;</del> when you put in the
<tl>point</tl><figure size="x-small" id="fig_p112v_2" link="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1iZMenWzoJUKZ6D5-OgX3-Sc4Ax6PTZDV">
</figure>,<comment rid="c_112v_01"/> pull it out with <del><fr>a</fr></del><comment rid="c_033r_01"/>
<del><tl>point</tl></del> the edge of your <tl>small pincers</tl>, &amp;
arrange it as it was. Push the other end of the <tl>point</tl> in the
<po>cake</po> of <m>clay</m>. Thus, the head will be held high,
which will have better grace, &amp; being secured, next, arrange the gesture
of the body &amp; the feet &amp; the entanglement as you think will
look best. And so that it is secure &amp; does not move at all when you
cast in the <m>sand</m>, <del>put</del> secure the legs
<del>&amp; the <fr>corp</fr></del> with little <tl>points of <m>iron
wire</m></tl>, having already made the first hole with a very sharp
<tl>needle</tl>. Do the same on the body parts that you will deem necessary,
<del>arranging</del> making sure that the <tl>points</tl>
passing through the animal are fixed in the <po>cake</po> of earth
and not so far in front that they jut out beyond the body of the animal
by a</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



Take a <tl>fine needle of <m>steel</m></tl>, &amp; which is the sharpest
possible, in order that, making with it the first hole to place the <tl>points
of <m>iron</m></tl>, it passes without forcing anything, &amp; by its
roughness does not push in or pull out the skin. Next, put in a thickish
<tl>point of <m>iron</m></tl> in thick places &amp; thin ones in thin
places. But heed as a secret to not plant, in the first go, the
<tl>point</tl> passed through the animal in the slab of <m>earth</m>,
<del><fr>for</fr></del> but having planted it, take it out of the
<m>earth</m> &amp; not out of the animal, &amp; <del>do <fr>ains</fr></del> 
next, fix it. This is done because, by fixing it the
first time, it pushes in the skin of the <al>snake</al>, and by taking
the <tl>point</tl> out, it replaces the skin in its original state.</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">

<hr/>
<comment rid="c_112v_02"/>When you put again the <tl>points</tl> you have already used, clean them
well of <m>rust</m> so that they do not take away some skin.<hr/></ab>

<ab margin="bottom" render="wide" continued="yes">

The principal disposition of your arrangement is to <del><fr>di</fr></del> place
the head raised &amp; looking sideways. For this effect, pierce the head
on a <tl>solid plank or table</tl> <del>&amp; <ill/></del>, making the
<tl>point</tl> pass through the bottom of the throat,
<del><fr>s&#8217;arrestan</fr></del> entering into the top of the head,

<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p112v_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5c3dzVlNzcUd6MnM">
</figure><comment rid="c_112v_03"/>

</ab>



</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p112v_1" categories="casting">


<ab continues="yes">bit, <del><fr>qua</fr></del> so that <del><fr>t</fr></del><comment rid="c_113r_01"/> you can
take it out if you need to. And take heed that it is necessary that
these <tl>points</tl> be of the most delicate <m>iron wire</m> possible
which can support the size of the animal. For the more delicate it is, the
smaller the hole that it leaves appears. However, one needs 
different thicknesses of these, because <del><fr>il</fr></del><comment rid="c_128r_02"/>
<del><fr>de</fr></del> the <tl>points</tl> which are put in the body
&amp; in thicker places, like under the throat, ought to be longer &amp;
stronger than the ones of the legs &amp; thin parts, where the
<tl>needles</tl> ought to be subtle &amp; delicate, almost like the
thickest <m>strings of <mu>spinets</mu></m>. And it is better that they
be of <m>iron wire</m>, which is firmer than <m>the one of latten</m>.
And if the end of the tail, or the end of a nail or a leg, ought to be
joined to the body, do not put the <tl>point</tl> there, not to corrupt
it. But place <m>wax</m>, <ms>as much as a <m>grain of
<pa>millet</pa></m></ms>, between the body &amp; <del><fr>ce</fr></del><comment rid="c_113r_04"/>
<del>which</del> the end of the tail, then with a bit of
flattened &amp; hot <m>iron wire</m>, touch this <m>wax</m> &amp; join
by lightly pressing. Thus having placed your animal on the
<po>cake</po> shaped like a <mu>mandore</mu>, place all around a
circle of the same

 <figure size="small" id="fig_p113r_2" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5YkE1Vm1ZMmRoVm8">
</figure>

<m>earth</m>, in this way,

 <figure size="small" id="fig_p113r_3" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5aW1sekxQWGJJY0E"><caption>b</caption>
</figure> &amp; join everything well together in a circle, then, with a
big <tl>knife</tl>, with which you have cut your <po>cake</po> to
the right size, trim the outside which exceeds it, &amp; place there a
piece to close it as you see in b.<comment rid="c_113r_02"/> Then, with a <tl>small curved
instrument</tl>, mark on the inside of the circle the thickness you want
to give to the <tl>mold</tl>, which will be for a <al>common snake</al>
as thick as two <ms><bp>thumbs</bp></ms>, in order that when you
cast in your <m>wetted sand</m>, you will see when it is thick enough. All of
this carefully arranged, moisten well everywhere with good <m>eau-de-vie</m>, with a <tl>paintbrush</tl>, the body of the animal
which is uncovered. For there is the secret, <del>of the most</del>
kept well hidden, because everything that will be <del><fr>v</fr></del><comment rid="c_113r_05"/>
touched by <m>eau-de-vie</m> will undoubtedly come out very
neatly &amp; without <del>porosity</del> any <df>small eyes or holes</df>
that one calls porosity, which usually come not at the back &amp; in the
thick sides of the <tl>mold</tl>, but on the edges. And as soon as you
have thus moistened everything with <m>eau-de-vie</m>, cast
in your <m>wetted sand</m> without letting the <m>eau-de-vie</m> dry,
which evaporates promptly. And wet it thus.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle" continues="yes">

<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p113r_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5MDEzX0RhXzJGcXc">
</figure><comment rid="c_113r_03"/><lb/>

and make sure that the <tl>point</tl> is longish, depending on how much you want to elevate the head, and that it be pointed on both ends. Once placed
thus, plant your <al>snake</al> on the slab of <m>earth</m>, &amp;
arrange the head first and then the rest.<hr/>

</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



If, after you have placed your animal on your <m>clay</m>
<po>cake</po>, you are distracted with other occupations, rub your
animal with <m>eau-de-vie</m>, &amp; under the belly, so that it
does not dry &amp; attach itself to the <m>earth</m>.

<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p113r_4" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Qm8wSlJPOWxfZWM">
</figure>
<hr/>
</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle" render="tall">

If, when you pierce your animal, it renders <m>water</m> from the bottom
of the side of the belly on the slab of <m>earth</m>, clean it well
with <m>cotton</m> for the <m>sand</m> that<lb/> 
<hr/>
<m>Eau-de-vie</m> in three goes.<lb/>
<hr/>
would touch it would be lumpy. If
it is on top of the animal, clean it very carefully and touch it
&amp; moisten well with <m>eau-de-vie</m>.

</ab>

</div></entry>