<entry><div id="p124v_3" categories="casting" continued="yes">



<head>A means to make the gate for small female <al>lizards</al></head>

<ab>Because you always have to make the gate by the tail, and because it is
<del><fr>u</fr></del>so<comment rid="c_124v_03"/> delicate and thin that the <del>gate would struggle</del>
<m>metal</m> would run with difficulty, especially when it is curled,
roll <m>wax</m> in little threads of this thickness

    <figure size="small" id="fig_p124v_2" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dWU4UEtpX0hBV0k">
</figure>

and apply some with the <tl>hot <m>iron wire</m></tl>, as is said, one at
the end of the tail &amp; the others, that are applied in the same way,
from one <del>edge</del> <add>side</add> of the tail to the other, as
you see depicted. But take heed to make sure that with the <tl>end of
the hot <m>iron wire</m></tl>, the end of the <m>wax</m> barely touches
the animal, for the <m>sand of the second cast</m> will not touch this part.
But make sure that the end of the <m>wax</m> arranges itself only at the
edge of the empty part of the first <tl>mold</tl>. Make also conduits of
<m>wax</m> around the legs &amp; around the contours of the body which
are a little long, &amp; they will serve as feeders for the
molded thing.</ab>

<ab margin="right-bottom" continued="yes">

<add>Follow here<lb/>
above</add> <mark>🝋</mark><comment rid="c_124v_04"/>

</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle" render="tall">
<hr/>
<add>When the tail, which is delicate and closer to the gate, comes out
well, the rest will also come out well.</add></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle" render="tall">



The principal thing is that the ears of the <al>snake</al> come out
well-molded.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle" render="tall">



Your gate must be very thin at the entrance of the animal &amp; of the
<ms>thickness of a <tl>knife</tl></ms>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle" render="tall"><figure id="fig_p124v_1" size="small" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5aGQ0OTFCTklrQ0k">
</figure></ab>


</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p124v_3" categories="casting">


<ab margin="top" render="full" continues="yes">

<mark>🝋</mark><comment rid="c_125r_01"/> From small rolls, you make your gates and vents without danger of
crusting &amp; removing<lb/>
anything from the <tl>mold</tl>, because the
<m>wax</m>, being taken away, leaves the empty space all made. Make
your vents</ab>
    
<ab margin="left-middle" render="wide">
coming from the head, which is in the bottom, toward the
gate. Make also your gate so that it is <del>too</del> <add>but a
little</add> thick, and make within its course two or three notches, for
this breaks up the fury of the <m>metal</m></ab>

<ab><hr/>&amp; from these conduits &amp; feeders, you can also
put in small threads of <m>wax</m> which are joined to the body, in
order that the <m>metal</m> goes more easily from one part to another
&amp; promptly runs everywhere. And from these conduits, you lead your
gate &amp; your vents without spoiling anything.<hr/></ab>

<ab>and makes it flow with ease,
without bubbling nor making excessive fumes, which hinders its run.<lb/>
You can divide it also in two or three branches thus
        
<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p125r_2" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bDlqQzJZemktSFk">
</figure>
        
when it approaches the molded thing, and always make holes in the
gate.</ab>
    

</div>

</entry>