<entry><div id="p112r_4" categories="casting" continued="yes">

<head>Putting to death the animal for molding</head>

<ab>You need to be careful not to wound it in taking it. And, having put
it in a <tl><m>glass</m> bottle</tl> <del><fr>d</fr></del><comment rid="c_112r_05"/> with
<m>bran</m>, or in a <tl>barrel</tl> <del>full</del> half full of
<m>fresh &amp; humid earth</m>, if you want to store them or keep them a
<tmp>long time</tmp>, give them live <al>frogs</al> &amp; not dead ones
to eat. For if you keep them without feeding them, they wither &amp;
grow thin &amp; have long wrinkled <fr><del>aulx</del></fr><comment rid="c_112r_06"/> skins. Thus the best would be to
mold it as soon as <del>after</del> possible
<del><fr>apre</fr></del> after it has been taken. But before, put it to
death in this way. Place it in a <tl>clean bottle or vessel</tl> so
that it would collect no dust. And put inside such a quantity of <m>good
vinegar</m> &amp; <m><bp>urine</bp></m> that it can be covered. And shake it
&amp; torment it therein until it is dead, which will be in <ms><tmp>an hour or a half</tmp></ms>. But if you are in a
hurry</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

To know if it is quite dead, take it out of the <m>vinegar</m> and take
it by the tail. If it moves it, do not mold it for it still has feeling,
&amp; when piercing it, it would draw back &amp; spoil the mold.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<al><env>Water</env> snakes</al> hardly bite.</ab>



</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p112r_4" categories="casting">




<ab>to cast, make him take through the mouth some good <m>eau-de-vie</m> or else mix a little with the <m>vinegar</m>. And soon it will
be dead, without any lesion which deforms it. For large animals, for
whom one would need a lot of <m>eau-de-vie</m>, one uses
<m>vinegar</m> and <del><fr>er</fr></del> <m><bp>urine</bp></m>. But for small
ones, only <m>eau-de-vie</m>, which is done sooner.
When your animal is dead, take it out &amp; clean it carefully of its
old skin, if it sheds, or of the <m>filth</m>, or of the <al>lice</al>, like
<al>lizards</al> have, and then arrange it thus.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



Now, put enough in a <tl>glass</tl>, &amp; soak &amp; continually keep in it
the head of the animal, or the whole of it, if it is not
big.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



Take heed, before it dies, to keep the eyes open <del><fr>es</fr></del><comment rid="c_112v_04"/>
by blocking the eyelids with a little bit of <m>wax</m> or something
else.</ab>

</div>

</entry>