<entry><div id="p150v_1" categories="casting" continued="yes">



<head>Molding hollow</head>

<ab>This <tl><m>iron wire</m> point</tl>, which is put thus
<del><fr>bi</fr></del> through the hole, is to better hold the 
core &amp; keep it from shifting. All of this being
<del><fr>d</fr></del><comment rid="c_112r_05"/> thus arranged, lay your <tl>mold</tl> on the
<tl>table</tl>, the hole at the top, as it is marked here on the side,
&amp; then adapt a <tl>circle of <m>soft clay</m></tl>
<del><fr>aultr</fr></del>, two <ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> high, around
the hole, like for other <tl>molds</tl>. And then temper your <m>molding sand</m>
moderately thick, &amp; cast it through the hole until it is well <corr><del>well</del></corr>
filled, up to the surface of the <tl><m>clay</m> circle</tl>. But take
heed to not cast <del><fr>r</fr></del><comment rid="c_150v_04"/> in through the middle of the
hole, but rather from the side, for, since the already made
<tl>mold</tl> drinks and sucks the moisture <del>of the new</del>, the
new one that you cast in <del>which dries quickly</del> on the edge of
the <tl>mold</tl>, being quickly dry, <del><fr>s</fr></del> would
obstruct the <tl>mold</tl>, &amp; it would not finish filling. And when
you cast from the side, if you recognize that it is obstructed, you can
clear a path. Having cast in, blow on the <del><fr>f</fr></del>
<corr><del>the</del></corr> wet gate, &amp; put the
<tl><bp>end of your finger</bp></tl> in the hole a few times, <del><fr>po</fr></del>
or some <tl>small point</tl>, to unblock it, &amp; make the hollow
<m>wax</m> fill up. Cast in, at the end, the <m>sand</m>, tempered a little
thick to give strength to the <tl>mold</tl>, for <m>water</m> coming
to the surface <del><fr>s</fr></del> <add>of the <tl>mold</tl></add>
always makes it softer. Having set, scrape off the <tl><m>clay</m>
circle</tl> &amp; the excess which is on the hole through which you
cast the <fr>noyau</fr>, &amp; nothing will be discernable. When your
<tl>mold</tl> is thus prepared, <m><tl>lute</tl></m> it all around with the
same <m>sand which served for the <tl>molds</tl></m>. Next, reheat it in a slow
fire at the beginning, &amp; the mouth of the gate at the bottom, in
order that the <m>wax</m> flows out gently. For if you were
to give it great heat until the <m>wax</m> came out, it would boil
inside &amp; leave some pustules &amp; lumpy things, although</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



This <tl>point</tl> is placed in the middle &amp; through the hole of
the gate when the <tl>mold</tl> is in several pieces, like a
<al>turtle</al>, and this is done in order that the core does
not shake. But when the <tl>mold</tl> is only of two pieces,<lb/>
    
<figure size="small" id="fig_p150v_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5eVVJSjUwSFhpUzg">
</figure><lb/>

it is not necessary to put <tl>points</tl><lb/> in the middle of it.<lb/>

    <figure size="small" id="fig_p150v_2" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SUk5cUNtNnpqbXc">
</figure>


</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

Before casting the core, make some notches all around the hole
through which you want to cast, in order to always better secure the
<tl>mold</tl>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

Mixed <m>tallow</m> is the reason that, when emptying the <m>wax</m>,
the hole does not become obstructed. One needs <ms>half</ms>
<m>tallow</m> &amp; <ms>half</ms> <m>black wax</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

All very thick pieces come out better in hollow, because a thick mass of
mostly <m>lead</m> remains hot a <tmp>long time</tmp> &amp; eats the
<tl>mold</tl>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

You can, after the cast is done, mold <del>a</del> the part of the shell
of the belly where you have made the hole on the natural
one,<comment rid="c_150v_03"/> and reattach it with
<m>solder</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="bottom" render="full">

<mark>X</mark><lb/> Note that, after your<lb/>
core is cast, it is<lb/>
better to put the <tl>mold</tl><lb/>
in <m>hot water</m> to open it, in order
to remove the most <m>wax</m> that you can, always softening
<del><fr>a</fr></del><comment rid="c_150v_05"/> it in <m>hot water</m>. For the less <m>wax</m>
that remains in it, the better, in order that, when reboiling in large quantity in
the <tl>mold</tl> when you reheat it, no pustules or lumps are made in
it. And then, if there is hardly any <m>wax</m>, you will not need to
reheat it as much. When opening the <tl>mold</tl>, the cast will break.
But it can easily be repaired, even though you
cast <mark>A</mark><comment rid="c_150v_02"/>
    <figure size="small" id="fig_p150v_4" margin="right-bottom" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Y3M2ZEk5Um5peGc">
</figure>
</ab>



</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p150v_1" categories="casting" continued="yes">





<ab>the <m>white wax</m> with which you have composed your <m>black
sulfured wax</m>, has such little substance, since being dry and
purified, that it leaves nothing inside, and flows very gently. As for
the <m>charcoal</m> which is mixed in, if some remains, it burns &amp;
reduces to <m>ash</m> &amp; is emptied afterward by blowing through
the gate. You could even open your <tl>mold</tl> after the <m>wax</m>
has melted, if there is no fanciful thing which could break, like some
reattached thing or similar. After having covered the <tl>clamps</tl>
with the <m><tl>lute</tl></m> from your <m>sand</m> &amp; having covered all of the
<tl>mold</tl>, give it on top a layer of <m><tl>common lute</tl></m>, &amp; then
sprinkle this with some <m><tl>pestled</tl> brick</m>, in order that you can
handle it better. Let the <m><tl>lute</tl></m> dry slowly before firing it,
which melts the <m>wax</m>. The <m>wax</m> having left through the gate,
that which remains with the <m>charcoal</m> will burn. Being reheated
for the first time, <m><tl>lute</tl></m> it <del><fr>pou</fr></del> once more,
<del>to reheat it the second time</del> because the <m>plaster</m>, not
being good, will have readily made the <tl>mold</tl> retract, and the
joints will crack open, which might make large flashing. And for the second
time, one ought not to reheat it if you only want to cast in
<m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m>, but rather only make sure that the
<m><tl>lute</tl></m> is quite dry &amp; the <tl>mold</tl> moderately hot. For
these <al>turtles</al> that have a large size &amp; enough thickness, it
is better to <del>mold <fr>ault</fr></del> cast <del>your
<m>lead</m></del> an alloy <ms>half</ms> of <m>lead</m> &amp;
<ms>half</ms> of <m>tin</m>, especially for hollow things. For, if you
only have very thin &amp; very weak things to cast, like flowers, rely
rather on the abundance of <m>lead</m> than of <m>tin</m>, which becomes
porous once cast a little thick, &amp; readily makes some flaw around
the cast. <pn><pro>Maistre</pro> Alexandre</pn><comment rid="c_151r_02"/> says that he has never gone wrong
with <ms>half</ms> <m>tin</m> &amp; <ms>half</ms> <m>lead</m> for things
weighty &amp; with the <ms>thickness of the <tl>back of a
knife</tl></ms>. If there is <m><la>crocum</la></m>, the joints hardly
appear, &amp; consequently, the flashing is very small &amp; thin. You can
repair &amp; through the hole of the belly, pull the <m>earth</m> of the
core, leaving it wet a <tmp>long time</tmp>;<hr/></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

When you have cast your <m>black wax</m> in the <del><fr>a</fr></del><comment rid="c_033r_01"/>
<tl>mold</tl>, &amp; when it is quite cold, you need to <del>the</del>
open your <tl>mold</tl> halfway, to make the cast. And if the
figure of <m>black wax</m> breaks, there is no danger, for it
can always be reattached with a <tl>hot <m>iron</m> <del>touching</del>
point</tl>. Or else, if the pieces are not separated from the
<tl>mold</tl>, <del><fr>qu</fr></del> they meet up &amp; join like
beforehand by joining &amp; binding well the two halves of the
<tl>mold</tl>. When the figure is large, one needs to cross
inside many <tl><m>iron wires</m></tl> to sustain the core.<lb/>

    <figure size="small" id="fig_p151r_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dEhadHEzVWlxejg">
</figure>

</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<mark>A</mark><comment rid="c_151r_01"/><lb/>
<hr/>only in <m>lead</m> or<lb/>
<m>tin</m>. One needs,<lb/>
however, to redden<lb/>
the <tl>mold</tl> nearly as<lb/>
much as if there were<lb/>
inside some<lb/>
animal to burn,</ab>
    
<ab margin="bottom" render="full">
in order that the
<m>wax</m> melts well &amp; leaves nothing inside &amp; flows on its
own by keeping the <tl>mold</tl> leaning toward the gate when
reheating it. And when the <tl>mold</tl> is reheated, leave it to cool
gently, then blow inside, and draw toward yourself, while sucking, in
order that the <m>ashes of the wax</m> come out. Do this with
<tl>bellows</tl>.</ab>



</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p150v_1" categories="casting">





<ab>however, do not remove it until you have completely repaired the
<al>turtle</al>, for you will use this <m>earth</m> as <m>cement</m> if
you need to embed something or repair with the <tl>small chisel</tl>. If
there is some flashing at the joints of the <tl>mold</tl>, you will remove
it, either with the <tl>burin</tl> called a
<df><tl><fr>chaple</fr></tl></df> or a <tl>very sharp penknife</tl>,
or with a <tl>small file</tl>, &amp; then with the <tl>small
chisel</tl>, always having the natural one, to do this better, in
front of you. You can curl on a <tl>file</tl> the point of a <tl>small
chisel</tl> which is not quenched to make something lumpy. For these
<del>two</del> <al>turtles</al> &amp; hollow things that
presuppose being large enough, cast your alloy of <ms>half</ms>
<m>lead</m> &amp; <ms>half</ms> <m>fine tin</m>. There is more work in
molding a <al>turtle</al> than for twelve <tl>molds</tl> of flowers. If
there is some <m><la>crocum</la></m> in your <m>sand</m>, there will not be
flashing, &amp; if, by some chance, there is some on the sides, it will be
thinner than <m>paper</m>, as long as your <tl>mold</tl> is tightened
well with a <tl>press</tl>.</ab></div>
    
    


<div id="p150v_1" part="y"><ab> And to make the scales of <al>turtles</al>
or other animals, you can make some <tl>little small chisels</tl> in
the fashion of a <tl>round cutting-punch</tl>, others in the fashion of a
<tl>gouge</tl> or the scale of a <al>snake</al> &amp; <al>lizard</al>,
and others on a <tl>file</tl> to make the curly &amp; lumpy bits.<comment rid="c_151v_02"/> The
<al>turtles</al> which are not molded hollow do not have as much work,
for they are molded in two pieces, to repair them with <tl>small
chisels</tl>,<comment rid="c_151v_01"/> <tl>small cutting-punches</tl>, <tl>small gouges</tl>
&amp; <tl>small serrated chisels</tl>.</ab>

    <figure size="x-small" id="fig_p151v_1" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bk1US2QxRTVwa2s">
</figure>

</div></entry>