<entry><div id="p167r_1" categories="arms and armor" continued="yes">



<head><wp>Petards</wp><comment rid="c_008r_04"/></head>

<ab><figure id="fig_p167r_1" size="large" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5QTU2dDJtWHU5Nmc">
</figure><comment rid="c_167r_01"/></ab>

<ab><wp>Petards</wp> are made of the best alloy of <m><fr>metal</fr></m> &amp; <m>fine
rosette</m> that one can, in order that they do not burst,
namely one part of <m><fr>metal</fr></m> &amp; two of <m>fine
rosette</m> or <m>old cauldron</m>, which is even better. Some
are of fifteen or seventeen <ms>lb</ms> &amp; <del><fr>ch</fr></del> are
loaded with two &amp; a half <ms>lb</ms> of <m>good grain
powder</m>, &amp; they are for applying on windows &amp; common doors.
Others are of the weight of 25 to 27 <ms>lb</ms> and are loaded with 4
<ms>lb</ms> of <m>powder</m>. Others weigh 45 <ms>lb</ms> &amp; are
loaded with eight <ms>lb</ms> of <m>powder</m>. And thus they are formed
according to the effort they have to make. On the outside, they are <del><fr>e</fr></del><comment rid="c_111v_02"/>
of a regular shape, but on the inside, they are made like a
<tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl>, <figure size="x-small" id="fig_p167r_2" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5OUZCVWpfdmlzbWc">





</figure> narrower on the inside of the breech &amp; becoming wider
toward the mouth. And this is to give force to the breech, because of
the quantity of <m>powder</m> they hold, &amp; so that they do not
burst. <del>At the breech one gives them</del> Those of 45 <ms>lb</ms>
have a thickness of eight <ms>lines</ms> at the breech &amp; become
thinner on the inside toward the muzzle, which is of 4 <ms>lines</ms>.
They are xii <ms><bp>thumbs breadth</bp></ms> long &amp; seven in diameter at
the muzzle &amp; opening.</ab>



</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p167r_1" categories="arms and armor" continued="yes">





<ab>

Those of 27 <ms>lb</ms> or thereabouts are ix <ms>inches</ms> long &amp; six in
diameter at the muzzle. At the breech, they are vi <ms>lines</ms> thick,
&amp; 3 at the muzzle. The ones weighing 17 <ms>lb</ms> are 8
<ms>inches</ms> long &amp; five at the muzzle. One covers them all
together, all the <tl>forks</tl> &amp; <tl>pegs</tl> &amp;
<tl>tools</tl> which one uses, with a <tl>thick canvas</tl> or <tl>thick
cloth</tl> in order that they do not make any noise. It
<del><fr>s</fr></del> is good that they should sit loaded for some time.
After one has put the <m>powder</m> in, one tamps it down quite
thoroughly, and then one puts in <m>pressed paper</m>, then a 
<m><po>cake</po> of wax</m> 
well tamped down, &amp; on the <m>wax</m> another <m>plate of
cork</m> that goes in quite precisely &amp; with force. In this way,
the <m>powder</m> remains well sealed &amp; gives much greater violence,
&amp; if you wish, you can put on the <m>plate of cork</m> one of
<m>wood</m> pierced in the middle, if the <wp>petard</wp><comment rid="c_008r_04"/> is pierced at the
breech, which one holds to be the easiest, &amp; which makes for greater
penetration because it cannot recoil. And for those that have a pierced
breech, one must have a good <tl>gimlet</tl> to first make the hole in
order that the <tl>peg</tl>, which is made <del>in</del> with a
<tl>gimlet</tl>-like point, may attach the <wp>petard</wp> faster &amp; without
noise. And <del>to</del> for these, one must cover the button, which is
quite evenly filed, <del><fr>p</fr></del> with <m>waxed canvas</m>, or
add <m>wax</m> to it in order that it precisely plugs the hole of the
breech. But because the doors are sometimes iron-clad &amp; the
<tl><m>iron</m> pegs</tl> cannot pierce it, one uses an <tl><m>iron</m>
fork made like pincers</tl> &amp; another <tl><m>iron</m> rod
<del><fr>q</fr></del> made with three claws at the end</tl>, as you see
depicted. And in this way, the <wp>petard</wp> holds itself well &amp; is quickly
placed. The <tl><m>iron</m> pegs</tl> must extend from the <wp>petard</wp> with
the entire point that is made like a <tl>gimlet</tl>, namely by three or
4 <ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms>, which goes entirely <del><fr>l</fr></del><comment rid="c_017v_04"/>
into the door. When the <wp>petards</wp> are placed, one fills the touch-hole
with good <m><fr>pulverin</fr></m><comment rid="c_167v_01"/> and
<del><fr>s</fr></del> one puts in it a <m>feather quill</m> filled with
<m>powder</m> tightly pressed &amp; moistened with <m>vinegar</m>, or,
if needed, one <po>presses</po> the <m>powder</m> in the hollow of the hand &amp;
having wetted it with <m><bp>saliva</bp></m>, one makes from it
something like a cocoon or</ab>



</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p167r_1" categories="arms and armor" continued="yes">

    <figure size="small" id="fig_p168r_1" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5RUdzVWVNM3l6QVU">
</figure>

<ab>a <tl>peg</tl> which one puts into the touch-hole, &amp; then, with
a <tl>rope</tl> wrapped around the end of a <tl>stick</tl>, one gives fire &amp;
promptly retreats to take cover. The small <wp>petards</wp><comment rid="c_008r_04"/> of 16 or 17
<ms>lb</ms> are attached promptly with a <tl>short hooked peg</tl> made
like a <tl>wimble</tl>,<comment rid="c_168r_01"/> &amp; if the <wp>petard</wp>
is of a good alloy, one can give fire by <bp>hand</bp> just as one does
with <wp>petards</wp> of 27 <ms>lb</ms>, but then one only puts in three
<ms>lb</ms> of <m>powder</m>. It must certainly be a strong door if the
seventeen <ms>lb</ms> <wp>petard</wp> does not blow it up. Some use <tl>little
bells</tl> worn by <al>oxen</al> or <al>mules</al> on a
<pro>peasant</pro> door. Others load two <wp>pistol</wp> barrels &amp;, with a
<tl>gimlet</tl> &amp; a <tl>string</tl>, attach them with the muzzle
against the door. If the <wp>petards</wp> are good &amp; do not explode, they
only recoil and cannot do harm if one is next to them.</ab>

<ab>A. This is a <tl>small peg, hooked like the hinge of a door</tl>
&amp; made like a <tl><oc>gimlet</oc></tl><comment rid="c_080r_01"/> on one end, for quickly
attaching a small <wp>petard</wp> with ear<comment rid="c_168v_01"/> of fifteen or xvii <ms>lb</ms> for a
common door or window.</ab>

<ab>B. This is a small <wp>petard</wp> with ears.</ab>

<ab>C. This is a <del><fr>gro</fr></del> common <wp>petard</wp> of 27 or 30 <ms>lb</ms>
pierced at the breech, through which a large <tl><m>iron</m> peg</tl>
passes, button-like on one end &amp; made like a
<tl><oc>gimlet</oc></tl> at the point, for quickly attaching the <wp>petard</wp>
against a door that <del>does not have</del> <add>is not</add>
<add>covered</add> with <m>iron plates</m>.</ab>

<ab>D. These are <m>plates of wax, cork &amp; wood</m>
for loading the <wp>petard</wp> &amp; sealing the <m>powder</m> well.</ab>

<ab>E. <del>This</del> <tl><m>Iron</m> fork made in the form of pincers
of the <ms>height of a man</ms></tl>, to quickly place the mortar
without a <tl>peg</tl>. It must be of <m>soft iron</m> in order
that its branches bend easily, if need be, to fit to the height or width
of the door.</ab>

<ab>F. This is another <tl><m>iron</m> fork</tl> of the same height that
props up the <tl>fork made like pincers</tl> &amp; also supports the
<wp>petard</wp>, and with its claw at the bottom prevents the <tl>pincers</tl>
from recoiling.</ab>



</div>
<div continues="yes" id="p167r_1" categories="arms and armor">





<ab>G. <wp>Petard</wp><comment rid="c_008r_04"/> with ear,<comment rid="c_168v_01"/> placed with its
<tl>peg</tl>.</ab>

<ab>H. <tl>Knife-like saws</tl> to cut a portcullis, if needed.</ab>

<ab>I. The <tl>large <m>iron</m> pegs</tl> which traverse &amp; attach
the <wp>petard</wp>.</ab>

<ab>K. These are <tl>common <m>iron</m> pegs</tl>, very round &amp;
covered with <m>canvas</m>, like all the rest, to turn the <tl>large
<m>iron</m> pegs</tl> pierced close to the head.</ab>

<ab>L. <tl>Axes</tl> that one must always carry to finish breaking down,
if by chance the <wp>petard</wp> has left anything whole.</ab>

<ab>M. A <tl>large mallet of <m>wood</m></tl> for knocking down what was
begun &amp; weakened by the <tl>saws</tl> or
<tl><oc>gimlets</oc></tl>.<comment rid="c_080r_01"/></ab>

<ab>N. Are <tl>large augers</tl> &amp; <tl><oc>gimlets</oc> of
<pro>wheelwrights</pro></tl> for smoothly cutting a door or window by
making large holes close to one another.</ab>

<ab>O. <tl>Crutches</tl> of the <ms>height of a man</ms>, which it is
necessary to carry to quickly put under a portcullis after the <wp>petard</wp>
has gone off &amp; to prevent the portcullis from falling.</ab>

<ab>P. Are <tl>small <m>iron</m> pincers</tl> for putting some <wp>petard</wp>
low on the straight part of the <tl>bolt</tl> or <tl><po>strap hinge</po></tl> of
the door.</ab>


</div>
</entry>