<entry><div continues="yes" id="p098v_5" categories="casting">





<ab><m>Earth</m> or <m>sand</m> moistened or ground with <m>water</m> wants
to be reheated more than <m>sand</m>.</ab>

<ab><m>Latten from a candlestick</m> is not pure, for one mixes in it
<m>iron filings</m> &amp; <m>potin</m>.</ab>

<ab><m>Latten</m> wants to be cast hotter than <m>copper</m>, <la>quod
non credo</la>.<comment rid="c_099r_03"/></ab>

<ab>To cast carefully, one ought not to take <m>metals already
alloyed</m>, but take them pure &amp; mix them.</ab>

<ab><m>Iron</m> hardly agrees with being cast in a mixture of
<m>copper</m> or <m>latten</m>.</ab>

<ab>It is better to mold all with one <m>sand</m>, be it in a <tl>frame</tl> or
<fr>noyau</fr>, rather than in various mixed ones.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">


One ought to reheat for one or two <ms><tmp>hours</tmp></ms> <del>and <fr>
p</fr></del>, in a fire <del>that</del><comment rid="c_099r_01"/> of <m>charcoal</m> which
lights by itself, a <tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl> with the substance inside, and
then blow &amp; cover the <tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl> with large <m>charcoals</m>
&amp; the mouth of the <tl>furnace</tl> with <tl><m>bricks</m></tl>, and
let it consume two or three feedings of <m>charcoal</m>, which
<del><fr>se</fr></del> fill the <tl>furnace</tl> above the
<tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl>. At the end, stoke it to a violent fire, &amp; when the
flame is very white &amp; the substance is in a liquid
bath like <m>water</m> &amp; casting off pale blue flames,
cast. The secret is to cast <add>very</add> hot &amp; in one go.</ab>
 

<ab><emph><m>Lean white sand</m></emph> without bond renders quite 
proper for casting, &amp;, having body, if
you grind it very finely on <tl><m>porphyry</m></tl> or calcine it,
reddening it several times in the fire, &amp; spread it in
<m>vinegar</m> or finely grind it with <m>water</m>, as you know. It
also molds very neatly <fr>en noyau</fr>, as I have experimented. But do
not moisten it with <m>salt water</m> if you want to promptly reheat it,
for <m>salt</m> boils on the fire &amp; makes pustules, being pressed by
the fire. I believe that the <fr>noyaulx</fr>, gently reheated, would not
do this. I molded very neatly <fr>en noyau</fr> the <m>substance of
skillets</m>. <m>White sand</m> <sn>smells like <m>sulfur</m></sn> when
reheated, and I believe it would melt. And since the substance has been
cast in it, it acquires in the <tl>mold</tl>
<del>as</del> a luster as if it were
<m>leaded</m> or vitrified. I believe that <pro>glassmakers</pro> could
use it.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">


<comment rid="c_099r_02"/>One needs very little <m>sal ammoniac</m> dissolved in
<m>water</m>.</ab>

</div>
</entry>