<entry><div continues="yes" id="p113r_1" categories="casting">


<ab>such that, while reheating, the two casts will unjoin. <del>And
for <fr>pl</fr></del> Therefore, for this effect, take several <tl>bowls of
different size which have a lip</tl>, to cast better. In these, pour
some <m>common fountain water</m>, &amp; mix into it <ms>as
much <m>sal ammoniac water</m> as can be held in an
<m>egg</m></ms>, <add><mark>#</mark></add><comment rid="c_112r_02"/> composed as mentioned.
If you want to cast in <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m>, because one would
need more for casting <m>gold</m> &amp; <m>silver</m>, the
<m>water</m> being in your <tl>bowl</tl>, <del>mix</del>
put <del>in it</del> your <m>sand</m> in it &amp; not the <m>water</m>
in the <m>sand</m>, &amp; add it <del><fr>a dista dista</fr></del> with such
discretion that, <del><fr>il</fr></del><comment rid="c_113v_03"/> while stirring &amp; mixing it
promptly with a <tl><m>wooden</m> spoon</tl>, it does not become thicker
than <m><del>clear</del> mustard</m>. And thus, cast <del>the</del> first into your <tl>mold</tl>
the lighter part, <del>which <fr>es</fr></del> as is always at the surface, with a shaking motion, &amp;
<del><fr>da</fr></del> from a little height. And doing so,
when the animal is nearly covered, blow strongly everywhere in order
to dissipate the small and big bubbles that the <m>wetted sand</m> makes &amp;
continue without delay to put all the rest which is at the bottom, &amp;
a little thicker than at the top, until everything is filled, up to the
mark for thickness that you made.
<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p113v_4" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bEE5QmFaQWxUYm8">
</figure><comment rid="c_112r_02"/> And do not forget to shake the <tl>mold</tl>
<del>in order</del> while casting, in order that the <m>wetted sand</m> runs
&amp; enters well everywhere. Also, tip your <tl>mold</tl> up on the side
of the head, which is higher than the body, and thus your <tl>mold</tl>
will have the same thickness, &amp; you will spare <m>sand</m>.</ab>
<ab>All of this being carefully done <del><fr>fai</fr></del>, let it set, which will
take a <ms><tmp>quarter of an hour</tmp></ms>. Then, release the
<m>clay</m> circle, which can be used another time. And leave it to dry
a little, &amp; separate your <tl>mold</tl> from the
<m><po>cake</po> of earth</m>, which also <del><fr>de</fr></del><comment rid="c_113v_04"/> will
be appropriate for molding right away, and trim the excess with a big
<tl>knife</tl>, giving <mark>||</mark><comment rid="c_113v_01"/> to it the long shape of a <mu>mandore</mu>.
<del><fr>Rasche</fr></del></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">
If you can, fill your half <tl>mold</tl> in one go, &amp; with
<del>the <fr>pre</fr></del> a tempered batch, it is the best.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">
<mark>#</mark><comment rid="c_112r_03"/><lb/>
<ms>or two <m>eggs</m></ms>, because there is no risk if there will be more.
<del>And the <m>water</m></del> If you cast in two goes, it is enough
to put <m>sal ammoniac water</m> at the first bowlful. </ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">
Make it clear like a <m>pureed broth</m>, or like <m>starch
water</m> that <pro>women</pro> use to make their <m>starch</m>. For
there is no risk in it being very clear, because <m>sand</m> always settles at
the bottom &amp; <m>water</m> separates &amp; remains on top. The sand that one 
scrapes as well <ill/><fr>mme</fr> too weak &amp; soft. And it will not<comment rid="c_113v_02"/> let
itself set quickly, for all things calcined dry out promptly from mixed
<m>water</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle" render="tall">
<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p113v_3" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dEdzS040X3RjbkU">
</figure><comment rid="c_112r_03"/><lb/>
If you do not fill in one go your <tl>mold</tl>
<del>tempered</del> with <m>tempered sand</m>, take heed to stir your
second cast with the <del><fr>e</fr></del><comment rid="c_017r_01"/> <del><fr>p</fr></del> surface of the first,
<del><fr>p</fr></del> by mixing with your <tl>spoon</tl> or <tl>spatula</tl> with which you temper it.</ab>
</div>
    
    
<div id="p113r_1" part="y">
<ab>Scrape &amp; cut also away the back <add>of
the <tl>mold</tl></add>, which is always the weakest, and adapt it
cleanly thus. And do not forget to make notches around, in order that the
second cast anchors itself there &amp; binds better
            
<figure size="small" id="fig_p113v_5" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5V29QdUxZVmxCUDQ">
</figure> without changing.</ab>
        
<ab margin="left-bottom" render="wide">
<m>Sal ammoniac water</m> is not necessary to small
<tl>molds</tl>, which require neither a big nor long fire to be
reheated; however, when you put some in, it will only be better.

</ab>
</div>


<div id="p113r_1" categories="casting" continued="yes">



<head>Tempering the <m>sand</m> and molding the first cast</head>

<ab>Take a <tl>bowl of <m>leaded</m> <m>earth</m></tl> of such size that
it can hold the <m>tempered sand</m> which will be needed <del>of</del> to
fill your <tl>mold</tl> in one go, which is <del><fr>mei</fr></del>
better than in two goes, because if you do not cast the second wet batch
 promptly, there is a risk that while you are preparing it, the
first one will set &amp; become solid,</ab>



</div>
</entry>