<div id="p128v_1" categories="casting;metal process">


<head>Whitening of cast <m>silver</m></head>

<ab>

Because one commonly casts in <m>base silver</m>, &amp; especially the
<pl>Germans</pl>, and that such an alloy readily makes a film
or crust, <del>which is contrary to</del> <del>our</del> <add>some</add>
<pro>goldsmiths</pro> <del>from <pl>France</pl></del> are usually quick
to whiten their works, especially rough ones, because they only
use <m>common <fr>bullitoyre</fr></m>, which is <m>tartar</m> &amp;
<m>common salt</m>, <ms>nearly as much of one as the other</ms>. But I
have seen an excellent <pl>German</pl> working thus. Having in my
presence cast a <al>little lizard</al> with an <m>alloy of
<cn>teston</cn></m>, he made a greyish <del><fr>noi</fr></del> crust.
And to clean it from it, he boiled it in the above-mentioned
<m><fr>bullitoyre</fr></m> of <m>tartar</m> &amp; <add>pulverized</add>
<m>common salt</m> <del>and</del> mixed with <m>common water</m>, in the
fire of his <tl>forge</tl>. Once taken out, he <tl>brushed</tl> it. And
because it was not as clean of this crust as he fancied, he burned some
<m>tartar</m> <add>in some <tl><m>paper</m></tl></add> until it was
black &amp; no longer <m>smoked</m>. Then, he wetted the aforesaid <m>tartar</m>
<del><fr>d</fr></del> with the <m>water of <fr>bullitoyre</fr></m>,
composed of <m>salt</m> &amp; <m>tartar</m>, &amp; covered all his
<al>lizard</al> with it. Then, he put it between the live <del>of</del>
<m>charcoals</m> of his <tl>forge</tl> &amp; blew a little. When the
<al>lizard</al> was red, he took it out, let it cool, then reheated it
in the <m><fr>bullitoyre</fr></m>. Next, he <tl>brushed</tl> it in
<m>clear water</m>. </ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<mark>+</mark><lb/>

Note that the <m><fr>bullitoyre</fr></m> for <m>silver</m> is never good
in a <tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl> because the <m>water</m>, taking the form of the
<del><fr>f</fr></del> <m>tartar</m>, evaporates. But the <tl>vessel</tl>
for boiling, being of <m>copper</m>, is excellent for the whitening of
<m>silver</m> &amp; for the mixture which colors <m>gold</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">


He took heed not to let his <m>water of tartar</m> boil so much that it
would have poured out on top, because then its strength goes away. Therefore, when this first fury of boiling comes, remove it from the fire &amp; put it
back. He held as a secret this <m>burned tartar</m> put on top for
<m>base silver</m>.</ab>

</div>