<root><page>003v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f12.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p003r_a3</id>
<ab>instead of <m>finer turpentine</m>.  And you can add to two lbs. of <m>common  turpentine</m> to one lb. of good quality <m>turpentine oil</m>, and then proceed as usual. This recipe will not cost you more than five or six sols a lb. to make and is sold for 40 sols a lb.</ab>


 <figure>
<id>fig_p003v_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5ZUY4SkZBblA5MjA</link>
<!--Image of alembic-->
<!--Pamela Smith: moor's head alembic?-->
</figure>
 
<ab>This <tl>vessel</tl> is used to make large quantities of <m>turpentine oil</m>, that is to say a bucket an hour. And you can use it to make either regular or high-quality <m>turpentine</m>.  As you know, start the process on low heat. And always maintain cold <m>water</m> in the cooler on top.  You can sell a lb. for xii sous and the <m>rosin</m>, known as <m><la>pix graeca</la></m>, remains at the bottom of the <tl>vessel</tl>. <m>Alcohol</m> is also produced from this <tl>vessel</tl> and one does not even need to distill it again. You do not need a <tl>stove</tl> for this <m>copper</m> <tl>vessel</tl>. You need only to place <m>charcoal</m> around it if the <tl>vessel</tl> is flat-bottomed. But if it is rounded, you can hang on it on a <tl>trivet</tl>.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
@ It is better to heat the <m>varnish</m> a little bit, rather than to put it out in the sun, because this makes panels warp.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
@ Some say it is not good to distil in this <m>copper</m> <tl>vessel</tl> since it makes things green. However, when <m>tinned</m>, it is good.</ab>




</div>
<div>
<id>p003v_a1</id>
<head>To varnish</head>
<ab><m>Turpentine</m> <m>varnish</m> does not need any <m>glue</m> since it is fat and viscous and does not penetrate the <m>wood</m> as <m>spike lavender</m>  and <m>sandarac</m> <m>varnishes</m> would. <m>Spike lavender varnish</m> does not require any <m>glue</m> on <m>iron</m> and similar materials which cannot be permeated, but on <m>wood</m> and on <m>colors</m> which do not contain <m>gum</m> or <m><fr>colle de détrempe</fr></m>, it is necessary to lay one coat of the said <m>glue <fr>de retailles</fr></m> and allow to dry, then varnish.</ab>
</div></root>