<root><page>004r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f13.image</image>
<div>
<id>p004r_1</id>
<head><m>Lavender spike oil</m> varnish</head>
<ab>One must heat <m>lavender spike oil</m> and, as it begins to simmer, put in powdered <m>sandarac gum</m> so that it soon melts. And stir continuously over a <m>charcoal</m> fire until the <m>sandarac</m> is well melted, which you will know by taking a little of the said varnish on a <tl>plate</tl> and, if it is fat enough when you handle it with a <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl>, it is ready. And for one pound of <m>lavender spike oil</m>, you should put five ounces of ground <m>sandarac</m>. Some only put in four ounces but this is not as good, nor as fat. The former dries promptly. To avoid the trouble of polishing their <m>ebony</m>, <pro>framemakers</pro> varnish it with this. So do <pro>guitarmakers</pro>. This <sup>varnish</sup> is not as fitting for paintings as fine <m>turpentine varnish</m>, though it is good for the paintings' moldings. When <m>linseed varnish</m> was in use, one would not commonly varnish the landscape of a painting because it would turn the landscape yellow. But with <m>turpentine varnish</m> one varnishes everywhere. Instead of <m>sandarac</m>, you can add to it pulverized <m>mastic</m> drop by drop or otherwise, and it will dry more quickly.</ab>
<ab>If you want to varnish <m>plaster</m> or a wall, first put on your <m>glue de retaille</m>, very hot, because if cold it would not penetrate the wall at all.  And when you would have put your varnish on, it would come off.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<m>Aspic oil varnish</m> is not as apt for colors as that of <m>turpentine</m>, because <m>aspic oil</m> eats the colors, since it is too penetrating.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<head>To remove varnish from an old panel painting that has yellowed and varnish it again</head>


<ab>Take some <m>white soap</m> and <m>ashes</m> strained through a <tl>sieve</tl>, and soak all together in <m>water</m>. And with a <tl>sponge</tl>, take some of the said <m>ashes</m> and <m>soap</m> and rub the painting with it. And when you see that the old varnish has been taken off, throw a bucket of <m>water</m> at the painting to clean it, then leave it for a quarter of an hour in the sun to dry and revive the colors. Once your painting is dried, you can apply your <m>turpentine varnish</m>.</ab>
<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Make sure the colors do not come off.</ab>
</div></root>