<root><page>006r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f17.image</image>


<div>
<id>p006r_1</id>
<head>To lay down and set burnished <m>gold</m> and give it a red or green or blue <sup>hue</sup></head>


<ab>
<m>Ceruse</m> and <m>lead white</m> is not appropriate for polished white nor for burnishing because it is fat, but it is quite good for matte <m>gold</m>, which is made with <m>oil</m>by mixing it with yellow <m>ochre</m> and <m>mine</m> and tempering the whole with <m>oil</m>, and this matte <m>gold</m> so applied lasts in the rain, like gilded <m>leadwork</m> and similar things. Therefore, for burnished <m>gold</m> take good <m>chalk</m>, quite white, well ground and soaked with <m>distemper glue</m> and do four coats of it, one after the other, on the <m>wood</m>. And when the last one is dry, rub it with <m><pa>prele</pa></m>, which is a kind of grass otherwise named <m><pa>horsetail</pa></m>, to render it well polished. Afterwards, take fine <m><pl>Armenian </pl>bole</m> and <m>sanguine</m>, as much of one as of the other, a bit of <m><al>lamb </al>tallow</m> the size of a <m>bean</m> or a <m>pea</m> depending on the quantity of <m>bole</m>, and a little <m>willow charcoal</m>, or as much as the <m>tallow</m>, and half a <ms><pa>walnut</pa> shell</ms> filled with half-burned <m>saffron</m>; some put in a little <m>candi sugar</m>. Grind everything together with <m>water</m> and apply it without <m>gum</m> or <m>glue</m>, and let it dry. And rub the place that you would like to <m>gild</m> with a piece of white cloth to better unify <sup>it</sup>, and when the rubbed place is a little shiny it is a sign that the <m>gold</m> will behave well. After rubbing, wash the place that you want to gild with a clean <tl>brush</tl> soaked with clear <m>water</m> and apply the <m>gold</m> at once, which you will burnish when dry. And if you want to set <m>rouge clair</m> and glaze with it, grind <m><pl>Venice </pl>lake</m> on the <m>marble</m> with <m>walnut<sup> oil</sup></m> or <m>linseed<sup> oil</sup></m>. After grinding, mix <sup>in</sup> <m>turpentine</m> varnish or <m>spike lavender <sup>varnish</sup></m> and apply on <m>gold</m> with the <tl>brush</tl>. <m>Brazilwood</m> and <m>laque ronde</m> fade. For green, temper <m>verdigris</m> with <m><pa>walnut</pa> oil</m> or <m><pa>linseed</pa><sup> oil</sup></m> and grind it, then mix in some <m>turpentine</m> varnish; not <m>aspic</m><sup> varnish</sup>, which is not suitable for <m>verdigris</m>. If you want to glaze with <m>azure</m> it must be set on burnished <m>silver</m>. Take <m>azure enamel</m>, and without grinding temper it with <m>turpentine</m> varnish and apply it.
</ab>
</div></root>