<root><page>007r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f19.image</image>
 


<div>
<id>p007r_a1</id>
<head>For gilding with <m>gold color</m> and <m>tinsel</m></head>


<ab>Once you have <del>gilded</del> <add>colored</add>, make your stamped ornament in <m>tin</m> as said, or in <m>iron</m> <del><fr>dest</fr></del> or <m>copper</m>, you must not put a layer of<m>glue</m> here as on <m>wood</m>, but take only <m>fatty oil</m>, which is made in seven or eight <ms>days</ms> <env>in the sun</env> with <m>walnut oil</m> and <m>lead white</m> <del>&amp; with</del>, stirring it often, or cooking it on the fire if one is in haste. Then, with the <m>oil</m> thus made fatty, grind a little <m>lead white</m>, <m>massicot</m> &amp; <m><fr>mine de plomb</fr></m> <del>[illegible]</del>, at discretion, as much of one as of the other. <m>Minium</m> gives color to the <m>gold</m>. Next, with this, you make a layer of it evenly on your stamp, taking care not to fill the hollows. And once it is almost dry, lay the <m>gold</m> leaf on it with <m>cotton</m>. Such <m>gold</m> will withstand rain on houses &amp; elsewhere. And if you have gilded with <m>tinsel</m>, color it with <m>smoke from a partridge</m> or from yellow or red <m>cloth</m>, &amp; it will be beautiful like pure <m>gold</m>. You can cover trunks, mirrors, canopies &amp; posts of beds of colored <m>velvet</m> or <m>satin</m> and then apply the gilded stamped ornament on them with strong <m>glue</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p007r_a2</id>
<head>To color trunks with stamped ornaments</head>


<ab>The stamped ornament made from sheets of <m>copper</m> or <m>latten</m> are made with <m>wood from a <pa>service tree</pa></m> engraved and cut, should you want to spend less. Next, the stamped piece is colored with the aforesaid lacquer colours of <m>lacquer</m>, <m>verdet</m>, <m>blue enamel</m>, and soaked in <m>turpentine</m> varnish. But wherever you want to make it azure, apply some fer blanc, which is more appropriate for an azure background.</ab>
  
</div>
<div>
<id>p007r_a3</id>
<head>Doublets</head>


<ab>Good <m>dragon's blood</m> soaked in <m>spirits</m> produces its own <m>mastic</m> or <m>glue</m>. So do <m>vert de vessie</m> and <m>saffron</m>.</ab>
  
</div>
<div>
<id>p007r_a4</id>
<head><m><al>Fish</al> glue</m> or <m>usblac</m> and <m>mouth glue</m></head>


<ab>It is made from <m><al>codfish</al> skin</m> that has been boiled rather than <m>salted</m>. <pro>Joiners</pro> use it on their masterpieces and <pro>guitar makers</pro> use it for their more delicate works. It needs to be strongly beaten, then soaked gently in barely boiling <m>water</m>.</ab>


<ab><m>Mouth glue</m> is made of <m>parchment</m> scraps and used to glue <m>paper</m> or similar things without fire, by wetting it with one's <tl><bp>mouth</bp></tl>.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
It is beaten and left to soak in <m>white wine</m> for one night, then melted over a low heat. Others soak it in <m>spirits</m>.</ab>
</div></root>