<root><page>007v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f20.image</image>
 
<div>
<id>p007v_1</id>
<head>For giving the color of all kinds of <m>metals</m> to <m>wood</m> and other things</head>


<ab>Take <m>touchstone</m> and <m>pumice stone</m> as much of one as of the other and grind them together and mix with a <m>glue de retailles</m> stronger than that used for painting, and paint it on whatever you like. Once dry, rub this layer with any <m>metal</m> whatsoever, then burnish it.</ab>
  
</div>
<div>
<id>p007v_2</id>
<head>Against windy colic</head>


<ab>Take a dozen dried <m>common <pa>walnuts</pa></m> and throw them one after another onto a good <tl>brazier</tl> where they may catch fire, and take them out with <tl>tongs</tl>, and let them burn and flame well in the air, and extinguish them in a glass of good <m>wine</m>. Then let the <m>wine</m> cool and filter it, then pour half of it, since six extinguished <m>nuts</m> make one dose. An excellent cure against suffocation of the matrix.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p007v_3</id>
<head>To relieve the pain of g{out}</head>


<ab>Take half a pound of finely powdered golden and yellow <m>marcasite</m>, half an ounce of <m>storax</m>, 4 lb. of <m>urine</m>, incorporate well together, little by little, in a <tl>mortar</tl>, then boil all together quite strongly. But the pot needs to be well covered so the smoke does not escape. Then distill the imbibed <m>urine</m>, separated by inclination, in an <tl>alembic</tl>, well luted and covered with a <m>copper</m> head. And soak a cloth with the said <m>water</m> and apply it lukewarm on the pain.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p007v_4</id>
<head>Against gonorrhea</head>


<ab>Cook .i. lb. of <m>old smiths' water</m>, .i. ℥ of <m><pl>Armenian</pl> bole</m> reduced in the finest powder, and .iii. ʒ of <m>common honey</m>, until the <m>honey</m> stops foaming. Once cooled, strain with great pressure and use the results of filtration by injection.</ab>


</div></root>