<root><page>009v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f24.image</image>


<div>
<id>p009v_1</id>
<head><pro>Painters</pro></head>


<ab>They melt <m>orpiment</m> entirely in a <m>glass</m> bottle on very hot <m>ashes</m>, but it would be more appropriate to sublimate <m>orpiment</m> in a long-neck <tl>matrass</tl> as for making <m>garnets</m>. The <m>orpiment</m> thus turns red like <m>red enamel</m> and it has to be ground first in distemper, because once entirely melted it is very brittle and difficult to grind. Then, once dry, you can thin it with <m>oil</m> and it will make a deep and saturated yellow. But to prevent <m>orpiment</m> from fading <sup>in contact</sup> with other colours and make it compatible with these and to make it dry quickly, a most rare secret is to <m>calcine</m> common <m>salt</m> and to grind it together <sup>with the <m>orpiment</m></sup>. <m>Green verditer</m> is not used with <m>oil</m>.</ab>
</div>
 @
<div>
<id>p009v_2</id> 
<head><pro>Merchant</pro></head>


<ab>The order that <pro>merchants</pro> are accustomed to keep in their books, which are the waste book, the sales book, and the ledger, also called the account book.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<ab>Waste book</ab>


<ab>First, François du Cros owes from 2 September 1581, for 1 canne of <m>batiste</m> at 8 livres per canne, total <figure>--</figure> 8 livres tournois</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Moved to the sales book at r. 25/</ab>


<ab>François du Cros owes from 2 September 1581, for 1 canne of <m>batiste</m> at 8 livres per canne, as shown by the waste book at r. 25</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Moved to the account book at r. 55/</ab>


<ab>François du Cros owes from 2 September 1581, for the merchandise taken by himself, as specified in detail in the sales book, No. 7, at r. 55, the sum of 8 livres, of which the aforesaid du Cros has made a bill on the aforesaid day, to be payed on Saint Andrew's day next, total <figure>--</figure> 8 [...] r.</ab>
</div></root>