<root><page>010r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f25.image</image>


<div>
<id>p010r_1</id>
<head>Imitation <m>jasper</m></head>


<ab>Take <m>horn</m> as is used to make lanterns, quite thin, and underneath imitate your <m>jasper</m>, <m>cornaline</m>, and other <m>stones</m>. That will look more appropriate than doing it on glass, which is too shiny. And the <m>horn</m> gives a lustre and a fatty polish similar to <m>jasper</m>.</ab>


<ab>You know how you can imitate <m><pa>rose</pa></m>s with scrapings of the said <m>horn</m>. The colors for this <m>jasper</m> need to have as a base clear <m>turpentine</m> or <m>spike lavender</m> varnish. And matte, opaque colours are not appropriate, no matter how fine they are. You have to <m>oil</m> the unpainted underside with <m>spike lavender oil</m>.</ab>


<ab><margin>top</margin>
Thin <m>glass</m> looks very fine for this effect</ab>


<ab><margin>left-top</margin>
You can inlay beds with it, and on the joints you can throw the filings of <m>talc</m> or of <m>pins</m> on the fresh <m>cement</m> of the said joints. You have to bond them with <m>gum amoniacum</m> soaked in <m>vinegar</m>. To better imitate <m>marbled jasper</m>, apply coarse<m>wool</m> hair dyed various colors and intermingled. After you have laid down all the colors, scrape oblique lines into them then lay down<m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m> leaves. If you lay down colors made of <m>turpentine</m> on the <m>horn</m>, give it a backing of <m>silver</m> or of <m>tin</m> leaf<m>.</m> You can also file <m>horn</m> and mix it with <m>strong glue</m> and lay it down onto the joints of the piece of <m>horn</m> and finish with a <tl>joiner's plane</tl>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p010r_2</id>


<head><m>Stil de grain yellow</m></head>


<ab>It is made in <pl>Lyon</pl> from the <m>juice of weld</m> &amp; <m>chalk</m> mixed together or better yet with <m>ceruse</m>, which is appropriate for <m>distemper</m> and <m>oil</m>. </ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p010r_3</id>
<head><pa>Roses</pa></head>


<ab>These are imitated either with the scrapings of <del><ill/></del> <m>horn used for lanterns</m>, or with scrapings of very clear, delicate &amp; dyed <m>parchment</m>, used as you know.</ab>
</div> 


<div>
<id>p010r_4</id>
<head>Purple color</head>


<ab><pro>Painters</pro> make it beautifully by making the first ground layer of <m>common azur</m>, or better yet <m><fr>azur d'esmail</fr></m>, &amp; next they glaze it with <m>lake</m>, which will be more appropriate for this if you mix in <m>alum</m>, which gives it a violet tint depending on the quantity that you mix in.</ab>
 </div> 


<div>
<id>p010r_5</id>
<pro>
</pro><head>Powder for hourglasses</head>


<ab>It must be made very fine and not subject to rust and with enough weight to flow. Taking i <ms>lb</ms> of <m>lead</m>, melt it and skim and purify it from its filth, then pour into it four <figure>℥</figure> of finely ground <m>common salt</m>, and take care that there are no <m>stones</m> or earth. And immediately after pouring it, stir continuously very well with an <m>iron</m> <sup>tool</sup> until the <m>lead</m> and <m>salt</m> are quite incorporated, and take it immediately off the fire, stirring continuously. And if it seems too coarse, grind it on a <tl><m>marble</m> slab</tl> and pass it through a fine <tl>sieve</tl>, then wash it as many as times as necessary until the <m>water</m> runs clear, throwing out the fine powder that will float on it, renewing the <m>water</m> as many times as necessary until it is completely cleared.</ab>
</div></root>