<root><page>011v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f28.image</image>


<div>
<id>p011v_1</id>


<head>Applying the color of <m><pl>Damascene</pl> steel</m> on <tl>knives</tl></head>


<ab>Rub the <m>steel</m> with <m>common <la>aquis fortis</la></m> mixed with <m>earth</m>.  After, rub everything with <m>ashes</m> or <m>sand</m>. Do with the <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m> as you would do on a <tl>touchstone</tl>.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p011v_2</id>


<head>Getting rid of red <bp>eyes</bp> or black <bp>eyes</bp></head>


<ab>Make two small licks of <m>raw <al>mutton</al> flesh</m>, and with a blindfold, apply it at night on your <bp>eyes</bp>.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p011v_3</id>
<head>For coating with <m><fr>or mat</fr></m></head>


<ab>There is nothing better than the black varnish of <pro>sword-makers</pro> to make a ground layer because it dries immediately &amp; makes the <m>gold</m> appear very beautiful.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p011v_4</id>
<head>Making <tl><m>diamond</m> points</tl> for engraving</head>


<ab>These are for sketching what you want to draw on <m>stones</m> and for engraving. When these <tl>points</tl> are too dull and cannot engrave, it is necessary to rub <m>diamond</m> against <m>diamond</m>; one can rub them with <m><tl>pumice stone</tl> powder</m>. It is necessary to strip what you want to engrave on a <tl><m>lead</m> wheel</tl> or with a <m><tl>stone</tl></m> or with <m><tl>glass</tl></m>, because the polishing is like varnish or <m>glass</m> and stops the <m>diamond</m> or <m>sapphire</m> from engraving well. This is why it does not engrave easily on <m>horn</m>, which is polished and fat.  But when the polish has been taken off, it is easy to engrave.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p011v_5</id>
 
<head>Polishing a <tl><m>copper</m> wheel</tl></head>


<ab>Instead of polishing your <m>stone</m>, it is necessary to remove the grease by rubbing the flesh side of a piece of <m>leather</m> <sup>on the <tl>wheel</tl></sup>, all while spinning the <tl>wheel</tl> if you have not worked on it in a long time.</ab></div></root>