<root><page>012r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f29.image</image>
 
<div>
<id>p012r_1</id>
<head>For molding from <m>sulfur</m></head>


<ab><m>Sulfur</m> is made beautiful by mixing in <m>soot black</m> or powdered <m>sanguine</m>, which makes it harder and stronger. After letting it melt entirely until it becomes liquid and similar to <m>oil</m>, <sup>then</sup> mixing it with <m>verdigris</m>, you can use it for casting a <al>lizard</al> or something else in <m>plaster</m>, very cleanly.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
You must not cast it until it has cooled down and lost all its bubbles and eyes, and its surface has fallen and become flat as <m>water</m>. <m>Soot black</m> gives it a fine luster and makes it neater. Use yellow <m>sulfur</m> of the best kind, as the greyish natural sulfur is no good. Don't cast it in the wind and cold for it would fill with bubbles.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p012r_2</id>
<head><m>Cimolee</m></head>


<ab><m>Cimolee</m>, otherwise known as fuller’s earth, or <pro><oc>fuller</oc></pro>s’ clay (fullers meaning those who finish cloth) is an excellent material for molding hollow or in relief. If you want to reheat it, it should first be warm and you should reheat gently from a distance, and little by little, otherwise it will crack. To reheat the figure put it in a <tl>pot</tl> in an <tl>oven</tl>, or in a <tl>closed oven</tl>. It comes out very smooth, clean and fine. With <m>cimolee</m> you can make a hollow mold of an animal and cast it in <m>lead</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The work needs to have dried for 4 or 5 days before you bake it. When you are molding and making a hollow in <m>cimolee</m>, don't press all at once, but gently, or else it would split.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p012r_3</id> 
<head><m>Paper</m></head>


<ab>The whitest and thinnest is the best. And when the hollow mold is quite clean, as when it is made of <m>sulfur</m> or baked <m>cimolee</m>, <sup>the paper</sup> comes out very clean. You can apply a layer or two of <m>white</m>, with a border of <m>gold</m>, to imitate <m>alabaster</m>. And after applying the <m>white</m> you may burnish it with a <tl>tooth</tl>. Yet in order for it to take burnish you should soak the <m>lead white</m> with <m>egg white</m> and <m>peelings from the fig tree</m>. Or better still, varnish your work with <m>white varnish</m>. Also while you are molding with <m>paper</m>, as it starts drying, burnish the back of it with the <tl>tooth</tl>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p012r_4</id>
<head><m>Plaster</m></head>


<ab>Mountain <m>plaster</m> is greyer, and that from the region of <pl>Albi</pl> is whiter. It has to be heated over a closed fire, such as a <tl>reverberatory furnace</tl> or <tl><fr>fours de barbiers</fr></tl>. The more freshly heated, the better it is to work with. It should be finely crushed on <m><tl>marble</tl></m>. After preparing your hollow mold of <m>sulfur</m> or another [material] and oiling it and surrounding it with a circle, soak your <m>plaster</m> in <m>water</m>, not too thick, and rub it well with your <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl>, and if it makes bubbles, throw on more powder of the said <m>plaster</m> and crush it with your <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl> until <figure>+</figure></ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<figure>+</figure> it makes no more bubbles. Then once more throw and sprinkle <m>plaster</m> powder on top and leave to set well, then scrape the powder off.</ab>
</div></root>