<root><page>012r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f29.image</image>
 
<div>
<id>p012r_1</id>
<head>Molding <m>sulfur</m></head>


<ab><m>Sulfur</m> is made beautiful mixed with <m>soot black</m> or pulverized <m>bloodstone</m>, which makes it harder and stronger. Having let it melt well until it becomes liquid, like <m>oil</m>, mix it with <m>verdigris</m>, and you <del>m</del> will cast in <m>plaster</m> very cleanly a <al>lizard</al>, or something else.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
You must not cast it until it is well cooled and has lost all of its lumps and bubbles, and it has settled down and become even like <del>[illegible]</del> <m>water</m>. The <m>soot black</m> gives it a fine luster and makes it neater. The most beautiful yellow <m>sulfur</m> must be used, for the greyish and lively <m>sulfur</m> is not good. Do not cast in <env>wind</env> and <env>cold</env>, for it would become porous.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p012r_2</id>
<head><m>Cimolee</m></head>


<ab><m>Cimolee</m>, otherwise known as <m><pro>fuller</pro>’s earth</m>, which prepares <m>cloth</m>, is excellent for molding hollow or in relief. And if you want to reheat it, it must first be warm, and reheat it gently on low, indirect flame, and little by little, otherwise it would crack. Put the figure for reheating in a <tl>pot</tl> in an <tl>oven</tl>, or in a <tl>covered oven</tl>. It is very malleable, clean and fine. <add>You can make a hollow for animals of <m>cimolee</m> and cast <m>lead</m> in it.</add></ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The work needs to be dry for 4 or 5 <ms>days</ms> before you reheat it. When you mold and make a hollow in <m>cimolee</m>, do not press too hard, but gently, for it would crack.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p012r_3</id> 
<head><m>Paper</m></head>


<ab>The whitest and thinnest is the best. And when the hollow mold is quite clean, as when it is made of <m>sulfur</m> or baked <m>cimolee</m>, <sup>the paper</sup> comes out very clean. You can apply a layer or two of <m>white</m>, with a border of <m>gold</m>, to imitate <m>alabaster</m>. And after applying the <m>white</m> you may burnish it with a <tl>tooth</tl>. Yet in order for it to take burnish you should soak the <m>lead white</m> with <m>egg white</m> and <m>peelings from the fig tree</m>. Or better still, varnish your work with <m>white varnish</m>. Also while you are molding with <m>paper</m>, as it starts drying, burnish the back of it with the <tl>tooth</tl>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p012r_4</id>
<head><m>Plaster</m></head>


<ab><env>Mountain</env> <m>plaster</m> is greyer, and <del>the</del> the one from the region of <pl>Albi</pl> is whiter. It must be heated over a closed fire, such as a <tl>reverberatory furnace</tl> or <tl><fr>fours de barbiers</fr></tl>. And the best to work with is the most recently heated one. It must be finely ground on <tl><m>marble</m></tl>. After preparing your hollow mold with <m>sulfur</m> or something else, and <m>oiling</m> it, and investing with a <corr>circle</corr>, temper not too thickly your <m>plaster</m> with <m>water</m>, and stir it well with your <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl>, and if it makes lumps, throw in more powder of the said <m>plaster</m> and <del>[illegible]</del> grind it with your <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl> until <figure>+</figure></ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<figure>+</figure> it makes no more lumps. Then immediaty throw in and sprinkle <m>plaster</m> powder and leave to set well, then scrape the powder off.</ab>
</div></root>