<root><page>012v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f30.image</image>


<div>
<id>p012v</id>
<head>Moulding <m>stucco</m> promptly</head>


<ab>Grind and pulverize finely <m>brick</m> or <m><pl>Armenian</pl> bole</m> or <m>bloodstone</m> and incorporate it with melted <m>wax</m>, and thus melted, throw like others on a relief medal, and thus you will have a cavity where you will be able to cast with plaster, crushed <m>paper</m> or <m>cimolee</m>.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Finely <tl>sieved</tl> <m>brick</m> is better, because the <m>bole</m> is too fat</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p012v_2</id>
<head>Cleaning yellow <m>pearls</m></head>


<ab>Gently boil them in a <pro>goldsmith</pro>'s <tl><fr>bouteure</fr></tl> then, with <m>tripoly</m> and a small piece of <m>leather</m>, sprinkled on the flesh side with the powder of the said <m>tripoly</m>, rub and polish the <m>pearl</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p012v_3</id>
<head>To whiten <m>enilanroc</m></head>


<ab>Some believe the <m>ceruse</m>-color crust that is on top to be natural. Others say that it is a lost secret of ancient <pro>lapidaries</pro>. Others say that it is <m>enamel</m> that has been reheated. And, from this crust, one can form multiple ciphers, letters, circles and other bizarre motifs. As to the means, I proceeded thus: I once wanted to add a layer of <m>arsenic</m> ground on <m><tl>marble</tl></m>. However, I did the experiment without it, and I put the above mentioned thing, <m>enilanroc</m>, in a small <m>iron</m> <tl>casket</tl> on the fire of my <tl><pro>goldsmith</pro>'s forge</tl> with three or four small half-burnt <m>coals</m> and blew on it only with my mouth. However, the thing caught fire and became all white, not only on its surface but also inside. And then I let it cool on its own near the fire, since otherwise, exposing it suddenly to cold air, it would have cracked. While it was all white, I passed it through my <tl><m>lead</m> wheel</tl> and I found it to be as hard as it was before. And after scraping off a little of the white, I found it to be of a clear fleshy tone. Finally, I polished it and observed that it took quite a beautiful polish luster and that it could compare with a quite beautiful <m>agate</m> for the purpose of engraving it with some beautiful face and applying it to a table of
</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>