<root><page>013r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f31.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p012v_3</id>
<ab>
<m>agate</m> of various colors. But because this overall whiteness did not correspond with the white crust on the surface that I was seeking, leaving the rest of the thing its natural color, I made a hole in a <m>brick</m>, precisely the same size as the object, and put it inside. Then I heated two <tl><pro>glassmaker</pro>'s soldering irons</tl> until they became red hot and, when they were red hot, I applied them one after the other onto the surface of the object until I got the white crust I was looking for, on which I made the drawing that I wanted, revealing the red background, with a <tl><m>diamond</m> point</tl>, and I polished it with <m>hog bristles</m> and <m>tripoli</m>. I don't know if it would be better to reheat it under hot <m>ashes</m>, and if it would be good to encase it in <m>alabaster</m>, which is quite cold, as I did in the <m>brick</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p013r_1</id>  
<head>Flesh color with <m>arsenic</m></head>
<ab><m>Sublimated arsenic</m>, that is to say, the white kind sold as stone, when powdered on <m><tl>marble</tl></m>, mixed with <m>vermilion</m> or <m>laque</m> or <m>mine</m>, produces a beautiful flesh color that always shines. <m>Yellow arsenic</m> has a very beautiful color, the white one works well in <m>oil</m> and goes well with <m>lake</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p013r_2</id> 
<head>To dye</head>
<ab>Mix <m>sal ammoniac</m> and <m>vitriol</m> and boil them together. Then mix in <m>lake</m> or <m>verdigris</m> and <m>azure</m> or similar <sup>colors</sup>, and dye. This will not come off unless the <al>animal</al> sheds. @<la>Non bona</la>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p013r_3</id>
<head>Polishing of <m>stones</m></head>
<ab>Engraved <m>stones</m> are not polished on a <tl><m>copper</m> wheel</tl>, but with <tl>brushes</tl> and <m>tripoli</m>. Yet faceted and flat stones are polished on the said <tl>wheel</tl>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p013r_4</id> 
<head>Fine <tl>sieves</tl> of raw <m>silk</m></head>
<ab>Tammy of raw <m>silk</m> is made on a weaver, to make very fine and delicate <tl>sieves</tl>. And for that effect, you must not choose raw <m>silk</m> whitened by <m>sulfur</m> smoke: this covers the <m>silk</m> in a sticky vapor that would hold the flour and in the end would prevent it from</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>