<root><page>013v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f32.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p013r_4</id>
<ab>
passing through so well. But for this effect, choose yellow and natural raw <m>silk</m> because it is stronger and rejects <m>flour</m> as <m><al>horse</al>hair</m> does.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p013v_1</id>
<head>To recognize good <m>azur dust</m> for <m>oil</m></head>


<ab>The one that piles up in small clods and is lumpy is the best because it is finer. Also the one that is also very pale in color, because <m>oil</m> darkens it. Certain sophists mix them together, but you will find this out if you pour some onto a piece of <m>paper</m> and lay it flat and spread it with your <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl> since, if it is mixed, it will be found varied and so to say with light and darker stripes, but if it is whole it will be even and of one color.
</ab>
</div>




<div>
<id>p013v_2</id>
<head>Whitening <m>pearls</m></head>


<ab>When they have been applied in embroidery on some garment, they are greasy and may be cleaned in <m>soapy water</m>.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p013v_3</id>
<head><m>Toadstone</m></head>


<ab>That which comes from the head of the <al>toad</al> and has the shape of the <al>toad</al>, painted naturally as you have seen, is the most excellent. It is said that if powder made from it is put on a <tl>brazier</tl> in someone's room at night, they will be unable to move, speak, or stop <pro>thieves</pro>.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p013v_4</id> 
<head><al>Snakes</al></head>


<ab>It is said that if one calls a <al>snake</al> in Greek, saying <greek>ΟΦΗ ΟΦΗ</greek>, it will flee. Likewise, if one <del>nom</del> calls a <al>swine</al> in Greek, <del>y</del> <greek>ïon</greek>, it will come.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p013v_5</id> 
<head>Candles</head>


<ab><pro>Candlemakers</pro> never make good candles when the <oc><env>autan</env></oc> wind blows because they always melt, however good is the <m>tallow</m> they use in them.
</ab>
</div></root>