<root><page>015r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f35.image</image>


<div>
<id>p015r_a1</id>
<head><m>Damask Cloth</m></head>


<ab>You can make <m>damask cloth</m> of two different colours and imitate embroidery without adding anything else to it, as follows. Once it is is <m>dye</m>d yellow, pounce onto it such a pattern as will please you. Then you will sew some <m>string</m> or a bigger <m>cord</m> loosely onto the pattern and throw it into a <m>dye</m> of <m>woad</m> or <m>pastel</m> and it will become green, except that which is beneath the <m>string</m>, which will remain yellow because the <m>green dye</m> will not have penetrated there. And you can do the same with other colours and, instead of <m>string</m> or <m>cord</m>, add some pieces of poor quality <m>cloth</m> cut in Moorish shapes on top of the first colour. In that manner, you will have cheap embroidery.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p015r_a2</id>
<head>Casting <m>metals</m></head>


<ab>Candlesticks and small works are cast in a <tl>frame</tl> with sand. Having stamped the work, sprinkle it with <m>flour</m> in order to make the <m>copper</m> or <m>latten</m> run better. When the sand has been in use for one month, it is necessary to take some new <sup>sand</sup> because that which has been used, being reheated <figure>+</figure>, dries &amp; loses its binding power. Yet it is used mixed with the new <sup>sand</sup>, because it makes the work less porous. Large works such as artillery, bells and similar things are cast in <m>earth</m>, and <m>copper</m> cast in <m>earth</m> makes less <m>crust</m> and is whiter than when cast in sand. The <m>earth</m> is <m>sandy clay</m> mixed with <m>horse dung</m> and <m>cloth</m> waste. The <m>earth</m> that has been used for casting, which is black, baked and as if burnt, is mixed with artificial sand, and is very good. For softening and making the <m>copper</m> run, once it is melted, one throws in some <m>lead</m>, which does not form an alloy but is found on the surface of the cast.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<figure>+</figure> by the heat of molten <m>metal</m></ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p015r_a3</id>
<head>Casting <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m></head>


<ab>The <m>sand</m> must be made from something very dry and arid and reheated well because, if it were humid, like <pro>founder</pro>'s sand, the <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m> would leap out <sup>of the mold</sup> and sustain damage. It is also necessary for the <m>earth</m> to absorb the <m>metal</m> because cast <m>gold</m> or <m>silver</m> become very porous. That is why it must be beaten out again, otherwise it is brittle, as seen in <tl>spoon</tl> handles.</ab>
</div></root>