<root><page>015v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f36.item</image>


<div>
<id>p015v_1</id>
<head>Tablets</head>
<ab>Some are made from <m>boxwood</m> inlaid with <m>ebony</m>, <m>sandalwood</m>, <m>ivory</m>, or <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m> like <m>damascening</m>. Then one writes on it with <tl>silverpoint</tl>, and next erases it with a <m><al>cuttlefish</al> bone</m> by rubbing them.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p015v_2</id>
<head>Making letters easier to read</head>
<ab>One cuts the largest pieces of <m>beryl</m> or <m>crystal</m> round on one side and flat on the other, then one fits it with a little handle and puts the flat side on the letter</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p015v_3</id>
<head>Stamping</head>
<ab>If you have a  <m>bronze</m> medal and you want to make it very light, make a <m>lead</m> cavity, then spread upon it a thin plate of <m>gold</m>, or sheets of <m>lead</m> or reheated <m>silver</m>, place your <m>bronze</m> medal on top and hammer it with a <m>wood</m> <tl>mallet</tl>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p015v_4</id>
<head>Softening <m>horn</m></head>
<ab>
Those who mount <del>acou</del> <la>Agnus Dei</la>s and make circles from <m>horn</m> for certain little boxes soften the said circles by soaking them in hot <m>water</m> and then shape them on a round or oval-shaped <tl>triblet</tl>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p015v_5</id>
<head>Ears</head>
<ab>When a defluxion occurs in the <bp>ear</bp>, be very careful not to put anything in it, and following the proverb, <bp>ears</bp> and <bp>eyes</bp> should only be touched with your <bp>elbow</bp>. However, to an affected <bp>ear</bp>, it is good to apply musky <m>cotton</m>, that is to say, <m>cotton</m> kept in <pa>musk</pa>, which comforts quite well.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p015v_6</id>
<head><bp>Tooth</bp>ache</head>
<ab>Some put a clove of <m>garlic</m> in the <bp>ear</bp> on the side of the aching <bp>tooth</bp>, and after two or three hours they feel better. Others put in their <bp>nostril</bp>, on the same side as the <bp>tooth</bp> that hurts, some green skin scraped from the stem of <fr>bisaube</fr>, namely that which is under the grey one that looks like a vine.</ab>
</div></root>