<root><page>016v</page> 


<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f38.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p016r_1</id>
<ab>which is usually of 3 <fr><ms>pan</ms></fr>s high. But first of all, you have to reheat your <tl>furnace</tl> with some big <m>charcoal</m>, so the bottom is red hot and then you will put the said <m>charcoal</m> measure in the middle of which you will put your <m>iron</m>, not at once but ten or fifteen <ms>pound</ms>s each time. And since it will be swallowed at the <tl>furnace</tl> bottom, keep putting some more. And add three or four <ms>shovel</ms>s of bigger <m>charcoal</m> and avoid it from getting consumed too quickly by wetting it. And when you will see your <tl>furnace</tl> full of two <ms>quintal</ms>s of matter, or less if you don't have that much, you will leave the <m>charcoal</m> consume itself. And when the <m>charcoal</m> is almost dying at the <tl>furnace</tl>'s level, you will be able to pour in the moulds and <m>iron</m> or <m>metal</m> shells, which is even better for one <m>metal</m> will bite the other. And the inside of the mold has to be covered with soaked <m>ashes</m>, so it doesn't adhere to it.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p016v_1</id>
<head>Against Go<exp>norrhea</exp></head>


<ab>Soak some <m><pa>quince</pa> seeds</m> in some clear <m>water</m> and inject this viscous <m>water</m></ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p016v_2</id>
<head>To take fine forehead hair off</head>


<ab>Have a loose <m>silk</m> <tl>needle</tl> and put it tight through hair bulbs and they will bite the <m>silk</m> like fine <m>cotton</m> wisps.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p016v_3</id>
<head><m>Silk</m></head>


<ab><m>Crimson silk</m> is more frequent than all the other ones because its colour is not as expensive as blue or green ones which are, also, good bargain for the <pro>worker</pro>. <m>Black silk</m> is less frequent because it costs a lot.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p016v_a4</id>
<head>How to keep <m>oranges</m></head>


<ab>You have to choose them whole and not rotten and then fill a firmly closed  <tl><m>tin</m> vessel</tl> with them and they will be fine for six months</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p016v_a5</id>
<head>Candles</head>


<ab>They can be kept in some <m>bran</m> which make them white and last more, according to some. I believe, however, that it is enough to keep them in a cool and dry place, so they are not pressed. It is better if there is a <m>hemp</m> thread inside the wick of the candle to give more light and maintain wick straighter. If it is otherwise all <m>cotton</m> made, as those of <pl>Montauban</pl> do, it needs to be snuffed out often because if it has been burning for a while, <m>cotton</m> falls down and make the candle drip.</ab>
</div></root>