<root><page>017r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f39.image</image>


<div>
<id>p017r_1</id>


<head>On <pro>cannon-makers</pro></head>


<ab>
Cannon has a range of five to six hundred <ms>paces</ms>, but for a battery, the range is a maximum of two or three hundred <ms>paces</ms> to be effective. It should not be any farther. Its cannonball usually weighs 40 <ms>lb</ms> of the King's standard. The fowler weighs 25 <ms>quintals</ms> and is a small, short cannon for fighting the casemates of moats and at close range. It shoots large cannonballs that weigh, like the others, 40 <ms>lb</ms> of the King's standard. The breech is two balls and a quarter thick; the mouth is one ball and a third thick. Its load is similar to the biggest ones, that is to say 20 <ms>pounds</ms>. And if you want to try it, don't overload it, for it would damage it. And the first time and the first five or six shots, it is better not to load it completely, it adjusts itself. What one can do in such a case, is to load 20 <ms>pounds</ms> of fine arquebus <m>powder</m> instead of ordinary cannon <m>powder</m>. And four good <al>horses</al> are enough to carry it. They are easy to use and on a small distance they are as strong as the big ones even for private houses and small <fr>billattes</fr> and less important fortresses. They are less prone to breaking than other <sup>cannons</sup> because they are short. What gives strength to the <m>powder</m> and increases the danger of breaking is the length of the cannon, because the <m>powder</m> burns entirely and its force is held longer within the longer cannon than the short one. The fowler is usually seven to eight <fr><ms>pans</ms></fr> long. It is true that this measure is a <ms><pl>Montpellier</pl> <fr>pan</fr></ms> and not a <ms>King's pan</ms>, the latter is not used for good cannon founding. Since the <ms><pl>Montpellier</pl> <fr>pan</fr></ms> is shorter, cannons made using this measure are shorter, but compensate in thickness the ones made using the <ms>King's <fr>pan</fr></ms>, which are longer, but more fragile. The Fowler's strength for battery is 80 <fr><ms>pans</ms></fr>.</ab>


<ab> 
<margin>left-top</margin>
The great cannon, because of its cannonball's weight, ranges not further than a thousand or twelve hundred <ms>paces</ms> without landing, and usually makes 3 jumps.</ab>


<ab> 
<margin>left-top</margin>
Fowlers have only a short range efficiency.</ab>


<ab> 
<margin>left-middle</margin>
You recognize a cannon's good alloy when you see it. If there is green color on the surface becomes red, it means they are made of a sufficient quantity of <m>rosette</m>. Otherwise, the cannon's <m>metal</m> will appear whitish. If you don't see it, just scratch it and you will see it. </ab>


<ab> 
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
The good alloy for the cannon is three <fr><ms>pans</ms></fr> of <m>rosette</m> and one of big bells' fine <m>metal</m>, where there is more <m>rosette</m> than in small bells' <m>metal</m>. This <m>metal</m> usually costs 15 <cn>pounds</cn> and fine <m>rosette</m> 15 or 16.</ab>


<ab> 
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<ms><pl>Montpellier</pl> <fr>pan</fr></ms> is equivalent to six <ms>King's inches</ms>, which is equivalent to two ordinary. </ab>


<ab> 
<margin>bottom</margin>
To level a cannon properly, one needs to have the mouth as high as the breech. Otherwise, you do not aim well.
</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>