<root><page>019v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f44.image</image>
<div>
<id>p019v_1</id>


<head> 
Mathematical figures without a <tl>ruler</tl> or <tl>compass</tl></head>


<ab> 
You know how to draw a circle correctly with the <tl>quill</tl> &amp; or else with the nail of your right <tl><bp>thumb</bp></tl> &amp; the bent <tl><bp>big finger</bp></tl>. If you do not have a <tl>ruler</tl>, fold <m>paper</m> in two five or six times to use it. And if you want to draw a column, arch, oval, escutcheon correctly without a <tl>compass</tl>, fold your <m>paper</m> such that the fold <del><fr>e</fr></del> gives you a straight line, at the required distance from which, trace a point <del>&amp; a</del> or a line &amp; saturate it well with <m>ink</m>. Then fold again the <m>paper</m> &amp; rub it on the back &amp; it will stamp however much you have made. In that way <del><fr>la l</fr></del>, A is the line without <m>ink</m> which the <m>paper</m> fold gives you, B is the line you have traced, C is the one which is stamped.


<figure>
<id>fig_p019v_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SUUzLXQ4UVlGR1U</link>
<!--Philip Cherian: Figure under text of block, placed after In this way-->
</figure>


<figure>
<id>fig_p019v_2</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5cy0tdXF5MGJTLU0</link>
</figure>


<figure>
<id>fig_p019v_3</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5R0VMdFQ3VC1lQmM</link>
</figure>


<figure>
<id>fig_p019v_4</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5TGJOZGVvTmV1LW8</link>
</figure>
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p019v_2</id>
<head><del><fr>P</fr></del>For writing as well from the left as from the right</head>


<ab> 
Write as best you can with well-gummed <m>ink</m> on as many little cards as you want to write words. &amp; once each letter is well saturated with <m>ink</m>, put it down on your <m>paper</m> &amp; rub with a <tl>tooth</tl> the back of the card.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p019v_3</id>
<head>Enemas</head>


<ab> 
They used to mount them with a <tl><m>leather</m> handle</tl> or <tl>pocket</tl>, the best one being of <m><al>cat</al> pelt</m> which is more padded than any other else. And then they started to fold the <tl>handle</tl> from one side and then they kept folding it and turning it on itself and in that way enema runs slowly, but this manner takes more time and is less easy than a <tl>syringe</tl> which has been discovered since then with which a man can give to himself an enema. It is true that it always gives wind at the end.</ab>
</div></root>