<root><page>019v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f44.image</image>
<div>
<id>p019v_1</id>


<head> 
Mathematical figures without a <tl>ruler</tl> or <tl>compass</tl></head>


<ab> 
you know how to draw a circle with a <tl>quill</tl> and otherwise with your right <tl><bp>thumb nail</bp></tl> and your folded <tl><bp>big finger</bp></tl> if you don't have any <tl>ruler</tl>, fold a <m>paper</m> sheet in five or six folds to use it. And if you want to draw a column, arch, oval, cartouche correctly without a <tl>compass</tl>, fold your <m>paper</m> so the fold is a straight line from which you draw within the relevant distance a point or a line and fill it with some <m>ink</m>. Then fold again the <m>paper</m> and rub it on its reverse and it will stamp whatever you have made. In that way, A is the line without <m>ink</m> made by the <m>paper</m> fold, B is the line you have drawn, C is the stamped one.


<figure>
<id>fig_p019v_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SUUzLXQ4UVlGR1U</link>
<!--Philip Cherian: Figure under text of block, placed after In this way-->
</figure>


<figure>
<id>fig_p019v_2</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5cy0tdXF5MGJTLU0</link>
</figure>


<figure>
<id>fig_p019v_3</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5R0VMdFQ3VC1lQmM</link>
</figure>


<figure>
<id>fig_p019v_4</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5TGJOZGVvTmV1LW8</link>
</figure>
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p019v_2</id>
<head>To write as easily from the left as from the right</head>


<ab> 
Write in the best manner possible with some well gummed <m>ink</m> on as many cards as many words you want to write and when your letter is full of <m>ink</m>, apply your <m>paper</m> and rub with a <tl>tooth</tl> the back of the cards.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p019v_3</id>
<head>Enemas</head>


<ab> 
They used to mount them with a <tl><m>leather</m> handle</tl> or <tl>pocket</tl>, the best one being of <m><al>cat</al> pelt</m> which is more padded than any other else. And then they started to fold the <tl>handle</tl> from one side and then they kept folding it and turning it on itself and in that way enema runs slowly, but this manner takes more time and is less easy than a <tl>syringe</tl> which has been discovered since then with which a man can give to himself an enema. It is true that it always gives wind at the end.</ab>
</div></root>