<root><page>020r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f45.image</image>
 
<div>
<id>p020r_1</id>
<head>@For making <m>millas</m></head>


<ab>You must have some <m>millet</m> soaked in order to remove the <m>chaff</m> and then clean it well. Next you must <tl>grind</tl> it again quite finely and pass through a cloth <tl>sieve</tl>. One must soak the <m>flour</m> with fresh melted <m>butter</m> and some <m>milk</m> so that it is very light, like the <m>pastry</m> to make <m>beignets</m>, and add <m>egg yolk</m> depending on the amount of <m>flour</m>, so that there are two <m>egg yolks</m> for each <m>millas</m>. Then you will put in some <m><pa>saffron</pa></m> if you want to give them a little colour.</ab> 


<ab>Afterwards you must have some <tl>mold</tl>s, which must be made from <m>terra<sup>cotta</sup></m>, in the shape of the bottom of the catholic hat, but it must be open at both ends. And then, having made a good fire, clean where you want to put your <m>millas</m> and then take your <tl>mold</tl>s and grease them very well so that the <m>pastry</m> does not stick to them when baked. Once you have done that, put your <tl>mold</tl>s in a place in the <tl>oven</tl> where you clean and sprinkle a bit of <m>flour</m> on the bottom and fill them with some of the aforementioned <m>pastry</m>. Then you will cover the said <tl>mold</tl>s, with a <tl>lid</tl> made like the <tl>mold</tl>, but it must be bigger and not open at the top. Then once done, you will put some <m>straw</m> on the said <tl>lid</tl> and a lot of hot <m>charcoal</m>, and set a fire around it, once done, you will open up one of them after a bit of time and will see when it is baked, it will be hard.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p020r_2</id>
<head>@<pro>Glazier</pro></head>


<ab><m>Glass from <pl>Lorraine</pl></m> is smoother and more even than <m>plate glass</m>. It is more durable and enduring. But commonly it is tainted with veins as if with straight lines and wrinkles, which happens because once the <pro>glassmakers</pro> have made it put it still hot on <m>straw</m> which therefore stains it. One can, however, rub it off with some varnish, <m>salt</m> and other <m>drugs</m> used by <pro>glassmakers</pro>. <m><pl>Lorraine</pl> glass</m> is sold by <ms>band</ms>s and each <ms>band</ms> is composed of three <ms>panel</ms>s. A <ms>band</ms> costs usually X <fr><cn>soul</cn></fr>s. The <m>plate glass</m> is made in <pl>France</pl>, it is whiter and clearer but it does not last as long as that from <pl>Lorraine</pl>. It is also commonly blown And in that case, it is better to cut little lozenges rather than large square pieces in the shape of a frame because they cannot sit themselves well evenly.</ab>


<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>
The <m>plate glass</m> is sold in <ms>set</ms>s. Every set contains 4 <ms>plate</ms>s that are usually sold at 10 or twelve <cn>lb</cn>s.</ab>
</div></root>