<root><page>020v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f46.image</image>


<div>
<id>p020v_1</id> 
<head>To whiten the <bp>face</bp></head>


<ab>Pound <m><pa>puffball</pa></m> in <m>cistern water</m>, and no other, and wash with this whitened <m>water</m>. This is highly regarded. And I believe that making it from <m><pa>wheat</pa> starch</m> and using that would be even better.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p020v_2</id> 
<head>Against windiness, colic, etc.</head>


<ab><m>Sap squeezed<sup> from <pa>orange</pa> peel</sup></m> or <m>water distilled from <pa>orange</pa> peel</m> is excellent against windy colics. <m>Candied peel</m> is also excellent for <bp>stomach</bp> winds. And to try it, having poured <m>sparkling wine</m> in a <tl>glass</tl>, press <m><pa>orange</pa> juice</m> on the <m>wine's foam</m>, which comes only from vapor and wind, and you will see that the foam will immediately disappear. Also, if you squeeze <m>juice</m> against a candle it will burn brighter.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p020v_3</id>
<head><m><fr><pa>Eschervis</pa> racine</fr></m></head>


<ab>They want to be planted in a very humid place or such that, with <sup>water from</sup> wells or fountains, they can be frequently watered, because this makes them tender. Otherwise a hard core forms inside, which takes away all their goodness.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p020v_4</id>
<head>Against burns</head>


<ab>Pound an <m><pa>onion</pa></m> with <m>verjuice</m> and leave it to soak like this, then apply it.
Or better, apply <m>black soap</m> on the burn. Experimented.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p020v_5</id>
<head>A common saying</head>


<ab>Steeple of <pl>Rodez</pl>, church of <pl>Albi</pl>, bells of <pl>Mende</pl>. However, the bell of <pl>Toulouse</pl> named Cardaillac is held to be one of the most beautiful in <pl>France</pl>, all the more since it weighs two hundred and fifty <fr><ms>quintal</ms></fr>s.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p020v_6</id>
<head>A form of regimen</head>


<ab>Every <tmp>morning</tmp>, take two or three <m>eggs</m> laid on the same day or the <tmp>day</tmp> before. Heat them up but do not cook them. Eat the <m>yolk</m>s well dusted with <m>sugar</m>. And afterwards drink one <ms><bp>finger</bp></ms> of <m>wine</m>. And in addition to being nourishing, it is good for the <bp>stomach</bp>.
</ab>
</div></root>