<root><page>028v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f62.image</image>
<div>
<id>p028v_1</id>
<head><pro>Pewterers</pro></head>


<ab>They think that the best <m>tin</m> is the one that comes in <fr>saulmons</fr>, which has not been remelted since it came from the mine, because the masters remelt it on the grill, weighing two or three pounds, to more easily cut it and sell it by the piece. And in this they often mix in left-overs from bars of <m>soldering</m> and common <m>tin</m>. And to recognise the best one, it is the most lustrous, which is almost burnished, because it is softer. Sometimes in their ingots they find pieces of <m>iron</m>, <m>stones</m>, or similar troublesome additions, made to cheat on the weight. The <m>tin</m> from <pl>England</pl> is so hard that the <pro>miners</pro> add <m>lead</m> to soften it. The one that comes from <pl>Germany</pl> is softer. Usually, the master <pro>pewterers</pro>, sworn in to the good cities, add 6 or 8 pounds of fine <m>lead</m> to a quintal of fine <m>tin</m>. The others, who work in the fields, add fifteen or twenty <sup>pounds</sup> or as much as they can, and to disguise the darkness and the softness of the <m>lead</m>, they put in <m>looking-glass tin</m>, 4 lb. per quintal, <figure>+</figure>, which whitens and hardens, and six or height lb. of <m>rosette</m>, to give the plate a good ring. To cast platters and plates, they make them out of <fr>pierre morte</fr>, that is from <m>grès</m>, and they form and polish them on the <sup>potter's</sup> wheel. They melt their <m>tin</m> in an <m>iron</m> posnet on a <m>charcoal</m> fire, and with an <m>iron</m> spoon that holds the quantity sufficient for a platter, they cast in their cold molds, which they keep joined and squeeze between their knees. Soon, they open the molds so that they do not heat up, and having taken out the casting which is on the female side, and which breaks easily. Then, with a <tl>piece of cloth</tl> soaking in <m>water</m>, which they always have at hand, they rub the middle of the back side of the plate and around the edge, so that it comes out better, and they rub the <tl>female</tl> mold with it.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<figure>+</figure> 
When the <m>tin</m> is fine, one adds less <m>glass-looking tin</m> to it, that is 4 lb. per quintal, but if the <m>tin</m> is low<sup>-quality</sup>, that is allied with a lot of <m>lead</m>, one adds at least five or six lb. of <m>looking-glass tin</m> to it. If there is not a lot of <m>looking-glass tin</m>, one adds about two or three lb. per quintal. One adds eight lb. of <m>rosette</m>. But if there is a lot of <m>looking-glass tin</m>, about 4 or 5 lb., one only adds six of <m>rosette</m>. And commonly, for one quintal of <m>tin</m>, one adds x lb. of both.
</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p028v_2</id>
<head>Go to the fifth page.</head>
</div></root>