<root><page>029r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f63.image</image>


<div>
<id>p029r_1</id>
<head><m>Stucco</m> for molding</head>


<ab>Take <m>tragacanth gum</m> and put it to soak until, having absorbed its <m>water</m>, it is swollen and becomes like <m>jelly</m>. Then crush it quite forcefully on the <tl><m>marble</m></tl> and then take <m><pa>rye</pa> flour</m>, which is better than that from<m><pa>wheat</pa></m> because it is more humid and does not make the paste as rough, and dust your <m>tragacanth gum</m> with it and thus continue to pound and mix in the very finely sieved <m>flour</m>, little by little. And knead as if you wanted to make <m>bread</m>, until you perceive that it has enough body and is as firm as <m>bread dough</m> that is ready for the <tl>oven</tl>. This is perceptible when it can stretch enough without breaking. And if it is not strong enough, it will not come off [the surface] properly. It being thus prepared, rub the hollow [part of the mold] with <m>oil</m> with a <tl>brush</tl>, so that the <m>oil</m> penetrates everywhere to make it come off better, and press the paste inside quite forcefully. And if it does not come off well, mix in more <m>flour</m> until it has enough body. With this you will mold very neatly such work, either masks or garlands, as you like, and they will be dry within one <ms>day</ms>. Afterwards, you apply them with <m>strong glue</m> or <m>paste glue</m>, as you like, and you will be able to paint and furnish them with <m>gold</m> and all colors. In <pl>Rome</pl> they make floor ornaments with it. You can make bed ornaments with it. <rub>If you want that the work remains white</rub>, it is better to mold with <m>plaster</m> instead of <m>flour</m>. It is true that it is also more brittle and firm, but it must be prepared like this: mix it while it is a powder in a good amount of <m>water</m> so that it is light-colored and pound it several times a day for fifteen <ms>days</ms>. Then pour water by inclination, collect the <m>plaster</m> and crush it fine on the <tl><m>marble</m></tl>, and put it in a clean <tl><m>lead</m> vessel</tl>, so that no dust or dirt falls into it, and leave it in the <env>open air</env> <fr><env>au serain</env></fr> for fifteen <ms>days</ms> with its <m>water</m>, and it will become matte, strong, white and light, very suitable to become the groundlayer for burnished <m>gold</m>. And you can mix some of this powder instead of <m>flour</m> with <m>tragacanth gum</m>, and your work will be beautiful. Instead of <m>plastre</m> you can mix in well ground <m>chalk</m> or <m>lead white</m>, and try <m>bole</m> and similar things. This <m>stucco</m> with the <m>tragacanth gum</m> has the peculiarity that it is pliable before it is dry, it fits on either round or flat things, as you like. It is to make an ornament at little expense.
</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
The <m>flour</m> is not good in this, but <m>chalk</m> or <m>lead white</m> [is].
</ab>
</div></root>