<root><page>029v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f64.item</image>


<div>
<id>p029v_1</id>
<head><m>Color of gold</m> without <m>gold</m> on <m>silver</m></head>




<ab>Color your applied <m>silver leaf</m> with <m><fr>terre emerita</fr></m> and once dry, give a handful of varnish of <m>aspic</m> and <m>sandarac</m>. And it will be more beautiful than <m>tinsel</m>.</ab></div>






<div>
<id>p029v_2</id>
<head><m>Layer of burnished gold </m> on <m>paper</m></head>


<ab>Make your ground layer of <m>starch</m> soaked in <m>water</m> &amp; your <m>gold</m> will burnish very well. Clear <m>starch water</m> layered on the <m>paper</m>, then dried, &amp; repeated in this manner three times, is a good layer for <m>burnished gold</m> on simple <m>paper</m> &amp; has no body.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p029v_3</id>
<head>Removing stains</head>




<ab>A good <m>eau de vie</m> takes it off if you rub your <m>cloth</m> with it.</ab></div>




<div>
<id>p029v_4</id>
<head>Ground layer of <m>gold</m></head>




<ab>Ground <m>terra emerita</m> with some <m>saffron</m>, all of it mixed with very clear <m><fr>colle forte</fr></m> &amp; passed through a <m>linen</m>.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p029v_5</id>
<head><m>Oil</m> extracts</head>


<ab><pro>Apothecaries</pro> say that anything with does not stick to a mortar while ground is oleaginous.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p029v_6</id>
<head><m>Dragon's blood</m></head>


<ab>Take a well chosen tear of it which shows off its transparent red. And put it in a <m>glass bottle</m> with enough quantity of the best <m>eau de vie</m> possible and close it diligently so it does not  get exposed to air otherwise it will be worth nothing and leave it so for a long time, because the longer it stays, the more beautiful and better it will be and it will dissolve if it is good otherwise it will become like <m>lees</m>. When you want to use some, make a small hole in the bottle stopper and pour some and close it again each time and apply it on gold. Good <m>dragon's blood</m> can be found in grands lopins like <m>cattle cake</m><add>this one has no worth if it is sophisticated</add> and broken it shows on its edges some transparent scale as light red enamel, it is also lumpy in some points like small rubies. The <m>eau de vie </m>must be very strong and plusieurs passes.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
The darker <m>dragon's blood</m> is the best and the larme is the most dying one, which you can find in lapin like <m>pitch</m> and <m>big nuts</m> which look like
<figure>
<id>fig_p029v_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5cXJfWVlSSGlKOGs</link>
<margin>right-bottom</margin>
</figure>
</ab>


 
<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
I put it in some ordinary <m>eau de vie</m>, adding some <m>aqua fortis</m> to give it strength. At the beginning the <m>water</m> turned slightly colored, but at the end it just looked like some tragacanth <m>gum</m> with which they sophisticate I think the <m>dragon's blood</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
When it is applied on <m>gold</m>, it is prone to break, this is why some apply on it some <m>turpentine oil</m>. Cold stops the <m>water</m> from pouring and taking the color off. And for that, you can hold it by the fire.</ab></div></root>