<root><page>030v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f66.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p030r_a2</id>
<ab>any dish or plate, they enlarge &amp; undo with the strike of a <tl>hammer</tl> the <m>iron</m> wedges that slide in the spokes of the <tl>wheel</tl>. And, when they are at the notch and the point that they need, they tighten the said wedges, striking them with the <tl>hammer</tl>.</ab>


<ab>When their plates or dishes have been cast, soldered if needed, &amp; recleansed of surrounding froth with the hot <tl>soldering iron</tl> &amp; then with a big <tl>file</tl>, they adapt it on the <tl>wheel</tl>. &amp; first of all they wrap the <del><tl><fr>desgrusouer</fr></tl></del> <tl><fr>desgrusouer</fr></tl> with a <tl>rope</tl> <corr><del>rope</del></corr>, as thick as the <ms><bp>little finger</bp></ms>, and lean it firmly on the <tl>crossbar</tl> to secure it well. And while someone else promptly turns the <tl>wheel</tl>, they guide the sharp edge of the <tl><fr>esgrusouer</fr></tl> by <bp>hand</bp> <del>s</del> towards the edge of the round cavity, &amp; gently guide it to the center of the circle. And this <tl><fr>desgrusouer</fr></tl> is for removing the first rough &amp;  lumpy skins of the work. And next, they even it out with a <tl>cutting <m>iron</m></tl> called a <fr>plane</fr>, on which they rub the sharp edge with a little putty, on a piece of wood nailed with leather <del>having</del>, and this, in such a way, that the flesh or grain is on the outside, for if the sharp edge of this <tl>plane</tl> was not thus rubbed &amp burnished, it would not polish <del>pas</del> &amp burnish the <m>tin</m>, <del>au</del> which would stay white, and not black &amp polished like a mirror. Moreover, they repair with this <tl><fr>plane</fr></tl> for the second time the work as they did with the <tl><fr>esgrusouer</fr></tl>. Then, with a <tl>knife</tl> or another <tl>sharp <m>iron</m></tl>, they scrape the edges of the plates or dishes to smooth them so that they are sharp while being handled</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>