<root><page>035v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f76.image</image>


<div>
<id>p035v_1</id>
<head>For preventing someone from eating <sup>a piece of</sup> <m>meat</m></head>


<ab>Dry some <m>calf's foot root</m>, otherwise <m>iarus</m>, and dust the meat with it. There is no danger in this. See @ Mattioli. </ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p035v_2</id>
<head>For making <m>grain</m> pass from one vessel to another</head>


<figure>
<id>fig_p035v_1</id>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5WEY2UUhMRTg4Y00</link>
</figure>


<ab>Take two small <m>wooden</m> cylindrical vessels @ of the same size, hollowed on the bottom exterior by about the width of one knife or more. One of the two will remain empty, and on the bottom of the other you will glue <m>grain</m> with <m>starch</m> so that it will be covered entirely with <m>grain</m>, and will appear to be filled with it. Also, take a <m>wooden</m> bell cover into which you will place as much grain as one of the vessels can hold, and over the top place a piece of plain <m>leather</m> that fits well inside the bell cover. Put all into a bag or a napkin or a folded handkerchief, unless you want to use a conjuror's pouch. First show the empty vessel, then in front of the audience fill it with grain, then replace it in the napkin. After, leave that one there and take the other where the grain has been glued with starch and it will appear to be the first one, filled with grain. Place it under a hat and place the bell cover on the table, gently this first time. And if you like, quickly and without stopping show the inside that is covered with white leather of the color of the wood. Then, pretending that you are showing the vessel that is under the hat, turn it deftly to the side that is empty and leave it covered, and then you will command that by invisibilim the grain pass into the bell cover, which you will have previously tapped on the table a little strongly, and the grain will fall to the bottom and cover the piece of leather. Then raise the hat, the vessel will be found to be empty and the bell cover full of grain, which you will scrape deftly with the piece of leather
</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>