<root><page>036v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f78.image</image>


<div>
<id>p036v_1</id>
<head><pro>Founder</pro></head>


<ab>Kitchen pots are high quality made, with the same metal used for bells, in order not to give meats a bad taste. It is true that <pro>founders</pro> add <m>latten</m> to pots to make them more yellow, in order to make them more saleable; but <m>latten</m> itself, just by touching it, is stinking and bad smelling.</ab>


<ab><m>Latten</m> does not lose (or just very slightly) its <m>calamine</m> in an air-furnace when it is melted in a crucible -- nor does it lose it in a wood furnace -- but it does lose it in a bellows furnace because bellows produce intense flames.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p036v_2</id>
<head>Air furnace</head>


<ab>Its mouth has to be narrower than its bottom; it is sufficient if the crucible can get in, and if there is space enough to remove it with pincers.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p036v_3</id>
<head><pro>Glassmakers</pro>' glass</head>


<ab>It is said that in <pl>Lorraine</pl> and <pl>Flanders</pl> <m>linking glass</m> is made of <m>fern ashes</m> and <m>pebbles</m>. First they blow up a long still that another worker breaks off and cuts vertically with big shears. Then this long still expands by being placed on a stone or large platine in a furnace slightly colder than one for melting. Furthermore, they flatten it by rolling <sup>over</sup> it a big and long iron stick. Then they take it out of the annealing  furnace. Similarly, they make some in <pl>England</pl> that are quite beautiful. Close to <pl>Rouen</pl> in <pl>France</pl>, flat glass is made with some <m>saltworth</m> and <m>pebbles</m> and is whiter and softer than the <pl>Lorraine</pl> one, because it can be melted with a candle, unlike the <pl>Lorraine</pl> one. This flat <m>glass</m> is blown up in a long still -- the end of which someone else cuts and blows up whilst turning it, then flattens it using a plane which is on the ground, and then reheats it. Thus the middle of the still, where it began, always stays the same.</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The <m>glass</m>, when wet, can be broken again with the flame of a candle, but not as precisely as with hot iron.</ab>
</div></root>