<root><page>037r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f79.image</image>


<div>
<id>037r_1</id>
<head><pro>Founder</pro></head>
<ab>The more it is melted, the whiter the <m>metal</m> becomes because the <m>tin</m> does not come off, and so it is more mixed. And, once it has been held in the fire for a long time, the <m>dust</m> is eaten away, which is what makes it sour. If you want to separate the tin from the <m>copper</m>, after it is well heated, throw <m>salpeter</m> on it often. Only this [saltpeter] and not the fire separates it, and purifies it, and eats away the <m>dust</m>. <m>Metal</m> can be cast very neatly. <m>Copper</m> is prone to swell, but because it is soft, it can be fixed with a hammer.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>037r_2</id>
<head>Medicine for the stomach which warms it [stomach] and unstops the liver</head>
<ab>Have some <m>wormwood powder</m>, dissolve it in some <m>capilli veneris syrup</m> or <m>preserves</m>, and make an opiate that you will take once a week on a piece of <m>bread</m> dipped in <m>wine</m>. Then you will be able to drink a bit of fully dipped <m>wine</m>. This clears the phlegm and gas which come from there. You can take six <m>pepper</m> grains, and grate their <m>rinds</m> so they are smooth, and swallow them without chewing them. This heals the stomach without warming the liver.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>037r_3</id>
<head>Sheets for precious stones</head>
<ab>Once they have been made, do not keep them in any <m>iron</m> or <m>metal</m> box because this stains them. But in some box of</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>037r_4</id>
<head>For preventing candles from dripping and making them [candles] white</head>
<ab>Once they have been made, put in a mould some fresh <m>water</m> whipped with some <m>bran</m>, which should by no means be purged again of its <m>flour</m>, so that the <m>water</m> is white. And dip your candles in this. Then leave them to dry. And do so thusly two or three times.</ab>
</div></root>