<root><page>038v</page>


<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f82.image</image>


<div>
<id>p038v_1</id>
<head>Black color for dyeing </head>


<ab>Take <m>lye made from quicklime</m> and <m>white lead</m>, mix and leave to soak and you will have a dark brown dye, and reiterating the same you will make black. Try other colours with the <m>lye made of lime</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p038v_2</id>
<head>Against nose bleeding and for dyeing</head>


<ab>Pound some of the kind of  <m>vinete</m> or <m>lapathum acutum</m> that is red-veined, which is called <m><al>dragon</al>'s blood</m>, and apply it on the bleeding person's forehead. This herb is a strong dye &amp; makes beautiful violet.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p038v_3</id>
<head>Beautiful artichokes</head>


<ab>You need to trim them every year so that only one stem is left, and water them a lot. Also plant some more every year, because the second year they will bear very beautiful fruits.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p038v_4</id>
<head>Planting trees </head>


<ab>It is said that rarely a tree planted on Saint Paul's day will fail to take. To cover the young shoots, oxen manure is very appropriate, for it doesn't come apart in the rain like earth.</ab>  
</div>


<div>
<id>p038v_5</id>
<head>Merchants </head>


<ab>Those who retail velvet and other materials do not keep double-entry books because they sell in small quantities and <sup>recording</sup> these details would be too much effort. They only have their sales book and account books. But those who sell in bulk and those who traffic in woad have a double-entry book.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p038v_6</id>
<head>Crimson</head>


<ab>Because one aulne costs seven or eight lb. to dye, they use <sup>cloth</sup>worth seven or eight francs. But if one wants something beautiful, one should buy some white cloth worth fifteen francs an aulne and dye it with some pure crimson woad &amp; a little cochineal. Black fabrics are very fine because the dye is inexpensive.</ab>
</div></root>