<root><page>039v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f84.image</image>


<div>
<id>p039v_a1</id>
<head><m>Enamel</m></head>


<ab><m>Enamel</m> takes more readily on <m>copper</m> than on <m>silver</m>. It is true that the cut needs to be well hollowed out &amp; rough. <m>Azure</m> in body &amp; the <m>red</m> called gules, white <m>enamel</m> &amp; thick <m>green</m> take to it very well. Having <m>enamelled</m>, one gilds the <fr>feuillages</fr> of the engraving<del>[illegible]</del>. <m>Copper</m> has a similar hardness for engraving as fine <m>silver</m> or <cn><fr>pistolet</fr></cn> <m>gold</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p039v_a2</id>
<head>Colors for illumination on <m>glass</m></head>


<ab>In order that your <m>turpentine</m> colors shall not spread, &amp; hold together, mix in a little of <m>tear of mastic</m> together with the <m>turpentine</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p039v_a3</id>
<head>Tracing some history on <m>glass</m></head>


<ab>If you want to trace a history in intaglio on <m>glass</m>, you can do so in different ways. Place your <m>glass</m> pane <del>on</del>, as thin as possible, over the printed history, &amp; having cleaned the <m>glass</m> well with <m>lye</m> &amp; <m>ashes</m> so that it is not at all greasy, trace over the lines visible to you with <m>oily black</m> or <m>scales black</m> with a <fr>pinceau</fr>, if you want to paint with colors in the manner of <pro>glaziers</pro>, who spread a wash of <m>scales black</m> all over their <m>glass</m> pane &amp; then scratch &amp; uncover what they want to coat with color, leaving that which is necessary for shading. But if you want to make gilt histories on <m>glass</m> with a background of colors, which imitates the basse-taille of <pro>goldsmiths</pro>, gild the whole <m>glass</m> pane with <m>gum water</m> or <m>garlic juice</m> or <m>fig-tree milk</m>. Then moisten your printed history with two wet <m>linen cloths</m> &amp; lay it down on the gilt <m>glass</m>. Then with a <tl>pin</tl> mounted on a small <tl>stick</tl>, follow the lines of your history as if you wished to pounce it, &amp; thus you shall vividly trace it on the gilding of the <m>glass</m>. &amp; next you shall uncover the background &amp; what needs to be empty with a quite pointy <tl><m>steel</m> awl</tl>, &amp; and neatly follow once more the lines &amp; accomplish your work &amp; fashion your faces &amp; flesh tones in pounded <m>silver</m>; then fill the background with <m><fr>azur d’esmail</fr></m> or <m>verdigris</m> or fine <m><fr>laque platte</fr></m>, tempered with <m>clear turpentine</m>, mixed with a little <m><fr>larme de mastic</fr></m> if you want the colors to be more unified &amp; not to run. Next, apply on the back of the <m>glass</m> &amp; over the colors a <m>white tin</m> sheet. And once this is dry, you can cover the <m>tin</m> sheet <del>of</del> with color to hide your secret. The <m>tin</m> sheet gives light to the colors. Thus you will be able to paint without being</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>