<root><page>040v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f86.image</image>


<div>
<id>p040v_1</id>
<head>Cross of the commanders of <pl>Malta</pl></head>


<ab>This beautiful <m><fr>rouge clair</fr></m> which makes the field of the white <m>enamel</m> cross is <del>blood</del> of fine tear of <m>dragon's blood</m> tempered with <m>eau de vie</m> or else <m><pl>Indian</pl> laque plate</m>, which in my opinion is made in <pl>Flanders</pl>, tempered with clear <m>turpentine</m> &amp; tear of <m>mastic</m> amp; laid down on a <m>silver</m> leaf, not the kind which the <pro>painters</pro> use, but a thicker kind, which is burnished by <pro>those who make foil backings for gemstones</pro> <del><fr>Av</fr></del> or by <pro>goldsmiths</pro>, amp; that gives it this beautiful brilliance.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p040v_02</id>
<head><m>Latten</m> and <m>calamine</m></head>


<ab><pro>Founders</pro> do not melt <m>latten</m> in a <tl><del>air</del><add>bellow</add> furnace</tl> but in <tl>crucibles</tl>, for in a <tl><add>bellow</add> furnace</tl> &amp; amid the <m>charcoals</m>, the <m>calamine</m> would disappear. <del>A</del></ab></div>


<div>
<id>p040v_03</id>
<head><m>Metal</m></head>


<ab><m>Tin</m> should be pure for if there is any <m>lead</m>, it will go up in smoke while melting. Mixed <m>tin</m> holds in the fire for a long time but the <tl><m><fr>cendrée</fr></m></tl> separates it.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p040v_04</id>
<head><m>Aqua fortis</m></head>


<ab>If your retort is well luted you should not surround it with <m>ashes</m>, which would only prevent the vapors from escaping properly. But when, towards the end, you fire it intensely, surround it with <m>charcoals</m> lit elsewhere beforehand, such as those in the furnace should be, so they do not crackle or smoke. Place said lit <m>charcoals</m> around the body of the retort, not close to the neck, which does not need to be heated as much. The top grate, on which you place your retort, should be sufficiently far, one <ms>dour</ms> or half a foot, from the bottom grate where the <m>charcoal</m> is placed, since thus you will not waste as much <sup>aqua fortis</sup>.</ab></div></root>