<root><page>040v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f86.image</image>


<div>
<id>p040v_1</id>
<head>Cross of the commanders of <pl>Malta</pl></head>


<ab>The fine rouge clair which is the background of the white <m>enamel</m> cross is of fine <m>dragon's blood</m> drops soaked with <m>eau de vie</m> or <m><pl>Indian</pl> laque plate</m>, which I believe is made in <pl>Flanders</pl>, distempered with clear <m>turpentine</m> and <m>mastic</m> drops and applied on a <m>silver</m> leaf, not the one used by <pro>painters</pro> but a thicker one, which is burnished by the <pro>makers of foil backings for gemstones</pro> or by <pro>goldsmiths</pro>, and that gives it its fine brilliance.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p040v_02</id>
<head><m>Latten</m> and <m>calamine</m></head>


<ab><pro>Founders</pro> do not melt <m>latten</m> in a bellow furnace but in crucibles, for in a bellow furnace and amid the <m>charcoals</m>, the <m>calamine</m> would disappear.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p040v_03</id>
<head><m>Metal</m></head>


<ab><m>Tin</m> needs to be pure because if there is any <m>lead</m>, it will go up in smoke whilst melting. Alloyed <m>tin</m> withstands fire for a long time but in <m>ashes</m> it will come apart.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p040v_04</id>
<head><m>Aqua fortis</m></head>


<ab>If your retort is well luted you should not surround it with <m>ashes</m>, which would only prevent the vapors from escaping properly. But when, towards the end, you fire it intensely, surround it with <m>charcoals</m> lit elsewhere beforehand, such as those in the furnace should be, so they do not crackle or smoke. Place said lit <m>charcoals</m> around the body of the retort, not close to the neck, which does not need to be heated as much. The top grate, on which you place your retort, should be sufficiently far, one <ms>dour</ms> or half a foot, from the bottom grate where the <m>charcoal</m> is placed, since thus you will not waste as much <sup>aqua fortis</sup>.</ab></div></root>