<root><page>041v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f88.image</image>


<div>
<id>p041v_1</id>
<head><pro>Glazier</pro>s’ <m>black</m></head>


<ab><m>Iron scale</m> taken from bars that have been in the fire for a long time, &amp; which is thick, is much better than the common delicate kind that falls under the anvil in the forge, because it imitates <m>niello</m>. To said <m>black</m>, described elsewhere, some add <del><fr>d</fr></del> a little <m>minium</m> to it.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p041v_2</id>
<head>Sheared <al>ewes</al></head>


<ab>If the <pro>shearer</pro> wounds them at some point, he applies the very excrement of the ewe on it. When they are fat, they are easier to shear and do not get hurt as easily.
</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
If the <pro>shearer</pro> wants to 'viscorter' them, that is to castrate them as [they] are one or two years old, he must not have been with his wife, because this would cause the <al>sheep</al> to die.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p041v_3</id>
<head>Colors and <m>gilding</m> on <m>glass</m></head>


<ab>One ought not to give as strong <m>gum water</m> on <m>glass</m> for the <del><m>gold</m> layer as for</del> <m>silver</m> layer as for the <m>gold</m> layer because a <m>silver</m> leaf is twice as strong as a <m>gold</m> leaf. Also, <m>silver</m> is harder and therefore does not scratch as easily. <del><fr>Q</fr></del> And if the <m>gum</m> was not a little strong for the <m>silver</m>, the latter would not crack so clearly. When you work, the exhalation of your <m>breath</m> humidifies the leaf lying on the <m>glass</m>, and therefore it would be good, when working, to heat it up a few times. You have to very thoroughly wash what you want to be empty and used as a surface painted with colors, because if it is not really clean of the <m>gum</m>'s <m>grease</m> and viscosity, and of other things, the colors will not be so clear on it. To advance your work you can smooth with a <m>pumice stone</m>, or [you can do this] to better lay down <m>gum</m> and leaf on a cut <m>paper</m>. This way, you will have to do very little repairs. If you want a <m>gold</m> color there without <m>gold</m>, mix soaked dried <m>saffron</m> with a little bit of <m>massicot</m>.
</ab>
</div></root>