<root><page>042v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f90.image</image>


<div>
<id>p042v_a1</id>
<head>Pounce for scratching <m>satin</m></head>


<ab>After pouncing with crushed <m>flour</m> or <m>chalk</m>, in order that the dots of the pounce not be erased, go over the trace with <m>egg white</m> beaten with the <m>milk</m> or <m>bark of a fig tree</m>, which will immediately make the <m>egg white</m> clear up like water, without becoming opaque, it will maintain the trace that you will go over again and scratch with a piece of glass or penknife.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p042v_a2</id>
<head>Canvas for <m>oil</m> painting without breaking</head>


<ab>In order that your <m>oil</m> painting be not broken or ruined as you bend it, make your (preparatory) layer with <m>honey</m>, a bit of <m>oil</m>, <m>water</m>, and <m>flour</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p042v_a3</id>
<head><m>Oil</m> painting on <m>taffeta</m></head>


<ab>In order that the <m>oil</m> not run, make your first layer with <m>honey</m>, <m>water of alum</m>, and <m>essence of amidin</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p042v_a4</id>
<head>Casting <m>sand</m></head>


<ab>The key is to grind it well upon marble, and that it be extremely fine; mix in a bit of <m>calcined alabaster</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p042v_a5</id>
<head>For decorating a painting</head>


<ab>Go over the lines with <m>lacquer</m> ground together with <m>olive oil</m>, which will not dry out.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p042v_a6</id>
<head>White <m>varnish</m> on <m>plaster</m></head>


<ab>Put down two or three layers of white <m>glue</m> for painting. Afterwards, varnish with <m>varnish of sandarac</m>, <m>aspic oil</m>, and a bit of <m>mastic</m>. Put it into a vessel at night, everything ground well together without fire, which would make it turn yellow. Then, with a paintbrush, it becomes dry immediately. Filter the <m>oil</m> that will have absorbed the substance.</ab>
</div></root>