<root><page>043r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f91.image</image>

<div>
<id>p043r_a1</id>
<head><m>Mericoton</m> and <m>pavis</m></head>


<ab>One should graft them before Christmas so that they will not freeze too much.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p043r_a2</id>
<head>White bronzing on <m>plaster</m></head>


<ab>One must apply four layers of <pro>painters</pro>' <m>distemper glue</m> onto the <m>plaster</m> portrait, leaving one layer to dry at a time. Then apply gently some burnt <m>English point</m> ground on a marble slab, or some <m>lead</m> burnt, ground and distempered with a bit of <m>gum</m> or <m>glue</m>. When dry, rub gently with a little <m>cotton</m> and the <m>plaster</m> portrait will look like <m>lead</m>. Others grind <m>minium</m> with <m>quicksilver</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p043r_a3</id>
<head><m>Purpurine</m></head>


<ab>Take half an ounce of soft <m>tin</m>, melt it in a spoon. Once it is melted, throw in an ℥ of <m>☿</m>, mix together. Once they are cold, grind on a <m>porphyry</m> slab. Then take an ℥ of <m>sal ammoniac</m> and an ℥ of the yellowest <m>sulfur</m> that may be found, grind both. And then mix very well all the aforementioned materials. Then put all together into a glass sublimatorium. Hold this over a small fire for an hour, and for an hour over a stronger fire, and for an hour over a very strong fire, and it will be ready. Then, to use it, apply <m>resin black</m> with the <m>glue</m> used by <pro>painters</pro> to paint, two or three times, until it is quite black. Then apply a bit of <m>varnish</m>. Once it is dry, apply the <m>purpurine</m> dry with a finger where you want. The more you apply, the finer it will look. Then, if you like, you can apply <m>varnish</m> on top.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p043r_a4</id>
<head>White bronzing</head>


<ab>Apply some <m>black</m> with <m>glue</m> on the medal, as described above, and then <m>varnish</m> it. Once dry, rub it with <m>English point</m> using a brush or your finger. The said rubbed <m>point</m> embellishes <m>lead</m> medals.</ab>
</div></root>