<root><page>047r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f99.image</image>


<div>
<id>p047r_1</id>
<head>For teeth</head>


<ab><m>Sal ammoniac</m> i <figure>℥</figure>, <m>rock salt</m> 1 <figure>℥</figure>, <m>alum</m> half <figure>℥</figure>. Make <m>water</m> with the cornue, and no matter how little of it you touch the tooth with, the tartar and blackness will go away. It is true that it has a bad odor, but you can mix it with <m>rose honey</m> and a little <m>clove oil</m> or <m>cinnamon<sup> oil</sup></m>.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p047r_2</id>
<head><m>Antimony oil</m></head>


<ab>It yellows quite strongly, even <m>silver</m>, if you put it on it once heated.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p047r_3</id>
<head>Against falling sickness or dizziness</head>


<ab>Wear, hung to your collar, some root of <m>paeonia</m> which has been plucked when the moon is waning.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p047r_4</id>
<head>Crucibles</head>


<ab>Those from <m>Bayonne</m>, which seem to be made of <m>grés</m> are better, for they last, without comparison, longer than others. And because they are not very thick, one wastes less <m>charcoal</m> melting <m>gold</m> &amp; <m>silver</m>, for they heat quickly. They do not absorb as much <m>silver</m> as much as the others, &amp; for this reason, there is not much <fr>laveures</fr> to be found in them. They are less likely to fall over as others that have a flat foot.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p047r_5</id>
<head>Against diarrhea and dysentery</head>


<ab>Against diarrhea, it is good to use preserve of <m>symphytum</m>, also [known as] <m>consolida maior</m>. And if it is against dysentery, you can rub the temples, the hollow of the hands, and the sole of the feet with <m>wax oil</m> and take a drop of two of it with a spoonful of <m>broth</m>. The root of <m>consolida maior</m>, crushed and put between <del>pieces</del> cuts in a piece of <m><al>beef</al></m>, then boiled, rejoins them, as it is said.
</ab>
</div></root>