<root><page>047v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f100.image</image>

<div>
<id>p047v_a1</id>
<head>A beverage which tastes like wine</head>


<ab>Take <m>tartar</m> from large vessels, dilute it in <m>water</m>, and it will taste like wine.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p047v_a2</id>
<head>Melting</head>


<ab>Some to make it flow neatly, put half <m>metal</m> and half <m>copper</m>. Others take a part of <m>potin</m> and a part of <del>copper</del><m>latten</m>. Others take a part of <m>latten</m> from candlesticks and a part of <m>latten</m> from a basin. And among basins, the <m>latten</m> from larger ones is harder than that from skillets because the material needs to be softer in order to give them such a small circumference. From the large ones, from which they take the more ample circumference, the harder material can be taken. The harder the <m>latten</m>, the better it flows and the neater it casts, but it must be cast very <del>neat</del> hot. <del>One</del> As one wishes to cast, one puts <m>lead</m> on the material, which makes it flow and run and goes up in smoke and be careful that the mold does not get damaged. And if you want to cast pieces on fire, mix more <m>rosette</m> than <m>latten</m>, so that it is less brittle. The crucibles used to melt <m>metal</m> should be better than those used by <pro>glassmakers</pro> because glass is not as heavy as <m>metal</m>. And in this instance, the crucibles need to be luted with <m>earth</m> and crushed <m>glass</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p047v_a3</id>
<head>Crucibles</head>


<ab>Those made during the winter and humid weather are not good. Those used by founders should be thick and should be coated.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p047v_a4</id>
<head>Cast</head>


<ab>Finely-calcinated <m>pumice stone</m> casts 22 carat <m>gold</m> without <sup>needing</sup> repair, but it needs to be ablaze and red as the metal. And it will survive many casts.</ab>
</div></root>