<root><page>048v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f102.image</image>



<div>
<id>p048v_a1</id>
<head>Regulus extracts</head>


<ab>Take one pound of <m>antimony</m>, half a pound of <m>black soap,</m> and half a pound of <m>Montpellier tartar</m>. Once it is all pulverized, you have to boil it in a <m>varnished earthenware pot</m> on a big <m>fire</m> as you stir it with a <m>piece of wood or iron</m>. The <m>soap</m> will burn off and be consumed by the <m>fire</m> and the rest will stay red. The quantity has to be reduced to a third. Then throw that on a <m>tile</m> and it will turn blackish. You will have to melt and pour that on a <m>tile</m> four or five times and then you will have <m>regulin from antimony</m>.</ab>


<ab>Others pulverise the <m>antimony</m> and mix it with equal quantities of <m>saltpeter</m> and powdered <m>tartar</m> and heat a <m>pot</m> or <m>crucible</m> until it is red hot, then add a little bit at a time, turning their back for fear of the smoke, and keep doing so until everything is added. They maintain the <m>fire</m> until everything is completely melted and melt that several times.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p048v_a2</id>
<head><m>Lead, tin</m></head>


<ab>They become brittle having been put back to melt, often or for a long time, and they thicken and burn, in such a way that even when one melts a <fr>saulmon</fr>, the <m>tin</m> thickens at the bottom if, while casting, one does not stir it often. It is best for casting to melt a little <m>lead</m> <del>&amp; the</del> or <m>tin</m> &amp; <del>renew</del> to renew at each melting. The <m>antimony</m> renders them breakable. The <m>looking glass tin</m> whitens them. <del>One</del> <pro>Pewterers</pro> put in <del>on the fine tin</del> one <ms>lb</ms> of <m>looking glass tin</m> per one <ms>quintal</ms> of <m>fine tin</m> &amp; two <ms>lb</ms> &amp; a half or three <ms>lb</ms> of <m>red and soft copper of cauldrons </m>, which is better than <m>latten.</m> There is <m>fine &amp; soft tin</m> &amp; <m>brittle tin</m>. The brittle one is cast in <fr>grille</fr> by the <pro>Pewterers</pro> to sell it better. <del>O</del> They go better &amp; more cleanly in <m>stone</m> moulds than in <m>copper</m> molds because <m>copper</m> is fat and draws the <m>mild tin</m> when heated. Or when casting a large work, three quarts of <m>lead</m> with one pound of <m>mild tin</m> produces a very liquid mixture which is appropriate for casting and is as shiny as a mirror. Laxunge <m>glass</m> lightens them. All things that lighten <m>metals</m> a lot and remove their thickness and natural density and make them as liquid as water make them appropriate for casting because their thickness stops them from flowing. The <m>mild tin</m> is more even than the <m>sour tin</m>, which is whiter and seems to have been polished like a mirror.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
To properly alloy the <m>tin</m> and the <m>lead</m>, you have to melt them together, Then, mix them together a little bit at a time and throw it often on a <m>marble tile</m>. And when it is going well, you will see it becoming unified and shining as if it were burnished. Because sometimes it becomes spotted due to too much <m>lead</m> and sometimes due to too much <m>tin</m>. There is some <m>tin</m> allied with more <m>lead</m>. Ordinary <m>tin</m> is allied with some <m>lead</m>.</ab>
</div></root>