<root><page>049r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f103.image</image>

<div>
<id>p049r_a1</id>
<head><m>Lead</m> casting</head>


<ab>Those who cast these small items, sold in front of the churches, melt half a pound of <m>lead</m> on a pound of <m>tin</m>, and cast in a <m>stone</m> frame. And if they want their work [to be] whiter, they use half of <m>tin</m> and half of <m>lead</m>, but the first mixture is the best, and does not make bubbles.You have to cast it hot enough, otherwise it won't flow. Some [people] smoke their molds with a <m>rosin</m> <m>candle</m> for neat casting. The <m>antimony</m> makes the matter harsh and breakable. The <m>looking-glass</m> <m>tin</m> makes the work whiter, but does not make it flow more than with <m>tin</m> that is correctly made with pure <m>lead</m>. Those who make very precise <m>lead</m> castings use puncheons. <pro>Tintiers</pro> cast with <m>copper</m> molds. It is said that one makes <m>lead</m> adhere to <m>glass</m> by using <m>resin</m>. Some people put a quarter of <m>tin</m> on <m>lead</m>. <m>Glass</m> <m>tin</m> makes the work stronger.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Poncet.They cast by using the souldure the <pro>glass-makers</pro> use. Lump [of metal] of [...] Calcinated <m>oyster shell</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p049r_a2</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> for <m>lead</m> casting</head>


<ab><m>Rye straw</m> ashes well boiled, dried and then well sieved. alloy it with <m>egg white</m>. One can add <m>copper</m>, <m>latten</m> and others.</ab> 


</div>
<div>
<id>p049r_a3</id>
<head>Other</head>


<ab>Burnt and calcinated <m>pumice stone</m>, burnt and calcined <m>cuttlefish</m> <m>bones</m>, in the same quantity; and ashes of <m>walnut</m> <m>tree</m> or <m>vine</m>, boiled, dried and finely sieved alloy with <m>egg white</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p049r_a4</id>
<head><pro>Pewterers</pro></head>


<ab>They add one lb. of <m>glass</m> <m>tin</m> to one quintal of <m>fine</m> <m>tin</m>, which makes the <m>tin</m> ticker. There is two kinds of <m>tin</m>, one which flows better, like lead<m>,</m> while the other one is sour and can be made thicker. They are casted in thick and solid <m>tin</m> molds or, to cast more neatly, in chisel-engraved <m>copper</m> molds, or <m>stone</m> or <m>earth</m> [molds]. <m>Latten</m> scrapings mixed in make the <m>tin</m> more breakable and harder, and more difficult to work with. They cast in the very hot molds some very hot <m>tin</m>. They perfume their <m>tin</m> molds with <m>resin</m> <m>candles</m>.</ab> 


<ab><m>Sour</m> <m>tin</m> is often mingled with <m>salmons</m>, easy to cut but difficult to work with and melts if it is not mingled with the other <m>soft</m> one. And thus it would become leftover.</ab> 
</div></root>