<root><page>049r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f103.image</image>


<div>
<id>p049r_a1</id>
<head><m>Lead</m> casting</head>


<ab>Those who cast those small works that are sold in front of <env>churches</env>, <del><fr>y</fr></del> melt <del>one</del> for one <ms>lb</ms> of <m>tin</m> half a <ms>pound</ms> of <m>lead</m>, &amp; cast in <m>stone</m>, &amp; if they want their work whiter, they put <del>p</del> <ms>half</ms> <m>tin</m> and <ms>half</ms> <m>lead</m>, but the first mixture is the best, &amp; does not become porous. One needs to cast it rather hot, for otherwise, it would not flow. Others smoke their <tl>molds</tl> with a <m>resin candle</m> to cast neatly. The <m>antimony</m> makes the substance brittle &amp; breakable. The <m>looking-glass tin</m> makes the work whiter, but not more runny, as for <m>tin</m>, it is good <del>to the</del> with <m>pure lead</m>. Those who make very neat <m>lead</m> casts, use <tl>bodkins</tl>. <pro>Pewterers</pro> cast in a <tl><m>copper</m> mold</tl>. One says that one makes the <m>lead</m> stick on the <m>glass</m> with <m>resin</m>. Others put into the <m>lead</m> a <ms>quarter</ms> of <m>tin</m>. <m>Looking glass tin </m> renders the work stronger.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<pn>Poncet</pn>.
They cast with <m>soldering</m> that <del><pro>pewterers</pro></del> <add><pro>glass-makers</pro></add> use. </ab>


<ab>
Lump of <m>iron</m>
<m>Shells of iron</m>, <m>calcined <al>oyster</al></m>.
</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p049r_a2</id>
<head>Sand for <m>lead</m> casting</head>


<ab><m><pa>Rye</pa> straw ashes</m> well boiled then dried &amp; then well <tl>sieved</tl>. Alloy it with <m>egg white</m>. One can cast there <m>copper</m>, <m>latten</m> and other things.</ab> 


</div>
<div>
<id>p049r_a3</id>
<head>Other</head>


<ab><m>Burnt &amp; calcined pumice stone</m>, <m>burnt &amp; calcined <al>cuttlefish</al> bones</m>, in the same quantity; &amp; <m>ashes of <pa>walnut tree</pa></m> or <m><pa>vine</pa></m>, boiled, dried &amp; finely <tl>sieved</tl> alloy with <m>egg white</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p049r_a4</id>
<head><pro>Pewterers</pro></head>


<ab>They put into one <ms>quintal</ms> of <m>fine tin</m> one <ms>lb</ms> of <m>looking glass tin</m>, which renders the <m>tin</m> thicker. There is two kinds of <m>tin</m>, one of them, nearly like <m>lead</m>, which runs better, the other, brittle, which renders itselfs thicker. They cast in solid <tl><m>tin</m> molds</tl> &amp; thick or, to do it more neatly in <tl><m>copper</m> molds engraved with a <tl>burin</tl>, or in <m>stone</m> or in <m>earth</m></tl>. <m>Latten</m> shards, mixed in, only rendering the <m>tin</m> more breakable &amp; harder &amp; difficult to work with, they cast <add>in</add> very hot <tl>molds</tl> <del>&amp; almost red</del> &amp; very hot <m>tin</m>. They fumigate their <tl><m>tin</m> molds</tl> with <m>resin candles</m>.</ab> 


<ab><m>Brittle <del><fr>dou</fr></del> tin</m> is found mixed into <fr>saulmons</fr>, easy for cutting, but difficult to put to work &amp;melts if it is not mixed with the other soft one. Otherwise, it would become waste.</ab> 
</div></root>