<root><page>050r</page> 


<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f105.image</image>


<div>
<id>p050r_1</id>


<head>Preserving fruit for the entire year</head>


<ab>Take a rounded <m>glass</m> phial, with a large enough opening to receive cherries and plums and whatever fruit you want.  Put in some <m>hot water</m> <sup>and leave it</sup> for two hours, and once your <m>water</m> is cold, throw it out and turn the phial upside down onto its opening on a perfectly even table and in a room where there is not a bit of draft or wind. Then prepare a stopper of fresh <m>wax</m>, wrapped in <m>oilcloth</m>, and adapt it precisely to the <m>glass</m> phial so that it will be ready to stop it once you have put in the fruit.  And once you have hand-picked the fruit, only the non-rotten fruit, and on a warm and dry day, withdraw to the room, well closed so that no wind or draft can get in, and put it gently and deftly in the bottle. Then stop the bottle well with the stopper and lute it, making your lute, if you want, with some <m>quicklime</m> and <m>oil</m>, so that no <m>water</m> gets in. Then put your bottles into a tub full of <m>water</m>, in a cellar, during the summer, and in the winter put your bottles into a basket filled with some weights and lower it to the bottom of a deep well. Because in the winter the <m>water</m> in the tub would be too cold if your cellar is not warm enough, because the <m>water</m> needs to be like <m>river water</m>.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>po50r_2</id>


<head>Molding</head>


<ab>If you want to quickly mold in demi-relief anything you come upon, fold some <m>paper</m> five or six times over, and place it on the medal and make sure the <m>paper</m> is folded around the edges of the medal so it is very secure. Next take a stick, broad at one end and with a well-dulled point at the other, and rub firmly on the <m>paper</m>, and retrace the lines with the point of the stick until you reckon that your impression is well done. Then, at your convenience, rub <m>oil</m> onto the <m>paper</m> lightly with a brush, and cast some <m>tallow</m> or <m>wax</m> or <m>sulphur</m> into it. And the <m>paper</m>, without burning, will give you a neat design that you can then mold in <m>plaster</m> or <m>tripoli</m> and then in <m>lead</m> and other <m>metals</m>.</ab>
 
<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>Polished <m>cardboard</m> of little thickness and slightly humid is appropriate. Then if you want, strengthen it with some <m>paper</m> glued on the reverse side.</ab></div></root>