<root><page>051r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f107.image</image>



<div>
<id>p051r_a1</id>
<head>Copying off patterns</head>


<ab>Make some <m>soap water</m> and with it, rub and moisten the <m>engraved stone</m> that you want to transfer the pattern from, then lay a white sheet of <m>paper</m> on it and rub strongly against it with a sharp piece or the bottom of a <m>glass</m> bottle and you will transfer your stamped piece. It is true that it will be on the left side, but if you apply <m>aspic</m> or <m>turpentine oil</m> on your <m>paper</m>, it will be stamped on the right on the other side. Then trace these lines with a paint brush or a quill, then heat the <m>paper</m> and the <m>oil</m> will evaporate and it will leave your <m>paper</m> white. And if you don't want that to be known if, by chance, you borrowed the <m>cut stone</m>, soak the <m>paper</m> and the polishing that the <pro>polisher</pro> made on the back side, which distinguishes what has been made, will not be recognizable. The <m>soap water</m> will turn the piece yellow, but well <m>gummed wate</m>r, which has the same effect, does not do this. If you want to, for the same effect, make <m>gummed wate</m>r then, dissolve some <m>soap</m> in it and do as is said.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p051r_a2</id>
<head>Cutters of printing plates</head> 


<ab>To clean the <m>copper</m> plates or to have used ones print better, boil them for four or five hours in a good <m>detergent</m> with quite used <m>laundry water</m>. Then make your <m>ink</m> with some <m>linseed oil</m> instead of <m>walnut oil</m> and press with the rollers. The <m>copper</m> plates are ready sooner than the <m>wood</m> ones, but they are not so clean to print promptly. The <m>wood</m> ones are tedious but would have sooner printed twenty sheets against two <x>sheets</x> of the other. To print with <m>wood</m>, the secret is firstly to poach, that is to say to lay the transferred pattern or drawn piece down on the <m>wood</m> plank and to make sure that the drawn side is stuck to the <m>wood</m>. Once dry, you will gently rub with a moist <m>handkerchief</m> the reverse side of the <m>paper</m> which, by being rubbed, will become so fine that what will remain will almost only be the drawn part, which, after, one should trace while cutting the pattern. You could do that to ornamented <m>glass</m> and <m>glass</m> layered with <m>black</m> cut pieces, to then scrape and layer your <m>colors</m> on the uncovered <x>side</x>. To make <m>ink</m> for <m>copper</m> plates</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
These rollers are good for printing promptly with thick sheets of <m>paper</m> cut in different kinds of pastes.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
One can place the plates among the linens when the <m>detergent</m> is rather fine, or also in a pot.</ab>


<cont/>
</div></root>