<root><page>051v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f108.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p051r_a2</id>


<ab>which is different from the printers' one, you have to boil for a long time some <m>walnut oil</m> or, even better, some <m>linseed oil</m>, and after boiling for a long time, you will add <m>garlic</m> cloves and <m>bread</m> crusts to skim them and leave again to boil on big fire, then eventually you will add a measure of <m>lampblack</m> that you would have ground with some <m>oil</m> previously on the <m>marble</m>. And lastly you will mix everything and until you see that the plate prints well. And when you will have spread the <m>ink</m>, dry the plate with a white sheet of <m>paper</m> and do that until the <m>paper</m> looks clean and then print. If you dry the plates with a <m>cloth</m>, it would remove the <m>ink</m> off. <m>Linseed oil</m> gets thicker while boiling and becomes similar to a varnish and risks catching fire as soon as you boil it, so make sure that when you boil it, it is in an open space or where the flame cannot damage anything. Some burn some <m>scale</m> until it turns black and grind it with some non-boiled <m>linseed oil</m> or <m>walnut oil</m> that some consider to be better. This black is beautiful but the <m>lamp smoke</m> one is blacker. When you want to print, take with your finger's end and reasonably spread some of the said <m>black</m> all over the plate previously cleaned with some <m>detergent</m> as said, then, rub it with a white sheet of <m>paper</m> until the paper is completely white and do not touch it with your bare hand but with a <m>paper</m> applied on it. And after cleaning the plate perfectly, rub again the sides and edges with a folded sheet of <m>paper</m>. Then, have <x>available</x> a small even table and on it a piece of <m>felt</m>, then a few sheets of <m>paper</m> and eventually the one you want to print on, moistened between two humid <m>napkins</m>. And on this sheet of <m>paper</m>, put your sheet then some more <m>paper</m>, and at least another piece of <m>felt</m>. Then put it through the rollers and you can print a dozen pieces consecutively while always charging the plate with <m>ink</m> and cleaning it as you did. But if you stop printing, the rest of the <m>ink</m> will dry out in the plate's lines and so you will have to let it boil in <m>detergent</m> or <m>urine</m>, as said, to clean it. The rollers must not be too loose.</ab>


</div></root>