<root><page>053r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f111.image</image>

<div>
<id>p053r_a1</id>
<head>Soldering a vise</head>


<ab>It is good that the jaws of the vise should be high for use in making a long piece, and that they join well to clamp a thin object. In order to solder the nut, after you have made the bolt, you will make a long <m>iron</m> strip of the right thickness to fit into the notch of the bolt when red hot, and you will bend it all around [the bolt] by striking it with a hammer. Once it is well wrapped around, you will insert the bolt around which the nut is wrapped.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p053r_a2</id>
<head><m>Copper</m></head>


<ab>If, while in the fire and while being cast, it touches the <m>iron</m>, that <m>iron</m> will be so sour that it will be impossible to forge.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p053r_a3</id>
<head><m>Lead</m> casting</head>


<ab>According to some it is mixed, half <m>tin</m> and half <m>lead</m> and, in order to heat it, a little <m>arsenic</m> is mixed in. It is cast well in small sizes in a <m>cuttlefish</m> <m>bone</m>, provided it is good.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p053r_a4</id>
<head>Molding from <m>paper</m></head>


<ab>Over hot <m>ashes</m>, boil some <m>cotton</m> in <m>aqua fortis</m> mixed with <m>sal ammoniac</m> like <m>aqua regia</m>. And the cotton will become very fine, like <m>powder</m>. Then soak it with gummed water and you will cast quite delicately.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p053r_a5</id>
<head>Almond trees, apricot trees</head>


<ab>They grow quite straight if they are grafted. And every kind of tree [whose fruit has] pits, such as nectarines, peaches, clingstone-peaches, apricots etc., comes best by shield budding on an almond tree by.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p053r_a6</id>
<head><m>Lead</m> and <m>copper</m> casting</head>


<ab><m>Lead</m> and <m>tin</m> come out well in <m>white chalk</m> but the softer it is the better. That from Champagne wins first prize, and it is transported to Lyon. Burnt and calcinated <m>horse bones</m> cast very neatly.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
I believe that the <m>marrow</m> from the <m>horns</m> of oxen or sheep, that is to say, the <m>spongy bone</m> from inside, casts quite neatly and is better than <m>bone</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>bottom</margin>
Note that any sour <m>metal</m> comes out better than a fat one. Also, lean <m>sand</m> receives it and absorbs it better than dense <m>sand</m>.</ab>


</div></root>