<root><page>056v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f118.item</image>


<div>
<id>p056v_1</id>


<head>To paint</head>


<ab>The <m>lacquer</m> and <m>rosette from <pl>Ghent</pl></m> and elsewhere lose their color and die in contact with the air.</ab>


<ab>Any <m>marble</m> on which a knife can [illegible] is not worth to grind fine colors.</ab>


<ab>The <m>chalk</m> is not thick with <m>oil</m>, the <m>ceruse</m> is more appropriate but even better is the <m>white lead</m>. The <m>ceruse</m> is the whitest and is to grind firstly with some <m>water</m>, the white lead is grayish. But turns perfectly white with some <m>oil</m>.</ab>


<ab>When you grind your colors, start by cleaning your workshop because if you raise some dust while walking that will damage your colors which will never be beautiful if they are not clean.</ab>


<ab>The <m>Florey</m> must not be mingled with some <m>azur enamel</m> or anything else for it turns it into green.</ab>


<ab><m>Ivory</m> is excellent to make a painter's' palette Knots of the fir tree The pear-tree and if it is walnut tree make sure to cut with the grain of the wood.</ab>




<ab>You always have to stamp on <m>wood</m> to <m>oil paint</m> in order to fill holes and unevenness. And stamp with some [illegible] and <m>ceruse</m> mixed with oil, then soften with a feather which evens more than a brush. Or when the stamp is dry, rub it strongly off with a knife.</ab>


<ab>To use some <m>azur enamel</m> with some <m>oil</m>, you have to choose the finest one and to make it thinner, do not grind for it turns white but wash it and because the bigger goes at the bottom, choose the one at the top of the <m>water</m> or pour the cloudy <m>water</m> out and pile the <m>azur</m>.</ab>
  
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Someone who operates with <m>oil</m> will not work properly with <m>distemper</m> if he has not been trained well during his youth. The manner of working is indeed very different because the brush point always has to be moisten for working with <m>distemper</m>. While when one cleans the brush in some <m>oil</m> to soften it, one should dry it well. Otherwise the work would drip and soon be damaged.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The Italians hatch with a flatten rough brush which makes some serration.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
And do not apply their shades at once like the Flemish but apply them by hatching from the lighter towards the light then a darker and then an even darker to make more contrast.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
With <m>distemper</m> do not mingle your various colors together for they will die but use each separately and in order to stop them from drying and to have time to soften, moisten the back of the canvas.</ab>


<cont/>
</div></root>