<root><page>056v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f118.item</image>


<div>
<id>p056v_1</id>


<head>Painter</head>


<ab>The <m>lake</m> &amp; <del><m>floree</m></del> <m>rosette of <pl>Ghent</pl></m> &amp; others lose their color &amp; die in the air.</ab>


<ab>All <m>marble</m> on which a knife can prick is worth nothing for grinding fine colors.</ab>


<ab><m>Chalk</m> has no body in <m>oil</m>. <m>Ceruse</m> is appropriate. But <m>lead white</m> more excellent. <m>Ceruse</m> is the whitest, when ground first in <m>water</m>, the lead white grayish. But <del>the white</del> it takes on its perfect whiteness in <m>oil</m>.</ab>


<ab>When you grind your colors, first clean your workshop well, for when walking, if you stir up dust, this will damage your colors, which will never be beautiful if they are not very <del>be</del> clean.</ab>


<ab><m>Florey</m> must not be mixed with <m><fr>azur d'esmail</fr></m> or another, for it makes it green.</ab>


<ab>For palettes to paint, <m>ivory</m> is excellent, knots of the fir tree, the pear tree &amp, if it is a walnut tree, make sure the grain of the wood runs lengthwise.</ab>


<ab><del>L</del> One always needs to prime <del>d</del> on <m>wood</m> to paint there in <m>oil</m> in order to fill the holes &amp; unevenness, and prime with some <m>stil de grain yellow</m> &amp; <m>ceruse</m> mixed in oil, then soften with a feather, which flattens better than a brush. Or when the primer is dry, scrape strongly with a knife.</ab>


<ab>To use <m><fr>azur d’esmail</fr></m> in <m>oil</m>, one needs to choose the most delicate. And to make it subtle, one ought not grind it, for this makes it whiten. But one needs to wash it, &amp; the roughest going to the bottom, choose the one that is at the top of the <m>water</m> or, by inclination, pour out the cloudy <m>water</m>, then gather the <m>azur</m>.</ab>
  
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
The one who makes his profession working in <m>oil</m> will hardly work well in <m>distemper</m> if he has not been trained well from adolescence. For the way of working is different, because when washing the <fr>pinceau</fr> for <m>distemper</m>, one always leaves it moist. And on the contrary, when one cleans the <fr>pinceau</fr> in <m>oil</m> to soften, one wipes the <fr>pinceau</fr> well. Otherwise, the work would run &amp; would soon be disfigured.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The Italians soften by hatching with a large flat <fr>pinceau</fr> which makes  serrations.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
And they do not lay their shadow all at once like the Flemish, but make them hatching lightest toward the light then a little darker next &amp; and finally a little blacker to better make recede and come up.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
In <m>distemper</m> do not mix your different colors together <del>But</del> for this makes them die, but use each separately. And in order that they do not dry &amp; that you have time to soften, moisten the back of the canvas.</ab>


<cont/>
</div></root>