<root><page>057r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f119.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p056v_1</id>


<ab>
<m>Lake</m> takes a long time to dry in <m>oil</m> and for that reason you have to crush <m>glass</m> with it, but you have to choose <m>crystallin</m> because it is neater. And since it would be too difficult to be crushed by itself, you have to heat it red hot, then, when it is entirely red, throw it into cold <m>water</m> and it will crumble and pulverize itself to then  be crushed easily. After being crushed with a lot of <m>water</m>, it looks like crushed <m>lead white</m>, but for this reason it has no body. I think it could be good for casting.</ab>


<ab>
<m>Lead white</m> is made with <m>lead</m> sheets beaten gently and put under some manure.</ab>


<ab>
White <m>turpentine</m> varnish or <m>aspic oil</m> and <m>turpentine</m> is colored with powdered <m>turmeric</m> boiled together with it. It gives a <m>gold</m> color on <m>silver</m> which is even more beautiful when burnished. It dries within a quarter of an hour. <m>Aloes</m> would made an even brighter color but it takes time to dry whereas the other one dries within a quarter of an hour in winter as well as in summer.</ab>


<ab>
Good <m>lake</m> moistened with <m>saliva</m> quickly darkens. That from <pl>Florence</pl> is mixed with too much <m>gum</m>.</ab>


<ab>
If you apply one layer of <m>printers' ink</m> on <m>velvet</m> and apply <m>gold</m> leaves and then stretch it, it looks grainy as if it was powdered with <m>gold</m> sprinkled on it.</ab>


<ab>
<m>Vermillion</m> crushed by itself is wan and pale but is more beautiful when it is crushed with <m>lake</m>.</ab>


<ab>In order to remove the <m>grease</m> off <m>marbles</m>, one crushes <m>ordinary ashes</m> on it, which afterward are good to make the first primer coat of a painting to be done in <m>oil</m> in order to seal the cracks and veins of the <m>wood</m>. They are thicker than <m>chalk</m> and are quite greasy. They are mingled with the aforesaid <m>chalk</m> or with colors collected from the vessel that is used to clean brushes, and they are desiccative and spare the colors. Once this primer coat has been made on the <m>wood</m>, it is scrubbed with a knife until even. After, one makes a second coat with <m>ceruse</m> or with the poorest colors mixed together. On an <m>oil</m> canvas painting one only applies one coat and the mixed <m>ashes</m> can be used. Also, after crushing a color, one crushes the <m>interior of a large loaf of bread</m> in order to remove the <m>grease</m> off the <m>marble</m>.</ab>


</div></root>