<root><page>057r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f119.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p056v_1</id>


<ab>
<m>Lake</m> takes long to dry in <m>oil</m> and for that reason one must crush <m>glass</m> in it. But one needs to choose <m>crystallin</m> because it is neater. And because it would be too difficult to crush by itself, one must redden it on the fire, then when entirely red throw it into cold <m>water</m>, &amp; it will be crumbled &amp; pulverized easily for crushing after. Being well crushed <del>it</del> with a lot of <m>water</m>, it resembles crushed <m>lead white</m>, but for this it has no body. I think it would be good for casting.</ab>


<ab>
<m>Lead white</m> is made with sheet <m>lead</m> beaten subtle &amp; put under the dung.</ab>


<ab>
White varnish of <m>turpentine</m> or of <m>spike lavender oil</m> and <m>turpentine</m> is colored with powdered <m>terra emerita</m>, making it boil together. It gives a <m>gold</m> color on <m>silver</m> and more beautiful if it is burnished. It is dry in a quarter of an hour. <m>Aloe</m> would make brighter color, but it takes long to dry &amp; the other is dry in a quarter of an hour, in winter as well as summer.</ab>


<ab>
Good <m>lake</m> moistened with <m>saliva</m> is rendered promptly dark. That from <pl>Florence</pl> is too <m>gummed</m>.</ab>


<ab>
If you make a layer of <m>printers' ink</m> on <m>velvet</m> and there apply <m>gold</m> leaf and then stretch the velvet, it appears grainy as if it was <m>gold</m> powder sprinkled on top.</ab>


<ab>
<m>Vermillion</m> crushed by itself is wan and pale, but crushed after <m>lake</m>, it is more beautiful.</ab>


<ab>For taking the fattiness from <m>marbles</m>, one crushes <m>ordinary ashes</m> on it, which is good afterward to make the first primer coat of a panel that is prepared in <m>oil</m> in order to seal the cracks &amp; chinks of the <m>wood</m>. They are thicker than <m>chalk</m> and are quite <del><m>croye</m></del> greasy. They are mingled with the aforesaid <m>chalk</m> or with colors collected from the vessel that is used to clean brushes, and they are desiccative and spare the colors. Once this primer coat has been made on the <m>wood</m>, it is scrubbed with a knife until even. After, one makes a second coat with <m>ceruse</m> or with the poorest colors mixed together. On an <m>oil</m> canvas painting one only applies one coat and the mixed <m>ashes</m> can be used. Also, after crushing a color, one crushes the <m>interior of a large loaf of bread</m> in order to remove the <m>grease</m> off the <m>marble</m>.</ab>


</div></root>