<root><page>058v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f122.item.</image>


<div>
<id>p058v_1</id>
<head>Blacks</head>


<ab>Coal black, ordinary black lead black, burnt ivory black, peaches stones black, black smoke, black light, burnt oxes' feet bones black</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p058v_2</id> 
<head>Shadows</head>


<ab>When you are making a painting with several persons shadows as well as skins have to be different</ab></div>
  
<div>
<id>p058v_3</id>
<head>Frescoes </head>


<ab><m>Azure</m> is not good for that but [illegible] and you have to work with long brushes. Frescoes cannot be made on <m>wood</m></ab></div>


<div> 
<id>p058v_4</id>
<head><m>Azure</m></head>


<ab><m>Turpentine oil</m> makes it very beautiful, try some <m><la>palma christi</la> seed oil</m>. <m>Nut oil</m> in <pl>Flanders</pl> costs at least a hundred sols a pint. The <m>azur</m> requires some greasy <m>oil</m> for it is not thick</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<m>Enamel azur</m> hates more than any other to be ground, even with some <m>water</m> for it dies and loses all its color. Because however it cannot be used if it is big, grind it not with some water but with some oil and grind it thickly and so it will not die</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Always choose the thinnest one</ab>
</div>


<div> 
<id>p058v_5</id>
<head>Brushes </head>


<ab>When the color has dried inside them and you want to clean them soak them in some <m>spike lavender oil</m> and they will turn immediately soft again as before, then you will finish to clean them in some <m>nut oil</m>. <m>Nut oil</m>is not as appropriate to soften them as the <m>spike lavender</m> one which is clear like water and penetrates and is not as thick as the <m>nut oil</m>. Brush handles are made by those who work with care from <al>porcupine</al> hairs, by some others from fine branches of <pl>Turkish</pl> <m>wood</m> with which they also make small sticks to rest their hand when they are painting</ab>
 


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
To work properly on small scale you need some very fine brushes with a strong point. And because the <m>hair</m> taken from a <al>squirrel</al>'s tale is <fr>mollesin</fr>, the most careful ones use the of oldest <m><al>rats</al>' hair</m> and even of <al>dormouses</al>  if they can find some and put two or three in the middle of a brush. These brushes draw a straight line like a quill and all the other <m>hairs</m> stick to them. The <m>hair of a <al>stone marten</al></m> or of a <al>weasel</al> and small animals used to make some <m>musk</m> are even better for just one <m>hair</m> is necessary in a brush</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>