<root><page>059r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f123.item</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p058v_5</id>
<ab><m>Lake</m> and <m>white lead</m> and <m>ceruse</m> are easy to work with some <m>oil</m>, but every kind of <m>azure</m> is difficult. And to make a beautiful <m>azure</m>, one has to lay it not with big strokes of the brush but with fine strokes of the end. Not only for <m>azurite ash</m> and <m>azur</m> from <pl>Acre</pl> but mainly for <m>enamel azur</m> which has to be very fine, otherwise you will not be able to work with it unless with hard work and you have to mingle it with some <m>turpentine</m> to thicken it and and to mingle it with some <m>white lead</m>. Any <m>azure</m> must not neither be ground nor washed for it loses its color and become pale. But put some of it powdered on your palette and you moisten it bit by bit with some <m>nut oil</m> or <m>turpentine</m>, dip a knife point in some <m>oil</m> and then mix it bit by bit on the said palette</ab></div>
  
<div>
<id>p059r_1</id>
<head>Shadows</head>


<ab>First shadows which are closer to the daylight have to be light and very faint then the last ones very dark to enhance strongly the relief. The <pl>Italians</pl> usually make three shadows, the first one very faint, the second one darker and the third one very dark, then put these three shadows together by hatching them from the darkest to the lightest</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The varnish is more beautiful on a painting when the color has been completely soaked up</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p059r_2</id>
<head><m>Azure</m></head>


<ab><m>Azure</m> is more beautiful when on the painting it has soaked up some <m>nut oil</m> with which it has been firstly thinned without any <m>oil of spike lavender</m>. If you want to know whether it is dry, breathe on it and it will not shine and will seem to be very soaked up, otherwise it will shine</ab>


<ab>Soaked with <m>oil</m>, <m>azure of email</m> leaves it and comes back to its first natural state if you dip it in some <m>water</m></ab>


<ab>Colors for small scale works have to be very strongly ground and to be worked with a brush point if you want your work to be very fine</ab>


</div></root>