<root><page>059v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f124.item</image>


<div>
<id>p059v_1</id>


<head>Painting weapons</head>


<ab><m>Black charcoal</m> mixed with <m>white lead</m> is very appropriate for painting weapons, also mixing in a little <m>azure</m> if you wish. <m>Charcoal</m> by itself is somewhat bluish.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p059v_2</id>
<head>Painting crepe</head>


<ab>First you need to make a greyish background using <m>charcoal black</m> mixed with <m>white lead</m> and a little <m>azure</m>. Then, after drying, highlight with strokes and lines in <m>white lead</m>.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p059v_3</id>
<head>Folds in clothing</head>


<ab>You must take care not to represent any <sup>folds</sup> falsely, but rather imitate natural effects. Thick cloth hardly makes any folds, <m>taffetas</m> and <m>silk</m> cloth make more, and <m>crepe</m> more still. Observe which folds go lengthwise and which across.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p059v_4</id>
<head>Siccatives</head>


<ab><m>White lead</m> and <m>massicot</m> are most siccative, nevertheless they need a good two days. If you want to verify whether an <m>oil</m> is siccative, use it to distemper <m>white lead</m>, and if it soon produces a crust it means that it will dry.</ab>
</div>




<div>
<id>p059v_5</id>
<head>Double layers</head>


<ab><m>Azures</m>, flesh tones and reds are applied twice. Other <sup>colors</sup> are not.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p059v_6</id>
<head>Mending cracks in a panel</head>


<ab>If a painted panel breaks you can glue it well on the reverse, but to fill in the cracks properly in order to paint and repair it, you must not use any <m>glue </m>, which weakens in damp weather and would swell when touched with the <m>oil</m> of the painting. But have some <m>white wax</m>, which is harder than the other sort. The <m>oil</m> mixed into the <m>wax</m> prevents it from melting in the sun. The <m>wax</m> must not be hard, but soft as if recently cooled. Apply it on cracks and crevices with the tip of a knife, then scrape.</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>