<root><page>060r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f125.item</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p059v_6</id>
<ab>and to prevent it from breaking, mix in a little <m>oil</m> and melt them together and fill the cracks and make them even and paint on them. And the  <m>oil</m> mixed with <m>wax</m> will help colors to hold since they are also distempered with <m>oil</m>.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p060r_1</id>


<head>First whitening of the painting</head>


<ab>Apply two or three layers of <m>chalk</m> distempered with <m>glue</m> on the painting, not with a paintbrush but with a <sup>large</sup> brush as if you intended to rub it down, and leave to dry. And repeat this two or three times, then make the last layer quite even using a knife, <add>then apply a layer of <m>glue</m></add> upon which you will later be able to put your underlayer and then paint. But make sure that your first white layer is not too thick for it would break easily. Flemish painters have such paintings made by the dozen.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p060r_2</id>
<head>Working neatly</head>


<ab>When you are at work make sure you do raise no dust, and when you leave your work cover it so that the said dust will not fall upon it. Also apply your colors as thinly as possible, for if they are thick you will be unable to soften them.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Do not apply color on color if they are not similar, such as white on black, but rather flesh over flesh, and so on. And leave empty spaces for shadows or different colors. By doing so, laying each sort of color directly on the underlayer, they will not fade and your work will be neat.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p060r_3</id>
<head><m>Oil</m></head>


<ab><m><pa>Walnut</pa> oil</m> extracted like<m>peeled <pa>almonds</pa></m> is very white. This one of <m><la>Palma christi</la></m>. And when the <m>oil</m> has had a little body, the colors soften. For if the <m>oil</m> is too clear, the colors run &amp; do <corr>not</corr> bind, even those that do not have body. <m>Fatty oil</m> that is not easily imbibed is appropriate for <m>varnish</m>. The <m>oil</m> is desiccative enough when it dries out as quickly as <m>common varnish</m>. <m>Oils</m> do not dry as quickly in cold countries as in hot countries. <m>Oil</m> <env>exposed to the sun</env> is clarified well. But it fattens. If you put in <m>ceruse</m> or <m>lead filings</m> or <m>lead white</m> or <m>calcined pulverized <del><fr>p</fr></del>glass</m>. To avoid this, put the <tl>vial</tl> in <m>clear water</m>.</ab>




<ab>Colors in  <m>oil</m>, once dry, sometimes do not easily receive the second colors, to prevent this, breathe on them &amp; the color will take.</ab>
</div></root>