<root><page>061r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f127.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p060v_4</id>
<ab>and unite it well and being quite dry, they draw their portrait and apply their natural skin color, leaving the areas of shadow like the forehead and the side of the cheek and the empty space around the eyes and drying until they have filled the rest. Afterwards they apply separately the shadows which they do not make as dark as they could naturally be. In sum, they don't apply shadow on skin color nor skin color on shadow. So white is on white and black is on black and each <sup>color</sup> is separate, and in this way their work is neat and colors don't fade away.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p061r_1</id>
<head>Skin colors</head>


<ab>It is necessary that you make it of two kinds, one more red to make the main layer, the other more pale for the highlights, as around the eyes. And then on this last skin color, you will touch lightly the main lights with a little <m>white lead</m>. But avoid applying too much of it because this will look like a face of death. The beautiful <m><pl>Florence</pl> lacquer</m> makes a beautiful vivid skin color that resembles the complexion of <m>alexandrine pink</m> and <m>incarnadine</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Certain colors need to be ground like <m>minium</m> or <m>massicot</m>. The ashes don't need to be ground at all.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p061r_2</id>
<head>Making <sup>things</sup> round</head>


<ab>If you want to model well, soften round things by rounding them off with the brush point and the rest with a flat part if it is flat, and thus for the others according to their nature, and lightly with the dry and flattened brush point and with patience.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p061r_3</id>
<head><m>White lead</m></head>


<ab>Without this, you can't work on a small scale for which it is necessary to soften with great care. But you can't do it with <m>ceruse</m> because it does not have enough body.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p061r_4</id> 
<head>Lights</head>


<ab>Your brush shows it to you by making some shadow which must always follow the back of your hand, not in a straight line like this, <figure/> because the light would be too crude and too harsh, but obliquely and as an incline like this. <figure/><figure/> It is necessary that the painting is not facing the light, but be half turned back against it, and above all look for a soft light, for it makes a <sup>soft</sup> shadow and soft work, like a harsh light <sup>makes</sup> a harsh work.</ab>
</div></root>