<root><page>0061v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f128.image</image>
<div>
<id>p0061v_1</id>


<head><m>Water</m> to make light for <pro>painters</pro></head>


<ab>Distill some <m>vine water</m> and put it into a big bottle. Put your <m>candle</m> behind that, and it won't disturb your vision.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p0061v_2</id>


<head>Chassis used by Germans</head>


<ab>Germans who work in small scale make 'chassis" not of <m>glass</m> but of <m>canvas</m> <m>oiled</m> with <m>clear turpentine varnish</m>, that is half of <m>turpentine oil</m> and almost half of <m>turpentine</m>, because such light, being less bright than <m>glass</m>, makes the lines appear thicker. And when they want to make something more delicate, such as veins and similar things, they use brushes made of two or three <al>rat</al> hairs.</ab>
 </div>


<div>
<id>p0061v_3</id>


<head><m>Azure enamel</m> with <m>oil</m></head>


<ab>One must choose the finest possible, for if it is coarse one cannot work in <m>oil</m>. And if you cannot find any that is fine enough, you may as well grind it, not with <m>water</m> but with <m>oil</m>, and grind it thick. Then lay it on your palette and mix in some <m>turpentine</m> but not much, to make it bind, and make it as thick as <m>butter</m> or <m>mortar</m>, and then, with a large enough brush, work it while always moving the brush freely. Then, to soften it, make jagged hatching <sup>movements</sup> with the tip of the brush. The highlights will be made using the same diluted with <m>ceruse</m>, which makes it bind, making it easier to work. I have seen it used thus. It must be very thick, so that you almost need an effort to spread it with your brush. And it will be all the better if you lay down your painting. All these difficulties do not occur when it is very fine and fluid without being crushed, and it doesn't run.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<m>Azure</m> needs to be applied neatly, which is why it always fades when it is applied over old, already tarnished, <m>azure</m> to mend an old painting. In such cases, it is better to scrape off the old layer and prime again and then apply the <m>azure</m>. It is the same for almost all other colors. Also azure mixed with <m>oil</m> always remains shiny, which is not good for <m>azure</m> because that makes it fade.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p061v_4</id>


<head>Grinding colors</head>


<ab>A slab of <m>glass</m> one inch thick is more appropriate than anything else for grinding colours neatly, especially for <m>lacquer</m> and for <m>whites</m>.</ab>
</div></root>