<root><page>062r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f129.image</image>


<div>
<id>p062r_1</id>
<head>Perspectives</head>


<ab>Perspectives in <m>oil</m> take a long time because of several lines that need to be done with a ruler, and for this reason one usually does them in distemper. One takes the points at one’s discretion. The main thing in having the knowledge of the point. One usually makes two or three of them, sometimes five.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p062r_2</id>
<head><m>Ochre</m></head>


<ab>It is put for faces, hair, skulls and rocks.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p062r_3</id>
<head>Distant people and animals</head>


<ab>One first does them roughly in gray or in purple, which is made of <m><fr>cendre d’azur</fr></m> &amp; <m>lake</m>. Once dry, one highlights &amp; finishes with flesh tones and other colors &amp; white. And it looks better &amp; is sooner done than in black and white. Armies are painted the same way.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p062r_4</id> 
<head>Pictures</head>


<ab>After you have primed your panel and scraped it with a knife to make it quite even, you will start drawing with the longest possible piece of <m>charcoal</m>, because with a short one you would not see your line so well and you would make it rougher. Let the tip of the <m>charcoal</m> be sharp, and to prevent if from quickly becoming dulled and blunt, drag the tip flat, thus you will constantly sharpen it. Hold your <m>charcoal</m> as far as possible, and accustom yourself to drawing with a light touch. Because if you become accustomed to drawing delicately with <m>charcoal</m>, you shall do the same with colors. And whoever is rough with <m>charcoal</m> is never exquisite with colors. And by a line of <m>charcoal</m>, masters assess their apprentices. First make the contour of your drawing, that is the outline, lightly and without too diligent work, rather with boldness. By so doing, you will learn to be an artist, and if you need to to erase anything, you will not waste as much time as if you had elaborated it. Afterwards work on all the details, not standing too close to your panel, but sometimes stepping back in order to better assess the proportions. Once you are satisfied with the first drawing, retrace all the lines with your paintbrush in pink or another <m>gummed</m> or <m>distempered color</m>. Thus you will work more surely with colors, and with less trouble.</ab>
</div></root>