<root><page>063r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f131.image</image>


<div>
<id>p063r_1</id>
<head><m>Amaranth</m> color</head>


<ab>Although it is said to be immortal, <m>white wine</m> removes its coloration and makes it light red and the dried <m>flower</m> ends up white. Note that <m>wine</m> does so, and I have tried it. <m>Spirits</m> have the same effect.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p063r_2</id>
<head>Drying of <m>oil</m></head>


<ab>If the <m>oil</m> does not dry, put in <m>massicot</m> and <m>minium</m>. There is no better <m>oil</m> than <m>walnut oil</m>, because it does not dry out too quickly nor too slowly.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p063r_3</id>
<head>Casting</head>


<ab>The Germans use <m>lead</m> from <pl>Flanders</pl> because it is very "doux". And to cast better they take <m>lead ore</m> and melt it, then separate the molten <m>metal</m> from impurities and <m>"mine"</m>, and pour it into a separate vessel, then they make their cast with it. This is because the <m>lead</m> must not have been used before, but must be completely new. Some people cast into forms of <m>iron</m> or <m>copper</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
or new <m>lead</m> coming straight from the mine. They melt this twice in a crucible. The first melting cleans it of impurities. With the second, they make the cast.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p063r_4</id>


<head>Shadows</head>


<ab>German <pro>painters</pro> shade their flesh tones with crushed <m>jet</m>, <m>stil de grain yellow</m> and <m>ochre</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p063r_5</id>


<head><m>Bister</m></head>


<ab>It is only employed in distemper, and is used for the color of <m>wood</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p063r_6</id>


<head><m>Verdigris</m> and another very beautiful, gay green</head>


<ab>One must not crush it with <m>water</m> alone, because that makes it fade. To make it beautiful in distemper, some crush it with <m>vinegar</m>, but that makes it turn pale and become whitish. To make it beautiful, crush it with <m>urine</m> and leave it to dry. Then, whenever you like, crush it with <m>oil</m>. And after you have collected it with the palette, before you finish cleaning the <m>marble</m>, crush it <sup>there</sup> with <m>stil de grain yellow</m>. And you will have a very beautiful green.</ab>
</div></root>