<root><page>064r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f133.image</image>


<div>
<id>p064r_1</id>


<head>Working neatly</head>


<ab>If you can avoid it, never apply two colors on top of one another. But after making your drawing with great care, keep the shadowed areas separate for themselves and the lights and highlights as well, particularly without smoothly laying a color, then add to this highlighting or shading. And in this way, you further your hard work, spare your colours and work cleanly, which as a result, the colors are not muddled nor mixed together, they do not decay and you soften then  better, thus finding it not so thick.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p064r_6</id>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<ab>
<head><m>Yellow ochre</m></head>


You need a bit in every flesh tone.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p064r_7</id>
<margin>left-center</margin>
<ab>
<head>Softening</head>


One softens in the same way on <m>oil paper</m> as on <m>wood</m>. But it is easier to soften on <m>canvas</m>, because the softening must be coarse there.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p064r_2</id>
<head>Greasy <m>oil</m></head>


<ab>Greasy <m>oil</m> does not work well with colors because it makes them thick, and as difficult to work as <m>azur enamel</m>. Thus use the clearest and freshest <m>walnut oil</m> that you can.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p064r_3</id>
 <head><m>Vermilion</m></head>


<ab>It must not be kept in <m>water</m> when crushed with <m>oil</m> because it loses its color. It is better to choose <m>whitish vermilion</m> than <m>dark vermilion</m> or or a <m>blackish vermilion</m>. Because <m>vermilion</m> is commonly mixed with a little <m>lake</m>, otherwise it would hardly be different from <m>minium</m>. But the pale one shows more vividly than the dark one. It does not dry by itself, so for that effect one mixes in <m>calcined crystal</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p064_8</id>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<ab> 
<head>Eyes</head>


An eye must always follow the circle of the compass and not be flat or square.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p064_4</id>
<head><m>Oil colors</m> in <m>water</m></head>


<ab>Commonly, after crushing them one puts a piece of <m>tin leaf</m> on top, and one puts them into <m>water</m> to keep them from drying out. But this is more appropriate for <m>white lead</m>, <m>minium</m> and <m>massicot</m> than for the others, for <m>lake</m> fades and loses its color, as does <m>azure vermillion</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p064_5</id> 
<head>Double layer</head>


<ab><m>Verdigris</m> does not fade, and therefore does not need to be applied twice. But <m>lake</m> and others, especially flesh tone, need two layers. Colors hardly change once they are dry.</ab>
</div></root>