<root><page>064v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f134.image</image>


<div>
<id>p064v_1</id>
<head>Apprenticeship of the <pro>painter</pro></head>


<ab>First, one gives him an <m>egg</m> to do in which one has him make half a face, then a whole one with the ears, next the neck, then the parts of the body separately, next joined, then one figure, then two &amp; three, finally a history, teaching him how to hold the <m>charcoal</m> by the end, &amp; also the <fr>pinceau</fr>. Once he knows how to draw, one teaches him how to layer colors.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p064v_2</id>
<head>One also presents him with these strokes &amp; lines</head>


<ab>The figure of the <m>egg</m> is the main pattern for faces <add>and for bent bodies</add>, as the cross is the model for a full, straight figure. Without these strokes you will never do anything well.</ab>
</div>


<figure>
<id>fig_p064v_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NmZDTmZwc1Jqb2M</link>
</figure>


<div>
<id>p064v_3</id>
<head>Softening</head>


<ab>To soften well, you must not lay the colors thick, but rather lay them twice, except for <m>azure enamel</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
All colors that lack body in <m>oil</m> also lack body in distemper. In distemper they even sink to the bottom. <m>Distempered colors</m> need to be fat, which you can tell when they stick to the palette after being distempered in <m>oil</m>.</ab>


</div>


<div>
<id>p064v_4</id>
<head>Straight lines</head>


<ab>You can use the ruler, but do not lay it flat on the painting, but somewhat lifted and resting on the edges of the panel. Otherwise you would smudge everything, and also you would not see the strokes well.</ab>


</div>


<div>
<id>p064v_5</id>
  
<head>Distemper</head>


<ab>It is necessary that <m>distempered colors</m> are kept darker while you distemper them, because they become lighter when they dry. But <m>oil colors</m> remain the same colors.</ab>
</div></root>