<root><page>065r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f135.image</image>


<div>
<id>p065r_1</id>
<head>Shadows</head>


<ab> Because blacks appear in different hues, some reddish black, others bluish, and others greenish, choose those verging on yellow in order to obtain beautiful shadows in <m>oil</m>, for shadows are yellowish, especially those of men. And for this effect use very strongly crushed <m>jet</m>, which you mix with a bit of <m>yellow ocher</m> and <m>white lead</m>. Or else, after you have crushed your <m>white lead</m> and gathered it with the <figure/>, crush the <m>jet</m> into it. Thus it <sup>the black</sup> will be more desiccative, and a yellowish black on its own. When mixed with a bit of white, it will be perfect for men's shadows. Blacks which appear greenish black are appropriate for women's shadows. Take then some black of  <figure/>, a little <m>sap green</m> and some <m>bistre</m>, and you will have a perfect shading for [flesh tone] in distemper for a woman.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
The powder of orberé <m>grain</m> is duller than <m>umber</m> and when you lack <m>umber</m>, the aforesaid powder may be used, but it lacks body.</ab>


</div>


<div>
<id>p065r_2</id>
<head>Flesh color</head>


<ab>You must know how to mix the colors and the appropriate shadows well, but above all make sure to soften them well. And note and observe that an object that appears flat needs to be softened in straight lines, such as from right to left like 
<figure>
<id>fig_p065r_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5eUhrRmdpaWNCZlk</link>
</figure>
, and whatever needs to be represented round must be softened in circles.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
One cannot lay down <m>oil</m> on cut <m>paper</m> or make a stencil as in distemper because the colour will run. Thus, in order to <m>gild</m> with matte <m>gold</m>, one has to pounce and then lay in the colors with the brush.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p065r_3</id>  
<head>Mirror</head>


<ab>When you paint flesh, it is useful to have a <m>crystal</m> mirror, which represents a lifelike image, and in which you will see if your shadows are soft enough or too crude. But do not look at it using a candle, because the light of the flame will make the shadows look reddish. The painter also learns for himself with a mirror, because he sees in it what a lifelike image can produce.</ab>


</div>


<div>
<id>p065r_4</id>
<head>Greasy colors</head>


<ab>After the laid-down colors are absorbed, if some part remains shiny and does not seem dry, it means that this part is greasy, and that the second colors you lay down would not adhere either, unless you scrub this part with <m>soap</m> or breathe on it, because humidity will make the colors adhere.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
All greasy colors, such as <m>ceruse</m>, <m>minium</m>, <m>massicot</m>, <m>ochre</m>, and <m>white lead</m> are good for making <m>gold</m> color.</ab>


<ab> 
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Any color or thing that thickens when mixed with <m>water</m>, while being crushed has body. But those that lack it, such as crushed <m>glass</m> and <m>lake</m> etc., become clear.</ab>


</div></root>