<root><page>065v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f136.image</image>
 
<div>
<id>p065v_1</id>
 
<head>Mid-bright colors</head>
<ab>When colors are absorbed into the <m>canvas</m>, it means that it has been primed only once, and for this reason the colors become matte rather than shiny. But that is best, as long as you retouch it twice, for in this manner, the colors, having more body, will not fade and are much more beautiful, especially <m>azure</m> and <m>lake</m> and those that lack body. But those who want to dispatch their painting carelessly prime twice. Thus the colors will not be absorbed, therefore they will not last as long. The second layer of these colors will not be absorbed and will remain shiny.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p065v_6</id>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<head>Lifelike</head>
<ab>There are some who paint lifelike images on <m>oiled paper</m>, and if they do not complete their work in one go, they put their <m>paper</m> and unfinished painting in <m>water</m> so that it will not dry. </ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p065v_2</id>
<head>Painting large figures</head>
 
<ab>You must attach your <m>charcoal</m> to the end of a stick in order to make your first drawing from a distance because up close, you would not be able to judge proportions as well as from a certain and sufficient distance. Also, when you paint up close, hold your <m>charcoal</m> as far as you can, practically with your fingertips. For in that way you will acquire an artist's touch and make your hand light. </ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
When painting on <m>paper</m>, <pro>illuminators</pro> distemper their colors with <m>gum</m> and mix in a little <m>soap</m> to make them run better.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p065v_3</id>
<head><m>Glazing</m></head>
 
<ab>One usually glazes with colors lacking body, such as <m>lake</m> and <m>verdigris</m>. However, in order to use other sorts, one mixes in plenty of calcined and ground <m>crystal</m>, which also has no body and reduces their thickness.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<pro>Painters</pro> should all learn how to paint from life, because it is their provision and annuity and means to earn their passage when travelling the land with only their <m>"cocon"</m>.
</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p_065v_4</id>
<head>White and black</head>
 
<ab>It is useful that an <pro>apprentice</pro> should work with black and white for two or three years in order to become an <pro>artist</pro>.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p065v_7</id>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<head>Priming</head>
 
<ab>You must be quite careful about this, and do not do it, as some will, using <m>gold</m> color made by cleaning the <m>oil</m> brushes, because <m>verdigris</m> and other corrosive colors included will end by fading the colors that are laid in after. It is useful to do it with <m>ceruse</m>, <m>yellow ocher</m>, and a bit of <m>massicot</m>, and make it scarcely thick so that it will not crack.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p065v_5</id>
<head><m>Lead white</m></head>
 
<ab>It does not fade and has a lot of body.</ab>
</div></root>