<root><page>066r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f137.image</image>


<div>
<id>p066r_1</id>
<head>Double layers</head>


<ab>The <pl>Flemish</pl> &amp; those who paint paintings by the dozen only apply one layer &amp; finish in one go. But the colors soon die. And when they are laid twice, they will not die. One needs to lay them lightly &amp; with minimal thickness, in order to soften them.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p066r_2</id> 
<head>Shadows</head>


<ab>For women: <m>asphaltum</m>, <m>umber</m> and a little <m>lake</m>.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p066r_3</id>
<head>Painting in distemper on <m>wood</m></head>


<ab>Because it is quite tedious to paint in distemper on <m>wood</m>, and difficult to paint a face well, some mix their colors with <m>egg white</m> seeped through a sponge, or mixed with the <m><sup>egg</sup> yolk</m>, <m>water</m>, and well beaten with the <m>peeling of the fig tree</m>. With this they paint &amp; soften on the <m>wood</m>, like with <m>oil</m>, and this supports the varnish, but this does not last.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p066r_4</id>
<head>Colors in <m>oil</m> that are imbibed</head>


<ab>It is best that colors in <m>oil</m> are imbibed, that is to say they do not remain shiny after they are dry, for they do not die. But if in some places they are shiny, it is that the fattiness of the <m>oil</m> has remained in that part which would make the colors die. The varnish mends all this &amp; unites &amp; renders it similar in one place as in another.</ab>


<ab>One needs <m>gold</m> color to be laid down thick, for if it is clear, it would be imbibed &amp; would run.</ab>


<ab>On <m>canvas</m> &amp; in distemper, one <m>gilds</m> with <m>bole</m> &amp; <m>honey</m> &amp; a little <m>garlic juice</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p066r_5</id>
<head>Gilding painting mounts with <fr><m>or</m> mat</fr></head>


<ab>See the other side of this folio this mark: <figure>*</figure></ab>


<ab>The <pl>Flemish</pl> give one layer of distempered <m>glue</m> on the mount, then they mix <m>lamp black</m> or <m>soot black</m> with the same <m>glue</m> &amp; leave to dry. Next, they pounce some <fr>moresque</fr> designs in the corners &amp; paint them with <m>minium</m>, <m>massicot</m>, <m>ochre de ru</m>, and a bit of <m>yellow ocher</m>, mixed with the <m>fatty oil</m> in which they clean their <m>oil</m> brushes, because the three aforesaid colors are griping and dry immediatly. And next, they apply the <m>gold</m>, then varnish on top of everything. And it seems by this way to some, that all of the black is painted in <m>oil</m>, but that would not be good because the <m>gold</m> attaches everywhere, and not only on the <fr>moresque</fr>. Go back to the top to <figure>*</figure></ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<figure>*</figure>
<rub><fr><m>Or</m>mat</fr></rub>
<ab>It is made with <m>massicot</m>, <m>minium</m>, <m>ochre de ru</m>, &amp; <m>yellow ocher</m>, so that the composition resembles <m>gold</m>. Gild the day after <fr><del>un jo</del></fr> it is applied, if you <del>in the</del> made the groundlayer the <sup>same</sup> evening as the color. Next, having gilded, leave it to dry &amp; rest for one day. Next, rub the gilding with a <tl>feather</tl> &amp; <tl>cotton</tl>, so that no small flakes remains, then varnish with <m><pl>Flanders</pl> varnish</m>, which you make, mixed with a little <m>spirit</m>, to make it desiccative.</ab> 


<ab>The varnish will dry in an hour. It will enhance the <m>gold</m> color. And this <fr><m>or</m> mat</fr> withstands rain, even if one rubs it, but it must be well dry, for eight or ten days.</ab> 


<m>Gold</m> color that is made of various colors cleaned from <m>oil</m> brushes is not so good &amp; with time tarnishes the <m>gold</m> because of the <m>verdigris</m>. One must not touch with the <bp>finger</bp> the layer made for the <m>gold</m> because that will prevent it from attaching itself there. The <m><fr>or moulu</fr></m> spoils if <m>water</m> touches it, but <fr><m>or</m> mat</fr> withstands well the rain &amp; in <m>water</m>. One must not burnish it, because the <tl>tooth</tl> would remove it. Collect the small flakes &amp; small bits that the <tl>cotton</tl> removed when the <m>gold</m> is dry and that you clean it, for as little as an <ms>ounce</ms> is still <m>gold</m>. In <pl>Flanders</pl>, women <del>make</del> <m>gild</m>. It is more beautiful when it is a little thick but in <pl>France</pl> they beat it too delicately. 


<ab>Breathe on the <m>gold</m> color, and if it loses its shine, it is dry enough, but if does not welcome the vapor of the breath, it is not yet dry enough.</ab> 


<ab>One should not do <fr><m>or</m> mat</fr> gilding after <del>with</del> having applied <m>gold</m> color, but wait one day and one night, <del>but take heed to not</del> and, when it appears to be dry, it will grip the gold. Next, one varnishes.</ab>
</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>