<root><page>067v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f140.image</image>
 
<div>
<id>p067v_1</id>
<head><tl>Files</tl></head>


<ab>If they are not <fr>trempées à pacquet</fr>, that is, in the manner described, with <m>soot</m>, <m>salt</m>, &amp; <m>vinegar</m>, they will not be good. The large <tl>square files</tl> used by <pro>locksmiths</pro> to draft their work are only made of <m><fr>fer doulx</fr></m>, But the <tl>soft files</tl> should be made of <m>steel</m>. <pro>Founders</pro> whose work is to repair <m>latten</m> &amp; <m>copper</m> should have their files coarse otherwise they fill up with <m>copper</m> which makes them smooth &amp; soon renders them useless. <m>Latten</m>, which is more brittle, welcomes softer files than <m>copper</m> does.</ab>
 </div>

<div>
<id>p067v_2</id>
<head><m>Oxen foot bones</m> for sand</head>


<ab>Once having been burned well twice &amp; pulverized, they mold very neatly in sand &amp; need not be recooked, but simply heated with the flame of <m>straw</m>. But if you mold them in a <fr>noyau</fr>, give it its first layer, simple  &amp; very thin, with a <fr>pinceau</fr>, &amp; leave to dry at ease. Next fortify the following layers with <m>wadding</m> mixed with the aforementioned tempered <m>bone</m> sand.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is the neatest sand that can be found for <m>copper</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p067v_3</id>
<head><m>Essential oils</m></head>
 
<ab><m><add>Walnut</add> oil</m> mixed with an equal quantity of <m>turpentine</m> and distilled with an alembic produces an <m>essence</m> whiter than common <m>water</m>. But this has no body &amp; does not unite colors, which are immediately imbibed, and then color is left unable to grip and fades away. Imbibed thus, they would not let you work with or soften them, anymore than in distemper. But you can rectify this flaw by giving it a little body with <m>turpentine</m>, <sup>but</sup> not as thickly as you would use for varnishing. And thus you can work with <m><fr>azur d’esmail</fr></m>, &amp; make perfect <m>lead white</m>. <m>Turpentine varnish</m> made from this <m>oil</m> dries within one hour.</ab>
</div></root>