<root><page>068v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f142.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p068r_3</id>
<ab>and immediately you will be able to crumble it between your fingers and to easily grind it in a <m>metal</m> mortar, or better yet, in an <m>iron</m> one. After, it will be easy to crush it, not on a <m>common marble</m> slab that would be damaged, but on <m>porphyry</m>, and it must be finely crushed with <m>water</m> so that when you place it on your fingernail, you will find it soft without any roughness like the colors that the painters crush for <m>oil</m> <sup>painting</sup>. You can use this one instead of sand, when it is dry, for the box mold, without humidifying it with anything and without reheating it. If you do not like it, fumigate the hollow of the mold with <m>sulfur</m> smoke or with the tip of the flame of a <m>wax</m> candle that barely smokes, and with pure <m>lead</m> and <m>tin</m> <sup>the mold</sup> will make a very clean, shiny, and smooth work. I would say the same for finely pulverized <m>rotten stone</m>, which does not want to be reheated or humidified. Using burned <m>cloth</m> is easier than anything because it does not need to be reheated, nor to be humidified, nor to be cast and removed subtly or very cleanly, like the others I mentioned, and it stands up to several castings. First you must burn it with a flame, then leave it to rot and be consumed with its fire until it is completely burned, then refine it on <m>marble</m> or <m>paper</m>. And if you reheat it in a red hot crucible all of it will be rendered fine and insubstantial[a], I believe that this make it even better. But because a lot of <m>cloth</m> is reduced to very little when it is burned, if you want to save some, sprinkle and cover only the medal that you want to cast with it, and fill the box mold with crushed <m>slate</m>, that also molds very neatly, but note that the first cast is always the most beautiful and the cleanest. By the way, if you cast the <m>soft tin</m> that <pro>pewterers</pro> sell, the kind that appears to be burnished on these little turning wheels, very well cleaned and approaching the color of <m>silver</m>, without being mixed with anything else, it is true that it must be cast quite hot and that the molded object must be four fingers from the cast. In order to know the temperature you must first melt it quite hot so that if you put a <m>paper</m> or <m>straw</m> in it when it is simmering it quickly burns it. Then remove it from the fire and leave it to rest a little and cast the <m>tin</m> mixed
</ab>
<cont/>
</div>


[a]I suggest to translate as "impalpable" as in French original, because this is a specific technical term for very fine powders (see Biringuccio's Pirotechnia, Dover edition 1990, p. 324)</root>