<root><page>069r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f143.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p068r_3</id>
<ab>with <m>half lead</m> comes out almost better than <m>tin</m> <del>pure</del> <del><add>or</add></del> or <m>pure lead</m>, even though in any case they come out well. Nevertheless take care not to cast <m>lead</m> not as hot as <m>tin</m>. In big works it is necessary to moisten the <m>sands</m> with <m>magistra</m> or <m>egg white</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p069r_1</id>
<head><pro>Joiner</pro></head>


<ab>Three things take the longest, leaves, hair &amp; garlands.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p069r_2</id>
<head><m>Sand</m></head>
 
<ab>You should not choose for casting the one that is in any way lean &amp; arid, such that it does not bind at all, like the one from the sea or <del>desei</del> from sandy paths dried out by the sun. But choose them <del>or in t</del> preferably from quar<del>reries</del>ries  or rock caves, because that one is best, as long as it is very fine. You will know the vein if, in the greyish rocks or quarries <del>qu</del> that seem to be made of <fr>arenes</fr>, you see after rainy weather, certain little amounts like dust attached to the said rocks, or if a little piece flakes off, easily crushed between your hands, due to humidity. You will also find it in lean soils, which comes off in <del>lop</del>  large lumps like stones of <fr>tuf</fr> <del>et ne</del>, or among <fr>terres boulvènes</fr>, which are much better than those from fat &amp; strong earths. And one ought not to take it from the surface, for fear that  it be mixed with common earth, but three or 4 feet below &amp; the closest to the <fr>tuf</fr> or stone. Since it comes out in large lumps one would say it starts to form itself in stone. But when it is wet, it comes apart easily. One needs to make sure that when breaking it up it is well granular, &amp; that when crushing it between the fingers, it renders itself really very fine,  <del>like impalpable</del>, keeping nevertheless its sandy asperity, without muddying the fingers like clay. It dries up slightly on the <m>fire</m>, then it disintegrates &amp; passes finely through a double sieve or a <m>linen</m> sleeve, then takes moistures with <m>wine</m> or <m>magistra</m> &amp; @ / <la>Green</la></ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The Toulouse <pro>molder</pro> reheats it strongly then grinds it finely on <m>marble</m> and passes it through a <m>linen</m> &amp; moistens <del>pass</del> it with <m>wine</m>.  He makes the cast very broad &amp;  <del>ne</del> flat &amp; barely deep.  He casts <m>pure latton</m> used for scales &amp; similar thin things. He casts very hot.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
@ Try calcined <m>vitriol</m>.</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>