<root><page>069v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f144.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p069r_2</id>
<ab>The <m>sand</m> near my area is very excellent. But in order to make an excellent work, take it fresh, hardly having been used. Because it dries out after having done a casting several times &amp; is arid &amp; has no body at all. If you cast some fine work which has hardly any thickness, your <m>copper</m> matter must be very hot so that it penetrates and runs.  Some people mix <m>lead</m> within this molten <m>metal</m>, but this is for large works &amp; not for small ones.</ab>


<ab><m>Sand from bulls' feet</m> twice-burned and finely ground melts more neatly with <m>copper</m>, &amp; without a coating, than <m>sand</m> that I've seen. I cast a medal with quite high relief in it, and slender, with the thickness of a knife blade or a card.  And there being a hollow on one side, the obverse, with the relief being on the other side.</ab>
 
<ab>Lean <m>sand</m> needs to be more moistened than others, that's to say with <m>magistra</m> or good pure <m>wine</m> or <m>wine boiled with elm tree roots</m> or something similar. But very fine <m>sands</m>, like <m>burned linen</m> which is fat and soft of its own accord, want to be applied dry.</ab>


<ab>All moistened <m>sand</m> needs to be very beaten and tumbled in order to make it fine &amp; flattened of the little globules that it makes in itself when it is drenched.</ab>


<ab>The <m>olive oil</m> that some people mix in with beaten <m>egg white</m> makes it puff out.</ab>


<ab><m>Sand of calcined glass</m> lasts for many fusions.  But there are only the first ones.  It also puffs out.</ab>


<ab><m>Latten</m> works well on its own, but it charges.  It is good to mix it with some <m>copper</m>, about a quarter part, with <m>frying pan material</m>.</ab>


<ab><pro>Founders</pro> cast box frames well up to about 30 or 40 pounds.  But no more.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is good for big work.  But for small it is troublesome to take away.  This is because it crumbles.  It would be good for it to be a little glued together with something fatty that binds, like molded <m>tripoli</m> or burned <m>felt</m> or <m>salt ammoniac</m> or <m>tripoli</m> &amp; similar things.</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>