<root><page>070r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b20500001g/f145.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p069r_2</id>
<ab>Once you have molded, it is good to reheat your mold with the <m>smoke</m> of the material you are melting, because the cast would absorb the quality of the <m>metal</m>, then this <m>metal</m> will flow more easily in something that takes after itself.</ab>
 
<ab>The <m>human bones</m> are the best for casting when they are calcined.</ab>


<ab>Your material needs to be quite hot in order to cast clean. To achieve this, when your material is melted, add some <m>iron shavings</m>, or <m>iron filings</m>, or [<m>iron</m> in other form], because it heats <m>copper</m> very much and it cleans it of its fat.  At the end, when you want to cast, add some <m>saltpeter</m>, and place your preparation between a folded sheet of <m>paper</m> in order to hide the composition of your mix, to keep it secret.</ab>


<ab><m>Sheep foot bones</m> are even better than the <m>ox foot bones</m>.</ab>


<ab><m>Oil</m> and <m>tallow</m> make fill with bubbles, and <m>crushed glass</m> and <m>copper</m> alone.</ab>


<ab><m>Ashy soil</m> molds very well.</ab>


<ab><m>Ashes</m> don't have enough body to hold <m>copper</m>.</ab>


<ab>It is better not to mix [different types of] <m>sand</m> at all, but to fill the chassis with one type [<m>sand</m>] only.</ab>


<ab><m>Brass</m> is always fat, and does not mold very clean. It is believed that it turns out better being alloyed with a quarter <m>copper</m>, but it must be cast very hot.</ab>


<ab><m>Copper</m> is good mixed with a bit of <m>metal</m>. If you mix <m>metal</m> with <m>brass</m>, it will be harder and more difficult [to handle].</ab>


<ab>A slightly coarse <m>sand</m> has more body.</ab>
 
<ab><m>Rock's sand</m> is always better, because it looks like tuff in small pieces which has a beautiful and very fine grain, a bit fat. Grind it, then dry it in a frying pan on the fire, until it stops smoking. Then filter it through a fine double sieve and use it to mold.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<m>Copper</m> or <m>brass</m> cannot come out well if the medal does not sufficient thickness and if it does not have it, give it some with some <m>wax</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Some mold through a hole done in the middle of the reverse side of the medal.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Some want to mold large works in <m>brass</m> mixed in the <m>sand</m> some ground <m>glass</m> to give the <m>soil</m> unity. But it makes it filled with bubbles. And you have to repair the work.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
One puts a good amount of <m>lead</m> within a large work to make it flow, but not in a small one because it leaves grime all around the work.</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>