<root><page>071r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f147.image</image> 


<div>
<id>p071r_1</id>
<head><m>Amber</m></head>


<ab>It softens like a paste when it is boiled in molten <m>wax</m>, and colors when boiled with the <m>grease</m> of a young <al>kid</al>, since that <sup>the grease</sup> of a <al>goat</al> would break it, especially if it is glazed.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p071r_2</id>
<head>Streaked <m>wood</m></head>


<ab>The <m>elm</m>has in its knotty roots beautiful veins streaked with grey and black, and the <m>root of the maple tree</m> as well, but the grain of the <m>wood</m> needs to be chosen carefully. One gives the <m>maple wood</m> a certain yellow color and then varnishes it.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p071r_3</id>
<head><m>Sugared</m> and <m>mulled wine</m></head>
<ab>
When the <pl>English</pl> have a cold, they mull <m>wine</m> in this way. They heat <m>wine</m> in a <del>large</del> <m>tin</m> pot until it boils, and when it becomes frothy, <del/>they light it with burning <m>paper</m> to determine if it is hot enough. After, to mull the whole of it, they pour it from one vessel into another, as if they wanted to churn <m>eau panée</m>, and as they do it, someone else lights with a burning <m>paper</m> what is falling from the one vessel into the other, such that you would think you were pouring fire. When the <m>wine</m> is mulled enough, heat it again a little while adding a few <m>cloves</m> &amp; a sufficient quantity of <m>sugar</m>. And they <sup>the <pl>English</pl></sup> <del/> drink it when it is as hot as possible in order to overcome their melancholy.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<pl>English</pl> commoners put <m>sugar</m> in <m>wine</m> as a substitute for new sweet <m>wine</m>, which they cannot have because, owing to the long sea crossing, the <m>wine</m> loses its sweetness and clarifies itself before it reaches their country.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p071r_4</id>
<head>Weary <al>horses</al></head>


<ab>In order to restore a harried <al>horse</al>, they make it drink some of the aforesaid <m>wine</m> through a horn, and it finds itself disposed to do an even harder labor.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p071r_5</id>
<head><m>Eau de vie</m></head>


<ab>The <al>Irish</al> do not drink any <m>wine</m> because they convert it into <m>spirits</m>, which they use almost as habitually as we use <m>wine</m>.</ab>
</div></root>