<root><page>071v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f148.image</image>


<div>
<id>p071v_1</id>
<head>Varnish</head>


<ab>Add 4 <figure>℥</figure> of <m>sandarac</m> and finely pulverized <m>mastic</m> to a half lb of <m>aspic oil</m>. First of all, boil your <m>oil</m> in a pot on a stove, and then add the aforesaid <m>gum</m> little by little, stirring continually with a small stick split and quartered at the end. And when you cannot collect any more <m>gum</m> on the end, it is totally melted and your varnish is done.  And to make it clearer, put into the concoction a little lump of <m>camphor</m>. It is true that with this it will not dry as quickly. Heed well that the <m>aspic oil</m> is quite clear and not at all fatty, otherwise your varnish will not be worth anything. You can test <del/> it by soaking some <m>paper</m> in it and heating it. If the <m>oil</m>, which will evaporate, leaves the <m>paper</m> clean, without <del/> a yellow mark, it is good, if not, it is fatty.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p071v_2</id>
<head><m><al>Sheep</al> fat</m></head>


<ab>In a certain part of <pl>England</pl>, the <al>sheep</al> that graze there have very yellow <m>fat</m> and are nevertheless just as good as others.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p071v_3</id>
<head><al>Spider</al></head>


<ab>There are no <sup>spiders</sup> in <pl>Ireland</pl>, &amp; if one touches them with some <m>wood</m> that they have there, they die. That is why some rich people from <pl>England</pl> make their floors with this <m>wood</m>, and in this way, they do not have any spiderwebs.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p071v_4</id>
<head>Sand</head>


<ab>The mold is very good for casting in <m>copper</m>. But do not use that from cutlery, because it's just <m>sludge</m>, but rather that of those who <del/> mold giant shears.</ab>


<ab><m>Filières' stones</m>, when smoothed by those who whet them, mold really neatly when scraped for <m>lead</m>. This is usually slate-colored. One frequently carries it from <pl>Carcassonne</pl> to <pl>Toulouse</pl>.</ab>
</div></root>