<root><page>072r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f149.item</image>


<div>
<id>p072r_1</id>


<head>Printer's letters</head>


<ab>The people who make the letters mix with the <m>lead</m> <del>nails</del> <m>heads of nails</m> &amp; <m>old horseshoes</m>, &amp; <m>antimony</m> to help melting. This mixture is good for printing, &amp;holds steady. It flows and is well suited to casting in <m>lead</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p072r_2</id>


<head><m>Copper</m> casting</head>


<ab>The box mold should be even-shaped &amp; well fitted onto the board where it is placed, so that it will hold steady &amp; even when one moulds. The sand should be clean &amp; carefully selected, well baked, &amp; regarding the sand you will pour directly over the medal and press the harder while molding, it should be very finely pulverised on the <m>marble</m>. Be careful not to oil your medal or the <m>metal</m> will be brittle. Bake slowly and thoroughly, &amp; let cool. Moisten your sand with <m>wine</m> boiled with <m>elm root</m>, and in it, cast <m>well-flowing latten</m> (that is, <m>latten</m> from scales and similar thin things). Cast as widely as possible, &amp; although the stream [of <m>metal</m>] will not be very thick, it will not be any worse. Still, make sure it enters the mold well. Cast from the foot of the medal up, so that the face, further away from the heat, comes out better &amp; the violent effect of the heat is softened. And if your box mold does not have furrows, draw some <del/> in the sand, from the borders of the mold towards the hollow where you will be casting. Cast very hot; you will know [if you are at the right temperature] by throwing a bit of your reserved material into what is already <del/> very molten, &amp; if it melts right away, it is a sign that [your metal] is hot enough. Then maintain a vigorous heat in your furnace with <m>bellows</m> of an appropriate size, while holding the mouth of your furnace well covered with a large <del/> <m>tile</m> or something similar that needs to be red before the casting. When you want to cast, have your mollettes red hot, &amp; the iron hook as well, to clean out the charcoals [fallen] in your material. Having cast, scrub your work with a <m>latten</m> wirebrush. The residual powder from large scissors &amp; large knives is very good for <m>copper</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is said to be a great secret to add <m>persicaire</m> to [the cast], in order to make it as fluid as lead. Try to extract <m>salts</m> from it.</ab></div></root>