<root><page>073r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f151.image</image>


<div>
<id>p073r_1</id>
<head>For making <m>blue varnish</m></head>


<ab>Take the <m>blue of flowers <add>florey or of <pl>Flanders</pl></add></m> &amp; <m>quicklime</m>, and put in around four <ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> of <m>water</m>, and let it soak one <ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms>. Take the <m>water</m> where the said <m>quicklime</m> has soaked, and put your <m>blue</m> with it, and lay it down <corr>on</corr>  the <m>wood</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p073r_2</id>
<head>For orange color</head>


<ab>Take the <m>water</m> where the <m>quicklime</m> will have soaked and some <m>turmeric</m>, and put them one with the other, and then you will put them on your <m>wood</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p073r_3</id> 
<head>For ridding <m>bone</m> or <m>horn</m> of fattiness</head>


<ab>One needs to make them boil in <m>quicklime</m>, and it must always have <m>water</m>, and take a very clean pan. And when they are washed, make them boil in the <m>ashes of vine shoots</m>, and put them inside the hottest pot you can, and put <m>verdigris</m> into the <pro>goldsmith's</pro> <m>water</m> pot, and leave for the space of some time, and you will see a very beautiful green color.</ab> 
</div>


<div>
<id>p073r_4</id>
<head>For making gray <m>wood</m></head>


<ab>Take <m>alum</m> with <m>river water</m>, make them boil together, then take <m>river water</m> with <m>bran</m>, submerge the <m>bran</m> and crush it together. Take <m>iron filings</m> &amp; <m>sulfur</m> &amp; <m>verdigris</m> and <m>fuller's earth</m> <gap/>, and make it all boil together, and crush <m>maplewood</m> which will have been soaked in <m>water</m> of <m>alum</m> and <m>well water</m>, &amp; put it to boil together. <add>All of this will be done better in hollow sandstone.</add></ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p073r_5</id>
<head>For making bronze in <m>gold</m> color</head>


<ab>Take one ounce of <m>sal ammoniac</m> and crush them in an <m>iron</m> mortar. Once well crushed, take one ounce of <m>sulfur</m>, and 
</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>