<root><page>073r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f151.image</image>


<div>
<id>p073r_1</id>
<head>For making <m>blue florey</m> varnish or <pl>Flanders</pl> <sup>varnish</sup></head>


<ab>Take the <m>blue florey</m> and <m>quicklime</m>, and put on around four fingers' worth of <m>water</m> and leave it to soak for one day. Take the <m>water</m> where the aforesaid <m>quickline</m> has soaked, and put your <m>blue <sup>florey</sup></m> with it, and put it on the <m>wood</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p073r_2</id>
<head>For orange color</head>


<ab>Take the <m>water</m> where the <m>quicklime</m> will have soaked and some <m>turmeric</m>, and put them one with the other, and then you will put them on your <m>wood</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p073r_3</id> 
<head>For degreasing <m>bone</m> or <m>horn</m></head>


<ab>They need to be boiled in <m>quicklime</m>, and be sure that there is always <m>water</m>, and take a well-cleaned pan, and when they are clean, boil them in the <m>ashes of vine shoots</m>, and put it inside the hottest pot you can, and put some <m>verdigris</m> into the <pro>goldsmith's</pro> pot of <m>water</m>, and leave for some time and you will see a most beautiful green color.</ab> 
</div>


<div>
<id>p073r_4</id>
<head>For making gray <m>wood</m></head>


<ab>Take <m>alum</m> with <m>river water</m>and boil them together. Then take <m>river water</m> with some <m>bran</m>, pour in the <m>bran</m> and crush them together. Take <m>iron filings</m> and <m>sulfur</m> and <m>verdigris</m> and <m>fuller's earth</m> <gap/>, and boil it all together, and crush <m>maplewood</m> which will have been soaked in <m>water</m> of <m>alum</m> and <m>rainwater</m>, and put it to boil together. All of this can be done better in a large crucible.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p073r_5</id>
<head>To make bronze with a <m>gold</m> color</head>


<ab>Take one ounce of <m>sal ammoniac</m> and crush it in an <m>iron</m> mortar. When it is well crushed, take one ounce of <m>sulfur</m>, and 
</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>