<root><page>075v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f156.item</image>


<div>
<id>p075v_1</id>
<head>For making gray <m>wood</m></head>
<ab>One needs to take three half <ms><fr>setiers</fr></ms> of <m>iron</m> filings for 18 <fr>deniers</fr> of <m><fr>alung de glace</fr></m>, &amp; for as much <m>green copperas</m>, for six <fr>deniers</fr> of <m>verdigris</m>, pitch, &amp; a quart of <m><pro>currier</pro> water</m>, and if you cannot find it, you will put <m>rainwater</m> <gap/> of slight degree. </ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p075v_2</id>
<head>For gilding on <m>wood</m></head>
<ab>First one needs to lay down a coat of <m>glue</m> very clear, and once dry, you will lay down a coat of <m>yellow gold</m>. And when it is done, you will take <m>fig tree wood</m>, &amp; put it to soak some space of time, &amp; wash the places you want to gild, and cut your <m>gold</m> with a knife to the price that you will lay down. And one must lay down the said <m>gold</m> with <m>cotton</m>. And if you can find <m>fig tree</m>, take the <m>the white of one egg</m> &amp; stir it vigorously.</ab>


<ab>
If your <m>gold</m> does not have beautiful enough color, you will take a <m>partridge feather</m>, &amp; make it burn it in a chafing-dish, and make the smoke go against what you have gilded.</ab>
</div> 


<div>
<id>p075v_3</id>
<head>For gilding of ground <m>gold</m></head>
<ab>Take a <ms>coquille</ms> of <m>gold</m>, soak it with gum water before you intend to work, and then apply it with a brush, and polish it with a <del/><m>wolf's tooth</m> once it is dry.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p075v_4</id>
<head>Recipe for coloring all <m>wood</m></head>
<ab>To make it black, the wood needs to be soaked in <m>olive oil</m> and tough <m>meat</m> in a similar case for four or five days, then boil it in where the wood has soaked for one hour, then take it <sup>the wood</sup> out of the oil. Take some <m>natural sulphur</m> if possible otherwise take another</ab>


<cont/>
</div></root>