<root><page>076r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f157.item</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p075v_4</id>
<ab><sup><m>sulphur</m></sup>. Cover the aforementioned <m>wood</m> with this powder, until it cools, and bring it back to a boil. Upon boiling one will see whether or not it is black enough. If it is not, take the aforementioned powder and apply some over the <m>wood</m> and boil it.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p076r_1</id>
<head>Making <m>Wood</m> Green</head>


<ab>
Take one quart of <m>white vinegar</m>, one ounce of green, and one ounce of <m>rock alum</m>. Mix them together and pour all your ingredients into a <m>leaded</m> pot over fire without taking any air. Then put the pot in <m>manure</m> for 15 days, after which time you shall remove and boil your materials for three hours.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p076r_2</id>
<head>Making <m>Wood</m> Red</head>


<ab>
Take one quart of <m>old urine</m>, three ounces of <m>madder</m>, and one ounce of <m>rock alum</m>, put all of the ingredients into your pot. Then follow the previously described green technique.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p076r_3</id> 
<head>Making <m>Wood</m> Blue</head>


<ab>
Take one quart of <m>urine</m>, as above, one ounce of <m>alum</m>, and two drams of <m>sal ammoniac</m>, and half an ounce of <m>woad</m>, grind it all to powder. Then follow the previously described green technique.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p076r_4</id>
<head>For <sup>Making</sup> Purple <m>Wood</m></head>


<ab>
Take one quart of <m>urine</m> and one ounce of <m>alum</m> and ten drams of <m>sal ammoniac</m> and one <sup>dram</sup> of lacquer, then do as previously described.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p076r_5</id>
<head>For <sup>Making</sup> Yellow <m>Wood</m></head>


<ab>
Take urine, as above, and two ounces of <m>woad</m>, one ounce of <m>fustet</m> and two <del>ounces</del>drams of <m>sal ammoniac</m>, then do as previously described.</ab>
</div></root>