<root><page>079v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f164.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p079r_3</id>


<ab>and put it into an <m>earthen</m>pot, &amp; it should have many hot <m>ashes</m> underneath, &amp; little by little you will make the fire underneath bigger and bigger, &amp; one ought not move it, &amp; when it will be cooked, &amp; it needs to be for six hours, mind that the smoke does not harm you for it is bad.</ab></div>
  
<div>
<id>p079v_1</id>


<head>For making <m>varnish</m></head>


<ab>Take some <m>mastic</m>, <m>sang <del><fr>daRage</fr></del> <add>darac</add></m>, <m>gum arabic</m> &amp; <m><pa>spike lavender</pa> oil</m>, as much of one as the other, &amp; make them melt all together, &amp; before coating it, lay a coat of <m>glue quite clear</m>, &amp; let it dry.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p079v_2</id>


<head>Antidote against the smoke of <m>metals</m></head>


<ab>In the morning, take a piece of thin <m>toast</m> with <m>butter</m>, neither <m>antimony</m> nor any other vapors will harm you. Or put half a <m><al>pig</al>'s bladder</m> in front of your face.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p079v_3</id>


<head><m>Tin</m> for casting</head>


<ab>They use <m>common tin</m>, which is the one that <pro>pewterers</pro> use to make dishes, which is composed of 9 or <del>ten</del> ten <ms>lb</ms> of <m>fine lead</m> for one <ms>quintal</ms> of <m>tin</m>.</ab>


<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>Some find that there is nothing better than <m>fine tin</m>.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p079v_4</id>


<head>Mixture for <pro>printers</pro></head>


<ab>Apply a coat of <m>antimony</m>, and pulverize on a coat of <m>latten</m>, old <m>metal scrapings</m>, or thin plates of <m>iron</m> or the <del/> <m>iron</m> nail heads, and continue in this way until the crucible is full. Melt it inside a four à vent.  And then mix in a little <m>tin</m> and fill the rest of the container with <m>lead</m><del/>. Build up the fire and stir continuously to make sure that the substances are well-allied. The mixture for large letters is harder.</ab></div></root>