<root><page>080v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f166.image</image>


<div>
<id>p080v_a1</id>
<head><pro>Founders</pro> of small <m>tin</m> work</head>


<ab>They usually cast from <m>soft</m> <m>solder</m> the things that should not become hollow, because hollow works require fine &amp; <m>soft</m> <m>tin</m>. However, these things would not otherwise lose their coat &amp; become hollow if they are mixed or include <m>glass tin</m> <del/> in them, just like they mix a little [<m>glass tin</m>] in the <m>soft tin</m>. They carve their work on <m>stones</m> of which the sharpening stones or barber's files are made. These are found in great flakes near the mountains, &amp; resemble slate. They are found in three colors: one <m>reddish</m>, that is not as perfect as the others because it does not sustain heat <del/>; [another] one <del/> is <m>the color of dark slate</m>, and the other is <m>whitish</m>. When they work a relief, first they print it on <m>carton</m>, which is one finger thick, to serve as a pattern. After planing their <m>stones</m> &amp; rubbing them together <del/>, they use a compass &amp; little <m>iron tools</m> to carve their figures. They make their molds with three or four <m>stones</m>, to make a circle or a square with the <m>stones</m> which join perfectly because the <m>stones</m> are of equal size. Before casting, they rub the mould over with <m>tallow</m>, and it [the mould] absorbs it quickly because it is hot. Then, having [put] fine powder of <m>quicklime</m> into a cloth, they rub the mould using <m>pounce</m> in beating the <m>linen</m> on top, then blow it a little on top; this prevents bubbles [from forming]. The main thing is to make some vents. If the work is big, they do as it is shown [on the picture]. They make a hole in the medal, somewhere where it is least visible, &amp; with a bit they pierce the mold on the side of the medal. 
<figure>
<id>fig_p080v_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5VktqeFlScTAyczQ</link>
</figure>
And if they want their work to last, they pierce [it] somewhere and fit in a piece of <m>cork</m> &amp; <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m> will not damage it. </ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Make sure the pegs of your frame fit in easily so <del/> it will open with ease without moving anything else. Your <m>box molds</m> should fit well, &amp; the table should be very flat. </ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Try to carve with <m>distilled vinegar</m>.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Try calcined <m>oyster shells</m>; they are said to be excellent for molding.</ab>


</div></root>