<root><page>081r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f167.image</image>



<div>
<id>p081r_a1</id>
<head><m>Sand</m></head>


<ab>Some excellent [sand] is found for use with <m>lead</m>, <m>tin</m> and <m>copper</m> close to the hill of <pl>Pech-David</pl>, close to <pl>Toulouse</pl>. It should not be reheated much because drying out  suddenly, it will lose its binding [properties] and retract [?] at the first inflow of <m>metal</m>, which makes the work become rough and unclean. It is much better to reheat it from a distance, instead of with a <m>straw flame</m>, which generates <del/> <m>grime</m>. Instead of filling the frame, you can use finer <m>sand</m> which you will have in a very <m>thin cloth</m>, and polish the medal and then the <m>wet</m> <m>sand</m> that you will put over it<m>,</m> which has more body<m>,</m> will grip it.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<m>Tallow</m> makes things fill with bubbles</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<m>Mercury</m> stops the burning when one wants to cast. Allow the <del>metal</del> <m>lead</m> to flow, but if it is pure, it needs to be cast quite hot so it flows and vents.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p081r_a2</id>
<head><m>Earth</m> for moulding</head>


<ab><m><pro>Sheath maker</pro>'s earth</m> or the one <pro><m>potters</m></pro> use to blanche  the pots to make the <m>lead</m> flow better on it and to prevent the <m>lead</m> from soaking into them is very good to cast the hollow parts of what you want in relief. It releases better than <m>plaster</m> or <m>sulphur</m> which become hard once they have grasped on [to the mould] because <m>earth</m> sticks. It needs to be beaten vigorously so that it does not break. If the piece you want to mould is very large you can mould different parts separately. If you reheat it, it must be over a <m>closed fire</m>. One finds this <m>earth</m> at <pl>Le Fousseret</pl>, and in another place called <pl>Ox</pl>.</ab>




</div>
<div>
<id>p081r_a3</id>
<head><m>Plaster</m></head>


<ab>It needs to be well cooked, which you will recognize when cooking it in an <m>iron</m> or <m>metal</m> casket. Mix it with an <m>iron</m> rod and if it sticks to the <m>iron</m>, it is not cooked enough, and if it doesn't then it is ready. The <m>water</m> with which you soak it has to be a little warm and the mould of the above mentioned <m>earth</m> or other, also should be a little hot.  The <m>plaster</m> work does not last and the faces and delicate things break if one does not use <m>glue</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p081r_a4</id>
<head><m>Carton</m></head>


<ab>It is necessary to take <m>paper</m> from Florence, which is the finest, and crush it and and soak it several times and change the <m>water</m> every day, that way it does not smell bad. And after having moulded it into the hollow, put a <m>cloth</m> over it, and from the back side, rub the back of your <m>paper</m> with a sharp piece, as if you wanted to polish it and it will mould very neat. Then <m>glue</m> some cloth from the back side with strong <m>glue</m>. </ab>
</div></root>