<root><page>081v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f168.image</image>


<div>
<id>p081v_a1</id>
<head><m>Sand</m></head>


<ab><m>Brick</m> alone, quite finely sifted, &amp; rubbed together, is good for casting <m>lead</m> and <m>copper</m>, when diluted with <m>urine</m>. This <m>whitish brick</m> should be used.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p081v_a2</id>
<head>Make <m>copper</m> and <m>latten</m> flow</head>


<ab>At the end of the casting, as it is very hot, add some <m>salt ammicke</m> &amp; <m>saltpetre</m>, it is a way to remove <m>grime</m>. Mix some <m>clay</m> with the <m>latten</m>. The <m>metal</m> must not touch the <m>iron</m> or the <m>latten</m> of the frame, but covered with <m>sand</m> or <m>luth</m>, it makes a very homogeneous cast.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p081v_a3</id>
<head><m>Sand</m></head>


<ab>Calcined <m>black pebbles from the river</m> are good [to use] for <m>lead</m>. But they are weakened if used with <m>metal</m>.</ab>


<ab>There is only <m>ardille clay</m> with which one can make <m>tiles</m>, recooked &amp; reddened &amp; passed through a <m>long narrow bag</m> carefully soaked with <m>raw egg white</m>.</ab>


<ab><m>Willow charcoal</m> is excellent with <m>sand</m> [and] <m>lead</m>.</ab>


<ab><m>Latten</m> flows better.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p081v_a4</id>
<head>Cast of the frame</head>


<ab>It is good to make it with <m>bow wood</m>. Turn it in order to make it homogeneous, as that is important for the casting. Cover the mouth of the frame with <m>clay</m> or <m>sand</m>, so that the <m>molten</m> <m>metal</m>, <m>copper</m> or <m>lead</m>, do not touch at all the <m>iron</m> or <m>latten</m> of the frame, because it would turn it sour, &amp; make it filled with bubbles. Always cast higher than the mold. Pay attention that the cast is not too wide or too deep because the narrowest is the best one. Because when it is large, the weight of the matter which runs breaks &amp; spreads the mold &amp; fills the matter with bubbles. When you have casted, gently hit your frame, so that the matter spreads better. <m>Black lead [de saulmon]</m> of the first melting, works very neatly.</ab>


</div></root>