<root><page>082r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f169.image</image>


<div>
<id>p082r_a1</id>
<head> Heat of <m>copper</m></head>


<ab>It is hot enough when you see it neat &amp; even on top, without <m>filth</m>.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p082r_a2</id>
<head>Box mold</head>


<ab><m>Iron</m> &amp; <m>copper</m> make it porous if the <m>metal</m> touches it, &amp; the <m>wood</m> warps. Thus, make a mold of <m>wood</m>, &amp; have box molds of <m>bricks</m> made inside this mold of whatever thickness that you want.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p082r_a3</id>
<head><m>Glair of eggs</m></head>


<ab><m>Glair of eggs</m> gives strength to sand to make several casts.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p082r_a4</id>
<head><pro>Watchmakers</pro></head>


<ab>To distribute the teeth proportionately on their wheels, they do not use a compass because there is no compass so fine that it can draw distances as small as those of the small wheels. But they make a platform (as they call it) out of <m>latten</m> <sup>that has been</sup> divided into various circles, &amp; each <sup>of those</sup> circle<sup>s</sup> is divided into equal sections marked by a point. And each circle has a certain number <sup>of points</sup>, as <sup>for example</sup> one <sup>has</sup> 30, another 36, others 40 &amp;. Then, on the pierced center of the platform, they place the little wheel. And on the center of the wheel <sup>there is</sup> a flat line or an alidade which points to the number on the circle that you want to mark on your wheel. Then with a point, they draw a line on the wheel. Then they return the alidade to the following point, &amp; they thus go on marking it <sup>the dial</sup>. And to mark the points on the circles of their platform, they divide the circle in three &amp; then divide this third part into as many sections as is necessary with regard to the total division of the circle. &amp;, in this manner, they make the teeth's division &amp; distribution as fine as they please.</ab>


<figure>
<id>fig_p082r_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5MG1jZS1LOUE2QWs</link>
</figure>


</div></root>