<root><page>083r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f171.item</image>


<div>
<id>p083r_a1</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> @ for <m>lead</m></head>


<ab>Recipe: Grey <m>soot</m> from the furnace of the <pro>silversmiths</pro>, <m>quick lime</m>, and <lat>ana</lat> <m>flour</m>, moistened according to the art, being the finest possible.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
The grey <m>soot</m> of <pro>locksmiths</pro>, which is held in the forge, is very fine once ground, molds very neatly, &amp; releases very well.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p083r_a2</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> for <m>copper</m> medals</head>


<ab>Recipe: Hat <m>felt</m> burnt over a covered fire, <m>dross of iron</m>, &amp; burnt <m>bone</m>, all of which ground very finely &amp; crushed &amp; watered with <m>saltwater</m>; &amp; make a paste of it &amp; mold it, &amp; wipe it over a <m>straw</m> fire. @These three sands, pulverized and very finely ground on <m>porphyry</m>, mold well, and I think that separately each of them is very good. Burnt hat <m>felt</m> molds very neatly and releases very neatly.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<m>Plaster</m> molds very neatly but it becomes porous. <m>Bone</m> has scarcely any body unless it has <m>iron dross</m>. <m>Felt</m> makes it release. </ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p083r_a3</id>
<head>Another <m>sand</m></head>


<ab> <m>Charcoal</m> of <m>vine shoots</m> &amp; <m>clay earth</m>, <del>bien recuitte &amp;</del> well sieved, as much of one as the other, &amp; joine them together with well-beaten eggs’ <m>glair</m>,  then calcine in the furnace, &amp; to use it, moisten it with <m>vinegar</m>.</ab>
 </div>

<div>
<id>p083r_a4</id>
<head>Another for <m>lead</m></head>


<ab>Recipe: Finely crushed <m>slate</m>, &amp; <del>calcinée</del> <m>pumice stone</m> mixed together. Calcine them in a well covered pot, &amp; thrice stoppered over a good fire, &amp; each time moisten them with <m>vernis</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p083r_a5</id>
<head>Another</head>


<ab>Recipe: <del>p</del> A <m>tile</m> little baked, ground &amp; moistened in <m>white wine</m> with burnt black <m><fr>trasse</fr> paper</m>. And if you add burnt horse <m>dung</m>, it will be all the better. Moisten with egg <m>glair</m>.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<fr>Trasse</fr> paper burnt over a closed fire is reduced just as <m>charcoal</m> &amp; very soft black, molds neatly &amp; makes it release well mixed with the others.</ab>




</div>

<div>
<id>p083r_a6</id>
<head>Excellent <m>sand</m></head>


<ab><m>Alabaster</m>, calcined  in a crucible over charcoal fire so that when touching it, it turns into powder. Once cold, pulverise it finely, pass it through a double sieve, &amp; and render it as if impalpable. And <del>d</del> with one <ms>lb</ms> of <m>alabaster</m>, one needs one ms><figure>℥</figure></ms> of <m>sal ammoniac</m>. Mix well &amp; incorporate everything together, then put them in a cellar or a damp place. And with this paste, mold what you will need, &amp; next dry the mold in the fire, &amp; cast whatever you wish, while the <m>sand</m> is hot.  And you will cast as neaty as the main one, &amp; the <m>sand</m> can still be used by placing it in a damp place &amp; drying it in the fire.</ab>
</div></root>