<root><page>083r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f171.item</image>


<div>
<id>p083r_a1</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> for <m>lead</m></head>


<ab>Recipe: <sup>Take</sup> grey <m>soot</m> from the <pro>silversmiths</pro>' furnace, <m>quick lime</m>, and <m>flour</m>. Moisten according to [the rules of] the art, in the finest possible way you can.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
The <pro>locksmiths</pro>' grey <m>soot</m> which is held in their forge is quite fine when ground. It molds and is removed very neatly.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p083r_a2</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> for <m>copper</m> medals</head>


<ab>Recipe: <sup>Take</sup> hat <m>felt</m> burnt on a covered fire, <m>iron dross</m>, and burnt <m>bone</m>, all of which you should grind very finely, crush and spray with <m>water</m> and <m>salt</m>. Make a paste of it, mold it, and wipe it with <m>hay</m> fire. These three pulverized <m>sands</m>, having been very well refined on the <m>porphyry</m> slab, mold very well and cast well. Know that separately each of them is quite good. Burnt <m>felt</m> molds well and is removed quite neatly.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<m>Plaster</m> molds quite neatly but it swells. <m>Bone</m> does not have much body while <m>iron dross</m> does. <m>Felt</m> allows for an easy removal of the cast.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p083r_a3</id>
<head>Other <m>sand</m></head>


<ab><sup>Take</sup> <m>charcoal</m> made from <m>vine shoots</m> and <m>clay earth</m>, both well searced, and mix them with well-beaten <m>egg white</m>. Next calcinate it <sup>the resulting paste</sup> in the oven and to use it, dillute it in <m>vinegar</m>.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p083r_a4</id>
<head>Other <sup><m>sand</m></sup> for <sup>use with</sup> <m>lead</m></head>


<ab>Recipe: <sup>Take</sup> finely crushed <m>slate</m> and <m>pumice stone</m> mixed together. Calcinate them three times in a covered and sealed pot in strong fire, and each time dilute them with <m>urine</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p083r_a5</id>
<head>Other <sup><m>sand</m></sup></head>


<ab>Recipe: <sup>Take</sup> a <m>tile</m> that has not been cooked too much, grind it and diluted it in <m>white wine</m> with burnt black <fr>trasse</fr> <m>paper</m>. If you add burnt horse <m>manure</m> to it, it will be all the better. Moisten with <m>egg white</m>.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Trasse paper burnt under a light fire becomes akin to <m>soft black charcoal</m>. It molds nealty and is removed easily when mixed with the others <sup>ingredients or sands?</sup>.</ab>




</div>

<div>
<id>p083r_a6</id>
<head>Excellent <m>sand</m></head>


<ab>Burn <m>alabaster</m> in a crusol under charcoal fire until it turns into powder. Once <sup>it is</sup> cold, finely pulverise it through a sieve to make it impalpable. With a pound of <m>alabaster</m>, one should use an ounce of <m>sal ammoniac</m>. Mix well and incorporate everything together. Next, put it in a cave or a wet location. And with this paste, mold whatever you need and then dry the mold under a fire. While the <m>sand</m> is hot, you cast whatever metal you may like and your cast will be as neat as the principal. And the <m>sand</m> <sup>will</sup> always work if it is kept in a wet location and dried by the fire.</ab>
</div></root>