<root><page>083v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f172.item</image>
 
<div>
<id>p083v_a1</id>
<head>A way for molding excellently with water</head>


<ab>
Dissolve in damp place some <m>tallow of glass</m>, and then  place this water on what you want to mold, having encircled it, and place it to coagulate on the hot ashes. Do the same with <m>vitriol</m> &amp; <m>copperas</m>, which, once well calcinated, reduce in water.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p083v_a2</id>
<head>
Molding in relief on one part and hollow on the other.</head>


<ab>
It is necessary to cast two pieces of <m>copper</m>, <m>latten</m> or similar <m>metal</m>, very neatly, and then when you have molded the cavity in the sand, leave the figure of metal that <corr>you</corr> have molded in the frame, without moving it from its place. And cast, &amp; if there is not enough thickness press a little &amp; push the figure down in the frame.</ab>


<ab>
It is good to mold always the faces not on the side of the cast, but with the head on the bottom, because the force of the substance is at the entry of the medal, &amp; there, where the force is, the filth &amp; grime accumulate. And, in this way, if you were mold the face towards the cast, some grime could be found there, &amp; it is better that is found on the clothing, which is easier to repair.</ab>
 
<ab>
<m>Vinegar</m> is better for moistening than <m>wine</m>. It is necessary that the frame be well smooth and even, otherwise <del>and that the cast be</del>, as you press on one side, the other one lifts.</ab>


<ab>
This is why the press is better, for it tightens evenly, &amp; more than your hands, and makes
the lumpy <m>sand</m>, which is damp, communicate its humidity to the soft and fine sand, which is sprinkled &amp; <fr>poncé</fr> dry on the medal.</ab>


<ab>
When you mold, always leave your medal <add>the</add> frames, <del>is</del> <add>without stirring it</add> because, if your cavity is not molded very neatly, you can put it back in the right place by means of pegs, which will prevent it from shifting. But, at first, <fr>ponce</fr> yout medal with very fine willow charcoal, &amp; <del>se</del> next clean it, for this degreases it, &amp; makes it easier to release.</ab>


<ab>Do not knock it when molding because this will shake loose the frame &amp; the sand.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p083v_a3</id>
<margin>left-middle</margin><head>Bellows</head>


<ab>To cast with a bellows furnace, &amp; cast the hottest you can. Do not place your bellows at the bottom around the base of the furnace, lest some coal should enter them. Place the bellows under the grate. It is wise to place your furnace in a place where there is wind so that the heat will grow better. It is necessary to stop carefully the doors of the furnace, &amp; that way only the bellows have an opening. At the end of the cast, you will blow slowly, as you did at the beginning.</ab>


</div></root>