<root><page>084v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f174.image</image>


<div>
<id>p084v_a1</id>
<head><m>Sand</m></head>


<ab>I tried the <m>hoof of an ox</m>, quite burned, pulverized and very well crushed on <m>porphyry</m>, until it is fine enough to slip through your fingers without being felt. On its own, it makes a very clean mold. But because on its own it is very dry and lean, it demands to be well wet and humidified, with a thick broth with <m>elm root</m>.</ab>


<ab><m>Dross of Iron</m>, very burned <m>ox hoof</m>, and <m>felt</m>, all burn well in a closed fire. All three ground very finely on <m>porphyry</m> mold very neatly in <m>lead</m>, without any need to reheat it much, and by casting in a box mold either hot or cold.</ab>


<ab><m>Felt</m> on its own provides a very clean mold if wet, and comes off easily. And also makes the other two come off easily</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
These <m>sands</m> can only undergo one cast.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
A fat <m>sand</m> which sticks together neatly, makes bubbles.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<ab>A fat <m>metal</m> needs lean <m>sand</m>.</ab>
</ab>
  
</div>
<div>
<id>p084v_a2</id>
<head><m>Eau Magistra</m></head>


<ab>Some people think that <m>salt water</m> is not good, because the <m>salt</m> releases gas when heated and as a result causes bubbles. [In this case], there is only <m>wine</m> boiled with <m>elm root</m>.</ab>
 
<ab><m>Sanding charcoal</m> makes [things] come off well. But one finds that <m>willow charcoal</m> creates bubbles, but <m>oak</m> or <m>beech charcoal</m> does the job without making bubbles.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Try burnt <m>oysters</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p084v_a3</id>
<head><m>Lead</m></head>


<ab>For casting, there is only <m>soft lead</m> that can be cast at a high temperature. And <m>soft tin</m>.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p084v_a4</id>
<head> <m>Sand</m>, for the most excellent <m>lead</m> of all, for large and small reliefs</head>


<ab> I took <m>white lead</m> and crushed it dry on <m>porphyry</m>, to make it very fine. Then I moistened it a lot with very well beaten <m>egg white</m>, so that it became like a paste, by making it stick together perfectly with the flat of a knife. I let it rest for a while. </ab>


<ab>
<figure><margin>left-bottom</margin>
X
</figure>
</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Mix it well with the knife.</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>