<root><page>085r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f175.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p084v_a4</id>


<ab>to rest on a very clean &amp; smooth table, &amp; since it is desiccative, I knew it would dry out <del>lor</del>, what I let it do in order to reduce it to powder, &amp; molding it with <m>sand</m>, once broken up with my fingers &amp; the sharp edge of a knife.  I <m>oil</m>ed my medal because <m>oil</m> cleans it without spoiling it. <del>And</del> And having dried it &amp; cleaned it with  a linen, &amp; small bristle brushes of <m>pork</m>, I once again lightly <m>oil</m>ed it with clear <m>walnut oil</m>, &amp; gently swiped it with a <m>cloth</m> so that <x>the medal</x> would not be too <m>oil</m>ed; having already considered that in this way <x>the medal</x> should come out easily, because the <m>white lead,</m> wet with <m>glair</m>, which would not damage the <m>oil</m>. This worked very well.  I molded a medal very cleanly in high relief, without it having any lumps, which a lot of good <m>sands</m> such as <m>felt</m>, burnt <m>bone</m>, &amp; <m>iron dross</m> failed to do on the first attempt. I re-cooked it &amp; my mold became hard like marble. And then I knew that <m>sands</m> used to mold big relief must be very moist with some kind of <m>water</m>, which gives body &amp; firmness, like <m>egg white</m>, <m>gummed water</m>, <x>or</x> one <x><m>water</m></x> boiled with <m>elm root</m>. And lightly <m>oil</m> your medal. It can take as many firings as you want because it is as hard as glass.  But soft <m>lead</m> &amp; sour <m>tin</m> must be cast at a very hot temperature.</ab>


<ab>Since that moment, I have realized that even though this <m>sand</m> is excellent &amp; can be cast often &amp; molds very neatly, it is fat and it makes bubbles. In this way, the <m>soft lead</m> does not suit the mold well.  But I have tried to mix it with lean <m>sand</m>, such as <m>pumice</m>, <m>metal scrapings</m>, &amp; similar things, in order to give it body, &amp; to help it come off easily, because lean <m>sand</m> <x>alone</x> does not come off easily; and yet it takes <m>metal</m> well.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Try to mix <m>white lead</m> or <m>minium</m> with other sands.</ab>


<figure><margin>left-top</margin>X</figure>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Oil &amp; smear with <m>aspic oil</m>, which will disappear when reheated, because the <m>oil</m> causes bubbling.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is necessary to mold with <m>egg white</m>, and then mix it well. And once it is in the box mold, beat it well on the top with a pestle, or something else clean. This helps to make molding better and come out more easily.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is best to fill the box mold in one go, because the mixture made of several <m>sands</m>, and the one from mines, that you use to fill the box mold, damages it.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p085r_a1</id>
<head><m>Green varnish</m> for medals of <m>copper</m></head>


<ab>Having casted them very neatly, cover them with <m><fr>sel de verre</fr></m> that we use for sand, &amp; moisten it,  &amp; in three or 4 <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms> it will be green. Oil them after &amp; keep them under the <m>dung</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p085r_a2</id>
<head><m>Glue</m></head>


<ab>The <pl>Flemish</pl> reglue their <tl><m>earthen</m> pots</tl> with gold color, that is to say <m>minium</m>, <m>massicot</m>, &amp; <m>varnish</m>. </ab>
</div></root>