<root><page>085v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f176.image</image>


<div>
<id>p085v_a1</id>
<head><pro>Casters</pro></head>
 
<ab>They mix beaten <m>egg white</m> with <m>earth</m> of which they make the first layer of the crown <sup>of a bell</sup> in pieces. <sup>They also make</sup> bells and all other said pieces which the said <m><sup>egg</sup> white</m>. This makes <sup>it</sup> come clean and sets and stabilizes the material. For the core of a small piece, <m>egg white</m> is also good.</ab>
 
<ab><m>Rosette</m> in order to make it come clean, wants the mold to be a little hot and <m>lead</m> which is mixed with the <m>red copper</m> <sup>is</sup> therefore chiefly for small pieces.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p085v_a2</id>
<head>Mortars</head>
 
<ab>They should be of the finest material possible. <sup>In the same way</sup>, it is better to use <m>copper</m> for a cauldron than <m>red copper</m>, because it better resists a blow.</ab>
 
<ab>The mortars, therefore, used for grinding are stronger and there is less danger of breaking them if they are of fine <m>copper</m>. And for a private home, they do not ring so much and do not make as much noise as those of <m>metal</m>. It is true that those that are of <m>metal</m> ring louder for <pro>apothecaries</pro>.</ab>
 
<ab>Grenades must be made from fine <m>metal</m></ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p085v_a3</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> from a mine</head>
 
<ab>It wants to be well recooked for big <m>metal</m> <sup>objects</sup>. Some people burn it inside a furnace until it becomes quite black and they grind it on the <m>porphyry</m>. Other people burn it with <m>asphalt</m>, but when it is too burned, it does not mold so cleanly, because it lacks body, and is too thin. You can give body to the <m>sand</m> with <m>tripoli</m> or burned <m>felt</m>.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p085v_a4</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> Experiments</head>
 
<ab>X I have tested <m>sand</m> of <pl>Th{oulous}e</pl>, and after seeing it well recooked two times in a skillet, I passed it through a fine <m>tammy cloth</m>, like the double <sup>sieve</sup> which <pro>apothecaries</pro> use, without grinding it further on the <m>porphyry</m>, as I have done other times. I moistened it <sup>the sand</sup> in  infusion with <m>elm root,</m> and in it, I molded a big piece of a portrait of Jesus. I found it unmolded very well without having to tire myself out by hitting it from behind and it molded cleanly on one side of the relief and on the other concave. And [it was] of the thickness of a coin of forty sols. I cast <sup>this</sup> very hot</ab>
 
<figure>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>X</figure>


<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>
<m>Sand</m> from a mine, well chosen and well reheated, is the most excellent of all without trying to find all other mixtures because it receives all <m>metal.</m> It does not like to be used hot because it bubbles the more finely. For large works, it is not the best because it does not have enough body to sustain <sup>it</sup>,</ab>


<cont/>
</div></root>