<root><page>087r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f179.image</image>
 
<div>
<cont/>
<id>p086v_a1</id>
<ab>In order to mold well, it is necessary to cast several medals together in a large box mold, because when there is a lot of material and the crucible is almost full, it becomes hotter. Then, if you do not succeed with one of the medals, another will be good.</ab>


<ab>It is better to melt with a bellows furnace than with a wind furnace, because it heats more vigorously. It is true that <m>latten</m> melts better in the wind furnace, because it is more brittle than <m>copper</m>.</ab>
 
<ab>Some <pro>founder</pro>s superstitiously believe that there are only three days in a week that are good for melting, that is, Tuesdays, <del>Wednesdays</del> Thursdays, and Saturdays. For them, the others are unlucky.</ab>


<ab>When you mold, do not excessively pound on the medal that is in <m>sand</m>, because that prevents it from being cleanly stripped, and cracks the mold.</ab>


<ab>See to it that <m>sand</m> does not go over the edges of the box mold, because if the molded medal is higher than the cast, <m>metal</m> will not easily enter the form. Therefore, always take care that the surface of your cast surpasses the mold in a straight line. To accomplish this, if you wish, put a piece of <m>cardboard</m> of whatever thickness you please on top of the mold.</ab>


<ab>To prevent their large casting works from becoming too porous, <pro>founder</pro>s are careful to heat their molds very well. And to know if the molds are heated enough, they tap them with their finger, and if they start ringing like a pot, they are heated enough.</ab>
 
<ab>In order to cast their canons cleanly, they mix with their <m><pro>founder</pro>'s earth</m> some fine casting <m>sand</m>, if they can get any.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p087r_a1</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> of <pl>Toulouse</pl></head>


<ab><del/>The <sup><m>sand</m></sup> generally considered good is the one found in a vineyard near Pech-David. But the best is the one is from the <pl>Touch</pl>, a river close to <pl>Saint-Michel</pl> and <pl>Blagnac</pl>, in a vineyard at a high altitude. This <sup><m>sand</m></sup> is thinner, and a bit greasier than the other, and better for small works. It should not be overheated.</ab>
</div></root>