<root><page>087v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f180.image</image>


<div>
<id>p087v_a1</id>
<head><m>Sand</m>, <m>slate</m>, and burned <m>earth</m></head>


<ab>Very burnt <m>sand</m> looses its bond. <m>Slate</m> is reheated &amp; molds neatly.  Next,  it is true that often it becomes porous, like burned <m>earth</m> also does,  like fat <m>sand</m> also does. .</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
I find that one ought not to knowck on very finely ground <m>sands</m>, for it shakes them loose, &amp; <del>make</del><sup> prevents them from releasing neatly. But one ought to press hard and moisten them sufficiently.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p087v_a2</id>
<head><m>Magistry</m></head>


<ab><pro>Founders</pro> take the <m>roots of a young elm</m> when it has sap, &amp; boil it in <m>wine</m>, or better yet <m>vinegar</m>, and keep it all year long in a cask.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p087v_a3</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> from the mine of <pl>Thoulouse</pl></head>


<ab> Casting sand coming from the mine, once passed through a double sieve, next put in with melted <m>resin</m>, burns &amp;inflammes &amp; becomes all red &amp; inflamed like iron. Once cold it is completely black and can be ground very finely on <m>porphyry</m>. Thus having prepared it &amp; render it without asperity on the fingernail, I moistened it with beaten egg glair &amp; beat it well, until it was not pasty but rather powdery.I found it of very good release, &amp; molded with it in <m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m> very neatly, but it wants to be well reheated &amp; at ease.</ab>


<ab>Others beat it well in a mortar, in small amounts at a time, &amp; thus it detaches andrenders very finely. Then they reheat it moderately, only to dry it. Then they grind it dry on <m>porphyry</m>. And thus it becomes as if impalpable, and not too dried out,  <del>it</del> and it retains body &amp; bond of the <m>earth</m> of which it is related, and is better than when it is very burnt. Once moistened with <m>egg glair</m> wiped with a <m>sponge</m>, it releases <del>very neatly M</del> very neatly in low relief, but not for figures in high relief. Therefore, since then I experimented <del>lexper</del> with moistening it only with very strong <m>vinegar</m>. It released a figure which I could not release previously. And I believe that, moistening the finest in the same way like with glair  &amp;  the lumpiest, to fill the <fr>chasses</fr with salt water or wine, that they do not ally so well. Since they are of the same nature &amp; are moistened the same, they embrace each other, &amp; hold together one with the other.</ab>


<ab>
To mold well, after having prepared your <m>sands</m>, mold in a day. Reheat Bake slowly the next day, then cast the other.
</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is necessary to choose <sup>sand</sup> that <del>like</del> comes in clods &amp; lumps, and deep down in the earth, because commonly the one near the surface is too much akin to earth, whereas the deep one is similar to rock.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
I have sometimes molded with <m>pure lead</m> cast very <del>clean</del> hot, &amp; the example as well as the principal were very clean, but since the <m>vinegar</m> gives it little binding, &amp; it held only for one cast.</ab>


</div></root>