<root><page>087v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f180.image</image>


<div>
<id>p087v_a1</id>
<head><m>Sand</m>, <m>slate</m>, and burned <m>earth</m></head>


<ab><m>Sand</m>, when overheated, does not hold as well. <m>Slate</m> is baked &amp; will mold clean, yet it is true that often it becomes porous, just like burned <m>earth</m> also does, as well as any kind of greasy <m>sand</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
I find that one must not hammer at all on <m>sand</m> <sup>already</sup> very finely pulverised, because it would damage it, &amp; then <del>make</del><sup>the sand</sup> would not be able to release the cast cleanly. Still, it needs to be pressed hard, and moisten it sufficiently.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p087v_a2</id>
<head><m>Magistry</m></head>


<ab><pro>Founders</pro> harvest the <m>roots of a young elm</m> when it is sappy, &amp; boil it in <m>wine</m>, or better yet <m>vinegar</m>. They prepare a year's worth of it and store it in a cask.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p087v_a3</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> from sand pit from <pl>Toulouse</pl></head>


<ab><sup>In order to use</sup> <m>sand</m> from a sandpit for casting, filter it through a double sieve, then having mixed it with molten <m>resin</m> it burns &amp; heats, &amp; becomes all red &amp; hot as iron. Once it has cooled down it is completely black and can be pulverised on <m>porphyry</m> very well. Having prepared it like this &amp; checked the smoothness of the surface with my nail, I moistened it with <m>egg white</m> &amp; beat it vigorously, until it was not a paste anymore but a powder. I found <sup>this sand</sup> to release the cast very well, &amp; molded very clean in <m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m> <sup>with it</sup>, however it needs to be reheated &amp; at leisure.</ab>


<ab>Others beat it strongly in a mortar, in small amounts at a time, &amp; thus it detaches and comes out very fine; then they bake it moderately, just enough to dry it, and then they crush it dry on <m>porphyry</m>. Thus it is made almost impalpable, and yet not too dry <del/>, and it retains the consistency &amp; the binding quality of the <m>earth</m> to which it is related, and is better than when it is burnt. When you moisten it with <m>egg white</m> and pass it through a <m>sponge</m> it releases <del/> very clean for a low relief, but not a figure in high relief. Considering this, since then I experimented <del/> with moistening it only with strong <m>vinegar</m>. <sup>That way</sup> it releases a figure I previously had not been able to release <sup>from the mold</sup>. I think that even when you wet the finest sort with <m>egg white</m>, or in a similar fashion, or the thick sort to fill  chasses with <m>water</m>, <m>salt</m>, or <m>vinegar</m>, they do not mix so well. However, given that they are of one and the same nature, &amp; are similarly moistened, they espouse each other, &amp; hold together.</ab>


<ab>
To mold well, when your <m>sands</m> are prepared, mold in one day. Bake slowly the next day, then cast the other.
</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is necessary to choose <sup>sand</sup> that <del>like</del> comes in clods &amp; lumps, and deep down in the earth, because commonly the one near the surface is too much akin to earth, whereas the deep one is similar to rock.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
I have sometimes molded with <m>pure lead</m> cast very <del>clean</del> hot, &amp; the example as well as the principal were very clean, but since the <m>vinegar</m> gives it little binding, &amp; it held only for one cast.</ab>


</div></root>