<root><page>088v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f182.image</image>


<div>
<id>p088v_a1</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> from pulverised <m>rock salt</m> and <m>sand</m> from a <m>minium</m> finely ground on <m>marble</m> </head>


<ab>After they have been dryly ground &amp; beaten in the mortar, they are ground finely on the <m>marble</m>. I mixed the same quantity of each material, and in order to mix them better, I ground them on the <m>porphyry</m> again, &amp; then filtered this through a double sieve or the sleeve of a <m>shirt</m>. Then, I put them on sheets of <m>paper</m> &amp; stored it on <m>marble</m> in a cellar. In one night, they were both moist enough <x>that there there was no need</x> to dampen them further because <m>rock salt</m>, like all other salts, dissolves in dampness. I molded with this very neatly because both should be quite fine. They need to be moist enough so it can be removed easily.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p088v_a2</id>
<head><m>Mineral sand</m></head>


<ab>It does not matter if the <sup>sand</sup> color is white or yellow. Above all it <sup>the sand</sup> must be lumped <sup>together</sup> &amp; much like a precious stone or a stone, &amp; the deeper <sup>in the earth</sup> one gets it from, the better. The signs of its quality is that it is thus gathered together, that, if the <m>stone</m> is removed as it should be <sup>i.e. in the correct way</sup>, it forms pieces &amp; <del/> lumps <sup>together</sup>, which demonstrates its <sup>capacity for</sup> binding, &amp; that it <sup>the sand</sup> is not too dry.</ab>


<ab>However, it should crumble in your hands. &amp; the grain must be <del/> quite small  &amp; fine, &amp; homogeneous. If this <sup>sand</sup> is not fine enough, you can filter it &amp; grind it up finely either with <m>water</m>, or through a sieve, <del>&amp; when it</del> or on the <m>porphyry</m>. &amp; That way it loses its dryness and becomes greasy &amp; well bound. You can mold it in <del/> a box mold or in a noyau without wadding, &amp; try it with <m>lead</m> because, if it does not swell &amp; casts neatly, it will bear out well too. Some say that fatty <m>sands</m> do not work for casting <m>metal</m> that is too hot. <pro>Artisans</pro> who undertake a big job &amp; who want to save money do not need to crush <sup>sand</sup> &amp; seek the curious <sup>properties</sup> of <m>artificial sand</m>; they have more to profit from finding natural sand that has the finest grain possible. &amp; for a small job, they take advantage of finding the finest natural sand they can. For a smaller job, they only filter the sand through the sieve. But those who work on a very small scale crush the <m>sand</m> &amp; grind it finely <sup>until it becomes</sup> impalpable, because they do not need as much <sup>sand</sup>.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Ground <m>wheat</m> makes a tawny-colored powder <sup>that is</sup> quite fine &amp; quite soft. Once this powder has been mixed, it can <del>mix</del> mold very neatly. Try <m>wheat flour</m> burned in an enclosed fire.</ab>


</div></root>