<root><page>090r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f185.image</image>

<div>
<id>p090r_a1</id>
<head><m>Sal ammoniac</m> and <m>iron dross</m></head>


<ab>I pulverized <m>sal ammoniac</m>, <sup>previously</sup> well dried in a <m>hot bronze</m> mortar over <m>heat</m>. Then I filtered the <m>salt</m> through a double sieve; it became very fine. But to make it finer, I dry ground it  on the <m>porphyry</m>, then I mixed it with <m>iron dross</m> which was pulverized and ground the same way. Both ingredients take a very clean cast of bas-reliefs, without being moistened with serain, or into the hollow mould, or anywhere else with the serviette, and the cast can be cleanly removed. </ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p090r_a2</id>
<head><m>Sand</m></head>


<ab><pro>Molders</pro> from <pl>Foix</pl> who cast their medals sideways use <m>crocum ferri</m> and <m>calcinated</m> <m>slate</m>. It is used for very flat things.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p090r_a3</id>
<head>Every kind of sand can be made useful</head>


<ab><pro>Artisans</pro> who do big works, and who need to search for things made by nature to pursue their work, because nature does not want to sell its wares to its children, and in order to save the time they would spend grinding, pulverizing and artificially preparing their sand, look for sand from sandpits, which is not too fat from the <m>soil</m>, nor too arid and, consequently, without any binder effect. From deep in the sandpit, one can find some lumps and gravel that show the sand's natural compaction; it is quite hard to break, with very small and fine grains, quite smooth between the fingers. And since it is found solely close to mountainous regions or arid lands, you cannot find any near every good town, where <pro>artisans</pro> live. Thus, if they can't find any close to their home, they prefer to order some of this sand from afar, like Lyon, Venice or Paris, near the Sainte Chapelle, and similar areas, instead of preparing it themselves. Nonetheless, you can be assured that in all locations, you can make sand from the sandpit</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>