<root><page>090v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f186.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p090r_a3</id>
<ab>good &amp; proper for molding. For if it is big, pass it through a <tl>sieve</tl>, and if it is not yet fine enough, wash it, &amp; when the <m>water</m> will be a little rested, empty the one which is still troubled in some separate <tl>vessel</tl>. The big ones will fall down quickly to the bottom of the first <tl>vessel</tl>, but the one which will have come from the troubled <m>water</m>, placed separately, having taken residence, will be very fine. And then, if it does not have enough bond, grind it well dry on <tl><m>porphyry</m></tl>, &amp; you will render it impalpable, &amp; which will have bond just like <m>chalk</m>. Then, if it seems to need it, you will reheat it, &amp; will crush it again &amp; mix it with <m>salts</m>, or <m>linen, <add>or</add> burned felt</m> or <m>ashes of paper</m> &amp; similarly washed things.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p090v_a1</id>
<head><m><fr>Terre fondue</fr> of <pro>potters</pro></m></head>


<ab>Grind it in a <del><tl>mortar</tl></del> <add><tl>mustard mill</tl></add> with some <m>water</m>, &amp;  and render it impalpable, dry it &amp; next moisten it with <m>salt water</m>, which gives strength to <del><fr>u</fr></del> all sands to withstands several casts.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p090v_a2</id>
<head>Orange trees</head>


<ab>In Italy, <sup>particularly</sup> in the coldest areas like Lombardia, people plant the orange trees inside squared <m>wood</m> planters. The planters are larger at the bottom than at the top. People make handles on each side, where they attach straps in order to carry the planter, like one carries the gout sufferers, because if one used wheels to roll them one would damage the garden's paths. Every two year they remember to open the sides of the planters and meticulously cut &amp; trim the ends of the orange tree's roots, which are dry. Otherwise, the roots find the <m>wood</m> <x>of the planter</x>, tighten on it &amp; they double over themselves &amp; the ends dry &amp; the tree dies. Once trimmed, the roots gain new space <del/> to expand, without encountering resistance from the <m>wood</m> <sup>of the planter</sup>. That is why it is better to join the sides of the planter with screws &amp; not with nails, to avoid shaking the <m>soil</m> when one opens them.</ab>
</div></root>