<root><page>090v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f186.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p090r_a3</id>
<ab>and will be good &amp; will mold cleanly. Because the <m>sand</m> is coarse and dry, filter it through a sieve. If it is not fine enough, wash it. &amp; when the <m>water</m> has settled a little, pour the <m>soiled</m> <m>water</m> into another pot. The <m>coarse grains</m> will quickly fall to the bottom of the first pot. But the <m>sand</m> from the <m>troubled water</m> pot, having settled, will be much finer. If this <m>sand</m> does not bind enough, dry crush it on the <m>porphyry</m>, &amp; thus making it impalpable, &amp; it will bind as chalk does.  If you wish you can reheat it, &amp; straight after crush it &amp; blend it with <m>salts,</m> or <m>burned cloth,</m> or <m>felt</m>, or <m>paper ashes</m>, &amp; similar material.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p090v_a1</id>
<head><m><pro>Potter</pro>s' clay</m></head>


<ab>Grind it in a <del>mortar</del> mustard mill with <m>water</m>, <sup>&amp;</sup> it will become as impalpable as possible. Dry it, &amp; then moisten it with <m>salt water</m>, which give force to <del/> all sands in order to allow several castings.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p090v_a2</id>
<head>Orange trees</head>


<ab>In Italy, <sup>particularly</sup> in the coldest areas like Lombardia, people plant the orange trees inside squared <m>wood</m> planters. The planters are larger at the bottom than at the top. People make handles on each side, where they attach straps in order to carry the planter, like one carries the gout sufferers, because if one used wheels to roll them one would damage the garden's paths. Every two year they remember to open the sides of the planters and meticulously cut &amp; trim the ends of the orange tree's roots, which are dry. Otherwise, the roots find the <m>wood</m> <x>of the planter</x>, tighten on it &amp; they double over themselves &amp; the ends dry &amp; the tree dies. Once trimmed, the roots gain new space <del/> to expand, without encountering resistance from the <m>wood</m> <sup>of the planter</sup>. That is why it is better to join the sides of the planter with screws &amp; not with nails, to avoid shaking the <m>soil</m> when one opens them.</ab>
</div></root>