<root><page>091r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f187.image</image>


<div>
<id>p091r_1</id>
<head>Grafting</head>


<ab>Any tree that has a large pith will be hard to <del>be</del> graft from, because the cutting is difficult to remove.  If the pith is damaged, the graft will take in an unstraight manner, like with vines of all peach and apricot trees.</ab>
 
<ab>Apricot trees have a very thin <m>bark</m>, and so it is necessary to graft them onto young trees whose own <m>bark</m> is not thick yet, such as the young shoots of prune trees or apricot trees.</ab>
 
<ab>The graft will not take if the cutting gets wet.  It is necessary therefore to graft in serein and mild weather, not too cold and not too windy.</ab>
 
<ab>One must use <m>old wood</m> to graft, if one wants to graft on a tree that is already mature and quite big; because if this is the case, it will compress the cutting, and if the cutting is of <m>young wood</m>, it will not grow properly. But <m>old wood</m> resists the compression of <m>old wood</m> better <del>than the young</del>, because it is harder than <m>young wood</m>. But if the graft is done with only <m>old wood</m>, it will never grow beautifully, but will be frail and short and will take a long time to grow.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p091r_2</id>
<head>Molding with <tl><m><al>cuttlefish</al> bone</m></tl></head>


<ab>Guard against keeping them <env>in a damp place</env>, for they are well prone to getting moist. If your medal is small, cut the <m>bone</m> in two then even it out with a <tl>knife</tl>. And on a <tl>hooked <m>rooftile</m></tl>, well dry &amp;well smooth &amp; covered with <m>pulverized <pa>willow</pa> charcoal</m>, rub &amp; smooth the two half <tl><m>bones</m></tl>. Thus they absorb this <m><pa>willow</pa> charcoal</m>, which makes them release them, guard against removing anything. Then on a <tl>counter bone</tl>, that is to say a lump of <m>brick</m>, smoothed to the size of your <tl><m>bone</m></tl>, place your medal,  &amp; then on this one, place the <tl><m>bone</m></tl>,  &amp; press well with some other piece of the same size above. And for the second time, mold it, but before, <fr>ponce</fr> on top with  <m><pa>willow</pa> charcoal</m> &amp; blow gently, then press as before, and it will come out neatly. If it is for a spoon handle, one needs two whole <tl><m>bones</m></tl>.  All cast work is brittle &amp; subject to breaking, because the <m>metal</m> expands when cast, &amp; retracts &amp; condenses when <tl>hammered</tl>. That is why, one ought to retrace the cast thing with a <tl>chisel</tl>, &amp; in this way the <m>metal</m> retracts, and let it thus <fr>escrouir</fr>.  If the piece for molding is of high relief, first trace the <tl>mold</tl> &amp; the cavity with a <tl>pen-knife</tl>, to make way for the medal &amp; then mold. And if the medal has two sides</ab>


<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>Before casting, heat the <tl><m>bones</m></tl> in order to make them lose only the coldness &amp; dampness.</ab>
 
<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>When the <m>lead</m> gets too hot, it calcines.</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>