<root><page>091r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f187.image</image>


<div>
<id>p091r_1</id>
<head>Grafting</head>


<ab>Any tree that has a large pith will be hard to <del>be</del> graft from, because the cutting is difficult to remove.  If the pith is damaged, the graft will take in an unstraight manner, like with vines of all peach and apricot trees.</ab>
 
<ab>Apricot trees have a very thin <m>bark</m>, and so it is necessary to graft them onto young trees whose own <m>bark</m> is not thick yet, such as the young shoots of prune trees or apricot trees.</ab>
 
<ab>The graft will not take if the cutting gets wet.  It is necessary therefore to graft in serein and mild weather, not too cold and not too windy.</ab>
 
<ab>One must use <m>old wood</m> to graft, if one wants to graft on a tree that is already mature and quite big; because if this is the case, it will compress the cutting, and if the cutting is of <m>young wood</m>, it will not grow properly. But <m>old wood</m> resists the compression of <m>old wood</m> better <del>than the young</del>, because it is harder than <m>young wood</m>. But if the graft is done with only <m>old wood</m>, it will never grow beautifully, but will be frail and short and will take a long time to grow.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p091r_2</id>
<head>Molding with <m>cuttlefish bone</m></head>


<ab>Pay attention to keep the <m>bones</m> in a dry place, because they are very prone to dampness. If you have a small medal, divide the <m>bone</m> into two pieces, then smooth the two parts with a knife. And on a dry, &amp; smooth <m>rooftile</m> &amp; [that has been] pulverized with <m>willow charcoal</m>, rub &amp; polish the two half <m>bones</m>. In this way, the <m>bones</m> soak up the <m>willow charcoal</m> so that the <m>bones</m> will come off cleanly from the cast, &amp; will not stick to it. Then on a <m>fake bone</m>, that is to say a bit of smooth <m>brick</m> of the same width as your <m>bone</m>, place your medal. &amp; then on the medal, put your <m>bone</m> &amp; press it firmly with another stone of the same size.  And for a second time, mold it, and instead smooth over the top with <m>willow charcoal</m> &amp; blow slowly, then press as before, and it will cast neatly. If it is for a spoon handle, two whole <m>bones</m> are needed.  Any work that is cast is brittle &amp; prone to breaking, because the <m>metal</m> swells when cast, &amp; contracts &amp; condenses when hammered. That is why it is necessary to retrace with a chisel the cast object &amp; in this way the <m>metal</m> will contract again and let it escrouir.  If the piece you have to cast is in high relief, first trace the mold &amp; the hollow with a penknife, to make a clear path for the medal &amp; then cast it. And if the medal has two sides</ab>


<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>Rather than casting, heat the <m>bones</m> only to make them lose the coldness &amp; wetness.</ab>
 
<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>When the <m>lead</m> gets too hot, it calcinates.</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>