<root><page>091v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f188.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p091r_2</id>
<ab>since the two <m>bones</m> are joined, <del>co</del>cut them evenly all around, &amp; make notches <del> in different places which cross <del/> through where the two <m>bones</m> are joined, so as to recognize the place where they were first joined. Or with little shards of <m>wood</m>, you can also pierce the <m>bones</m>, or coat the joints with <m>clay</m>, &amp; leave it to dry. Compress <del>between them</del> it with your two hands in between your knees;  &amp; do not use a <sup>normal</sup> press, otherwise the <m>bones</m> will break. Mold at your leisure &amp; two or three times, until you can see that it has the design come up &amp; is well imprinted.  And on each occasion rather than putting the piece straight back in the mold, smooth with <m>willow charcoal</m> because it helps it to come out easily. Once you have cast, rub your medal with <m>oil</m> &amp; <m>willow charcoal</m> &amp; with a brush, to make it dull.  Take care that your medal is not greasy or oily when you cast it in <m>cuttlefish bone</m>. Once you have cast, leave it to cool rather than taking the medal out straight away, because when one takes it out hot, some <m>bone</m> will come away with the medal.  Cast at medium heat, which you will recognize because the bone should stay almost <del/> white. But when it is too hot, the <m>bone</m> becomes brown. The proportion of <m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m> is equal, one to the other. If the piece is difficult to cast, &amp; composed of various pieces, cast it with a forked pattern, of three or four grooves, <del>and make</del> &amp; make these grooves where the <m>metal</m> is the thickest. Also make these grooves around the medal and directly on the head because this attracts the <m>metal</m> &amp; will fill the figure best.  Lift your boxmold a little, once you cast, and in this way you will be able to make several clean casts.  <m>Tin</m> that is too hot burns the <m>bone</m> which becomes damaged. Moreover, having come out of the mold hot <del/>, it risks breaking.
<figure>
<id>fig_p091v_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Q2hHbzNsX1JlYUU</link>
</figure>
</ab></div></root>