<root><page>092r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f189.image</image>


<div>
<id>p092r_1</id>
<head><del>Sand</del>Mixture easy to melt</head>


<ab>One <del>℥ of</del> part <m>soft tin</m>, one part fine <m>lead</m>, one part <m>looking-glass tin</m> &amp; one part <m><fr>argent vif arresté</fr></m> makes an alloy &amp; a solder, so easy to melt that it could easily be melted in a dish of fine <m>tin</m>.</ab>
  
</div>
<div>
<id>p092r_2</id>
<head>Molding hollow on one side and in relief on the other</head>


<ab>And for this effect, one casts a medal of fine <m>tin</m>, which is harder to melt. And since it is neat, one molds with it.  And one leaves it in one half of the box mold, &amp; presses it a little so that it holds better. And next, you shall cast in your box mold the solder described above, or another more meltable than fine <m>tin</m>. And thus, the second medal will melt &amp; mold itself on the first one without ruining it. But to be safer, temper <m>lamp black</m> with <m>water</m>, &amp; with a <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl>, give a light coat of this to the medal, which remains in the box mold, &amp; leave to dry. Thus it will not melt.</ab>


<ab>But if you have a  medal of <m>copper</m> or <m>silver</m>, you can leave it in the casting, if you want to cast with <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m>; but it is necessary that it be a little hot, for the cold would make the <m>tin</m> contract.</ab>


<ab><m>Tin</m> needs to be cast quite hot to come out neat.</ab>


<ab><m>Tin <fr>doulx</fr></m>, which is the best for the cast, is the one that once cast <fr>en grille</fr>, is <del>burnished &amp;</del> shiny &amp; polished like a mirror, &amp; appears to have been burnished, does not have holes like the one that is brittle, &amp; that is not shiny, as if burnished.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p092r_3</id>
<head><m>Potin</m></head>


<ab><m>Potin</m>, once cast very hot, runs &amp; drips like <m>tin</m>. But the medal becomes whitish and immediately casts off the green, which good substances do not do.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p092r_4</id>
<head>Molding statues</head>


<ab>Half <m>founder’s earth</m>, which <pro>founders</pro> use, &amp; half <m>clay earth</m> renders very neatly.</ab>
</div></root>