<root><page>092v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f190.image</image>


<div>
<id>p092v_a1</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> from <m>river tellins</m> and <m>mussels</m> from the river</head>


<ab> The long <m>shells</m> that can be found in <m>fresh river waters</m>, once calcined, makes an <x>impalpable</x> white sand</m>, which moulds very neatly.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p092v_a2</id>
<head>Freezing  <m>mercury</m></head>


<ab>It freezes, just as I tried, by boiling it one or two hours in a rather large <m>iron</m> posnet, putting in, for an <ms><figure>℥</figure></ms> of <m><figure>☿</figure></m>, ii  <ms><figure>℥</figure></ms> of  <m><fr>verdet</fr></m> <del>de</del> and  <m>vitriol</m> of <m>saltpetre</m>,<ms><gk>ana</gk></ms>, with sufficient quantity of old water from <pro><fr>mareschaulx</fr></pro></m>.</ab>


<ab>Or else, melt 4 <ms><figure>℥</figure></ms> of <m>tin</m>, &amp; as it cools, purify it of its filth, which is on top, then, make a hole in it &amp; put in there i <ms><figure>℥</figure></ms> of <m><figure>☿</figure></m> &amp; it will come out like tin if you remelt it, but it will be breakable. And If you want to assay if it is <m>tin</m> or <m><figure>☿</figure></m>, redden a shovel &amp; put a small lump of your ingot on top. If it is <m>tin</m>, it will melt &amp; stay, but if it is <m><figure>☿</figure></m>,  will quickly melt, then when crackling well, it will evaporate. One ought to freeze it in a spoon or in a hollow crucible, &amp; make a moderately sized hole.</ab>


<ab>It can also be frozen, as I assayed, in <m>aqua fortis</m> which beforehand will have eaten a little <m>silver</m>. This one, mixed, makes <m>tin</m> &amp; <m>lead</m> run.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p092v_a3</id>
<head>Mixture</head>


<ab><m>Fine tin</m>, <m>frozen mercury</m> with the smell of tin, <m>looking glass tin</m>, <m>fine lead</m>, as much of one as the other, makes a substance that melts very quickly, but breakable &amp; white. I think that it would be good for solder. A long time to cool.</ab>
</div></root>