<root><page>093v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f192.image</image>


<div>
<id>p093v_1</id>
<head>Faces painted with <fr><m>distemper</m></fr></head>


<ab>Because colors painted with <m>distemper</m> dry quickly &amp; one would not have enough time to complete the shadows and touches on the face, one wets the reverse of the face, on <m>canvas</m>, with a wet <tl>sponge</tl>. Then, with a small <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl>, one makes the shadows, which won't come off. Next, one lays the flesh tones, which do not prevent the already painted shadows from appearing. And then, one retouches the more prominent areas with lively flesh tones. And with another <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> one retouches the shadows in hatching. The shadow strokes do not come off because they are made of <m>bister</m>, which stains the <m>canvas</m> like rust. The said <m>bister</m> is good for making shadows with <m>distemper</m>, for in <m>oil</m> it has no body and would dry with great difficulty. One mixes <m>ru ochre</m> in the said <m>bister</m> for shadows with a little <m>sap green</m>. The best <m>bister</m> is the rich, shiny one from the fireplaces of large kitchens. It is difficult to grind and screeches on the <m>marble</m> slab.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p093v_2</id>
<head><m>Azure</m></head>


<ab><m><fr>Azur d’esmail</fr></m> always wants to be cleaned because the filth that can be seen in the <fr>laveures</fr> makes it die. One needs to coat it two times, &amp; the first very thick, moving the <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> by laying it first lengthwise then across. <figure/> It is better used on <m>canvas</m>, where it is imbibed immediately, than on <m>wood</m>. <m>Varnish</m> returns it to its vigor, because being imbibed, it becomes dark. To try it, <pro>painters</pro> bring their <tl>palette</tl> to the <pro>grocers</pro>, &amp; distemper &amp; alloy it with a little white crushed in <m>oil</m>, for in this way, the beautiful shows its <fr>turquine</fr> vivacity, but the bad is lavender grey. The most delicate is the best for working. It is thinned <del>working</del> by washing it.</ab> 
</div>


<div>
<id>p093v_3</id>
<head><m>Purple</m> and <m>lake</m></head>


<ab>It is made of <m>azure</m> and <m>lake</m> which is also tested on the palette with <m>white</m>. The one which gives a clear red rose color, tending slightly towards purple, on a <m>polished knife</m> or on <m>glass</m>, is esteemed beautiful. The dark red one is not as pleasant.</ab>
</div></root>