<root><page>093v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f192.image</image>

<div>
<id>p093v_1</id>
<head>Faces painted with <fr><m>distemper</m></fr></head>


<ab>Because colors painted with <m>distemper</m> dry quickly and one would not have enough time to complete the shadows and touches on the face, one wets the reverse of the face, on <m>canvas</m>, with a wet <tl>sponge</tl>. Then, with a small <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl>, one makes the shadows, which won't come off. Next, one lays the flesh tones, which do not prevent the already painted shadows from appearing. And then, one retouches the more prominent areas with lively flesh tones. And with another <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> one retouches the shadows in hatching. The shadow strokes do not come off because they are made of <m>bister</m>, which stains the <m>canvas</m> like rust. The said <m>bister</m> is good for making shadows with <m>distemper</m>, for in <m>oil</m> it has no body and would dry with great difficulty. One mixes <m>ru ochre</m> in the said <m>bister</m> for shadows with a little <m>sap green</m>. The best <m>bister</m> is the rich, shiny one from the fireplaces of large kitchens. It is difficult to grind and screeches on the <m>marble</m> slab.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p093v_2</id>
<head><m>Azure</m></head>


<ab><fr><m>Azur desmail</m></fr> always wants to be cleaned because the filth that can be seen in the used water <sup>would</sup> makes it die. It always needs to be coated twice, &amp; first very thickly, driving the <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> by laying it lengthwise then across. It is better used on <m>canvas</m>, which imbibes it immediately, than on <m>wood</m>. <m>Varnish</m> restores its vigor, because while imbibing, it becomes dark. To try it, <pro>painters</pro> bring their palettes to the <pro>grocers</pro> and distemper and mix @ it with a bit of <m>white</m> crushed in <m>oil</m>, for in this way the beautiful shows its <fr>turquine</fr> vivacity, while the mediocre is lavender grey. The thinner one is best to work with. It is made thinner by being washed.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p093v_3</id>
<head><m>Purple</m> and <m>lake</m></head>


<ab>It is made of <m>azure</m> and <m>lake</m> which is also tested on the palette with <m>white</m>. The one which gives a clear red rose color, tending slightly towards purple, on a <m>polished knife</m> or on <m>glass</m>, is esteemed beautiful. The dark red one is not as pleasant.</ab>
</div></root>