<root><page>096v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f198.image</image>

<div>
<id>p096v_a1</id>
<head>Grey hilts</head>


<ab>When they are white, it is necessary only to clean them well, and then to heat them over a fire, and make them turn blue. And take good care that they do not turn too blue, since neither <m>gold</m> nor <m>silver</m> nor any color would set. To accomplish this, which is called <fr>les faire passer</fr>, have a caldron full of <m>ashes</m> that you cover with some <m>blazing hot charcoal</m>, and heat the <m>ashes</m> thus very well, for an hour or two. And when the <m>ashes</m> are very hot, put the <m>charcoal</m> aside and put the hilt where the <m>charcoal</m> was, and cover it completely with <m>ashes</m>. And when the body, which is the main part of the hilt, is completely colored, flip it onto the other side. In that way, the grey cannot color it too dark, unless some <m>hot coal</m> touches it. Greying can be achieved in an ordinary fireplace, too, but there is a danger that it may sit there too long and make a crust which which will prevent the color from setting. Blue coloring is obtained as soon as the <m>ashes</m> have heated the hilts a little bit, but it will always be grey on some sides. After blue comes grey.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p096v_a2</id>
<head>Color of water</head>


<ab>For the color of water, pass a <tl>soft file</tl> on the hilts to whiten them, then the <tl>burnisher</tl>. Afterwards, you color them blue until they become grey. Next, when they are still slightly hot, pass <m>bloodstone</m> over them, and, as they cool, one turns them to reheat them, since the color of water is achieved only after doing this a few times. And if hilts weren't warm, the <m>bloodstone</m> would scrape them and undo the color. Pay attention that hilts don't become too grey, since they would give off soot that would prevent the color from setting. Almost one day is necessary to prepare, soften, and set the color of water, but as soon as they turn a little blue, it is enough for grey or other colors. Grey is the lesser color, after varnish made of two colors, either yellow or black.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p096v_a3</id>
<head><m>Yellow varnish</m></head>


<ab>One should vigorously whiten and clean the hilts well. After that, with a feather, one coats them entirely, when they are cold, with <m>nut <del>olive</del> oil</m>. Then, turn them over a good <m>charcoal</m> fire  like that of the <pro>furbishers</pro>' furnace without letting them touch the <m>charcoal</m> or <m>ashes</m>. And when they stop smoking, it is done.</ab>
</div></root>