<root><page>097r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f199.image</image>


<div>
<id>p097r_1</id>


<head><m>Black varnish</m></head>


<ab>It is said, at the beginning of the book where you can see it, that it is made with  <m>galipot</m>.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p097r_2</id>
 
<head><m>Gilding</m></head>


<ab>One prepares the guards thoroughly with a soft, very <tl>soft file</tl> such that there is nothing black left on any of the guards, and next heat them, &amp; pass them as said. But to <m>gild</m> &amp; <m>gild</m> with <m>silver</m>, they ought not to pass, except maybe a little towards blue. Then while the guards are hot, one attaches them to a wood block &amp; with some tweezers one layers the gold &amp; one makes it sit with <m>bloodstone</m>,which is quite clean &amp; rubbed with <m><fr>pottée</fr></m>. And as soon as the guards are cold, one reheats them, then one layers the <m>gold</m> as above. And first one gives <del><fr>de</fr></del> two layers, until the entire guard is well-adorned. And next one reheats as at the beginning, &amp; one gives the third covering of <m>gold</m>. Then one burnishes very thoroughly and with great force with a large <m>bloodstone</m>. <del>And</del> But note that <add>to</add> burnish well, the guard always needs to be warm. And to know this, one smells it &amp; brings it close to the nose.  For one ought not to touch with the fingers, but one <del>grasps </del> picks it up from on top of the warm ashes with a small <m>iron</m> rod, which has been purposely made to fit into the eye of the hilt.  And when you have finished burnishing it well, rub it well with a piece of white <m>linen</m>, and make sure your <m>gold</m> is thicker and stronger than the ones <pro>painters</pro> use.  A quarter of a pound is worth fifty or lx s<exp>ols</exp>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p097r_3</id>


<head><m>Gilding</m> with <m>silver</m></head>


<ab>You must prepare the hilts and whiten them with a <m>file</m>, coarser than the one used for <m>gold</m>.  And you want to pass them <sup>change their color</sup> to grey, as you have done for the <m>gold</m>.  And since they are warm, you must double the leaves of <m>silver</m> and then divide them with a knife, and then apply them to the hilt with tweezers and a burnisher.  And then heat them again, and apply <sup>the silver</sup>, until they are all <m>gilded</m> in <m>silver</m>.  Then you must apply, for the third time, your doubled leaf as has been said, then burnish them very strongly and with good strength, not with the <m>sanguine</m>, but with a strong burnisher, just as you would not use a burnisher on <m>gold</m>.</ab>
</div></root>