<root><page>097r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f199.image</image>


<div>
<id>p097r_1</id>


<head><m>Black varnish</m></head>


<ab>It is said, at the beginning of the book where you can see it, that it is made with  <m>galipot</m>.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p097r_2</id>
 
<head><m>Gilding</m></head>


<ab>One prepares the hilts very well with a soft, <sup>indeed</sup> very soft <m>file</m> until there is no blackness left on the hilts, then heat them, and pass them as has already been said.  But to <m>gild</m> and <m>gild</m> with <m>silver</m>, they must not be passed <sup>change their color</sup> too much, except maybe leaning towards a blue.  Then while the hilts are hot, one ties them to a wood block and with some tweezers you apply the gold and fasten it with the <m>sanguine</m> and the <m>sanguine</m> is very neat and has been rubbed with <m>putty</m>. And when the hilts become cold, reheat them, then apply <m>gold</m> as said above.  And you must start with giving the hilt two layers, until it is well-covered.  And then reheat it as you did at beginning, and give it its third layer of <m>gold</m>.  Then burnish it with a <m>sanguine</m>, very strongly and with good strength.  But note that if you want to burnish well, your hilt must remain warm.  And to know this, you bring it close to your nose and smell it.  And because you cannot touch it with your fingers, take it out of the warm ashes with a small <m>iron</m> stick, which has been purposely made to fit into the eye of the hilt.  And when you have finished burnishing it well, rub it well with a piece of white <m>linen</m>, and make sure your <m>gold</m> is thicker and stronger than the ones <pro>painters</pro> use.  A quarter of a pound is worth fifty or lx s<exp>ols</exp>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p097r_3</id>


<head><m>Gilding</m> with <m>silver</m></head>


<ab>You must prepare the hilts and whiten them with a <m>file</m>, coarser than the one used for <m>gold</m>.  And you want to pass them <sup>change their color</sup> to grey, as you have done for the <m>gold</m>.  And since they are warm, you must double the leaves of <m>silver</m> and then divide them with a knife, and then apply them to the hilt with tweezers and a burnisher.  And then heat them again, and apply <sup>the silver</sup>, until they are all <m>gilded</m> in <m>silver</m>.  Then you must apply, for the third time, your doubled leaf as has been said, then burnish them very strongly and with good strength, not with the <m>sanguine</m>, but with a strong burnisher, just as you would not use a burnisher on <m>gold</m>.</ab>
</div></root>