<root><page>097v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f200.item</image>


<div>
<id>p097v_1</id>
<head><m>Mastic</m> varnish dried a half hour</head>


<ab>
Some use 2 <figure>℥</figure> of <m>mastic</m>, half <figure>℥</figure> of <m>turpentine</m> and of <m>turpentine oil</m>, and <m>spirits</m> at your discretion since it evaporates when heated and nonetheless makes a more desiccative varnish. But I made it like this: I use <m>turpentine oil</m>, at my discretion, and add very little <m>turpentine</m>, since it remains humid and gets tacky if we add too much, together with some <m>spirits</m> and heat the <m>oil</m> in a varnished bowl and, as it become very hot I add some finely ground <m>mastic</m> and pass one-third of the <m>oil</m> through a sieve and let this heat up until it is melted, which will occur quickly on hot <m>ashes</m>. Once it is all melted, try it on your knife, and if you see that it has too much body add a bit of <m>turpentine oil</m>, and if it does not, add some <m>mastic</m>. And so it is finished, and keep it well covered so that no rubbish gets in. When you want to make this, take care to separate and choose the <m>mastic</m> that is white and pure of any dirt and dust and black dross. And when you wash it and dry it, make it very white and clean and make it even better, because if you don't purge it of these dregs and marks they will be pulverised into it, remain within the varnish, and when you wipe it onto some white or flesh-tinted <sup>surface</sup>, it will seem as if it were spotted and dirty. Having properly selected, pulverise it in a mortar and pass it through a very fine sieve, and afterward mix it in <m>oil</m>, as stated above. But if you want to make it more carefully, take a drop of <m>mastic</m>, as you know, pulverise, pass it, and mix, and you shall have something very singular for small projects. Be well advised when varnishing to not breathe on it for it will make the varnish white and thick.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
It almost dries as you are working on it.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
We know that this varnish does not have enough body when it doesn't take well to an <m>oil</m> painting, since it is like <m>water</m>. Add, therefore, powdered <m>mastic</m> and heat it until it is good. This varnish is very white and beautiful not at all like the <m>aspic</m> one.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
For some, instead of <m>turpentine oil</m>, use some <m>spike lavender oil</m>, which is not as good.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
This varnish is to be applied cold on the canvas with a very clean fingertip, and spread quickly.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The Italians hardly varnish their paintings since they layer their paints very thick and these take a long time to be dry on the inside, even though they have a dry skin and crust on the surface.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The varnish is applied with one's finger in order to thinly layer it, because it will yellow afterward.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p097v_2</id>
<head>To work nearby</head>


<ab>
It is a strange thing that the workers in this craft can only work if they have good breath, for if they have bad breath their work will crack when refired.</ab>
</div></root>