<root><page>097v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f200.item</image>


<div>
<id>p097v_1</id>
<head><m>Mastic varnish</m> dry in a <ms><tmp>half hour</tmp></ms></head>


<ab>
Some take 2 <ms><figure>℥</figure></ms> of <m>mastic</m>, <ms>half <figure>℥</figure></ms> of <m>turpentine</m> &amp; <ms>half <figure>℥</figure></ms> of <m>turpentine oil</m> &amp; <m>eau de vye</m>, a little at your discretion, because it evaporates when heated &amp; nonetheless makes the <m>varnish</m> more desiccative. But I made it thus: I take <m>turpentine oil</m> at  discretion &amp; put in a good bit of <m>turpentine</m>, because it remains always moist &amp; attaches itself if one puts in too much, &amp; <m>eau de vye</m>, &amp; heat in a <tl>varnished bowl</tl> the said <m>oil</m>, &amp; when it begins to be very hot, I put in some <m>subtly ground mastic</m> &amp; around <ms>one-third</ms> of the <m>oil</m> passed through a <tl>sieve</tl> <del>l</del>, and let reheat until it is melted, which will be soon on hot <m>ashes</m>. Once all melted, try it on the <tl>knife</tl>, and if you see that it has too much body, add in a little <m>turpentine oil</m>, and if it does not have enough, add in <m>mastic</m>, and thus it well be done. And keep it well covered so that no filth gets in. When you want to make it, be careful to sort &amp; choose the <m>mastic</m> that is white &amp; purified of any dirt &amp; dust &amp; black dross. And when you wash it &amp; dry it to render it very white &amp; clean, it will be even better. For if you do not purge it well, these straws &amp; marks, pulverised into it, will remain within the varnish, &amp; when you set it on white or carnation, it will appear that they are fleas &amp; blemishes. Once well chosen, pulverise it in a mortar and pass it through a very fine sieve, and next mix it in <m>oil</m>, as is said. But if you want to make it more carefully, extract a tear of <m>mastic</m>, as you know, pulverise, pass, &amp; mix, and you will have something very singular for small works. Take heed when varnishing not to breathe on it, for this will make the varnish whiten &amp; take body.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
It almost dries when working.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
One knows that this varnish does not have body enough when it does not take well on a panel in <m>oil</m> for it is like <m>water</m>. Add in therefore powdered <m>mastic</m> &amp; heat  until it is good. This varnish is very white &amp; beautiful, &amp; does not go to your head like that of <m>spike lavender</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
For some, instead of <del>tour</del> <m>turpentine oil</m>, put <m>spike lavender oil</m>, which is not as good.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
This varnish is laid down cold on the panel with a very clean fingertip, &amp; one needs to spread it vigorously.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The Italians scarcely varnish their paintings because they lay their paintings very thick &amp; they are a long time drying on the inside, though on top they make a dry skin &amp; crust.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
One lays the varnish with a finger so as to lay it thin, because when thick, it yellows.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p097v_2</id>
<head>To work nearby</head>


<ab>
It is a strange thing that the workers in this craft can only work if they have good breath, for if they have bad breath their work will crack when refired.</ab>
</div></root>