<root>.<page>098r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f201.image</image>
 
<div>
<id>p098r_a1</id>
<head><m>Varnish</m> for lutes</head>


<ab>They take a little <m>turpentine</m> and some <m>turpentine oil</m>, or <m>spike lavender [oil]</m>, and some <m>amber</m> pulverized and very finely sieved &amp; proceed as with that of <m>mastic</m>, &amp; they add some <m>dragon's blood</m> to color it and turn it red. And others some <m>terra merita</m> to turn it yellow.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p098r_a2</id>
<head>Borders for a Garden</head>


<ab>You have to work the ground, then then it with a rake, and afterwards if it is dry you must <m>wet</m> it. Then stretch a cord clean on the ground, and along its length hit the cord with the back of a pruning knife, so that the cord marks a right line. Along its length you will make holes with an <m>iron</m> stake, where you will plant rosemary, its head lopped off &amp; cut to measure and thinned out at the foot.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p098r_a3</id>
<head><pro>Locksmith</pro></head>


<ab>To <m>tin</m> nails and other work, they file their work neatly, then in order to clean &amp; degrease it well, it is boiled in <m>vinegar</m>. Then they dry it with <m>linen</m>, afterwards they heat it &amp; pass some <m>resin</m> over it, which induces a shining skin like varnish. This done, they melt some pure &amp; fine <m>tin</m> in their <m>tin</m>ning tool, which is a <m>square little iron box.</m> And when the <m>tin</m> is well melted and moderately warm, they throw some <m>resin</m> in to consume the scum, &amp; then they temper the head of a nail or something similar for a bit, and having been left in for seven or eight pauses, they take it out and shake it, hitting it with some <m>iron</m> to make the the superfluous <m>tin</m> fall off, &amp; clean it with a small stick wrapped in <m>tow</m>. And if it is not well <m>tin</m>ned, you will hit it until it it hot with a piece of <m>resin</m> and do as before before and leave it to get cold. When the work cools down it becomes yellow, which is a sign that the <m>tin</m> is the right temperature. But it becomes blue if the <m>tin</m> is too hot. Things so <m>tin</m>ned are of a duration, &amp; do not come undone at all, like the tinning done by leaves. But at the end of a year they can be clarified &amp; renewed by heating &amp; striking them.</ab>


<ab><pro>Leadsmiths</pro> say that making a lizard die in the <m>melted tin</m> makes the <m>tin</m>ning become very golden. Or else by adding <m>sal ammoniac</m>.</ab>
</div></root>