<root><page>098v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f202.image</image>


<div>
<id>p098v_a1</id>
<head>Small dogs</head>


<ab>Small barbet dogs are recognizable thanks to their muzzle which is larger than that of other dogs.</ab>


 </div>
<div>
<id>p098v_a2</id>
<head>Salted <m>artichokes</m></head>


<ab>One should put them fill and not too ripe in a small barrel full of <m>brine</m>. Then can be served all year long, with salads, <m>oil</m> and <m>vinegar</m>, raw, as prepared in this way they take long to cook. Make sure to try your <m>brine</m> with an <m>egg</m>: if it is good, the <m>egg</m> will float in it. If it does not float, it means <x>the <m>brine</m></x> is not strong enough and would not conserve the <m>fruits</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p098v_a3</id>
<head>Trees</head>


<ab>Those which carry <m>fruits</m> age early and do not last long.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p098v_a4</id>
<head>Birds</head>


<ab>Those who have been fed at the spit do not sing among or the company of other birds, they do only when they have their own cage. To teach them to sing well, they have to be taken from their nest as young as possible, and be covered with a <m>duvet</m> or <m>rabbit skin</m>. That way, having not seen their father and known their voice, they learn better to sing the way they are taught to.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p098v_a5</id>
<head><fr>Fonte</fr></head>


<ab>The <m><fr>potée</fr></m> is made of <m>burnt earth</m> which was used in the <fr>fonte</fr>, this is <m>earth <fr>bourre bolvene</fr></m> in which one has melted it. One grinds it on a big <tl><m>stone</m></tl>, &amp; with this one one makes the <del><fr>chappe</fr> of</del> first coat of the <fr>chappe</fr> of bells, where there are letters &amp; works, &amp; <del><fr>le</fr></del> only needs to be reheated in the flame of a <m>straw</m>, and mold very neatly.</ab>


<ab>The <m>earth</m> which molds in <fr>noyau</fr> is subject to making it porous, if you do not rub well with a <tl>brush</tl> or your <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl> on the molded piece, which should be well <m>oiled</m>. And do it coat by coat, &amp; not all at once.</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>