<root><page>098v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f202.image</image>

<div>
<id>p098v_a1</id>
<head>Small dogs</head>


<ab>Small barbet dogs are recognizable thanks to their muzzle which is larger than that of other dogs.</ab>


 </div>
<div>
<id>p098v_a2</id>
<head>Salted <m>artichokes</m></head>


<ab>One should put them fill and not too ripe in a small barrel full of <m>brine</m>. Then can be served all year long, with salads, <m>oil</m> and <m>vinegar</m>, raw, as prepared in this way they take long to cook. Make sure to try your <m>brine</m> with an <m>egg</m>: if it is good, the <m>egg</m> will float in it. If it does not float, it means [the <m>brine</m>] is not strong enough and would not conserve the <m>fruits</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p098v_a3</id>
<head>Trees</head>


<ab>Those which carry <m>fruits</m> age early and do not last long.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p098v_a4</id>
<head>Birds</head>


<ab>Those who have been fed at the spit do not sing among or the company of other birds, they do only when they have their own cage. To teach them to sing well, they have to be taken from their nest as young as possible, and be covered with a <m>duvet</m> or <m>rabbit skin</m>. That way, having not seen their father and known their voice, they learn better to sing the way they are taught to.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p098v_a5</id>
<head>Melting</head>


<ab>The <m>potée</m> is made of <m>burnt earth</m> which has served for the melting. It is the <m>earth</m> bourré bolvene in which it has been melted. It should be ground against a large <m>stone</m> slab, and of this one should make the first coat of the mantle of the bell, where the letters and ornementations are to be found. It does not require to be cooked again against <m>hay fire</m> and will mold very neatly.</ab>


<ab>The <m>earth</m> used for the molding of the core is likely to swell if you do not strongly rub the molded piece with a brush or the finger and if it is not well <m>oil</m>ed. And you need to do it one coat at a time rather than all at once.</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>