<root><page>099r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f203.image</image>
<div>
<cont/>
<id>p098v_a5</id>


<ab><m>Earth</m> or crushed <m>wet sand</m> with <m>water</m> needs to be reheated more than <m>sand</m>.</ab>


<ab><m>Latten from a candlestick</m> is not pure since some <m>filings</m> and <m>pot metal</m> are mixed into it.</ab>


<ab><m>Latten</m> needs to be cast warmer than <m>copper</m>, which I do not believe.</ab>


<ab>To cast scrupulously, you must not take all of the <m>alloyed metals</m> together, but take them in [their] pure [form] and mix them.</ab>


<ab><m>Iron</m> shoul not […] to cast in <m>copper</m> or <m>brass</m>.</ab>


<ab>It is better to mold <m>sand</m> at once, either as a molding box or <m>noyau</m>, rather than several casts.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>

You must reheat a crucible on a charcoal fire which easily ignites for one or two hours with the material inside. Then breathe on it and cover the crucible with large pieces of charcoal and the opening of the stove with bricks, and let it consume two or three lumps of charcoal which shall fill the stove beneath the crucible. Eventually put the molding box on the fire and when the flame is very white and the material is as light as <m>water</m> and spitting some pale blue flames, [make the] cast. The secret to casting well is to do so at a very high temperature and speedily.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p099r_a2</id>
<head>Thin white <m>sand</m></head><ab> without bond is perfect for casting and it becomes thicker if you crush it very finely on <m>porphyry</m> or you calcinate it by making it red-hot several times, and if it becomes <m>vinegar</m> or thinner with <m>water</m>, as you know, it casts as well very precisely in a core, as I did the experiment. But don't soak it with salted water if you want to anneal it quickly for salt boils on fire and creates more dust while it is being pressed by the fire. I think that reheated cores gently would not react like this. I cast very neatly as a core some matter and […]. white <m>sand</m> smells <m>sulphur</m> when it is reheated, and I think that it would melt. And since the material has been cast into it, it takes in the mold a luster as if it were leaded or vitrified. I think that <pro>glassmakers</pro> could use it.</ab>
 


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>

A very little <m>sal ammoniac</m> must be dissolved in water.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p099r_a3</id>
<head> 
Bell handles</head>


<ab>
They can be repaired well without remaking the bell, which you must put back into the pit and the mold inside. But it is thought impossible to give back to it its original tone when soldering a cracked bell.</ab>
</div></root>