<root><page>099v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f204.image</image>


<div>
<id>p099v_a1</id>
<head>Quince trees</head>


<ab>They have to be pruned often; otherwise they die and do not produce good fruit.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p099v_a2</id>
<head>Cannons</head>


<ab>They are very difficult to drill when they are made of <m>metal</m> since the material is rough and brittle. But you must not push the drill too strongly or push all at once, but remove it often. In that case, the cannon mouth is bigger than the bullet in order to avoid drilling, since the material can be easily cast and slides. The drill should not be like a dovetail, or a point, but should be cut in round like a crankshaft. If it breaks, don't leave it to rust <figure>+</figure></ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<figure>+</figure> but instantly take it off from the light. What you will do is pour a little <m>oil</m> on it and then turn it down opposite to the light, strike the opposite side, and it will fall out. You have to drill gently when a piece is made of metal.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p099v_a3</id>
<head>Bells</head>


<ab>One does not make them in the pit if they do not fit.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p099v_a4</id>
<head>Gilding <del>your</del> molding for panels without <m>gold</m></head>


<ab>Some take <m>orpiment in leaf form</m> &amp; pulverize it &amp; make <fr>moresque</fr> leaves &amp; burnish it, and it is this <m>orpiment</m> which is shiny like <m>gold</m>. However, <m>ground metals</m> or <m>ground <fr>cristallin</fr></m> or <m>touchstone</m> are better.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p099v_a5</id>
<head><m>Orpiment</m> orange</head>


<ab>One sublimates it &amp; one grinds it &amp; some put in a little <m>arsenic</m> to make it melt instead.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p099v_a6</id>
<head><m>Varnish</m></head>


<ab>Some make this of <m>mastic</m> with two <ms>ounces</ms> of <m>mastic</m> and one of <m>clear &amp; white turpentine oil</m> &amp; <m>eau de vye</m> as above. Heat it on <m>ashes</m> until it is melted, then let it rest &amp; put it in another <tl>vessel</tl> to purge it of dregs.</ab>
</div></root>