<root><page>099v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f204.image.r=Recueil%20de%20recettes%20et%20secrets%20concernant%20l'art%20du%20mouleur,%20de%20l'artificier%20et%20du%20peintre </image>

<div>
<id>p099v_a1</id>
<head>Quince trees</head>


<ab>They have to be pruned often; otherwise they die and do not produce good fruit.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p099v_a2</id>
<head>Cannons</head>


<ab>They are very difficult to drill when they are made of <m>metal</m> since the material is rough and brittle. But you must not push the drill too strongly or push all at once, but remove it often. In that case, the cannon mouth is bigger than the bullet in order to avoid drilling, since the material can be easily cast and slides. The drill should not be like a dovetail, or a point, but should be cut in round like a crankshaft. If it breaks, don't leave it to rust X</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
X but instantly take it off from the light. What you will do is pour a little <m>oil</m> on it and then turn it down opposite to the light, strike the opposite side, and it will fall out. You have to drill gently when a piece is made of metal.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p099v_a3</id>
<head>Bells</head>


<ab>They are not made in a pit if they do not fit</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p099v_a4</id>
<head>To gilt frames paintings without <m>gold</m></head>


<ab>Some use some leaved <m>orpiment</m> and then powder it and make the leaves look Moorish, burnish them, and the <m>orpiment</m> shines like gold. However, ground metals or ground crystalline or touchstone are the best.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p099v_a5</id>
<head>Orange Orpiment</head>


<ab>Mix it with <m>arsenic</m> and grind it. Some prefer to melt it and then add a little <m>arsenic</m>.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p099v_a6</id>
<head>Varnish</head>


<ab>Some make the <m>mastic varnish</m> with two ounces of <m>mastic</m> and one of clear, white <m>turpentine oil</m> and some <m>spirits</m> as aforesaid; heat that on <m>ashes</m> until it melts and then leave it still and put it in another vessel to remove dust.</ab>
</div></root>