<root><page>101r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f207.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p100v_2</id>
<ab>again quite hard, and then add to it three <figure><ms>℥</ms></figure> of <m>minium</m>, &amp; pound again together &amp; put it in the <tl>crucible</tl>, which you will cover with an appropriate <tl>tile</tl>, not too thick, so that heat reverberates better. Then put it on the <tl>grill</tl> of your <tl>furnace</tl>, having put a few thick, rounded <tl>tiles</tl> under it. Next, fill your <tl><m>charcoal</m> furnace</tl> to the <bp>mouth</bp> with <m>charcoal</m>, heaped to the top, and let it light, and always maintain the heat even, without letting the <m>charcoal</m> go down. And to this effect, always ensure that the <tl>furnace</tl> is heaped to the top &amp; full of <m>charcoal</m> and maintain it like this for one <ms>day</ms>. The first experiment I made, only a yellow mass emerged, like <m>minium</m> alone when vitrified, &amp; with <m>gold</m> grains, in a mass at the bottom. Try cemented <m>gold</m> together with <m>antimony</m>.</ab><m>
</m> 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
If you need more heat, put <m>tiles</m> on the edge of the <bp>mouth</bp> of the glowing <tl>furnace</tl>, lean them one against the other to make the heat reverberate.</ab>


<figure>
<id>fig_p101r_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dnlodmJvNkRMaWM</link>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
</figure>
</div>


<div>
<id>p101r_1</id>
<head><m>Topaz</m></head>


<ab>The same dose can be observed for all <m>gemstones</m>, which is one <ms>part</ms> the weight of calcined <m>pebbles</m> with three <ms>parts</ms>the weight of <m>minium</m>, pounding all separately in a <tl><m>copper</m> mortar</tl> for <m>emeralds</m>, &amp; in an <tl><m>iron</m> mortar</tl> to make <m>topazes</m> or <m>amber</m> color, with <tl>pestles</tl> similar to the <tl>mortars</tl>. <m>Emerald</m> &amp; <m>topaz</m> are of the same heat, &amp; for an <ms>hour</ms> &amp; a half, otherwise they could burn. <m>Ruby</m> wants more time &amp; more fire, &amp; colored with <m>gold</m> leaf. I believe that <m>pumice stone</m> or <m>fire-stone</m> for the <m>ruby</m> would be better. See <m>enamels</m>. Also try to mix pieces of colored <m>glass</m> or <m>enamels</m> instead of <m>pebbles</m>. If the mass is not colored enough, pound it further in the <tl><m>iron</m> mortar</tl>.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Slightly burnt <m>tartar</m> mixed in makes beautiful yellow, but not much is needed. <fr><m>Arene</m></fr> also makes it more yellow.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p101r_2</id>
<head><m>Salt</m> for melting</head>


<ab>Mix <m>saltpeter</m> &amp; <m>common salt</m> and melt them together &amp; throw them onto <m>copper</m>, molten or in a <fr>bain</fr>, &amp; it will purify it &amp; makes it run marvellously. First, <m>ordinary salt</m> needs to be decrepitated, which is to say holding it over good heat until it crackles no more; or to melt it better, in an <tl><fr>four à vent</fr></tl>. Throw it neatly onto a <m>marble</m> <sup>slab</sup>, then pestle it &amp; crush it very finely, then put it in a <tl>crucible</tl>on as much <m>saltpeter</m>. &amp; Let it boil &amp; mix them together until</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
It cleans &amp; purifies metal well.</ab>


<cont/>
</div></root>