<root><page>101v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f208.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p101r_2</id>
<ab>the <tl>crucible</tl> is red. Next, throw it on <tl><m>marble</m></tl>, and you will have a substance white, hard &amp; even, like <m>alabaster</m>, with which you will be able to cast medals which will resemble <m>marble</m>, but keep them out of the humidity.</ab>
</div>
  
<div>
<id>p101v_1</id>
<head><m>Jacinth</m></head>


<ab>It is made, like <m>rubies</m>, with <m>gold</m>; but you do not need such a great fire. <m>Rubies</m> want fire for a whole day, and if there is not enough fire, it will only have red veins.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Always heat up your crucibles.
</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
One holds that rubified <m>antimony</m> makes <m>jacinth</m>.
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p101v_2</id>
<head><m>Topaz</m></head>


<ab>I melted one part of calcinated &amp; pulverized <m>pumice stone</m> <del><fr>&amp; tr</fr></del> with three parts of <m>minium</m>, the stone having been pulverized in a steel mortar. A very beautiful yellow came to me, without any grain more yellow than the others. It is true that it was strongly charged with colour. I believe it would be better to pulverize the <m>pumice</m> in a glass mortar, because it &amp; the <m>minium</m> make enough yellow by themselves. A mass came to me, the top of which was the beautiful yellow, as mentioned, and the bottom was like a <m>fire-stone</m> without transparency. With which, in mixing other</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p101v_3</id> 
<head><m>Varnish</m></head>


<ab>The <pl>Germans</pl> make <m>minium</m> boil a lot in <m><pa>linseed</pa> oil</m>, &amp; to give it the body of <m>varnish</m>, they mix in <m>very pulverized yellow amber</m>.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p101v_4</id>
<head><m>Ammoniacum</m></head>


<ab>One puts it by small lumps into a bit of good <m>vinegar</m>, &amp; heats it,  then passes it through a cloth strainer. All medicinal <m>gums</m> dissolve in <m>vinegar</m>.</ab>
</div></root>