<root><page>102v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f210.image</image>


<div>
<id>p102v_1</id>


<head>Painting on <m>crystal</m> or <m>glass</m></head>


<ab>They paint without any traces of <m>oil</m>, except for faces where they outline the nose and the mouth in very fine black work. Then they make strokes and highlight them in white, and then they apply a coat of <m>flesh-tinted color</m>.  As for the background, they do it in natural <m>azur</m> from <pl>Acre</pl> to make it more beautiful, or <m>lacquer</m> for a quickly-done red, or for a finer red, <m>dragon's blood</m>. But it is necessary to apply it little by little so that it is smooth and of one color, and in the same way for other colors. Then they apply underneath it, a leaf of <m>topaz</m>, <m>gold</m> or <m>silver</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p102v_2</id>


<head>Infusion of <m>anthos</m> or <m>rosemary</m></head>


<ab>It is better to cook the flower in August and more suited to <m>oil</m>-making. Take as much as you want. Then put it into a bottle very well corked, and leave them to wilt in the shade for a day. Then add the first substance of <m>wine</m> and leave to settle three or four days; and express it all in another vessel and into this very same substance of <m>wine</m>, add seven or eight infusions made out of new flowers. Then leave the latest infusion in the sun for a month. Then distill it through a still. Then mix two ounces of this <m>water</m> with two or three spoons of <m>white wine</m>; but this is for the elderly. Paul the Third used it.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p102v_2</id>


<head>Casting</head>


<ab><m>Tin</m> casts better when it is thin and delicate, than when it is thick, because when it is thick it contracts in high heat. So if you want to mold a thick piece in <m>tin</m>, mold it only one one side, and if it is possible, make it hollow on the other side. In this way your piece will be neater. And then you can solder two half pieces together. But if you have no choice but to mold it thick, make the shape of it and mold force abreuvouers around the figure in this way.
<figure>
<id>fig_p102v_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SjZwV0ZHdW93ZEk</link>
</figure>
</ab>
</div></root>