<root><page>104v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f214.image</image>


<div>
<id>p104v_a1</id>
<head>Against dogs' mange</head>


<ab>For normal-sized dogs, take half an <figure>℥</figure> of <m>stavesacre</m>, &amp; one <figure>℥</figure> for big dogs, as fine powder beaten with two <m>egg whites</m> &amp; one quarteron of <m>oil</m>. They must drink the beverage on an empty stomach, after keeping them locked without any food. Approved.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p104v_a2</id>
<head>For casting</head>


<ab>If you've got a big piece which does not allow an easy stripping of casting, mold it with some <m>wax</m>, either on the hollow side or in relief, because it is soft &amp; hollow and so can easily be separated from the piece without leaving anything. But be sure that the melted <m>wax</m> is neither too hot nor too cold. Some people use for molding some <m>wax</m> warmed in <m>boiled water</m>, but while pressing the mold it bends &amp; becomes unusable. Once you have made your <m>wax</m> cavity, you can cast in some very soft &amp; clear <m>clay</m>, &amp; let it dry. Then, upon it you will make a <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m> cavity, in which what you will make will easily be stripped.</ab>


 </div>
<div>
<id>p104v_a3</id>
<head><pro>Goldsmith</pro></head>


<ab>Know what it is to work on spangled garments, it is small pieces of pure <m>silver</m> &amp; of <m>silver-gilt</m> with which one makes the <pro>archers'</pro> coats.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p104v_a4</id>
<head>Spinet playing by itself</head>


<figure>
<id>fig_p104v_1</id>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5cWFSaUU5a2R6N2s</link>
</figure>


<ab>Make an axle surrounded with wheels pierced all around in their thickness and attach feathers as for a cittern or a spinet &amp; arrange them according to the song you want it to play, leaving a suitable distance. And, turning the axle either by yourself or by a clock spring, your invention will effect itself.</ab>
</div></root>