<root><page>107r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f219.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<ab>
<figure>
<id>fig_p107r_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5RFFFT3hSbnlGaVU</link>
</figure>
 as heavy as before, and it should be like a paste not very thick, &amp;it must not be as easy to stir &amp; as a liquid. This state shows you that it is cooked enough. It must boil in the middle, &amp; all around you must have a thick mixture. If you reheat it too much your mixture would be short of body, because if it becomes red the mixture will lose its strength &amp; it will spoil the <m>sand</m>. Let it cool before mixing it to any other <m>sand</m>. <x>…</x></ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p107r_a1</id>
<head>Catching <m><al>lizards</al></m> and <m><al>snakes</al></m></head>


<ab>Take a stick, pin a net with a slipknot to the top. Whistle, and move the net nearer to the head of the lizard, and pull when it put it's head inside the net. It is more difficult to take a lizard with your hands than a snake, &amp; because lizards bite without letting go, &amp; bite as strong as pincers.</ab>


<ab>You can take snakes with your hand, but cover your handle with a woollen cloth, because the teeth of the snake could go through a common cloth. You can recognize dangerous snakes by their blue eyes. They do not bite into water, as it is known by <pro>crayfish catchers</pro>.</ab>


<ab>The <m>sand</m> mixture is made of two thirds of ground <m>plaster</m>, &amp; reheated as it is said before, &amp; of one part of reddened <m>tiles</m> which are finely ground afterwards. Use also <m>stone alum</m>, half of the quantity of the <m>tiles</m>. Use two full pots of <m>plaster</m>, one pot of <m>tile</m> &amp; half a pot of <m>stone alum</m>. Do not use too much <m>stone alum</m> because that binds the <m>sand</m>, and allow <m>sand</m> to withstand fire without cracking &amp; breaking. Without it <x><m>stone alum</m></x> <m>sand</m> would not withstand fire, you can use it for all kind of <m>metal</m>, but for <m>gold</m> add a bigger quantity of <m>stone alum</m>, &amp; add also <m>crocum ferri</m>, because they <x>these <m>filings</m></x> attract <m>gold</m>.</ab>


<ab>All the <m>sands</m> you will cast, must withstand fire very well, it must withstand high temperature without spoiling anything.</ab>


<ab>It is difficult to grind <m>stone alum</m>, and it cannot be sieved, you must grind it on a <m>marble</m> slab. The white <x><m>stone alum</m></x> powder the <pro>apothecaries</pro> sell is good, it is easy to crush it into a mortar, &amp; use the pestle slowly, that way you will make it <x>the <m>stone alum</m></x> very fine.</ab>


<ab><m>Crocum ferri</m> must be heated into a <pro>glassworker'</pro>s furnace during four days.</ab>
</div></root>