<root><page>107r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f219.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p106v_2</id>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<ab>
<figure>
<id>fig_p107r_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5RFFFT3hSbnlGaVU</link>
</figure>
 as heavy as before, and it should be like a paste not very thick, &amp;it must not be as easy to stir &amp; as a liquid. This state shows you that it is cooked enough. It must boil in the middle, &amp; all around you must have a thick mixture. If you reheat it too much your mixture would be short of body, because if it becomes red the mixture will lose its strength &amp; it will spoil the <m>sand</m>. Let it cool before mixing it to any other <m>sand</m>. <x>…</x></ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p107r_a1</id>
<head>Catching <m><al>lizards</al></m> and <m><al>snakes</al></m></head>


<ab>Take a stick and attach a string at the end, with has an <del>knot</del> <del>eyelet</del> <add>eyelet</add> that slips at the end. And, being two to three, to distract the lizard while whistling, approach him with the noose of the eyelet, and when he has his head inside, pull. The lizard is more tedious to catch by hand than the serpent &amp; bites without letting go &amp; grips like pincers.</ab>


<ab>Snakes can be caught by hand, provided that it is covered by a thick woollen cloth, for the teeth of the snake stay in the cloth, &amp; and cannot pierce like they would with a linen. The dangerous ones are recognisable by their blue eyes &amp; <del>asses</del> deep azur. They hardly ever bite in water, which crayfish catchers have experienced.</ab>


<ab>The <m>sand</m> mixture is of two thirds of <m>plaster</m>, pulverized &amp; reheated as it is said, &amp; one part of <m>tile</m>,  reddened <del>et p pre</del> <add>in a good fire</add>, after the first cooking &amp; then finely pulverized, and of <m><fr>alum de plume</fr></m>, half of brick, namely two full crucibles of plaster, one of brick &amp; a half of <fr>alum de plume</fr>. There can never be too much <fr>alum de plume</fr>,<del>s</del> for this is what gives bond to the sand, and because it does not burn, it makes sand withstand the fire without cracking and bursting.  Otherwise, without it, the sand would not withstand. This sand, thus composed, is appropriate for all metals, but if you want to use it for gold, it needs more <fr>alum de plume</fr> <del>&amp;</del>,than the above mentioned composition, and mix in some crocum ferri, and for it is this one that attracts gold.</ab>


<ab>It is necessary that all <m>sand</m> with which you want to cast, withstands the fire well, that is to say that it withstands <del>abon</del> <del>c</del> a great firing without getting spoiled.</ab>


<ab><fr>Alum de plume</fr> is troublesome to crush, and it does not pass through the sieve. Thusly one ought to grind it finely on <m>marble</m>. And the one, white <del>que v</del> in powder form, that <pro>apothecaries</pro> sell, is good. It is finely ground better <del>su</del> in the mortar by crushing &amp;dragging the <fr>pinon</fr>, thus you will render it very fine.</ab>


<ab><m>Crocum ferri</m> must be set ablaze in a <pro>glassworker</pro>’s furnace for four days.</ab>
</div></root>