<root><page>107v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f220.image</image>
 
<div>
<cont/>
<ab>Molds for fine things, like <m>wormwood</m> or something similar, can only be used once, dip the molds into <m>water</m> before breaking them. Things twice reheated are dissolve easily into <m>water</m>. If you don't do that your work will be hard to be stripped of the mold without being spoiled.</ab>


<ab>Good <m>stone alum</m> is white and as shiny as white silk, this <m>stone alum</m> is made of long pieces, as long as a finger, &amp; is very fragile &amp; woolly and fluffy. <m>Stone alum</m> made of <m>stone</m> is harder &amp; not so good. The best quality can be found in France near Ronan. For our <m>sand</m>, <m>stone alum</m> must be crushed into a mortar, and must be ground on the <m>marble</m> again. Don't even think about sieving it because this matter is fat &amp; woolly, it wouldn't pass through any sieve because of the very fine &amp; soft filaments. These filaments give the <m>sand</m> a much greater binding effect than natural <m>wool</m> or even the <m>filler</m> the <pro>foundry owner</pro> uses for big works, because natural <m>wool</m> &amp; <m>filler</m> burn and <m>stone feather alum</m> resists fire.</ab>
 
<ab>When you cast surround the <m>sand</m> of your mold with very beaten greasy <m>earth</m>. Make a circle &amp; around your mold with this <m>earth</m>.</ab>


<ab>Archanum omnibus fere reconditum est in re fusoria,<lb/>
v<exp>idelicet</exp> res exprimenda formis, sive <m>herba</m> sit sive <m>animal</m><lb/>
ut <m>lucerta</m>, inmergatur primum in <m>vini spiritum</m><lb/>
aprime rectificatum, deinde pulvere composito aspergatur<lb/>
sive illinatur (si pulvis in formam pultis redactus sit, ut<lb/>
assolet)</ab>
  
<ab>When you want to mold something hollow, the core must be made of the same matter, if the snake or the animal is curved or folded you must do your core in several pieces.</ab>
 
<ab>Try <x>to see</x> if distilled <m>vinegar</m> is good for eating away, &amp; it will dissolve the <m>animal</m> inside the hollow mold.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
If you know that your <m>plaster</m> cannot endure fire without breaking, do not take the recipe of the mixture literally, sometimes you can add less <m>stone alum</m> than above. Because <m>stone alum</m> soften molds. Once reheated do not grind the <m>stone alum</m> again, leave it ground as the <pro>apothecaries</pro> did. It will not prevent the cast from being neat, &amp; will give more binder to your cast. When the mold holds the color of the brick and is reddened then it will be harder.</ab>
</div></root>