<root><page>108r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f221.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<ab>To hold the cores, some <x>people</x> use <m>wire</m> made of the same <m>metal</m> as that to be cast because it boils down and is made similarly, but when it is melted or pliant the core varies. Other <x>people</x> find it serves them better to use sharpened <m>iron wire</m> about the borders because it holds more firmly, and having fine points it does not rise up any more than the point of a needle and one can apply <m>gold</m> or <m>silver</m> on this rather than putting it in works <x>where</x> one makes a hole in the work with a small chisel.</ab>
 
<ab><m>Spirits</m> prevent the sand from bubbling and do not make little holes on the borders of the mold if the thing to be molded is very damp, the holes and farts and bubbling does not make it in the place of the mold which is thick but at the borders which are more delicate.</ab>
 
<ab>One casts ordinary <m>silver</m> of the sort <pro>goldsmiths</pro> coarsely work, which is made with mediocre <m>alloys</m>. And when one casts with <m>solder</m>, it runs even better.</ab>
 
<ab><m>Spalt</m> is a whitish stone which can be found in Germany, mainly in Augsburg from which can be made the most excellent <m>sand</m> that can be found for <x>casting</x> <m>lead</m>, <m>tin</m>, <m>copper</m>, <m>silver</m> and <m>gold</m>. And the more it is used, the better it is. It is clean for casting flat things in a frame. For rounded things, it is not as attractive <x>because it</x> does not hold in the fire as the aforementioned <x>things</x> composed of <m>plaster</m>.</ab>
 
<ab>The snippings of <x>a</x> large <x>piece of</x> greasy <m>leather</m> are good to cast in melted <m>copper</m> and <m>brass</m> because they clean it and take away from it all its <m>filth</m>. </ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p108r_a1</id>
<head><m>Spalt</m></head>
 
<ab><m>Spalt</m> is white like cooked <m>plaster</m> and one can find it in mounds and stones made in long stairs and long veins. It is very soft such that with a fingernail and it makes a powder like that of our <m>chalk</m> from Champagne. And because everything which is provided from the <m>earth</m> is mixed with some other substance, to purify it <x>the spalt</x>, one boils it with somewhat large <m>gemstones</m> then tempers it with <m>essence of sal ammoniac</m>. One puts <x>a lump of it</x> the size of a walnut in a large bottle of <m>water</m> and</ab>
</div></root>