<root><page>111r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f227.image</image>


<div>
<id>p111r_a1</id>
<head>Reheating molds</head>


<ab>Box molds dry out readily, &amp; do not get reheated, because to reheat is properly to turn molds red and inflamed in the fire, and drying out is to let both molds dry, or make them evaporate their humidity, placing them before a fire of flames or one of charcoal. Molds de noyau reheat easily &amp; box molds dry out.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p111r_a2</id>
<head><m>Latten</m> <m>smoke</m></head>


<ab>
It is good to reheat molds for casting <m>latten</m> in it, because this yellow <m>chalk</m>, which appears nevertheless to refill the molds, casts very neatly, being of the same nature.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p111r_a3</id>
<head>For <m>red copper</m></head>


<ab>When it's melted, it is good to throw in a little fine <m>tin</m>, because this makes it run.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p111r_a4</id>
<head><m>Clay earth</m></head>


<ab>This, wet &amp; well beat &amp; kneaded as you know, is necessary for you to make the contour of your molds. But attend that it not be too soft. But likewise <x>attend that it be</x> sort of half dry such that it doesn't attack the hands at all, because otherwise it would attack your work. Always keep it in a damp place, and make some holes in it, and fill them with water, to keep it fresh.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The gray <x><m>earth</m></x> is best which does not cleave at all.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is neater than <ill/> of <m>lead</m>.</ab>


<figure>
<id>fig_p111r_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5X085N09VejNheTQ</link>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
</figure>
</div>

<div>
<id>p111r_a5</id>
<head><m>Iron</m> wire</head>


<ab>You have to be provisioned with different thicknesses according to the molds that you want to make, some large like packthread from <ill/> &amp; some thin, like the fat cords of a spinet, for small works. With it reheated, make clamps to close the molds &amp; make points like needles of various lengths according to your need, to fasten the animal to the mold &amp; hold it subject. Needles would not be good for this since your points must be hollow &amp; of the same thickness throughout, except at the point. And then you have to make them as long as you have need. <m>Iron</m> wire is harder than that of <m>latten</m>.</ab>
</div></root>