<root><page>112r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f229.image</image>


<div>
<id>p112r_1</id>
<head>To temper the <m>sand</m></head>


<ab>You should have: a large basin full of <m>water</m> to dip the molds into in order to open them, a tankard full of <m>common water</m>, a dish to temper the <m>sand</m>, a small <m>wooden</m> spoon to pick up the mixed <m>sand</m> in the dish.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
To make handles for your large oil brushes, if you do not have large enough <m>feather pipes</m>, take two of them, &amp; melt them &amp; join them together.</ab>


<figure>
<id>fig_p112r_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5MHphUzNsdW9DQ1U</link>
<margin>left-top</margin> 
</figure>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p112r_2</id>
<head>Decoction of <m>sands</m></head>


<ab>Already said</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p112r_3</id>
<head>Molding en noyau. Mixing of <m>sand</m></head>


<ab>Once you have reheated your <m>sand</m>, that is the <m>plaster</m>, the <m>stone alum</m> &amp; the <m>brick</m>, &amp; once you have finely filtered them through a <m>cloth</m> sieve, <figure>#</figure> mix them the following way: take four measures of <m>plaster</m>, two measures of <m>bricks</m>, &amp; one measure of <m>stone alum</m>. Mix them all together with the hands, so that one may not discern one <x>ingredient</x> from the other. Once your <m>sand</m> is ready, you need to kill the animal that you wish to mold in this way.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<figure>#</figure> except for the <m>stone alum</m> which should be ground in a mortar.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p112r_4</id>
<head>Killing the animal to mold</head>


<ab>You must have been careful not to hurt it while capturing it. If you have a stock <x>of animals</x> and you wish to keep them for a long time, place it in a <m>glass</m> bottle with <m>bran</m> or in a large barrel half full of damp &amp; fresh <m>earth</m>. Give them frogs to eat, live &amp; and not dead, because should you keep them without feeding them, they would wither &amp; become emaciated, &amp; their skin would become saggy and wrinkled. Therefore, the sooner after its capture you mold it, the better it will come out. And kill it in the following manner: place it in a clean bottle or vessel so that <x>the animal</x> does not carry any <m>dust</m>; fill <x>the bottle</x> with enough good <m>vinegar</m> &amp; <m>urine</m> so as to cover <x>the animal</x>. Shake <x>the bottle</x> &amp; torment <x>the animal</x> inside there until it is dead which should take an hour or half an hour. But if you are in a hurry</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
To know if <x>the animal</x> is quite dead, take it out of the <m>vinegar</m> and take it by the tail. If it moves its tail, do not mold it because it still has feelings, &amp; when pricking <x>its members</x>, it would remove itself &amp; harm the mold.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Water snakes do not bite much.</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>