<root><page>113v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f232.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>113r_1</id>
<ab>and this way, while heating it again, the two casts will dissolve. Therefore, have several dishes of various sizes with a pouring beak in order to cast better. In these, pour some regular <m>fountain <m>water</m> &amp; mix into it as much as an egg <figure>#</figure> can hold of <m>sal ammoniac water</m>, mixed as described. If you want to cast <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m> - because one would need more for casting <m>gold</m> &amp; <m>silver</m> - having the <m>water</m> in your dish, add the <m>sand</m> &amp; not the other way around <x>by adding the water to the sand</x>, &amp; adjust it with such attentiveness that, while mixing it vigorously &amp; wetting it quickly with a <m>wood</m>en</m> spoon, it does not become thicker than mustard.  And in such a way cast <x>i.e., pour</x> first the clearest part, as is always at the surface, by shaking it &amp; a little higher in your mold.  And doing so, since your animal is nearly covered, Once your animal is covered, blow on it very strongly to eliminate the small bubbles from your soaked <m>sand</m>. &amp; then pour immediately the rest which is at the bottom &amp; which is thicker than the upper part, fill your mold to the thickness mark you have made. <figure>
<id>fig_p113v_4</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bEE5QmFaQWxUYm8</link>
</figure> And while casting do not forget to shake your mold, that way your soaked sand runs &amp; get in through every parts. Also tip your mold up on the side of the head, which is higher than the body. That way the contents of your mold will have the same thickness, &amp; you'll spare <m>sand</m>. This being done with care, your <m>sand</m> will harden within a quarter of an hour. Then peel the <m>clay</m> contour which can be used later. Let it dry a little bit, &amp; separate your mold from the slab of earth, and you can mold properly straight after. Cut away the extra parts with a knife, and make it mandore shaped. You can reuse the <m>clay</m> frame. Scrape &amp; cut away what's on the back of the mold, because this part is the weakest; do not forget to make notches around it, that way the second cast would bind much better 
<figure>
<id>fig_p113v_5</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5V29QdUxZVmxCUDQ</link>
</figure> and would not move.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Your half mold, in one shot &amp; one mix is the best.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<figure>#</figure>
or two <m>eggs</m>, because there is no danger if there is more. If you cast twice, just add <m>sal ammoniac water</m> into the first pouring.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Make your mixture as clear as a pureed broth, or <m>starch water</m>, the one women use make their <m>starch</m>. It is not a problem if the mixture is very thin because sand settles in the bottom &amp; <m>water</m> stays on top of it, which we scape as too weak &amp; soft. It will not take long to harden, because burned things dry rapidly.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<figure>
<id>fig_p113v_3</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dEdzS040X3RjbkU</link>
</figure>
If you don't fill your mold with soaked <m>sand</m> at one go, do mix your second cast with the top part of the first cast, stir with a spoon, or the stick you had took to soak your sand.</ab>


<ab>You do not need to add <m>sal ammoniac water</m> if you cast small molds which do not need to be reheated too long. However it is better to add some.</ab>
</div></root>