<root><page>114v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f234.image</image>


<figure>
<id>fig_p114v_1</id>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dmlRQm1lTjc4aXc</link>
</figure>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p114r_1</id>
<ab>This thus prepared, put your first half-mold on the disc of <m>clay</m>, &amp; surround it with <sup>a clay</sup> circle &amp; do a thickness mark similar to the first one. Then, with a rather thick brush, wet with <m>spirits</m> all your animal's exposed half, without, if possible, missing any part, because therein lies the secret to casting neatly. Then, as fast as possible before the <m>spirits</m> evaporate, soak your sand, and cast it, shaking, blowing, &amp; moving the mold, as you did for the first one, making sure that what you pour first on the animal is clearer than the rest, so that it is soaked everywhere &amp; highlights the finer parts. So, leave it for fifteen minutes so it sets, then remove the <m>clay</m> circle &amp; disc. And, with a knife, join you two molds together in a longish form, like a mandore, as we say, because of how you cast. Then soak a little in <m>water</m> the whole mold up to the level of the joints. Because this is another secret to separate them <sup>more easily</sup>. Otherwise, you would break everything. Separate them like this skillfully. After this, gently &amp; patiently remove half of the animal still in the mold, pulling it sometimes on one side &amp; sometimes on the other, in order to avoid breaking it, or ruining parts of the mold. The mold, being empty, rejoin both half so that no dust comes in, &amp; put them aside until you want to heat them up, make the runners, &amp; the vents &amp; put the clamps. As for the animal, to avoid it drying, &amp; in order to be be able to use it to mold 4 or 5 of times, put it on <m>water</m>. I believe that it would be better preserved in <m>spirits</m>. However, it would be best to make the 4 or 5 molds the same day because these animals rot and 
will smell within the day. Having left your molds to dry out, for they will stay humid for at least a month, make the vents for one half. <figure>
<id>fig_p114v_3</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dkk3MW10YzNIbDg</link>
</figure></ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<figure>+</figure> Note that once you have made your second casting, if you left your mold without opening it for a day or a night, you would then need to put it into hot <m>water</m> or reheat it, rather than open it, like for the <al>crab</al>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
If after both halfs of the noyau have set &amp; hardened, it would not open if you did not dip it into <m>water</m>. But as you dip the back of your mold into <m>water</m>, <m>oil</m> comes back to the top &amp; touches the joints &amp; separates them.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
However, be sure that your second mold is thick enough, &amp; hard enough otherwise it could break while dipping it into <m>water</m> &amp; if you want to open it. To avoid this mistake dip the entire mold into <m>water</m> rub it everywhere, if the mold has set enough it will harden. Then take both molds with a rough cloth, in order to grip it better. Then strongly separate the molds as if you wanted to tear <m>bread</m> apart. But in case it breaks, rejoin them, &amp; fortifies the joints with clamps.
<figure>
<id>fig_p114v_4</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NmZxVUxKTmhYSXM</link>
</figure>
</ab>


<ab>
<margin>bottom</margin>
Afterwards you can repair the mistakes with a small pair of scissors.
<cont/>
</ab>
</div></root>