<root><page>117r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f239.image</image>


<div>
<id>p117r_a1</id>
<head>A way to mold <pa>flower</pa>s and <pa>herb</pa>s</head>


<ab>It is necessary to pick them in full bloom and color, and only pick them, if it is possible, when you are ready to mold them so that they will not wilt. Or if you need to carry them from afar, put their stems in a bottle of <m>water</m>, or even better in <m>wine</m>. Start with making a <m>wax</m> stick pointed like a big peg, of a size adapted to what you want to cast, as you see in the margin, marked A. At the bottom of this peg, put and prick a bit of <m>iron</m> wire, rather thick and strong. And at the pointed end of the big peg, you will fit your <pa>flower</pa> stem or your <pa>herb</pa>.  This done, set it aside.  Arrange your <m>clay</m> circle and outline as you did for the <al>snake</al>s, in the shape of a <mu>mandore</mu> according to the size of your <pa>herb</pa>. Then take the <pa>herb</pa> you have prepared to be cast, as we have taught you, and wet and moisten it daintily with good <m>spirits</m> with a <tl>brush</tl>. Then place the wire end through through the end of the <m>earthen</m> mold, shaped like a <mu>mandore</mu>, so that the <m>wax</m> peg, where the <pa>herb</pa> is, touches the edge of the <m>earthen</m> <mu>mandore</mu>. And arrange your <pa>herb</pa> that lies thusly so that it remains in the middle of said <mu>mandore</mu>-shaped mold, without touching any of the side. So that the sand that you put in the mold will be of equal thickness everywhere, and will be two <ms>finger</ms>s higher than your <pa>flower</pa>. And having made sure that the wire is secure, quickly throw your <m>wet sand</m> that will be much clearer than the one used for serpents, in the <mu>mandore</mu>-shaped mold, and the quicker the better, so that your <m>spirits</m> do not evaporate.  And adjust your mixture with a bit of <m>essence of sal ammoniac</m>, unlike the one for serpents.  And when you make sand especially for casting your bouquets, mix in a bit of <m>feather alum</m>, this will only make it better. In this way, your mold will be in one piece and it will not be necessary to separate it, but you will have to separate it from the <m>clay</m> once it will have set.  Let it dry. And then fire it again until the herbs are burnt. Note that if the herb you want to cast has a strong stalk and stem, you can cast it lying down, as said. But if it is fine and delicate, plant up standing up with the <m>wax</m> peg  so that the sand will always raise it up, it being very clear.  Do not forget to arrange two vent holes with two small <tl>stick</tl>s, which will start at the bottom of the cast, which is the pointed end of the <m>wax</m> peg.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
If the <pa>flower</pa>s are so delicate that they come off the top when you are putting in the <m>wet sand</m>, you can stop this and curtail it with a <m>net</m> sewed onto the mold with a <tl>needle</tl>.</ab>




<figure>
<id>fig_p117r_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5WnpBbm8wN2gyTWs</link>
<margin>left-top</margin>
</figure>


<figure>
<id>fig_p117r_2</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5VURRYzlWOFByNzQ</link>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
</figure>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The more delicate the <pa>flower</pa> is, the clearer the sand must be.</ab>
 
<figure>
<id>fig_p117r_3</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dVB5bzVUWWJuS0U</link>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
</figure>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
This is a core mold.</ab>
</div></root>