<root><page>118r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f241.image</image>


<div>
<id>p118r_a1</id>
<head><al>Snails</al></head>


<ab>Those which are found in the <env>ocean</env> and similarly those in which certain small crabs dwell are very beautiful for grottoes, if they have been rid of the first layer of their shell with <m><la>aqua fortis</la></m>, because they really look to be made of <m>mother-of-pearl</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p118r_a2</id>
<head>For removing flaws and flashing from things <tl>molded</tl> in a <tl>core mold</tl></head>


<ab>If your <tl>molds</tl> are made of good <m>plaster</m> which withstands fire, they will not crack, especially if they are squeezed well between two tables with <tl>presses</tl> or in a <tl>pot</tl> filled with <m>ashes</m> or sand, and, therefore, they will not develop flaws. If they they develop some <sup>flaws</sup>, you can remove them with a <tl>burin</tl> called <fr><tl>chaple</tl></fr> which has a tip like a small <tl>chisel</tl>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The old <pa>vine</pa> stocks</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p118r_a3</id>
<head>For grottoes</head>


<ab><m>Stone</m>s made from water called <m>stuf</m>; <m>charcoal</m>; the confection of <m>tin</m> and pure <m>brass</m>; <m>paper</m> ground up and mixed with ground up <m>glass</m>; <m>cork</m>; <m>heated parchment</m>, <sup>and</sup> <m>white coral</m>, all of them are appropriate for making grottoes. But, once dry, bizarre pieces of <m>wood</m>, which [the bizarre pieces of wood] are found in the forests and among <sup>regular</sup> mushrooms and <fr><pa>potirons</pa></fr> <sup>growing on</sup> trees, are better than all of them because they are light. Mix in with small pieces of <m>looking-glass tin</m> which have a shiny luster. Grind in a little of a different kind of <m>marcasite</m> in order to clean the <m>earth</m> away, then powder the work, which is very beautiful. If there is no spring in the grotto, glue all of this with strong <m>glue</m>, and then the work is done. You must show all kinds of <m>mines</m>. The <m>sulfurous marcasites</m> which do not have a grain but are even like <m>looking-glass tin</m> are very beautiful.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<m>Red copper</m> is found sometimes mixed with certain brittle lumps which are pulverized under the <tl>hammer</tl>, which are very beautiful pulverized on grottoes.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p118r_a4</id>
<head><m>Looking-glass tin</m></head>


<ab>If one ounce of <sup><m>looking-glass tin</m></sup> is put in with it <sup>pure <m>tin</m></sup>, pure <m>tin</m> whitens and becomes firm, that is, i <figure>℥</figure> of <m>looking-glass tin</m> in one <ms>lb</ms> of pure <m>tin</m>.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p118r_a5</id>
<head><m>Salt ammoniac</m></head>


<ab><m>Salt ammoniac water</m> is naturally quite good for <tl>casting</tl> in <m>gold</m> and in <m>silver</m>.</ab>
</div></root>