<root><page>120v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f246.image</image>


<div>
<id>p120r_3</id>
<ab>eat by itself. And so that he likes it better, you can add to the meat and the egg some mealworm, because nightingales love them.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p120v_1</id>
<head><m>Crocum ferri</m></head>


<ab>It is excellent applied to wounds to stop the bleeding. The best one is made of <m>needle filings</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<m>Crocum ferri</m> hardens moulds that have been reheated, the more <m>feather alum</m> is added, the softer and pliant they become.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p120v_2</id>
<head>Anatomy</head>


<ab>You must skin the animal and boil it. Or skin it and put it into <m>quicklime</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p120v_3</id>
<head>Making <m>silver</m> runny</head>


<ab>If it is for a large work, <m>arsenic</m> and pulverized <m>tartar</m> thrown into melted <m>silver</m>, makes the <m>silver</m> runny. This is enough <x>for silver.</x>  But for subtle work, you need <m>bronze, filings, copper,</m> even <m>antimony</m>, <m>sublimate</m>, all neatly ground. All of this makes a mass that does not get smaller.  If the <m>plaster</m> is good, you do not need to add <m>crocum</m> for <m>silver</m>, but one puts in more <m>feather alum</m>. It is also necessary to add melted <m>common salt</m>, and some <m>saltpeter</m> and the aforementioned drugs: <m>arsenic, tartar, bronze, copper filings, antimony</m> &amp;</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<la>S<sup>c</sup>iscitatio dubia</la></ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
A bit of <m>tallow</m>, and some <m>arsenic</m>.</ab>


<figure/>


</div>
<div>
<id>p120v_5</id>

<figure><margin>left-middle</margin>+</figure>


<ab>See the second folio following <x>this</x></ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>
Flowers can also be kept in their same beauty in distilled <m>vinegar</m> in a vase, well-sealed so it takes no draft, well-sealed with <m>wax</m> and <m>mastic</m>. Carnations and roses, the residue of common <m>vinegar</m> makes them rot.  If the <m>sand</m> makes dust, and sticks to the flowers and hardly comes off with a brush, it is no good. The most lean is the best.</ab>


</div>


<div>
<id>p120v_6</id>




<head>Keeping dried flowers in the same condition all year</head>


<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
<m>River sand</m>, that is washed by the current of water, is good when strained in a cloth to make the powder compact.</ab>


<ab>This is a rare secret, and which is pleasing for decorating tables, rooms, studies out of season when winter denies you flowers. Be advised to pick them when they are in full vigor and still growing, because if you take them when no longer in bloom or when they are starting to wilt, they will not keep.  Having therefore chosen them, take some <m>sand</m>, the leanest and driest you can find, that must be very well ground, like the one <pro>goldsmiths</pro> use to sand <m>enamel</m>, or like the one <x>used</x> for engraving. But this <m>sand</m> must not be dusty at all, nor must it stay on your hand or leave a trace when you have ground or poured it, because it is</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<figure>+</figure>
Make sure your box is well sealed so that the <m>sand</m> does not get out. Keep it uncovered in sunlight and keep it away from the evening dew, and the moisture of the night, and cover it and keep it in a dry place.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
You can not put these aforementioned flowers in big vases, because if you want to take one out, you will take the whole bunch with it. </ab>


<ab>
<margin>bottom</margin>
Be advised to not pick your flowers when it is rainy or humid, but when the sun has been shining on them.</ab>




<cont/>
</div></root>