<root><page>0121r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f248.item</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p0120v_4</id>
<ab>a sign that there is some humidity, and if the flower was also somewhat watery it would rot. Nor should it be <del/> too rough, because its weight would burden the flower and make it lose its original shape. Once you have chosen it as needed, take a <tl>box</tl> and inside this start by making a small mound of sand on top of which you will lay the stalk of the flower flat, so that the flower touches neither the bottom nor the edges of the <tl>box</tl> but remains in the air. Then add more <del/> sand on the stalk so that it remains firm and fixed. Finally take some of the same sand and pulverize and sprinkle it finely with two <tl><bp>fingers</bp></tl> on the flower, imitating the flow of an <ms><tl>hourglass</tl></ms>. And once the flower is <del/> half covered or so, strike with your <bp><tl>fist</tl></bp> the table on which the <tl>box</tl> is laid, so that the sand drops and enters everywhere. Finally cover the entire flower and lay other flowers in order, one over the other, as many as the <tl>box</tl> will hold. After you have arranged them thus, put the <tl>box</tl> out in <env>hot sun</env> for <ms><tmp>several days</tmp></ms>. And while the flower is drying, the sand that is packed together, by continuously holding it, does not allow it to shrivel and shrink. On the contrary, it needs to dry remaining in the same state as when you put it there. But to that effect take care you chose <pa>knapweed</pa>s, <pa>marigold</pa>s, the <pa>yellow meadow flowers</pa> called <la><pa>ranunculus</pa></la> or <la><pa>palta lupina</pa></la>, <pa>amaranth</pa>s, and similar flowers, such as <pa>broom</pa> and others that you will know from experience.</ab>
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
The sand that <pro>goldsmith</pro>s use to rub <m>enamel</m>s and the white one that <pro>glassworker</pro>s use and any thin sand that does not set, you put through a <tl>sieve</tl> made of <m>horsehair</m> because it needs not be too thin. Then dry the sand well in the <env>sun</env> for <ms><tmp>several days</tmp></ms> in order to remove its humidity, and ventilate it as you would do with <m>wheat</m> so that the dust becomes separated from it. After taking that dust, well dried, use it as you know.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<pa>Pansies</pa> are preserved in the same way.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p121r_1</id>
<head>Keeping fruits throughout the <ms><tmp>year</tmp></ms></head>


<ab>You need to pick them in calm and quite dry weather &amp; by the stem, without <sn>touching</sn> the fruits with your <bp>hand</bp>, and to put them into <tl><m>glass</m> bottles</tl> that have wide necks, such as tall <m>glass</m> <tl>jars</tl> for preserves. Protect them with <m>straw</m> or something else so that they may not break, and seal them well with <m>wax</m> so that they may not breathe. And if they have <m>glass</m> lids well sealed with <m>wax</m>, it will be all the better. Put them in a <tl>case</tl> and put this in the <env>well</env>, or in the <env>cellar</env>, or in a vat or plot of <m>earth</m> full of <m>water</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Because wherever the <bp>hand</bp> <sn>touches</sn> them they will rot, and it is even best not to breathe on them. You can also put <m>vine leaves</m> with them.</ab>
</div></root>