<root><page>122r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f249.item.r=</image>


<div>
<id>p122r_1</id>
<head>Fixing different animals</head>


<ab>When you discover some twisted <al>lizard</al>s which bite each other are the most difficult thing to mold because of the number of their feet and because of the tip of their tail which are very fine, steady the parts which are uncovered and which look like suspended in mid air, that way the second cast will not vary anything. If you need to steady the parts hanging in mid air, take a bit of <m>wax</m>, rub it and elongate it on a <tl>table</tl>, make it big needle shaped, then cut the part you need with a hot <tl><m>iron</m> wire</tl> then join where it is necessary. Steady also the part which does not stick to the <tl>mould</tl> (when you uncover the half of the womb) with some <m>wax</m> with the point of a <tl>knife</tl> @, joined and melted with the <tl>wire</tl>. When you cast, pour only to the spot and at the edge of the <m>wax</m> which being attached to the animal will melt but still lead the cast towards it without damaging anything. This is a secret.</ab>


<figure>
<id>fig_p122r_2</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5TVo3Y3lKWjA0dXM</link>
</figure>


<ab>One can arrange embracing <al>snake</al>s, but only small ones.</ab></div>




 <div>
<id>p122r_2</id>
<head>Flower in the mouth of a <al>snake</al></head>


<ab>If you want to put a flower in the mouth of a <al>snake</al> or a branch of a herb which guards against its bite, take the best arranged little branch you can find, and display its stalk into its mouth. Then put <ms>two little pieces of <m>wax</m></ms> around the stalk of the herb. Melt a bit of <m>wax</m> with the point of a warm <tl><m>iron</m> wire</tl>, while you are closing the jaws of the animal with your <bp>hand</bp>. And then you can cut the head to make it burn with the flower. If the herb is strong enough, it will stay in the same position by itself but if the flower is light, like <pa>wormwood</pa>, which droops, the dampness of the sand will lift it up, make it swim and stand by itself, without any support, as well as if you had put some <m>thread</m> under it passing through with a <tl>needle</tl>.</ab>


<figure>
<id>fig_p122r_1</id>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5ZDJlZ0g5OXNKeDQ</link>
</figure>


<del>
<figure>
<id>fig_p122r_3</id>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5UDgyYnNSZnlndjg</link>
</figure>
</del>


<del>
<figure>
<id>fig_p122r_4</id>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5elo4VzJZRUppOWc</link>
</figure>
</del>
</div></root>