<root><page>125r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f255.item.r</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p124v_3</id>


<ab>and with your pipes and abrevouers @, you can also place small threads of <m>wax</m> which are applied to the body so that the <m>metal</m> goes more easily from one part to another and runs quickly throughout. And with these pipes, you can guide
your cast and your vents without having ruined anything.</ab> 


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<figure>
<id>fig_p125r_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5ZHJJRXJlU2RFZlk</link>
</figure>
small rolls, you make your casts and vents without danger of chipping or [...] any of the mold because the <m>wax</m>, once it has been removed, leaves a thoroughly empty place. Make your vents proceed from the head [of the cast], which is at the bottom, towards the cast. Make your cast so that it is not thick, and make two or three notches inside the passage because this impairs the <m>metal</m> fury. And it makes it flow easily without filling with bubbles, [and] it does not make too much smoke which dams up the passage. You can also divide it into two or three branches thusly 
<figure>
<id>fig_p125r_2</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bDlqQzJZemktSFk</link>
</figure>
when it [...] with the molded thing, and always make holes in the cast.</ab>


<figure>+</figure>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p125r_a1</id>
<head><m>Plaster</m></head>


<ab>When you mold something in order to cast with <m>wax</m>, first mold only <m>plaster</m>, you mold with <m>plaster</m> [that is] only reheated after [it] has been pulverized. Because, once [it] has been reheated on the <m>stone</m> slab, the outside is burnt, and the inside remains nearly unburnt. Transparent grey <m>plaster</m> is not strong, but the good one [<m>plaster</m>] becomes white once it has been soaked, and [it] sets well quickly. Nevertheless I have found the grey [<m>plaster</m>] to be quite firm and hard after it has set, but it takes longer [to work with it]. Know the nature of each. You will never mold very neatly if you do not soak until it is quite clear and liquid, your <m>plaster</m> or the core's <m>sand</m>. Soak it straight away after it has been reheated.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
However, if you mold with <m>plaster</m> that has been reheated once as said, coat the first mold well with <m>oil</m>. And when the second cast has set and you have prepared it, soak it in <m>water</m> for a long time. And if it does not release, soak it in hot <m>water</m>, because cold <m>water</m> hardens it.</ab>
 
<ab>[Something] to know</ab>


<ab>And hot <m>water</m> softens it [<m>plaster</m>] more than cold <m>water</m> [which] does not penetrate it [<m>plaster</m>] as [it does] <m>mixed</m> <m>plaster</m> because it [<m>plaster</m>] is stronger and <m>mixed plaster</m> is spongier. <m>Medal</m>s are cast from this <m>powder</m>ed, reheated <m>plaster</m>, [and the <m>medal</m>s] will be waterproof as though they were <m>varnish</m>ed. In Germany, people hang these <m>medal</m>s on houses. See to it that the <m>water</m> is very hot, and if the <m>water</m> is boiling, it will not endanger [it]. All molds [made] of plaster only or molds [made of] <m>mixed</m> <m>plaster</m> are stripped from it.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p125r_a2</id>
<head>Scimitars</head>


<ab><pro>Workers</pro> from Damascus or from Hungary, neighbors to the Turks, separate <m>iron</m> from the <m>mine</m>s with <m>steel</m>. And they cast the blades of the scimitar in <m>sand</m> with this first <m>steel</m> [that was] first casted from its <m>mine</m>. Afterwards, they [the blades] cut other <m>iron</m> without without great difficulty because all melted <m>iron</m> is harder than soft <m>iron</m> beaten into [...] and bars. Thus is the <m>steel</m> of scimitars, but it is quite brittle. When someone takes the haft of a scimitar off, that person recognizes [it] well by the tip in the haft which is cast in <m>sand</m>.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p125r_a3</id>
<head>Hearing from afar</head>


<ab>Make a small hole into the ground, put your ear against it during the night or during an equally quiet time, and you will easily hear the muffled sound.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p125r_a4</id>
<head>Secret</head>
</div></root>