<root><page>128r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f261.image</image>




<div>
<id>p128r_1</id>
<head>Casting with <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m></head>


<ab>
To cast <m>silver</m> and <m>gold</m> do always put a little ground stone of <m>borax</m> on the bottom of the crucible, and put your matter on it. That way the acid <m>smoke</m> won't corrupt these two matters, but it is especially efficient for <m>gold</m>.</ab>


<ab>
If you have several molds to cast, do not fill them all in one cast, because <m>metal</m> would get cold. Cast one after another.</ab>
 
<ab>
When your mold start being red inside, look at the cast, if you do not see any black spot keep the same heat, and if needed, add a few half lighted <m>charcoals</m> with the help of pliers. However, put ground <m>borax</m> at the bottom of the crucible, and put <m>silver</m> on the top of this matter, then put your crucible into the forge, reheat your crucible which is between lighted <m>charcoals</m>, until it becomes red; do not blow before that. When you'll use the bellows, make continuous longitudinal moves, tug a little bit the bellows, push and pull, that way the heat will become greater. From time to time remove your crucible out of the top of the forge with the help of your warm pliers, because if your crucible is close to the tuyere <m>silver</m> would cool down rather than heat up. That why it is better to put the lighted <m>charcoals</m> above the tuelle, three fingers far from the wall of the forge. That way the crucible is heating much better. When your <m>silver</m> starts melting, if you find that it is too acid by noticing that the lumps are cracking and bursting, take the size of a walnut of  <m>arsenic</m>, and twice as much of <m>crude tartar</m> which is coarsely ground, that way it will heat better. Pour some of this mixture on <m>silver</m> in the crucible, it will get clearer. But if you have some of that sublimate crust on the <m>metallic matter</m>, and which looks like grains of <m>steel</m>, <figure>#</figure> put some of this matter in your melted <m>silver</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>right-top</margin> 
Some people leave the silver to rest a little out of the heat before casting.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin> 


<m>silver</m> and <m>gold</m> which are melted with the above matters won't become porous.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>  
For <m>gold</m>, you need not as much <m>crocum</m> as <m>stone alum</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin> 
Small molds can be reheated soon. But you should oven-dry large and small molds because dampness go out of the mold with the heat. The intense heat of <m>charcoals</m> drives the heat from within outside.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>  
All <m>silver alloy</m> make chape and all other metals too. </ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin> 
<m>Silver</m> should not be peeled off when <x>still</x> molten.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin> 
<figure>#</figure> Coarsely powdered.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>bottom</margin>  
Lumps of deteriorated <m>silver</m> vitrify red because of <m>arsenic</m> and <m>orpiment</m>.</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>