<root><page>130r</page>


<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f265.item.r=</image>


<div>
<id>p130r_1</id>
<head>Drying animals in an oven</head>


<ab>One can skin small <al>cats</al> and remove their eyes and all their guts. Then place a small stick vertically between the teeth in order to open their mouths. Then with <m>iron nails</m> one should attach their feet to a small board, arrange the required position. Once they are tied by their feet with small <m>iron rings</m>, one has to hang them upside down into the sun. By doing so, they will get the right shape and dry, the belly will tighten and the the tail will remain high up thanks to the twist that you made. Once they are already a bit dry, one may twist the head as he wishes and secure the position with any tool. One may finish to dry the animal by placing it in an oven once the bread has been taken off. Then place some realistically painted <m>lead</m> balls or <m>wax</m> balls in the eye-sockets. One should paint them with <m>gummed ink</m> so that they look like jet. One can add a painted tongue, or horns, or wings or anything you may imagine, same goes for <al>rats</al> or any animal.</ab></div>
 
<div>
<id>p130r_2</id>
<head>Reddening lively <al>crayfish</al> which will look as if they were boiled</head>


<ab>Rub your <al>crayfish</al> with good <m>vinegar</m> diluted with a little <m>eau-de-vie</m> and not much, then you can present them as if they were cooked and yet they will walk.</ab></div>
 
<div>
<id>p130r_3</id>
<head>Molding a single <al>spider</al></head>


<ab>One has to display it on the jacket of <m>clay</m> as it is said for the <m>vine leaf</m>. Then do the first cast. And once it dry, peel the mold off to the middle of the legs and do the second cast.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p130r_4</id>
<head>Molding a single <m>vine leaf</m></head>


<ab>Attach it with <m>brass</m> wire points on the jacket of <m>clay</m> and then cast the first mold. Once it is dry peel off the back side and make the second cast. Then peel away the back side, and make your second cast. Once it is dry, you may remove the leaf. You must heat your mold only once, because there is nothing to be burnt inside.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<figure>
<id>fig_p130r</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5cHVsNnNVQ1l5RnM</link>
</figure>
which surround the fingers of the paws and which stick in the jacket of <m>clay</m>.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Also. One cannot mold the hairy legs of big <al>spiders</al> or any other hairy animal if they had not been rubbed with <m>wheat oil</m> before they are laid flat. This will make the <m>hair</m> firmer and will dry very quickly.  Hairy things entangle in the  sand, and do not burn very well.</ab>
</div></root>