<root><page>131v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f268.item.r=</image>




<div>
<cont/>
<id>p131r_5</id>


<ab>to be cast with <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m>. Do not add to your wax all the drugs you are preparing, but only melted <m>sulphur</m>, as the candle melts, and also <m>candle smoke</m>. Melted <m>sulphur</m> falls down to the bottom of your mold, but lets the <m>wax</m> keeps some of its quality, melting it but leaving it a little firm. You can thus melt your <m>wax</m> representation on fire. If your wax is composed of <m>cerussite</m> or something similar, you need to put your mold into boiling water.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
You don't need all this to mold flat representations made of <m>wax</m>, because the <m>wax</m> can be removed completely from the mold, and won't remain inside it.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p131v_1</id>
<head>When <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m> casts fill with bubbles</head>


<ab> 
If your casted work became porous, it can be repaired with very firm wax, and you can gild  or silver it afterwards. If you cast fine, the alloy of one ℥ of <m>lead</m> to one lb of tin is good. But if you cast with <m>lead</m><add><del>[ligue <ill/>]</del></add>, indeed you need one lb of <m>lead</m> to two ℥ of tin, because lead is fat and sticky, goes over the alloy. I have cast a very small lizard that way. If you cast something thick, which keep the heat for a long time, it will make bubble if there is not enough <m>tin</m>. Your mold should not be cold, but cool enough that you can hold it without burning your hand, or that you can hold your finger into the cast without burning yourself. Your <m>tin</m> or <m>lead</m> must be like red. Cast your lead first, then cast tin. When you are going to cast, add a piece of <m>resin</m> to your mixture, then a little <m>looking-glass tin</m>. If you add too much <m>lead</m> to your <m>tin</m>, the mixture wouldn't be fluid enough. To know [the right proportion], If <m>tin</m> cries loudly, it means that there is not too much <m>lead</m>; if <m>tin</m> cries softly, it means that you added too much <m>lead</m>. Be wary</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
You can solder with the same matter, then rework it and [remove away all the unwanted thick parts] with a burin.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>

<m>Tin</m> is a metal that can[…], makes bubbles and burn, and more capricious to work with than <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m>.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<m>Lead</m> must not be only red, it must be quick, and as liquid as water, which is a sign of its perfect heat. Your mold must be so hot that you couldn't bear to put your finger into it. Do not open your mold until is has cooled down. Just as for <m>silver</m> and <m>gold</m>, it is a sign of good casting when <m>lead</m> comes out through the vent holes.</ab>


<cont/>
</div></root>