<root><page>133r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f271.image</image>


<div>
<id>p133r_1</id>
 
<head>Hard <m>wax</m> to imprint seals</head>
 
<ab>One makes these [seals] out of white <m>wax</m> which is harder than the other and one mixes in it some <m>cerussite</m> or <m>leaded white</m> very finely ground such that it is as hard as you like and mix in a drop of <m>turpentine</m> to bind it. Afterwards mix it in the color that you want. It is in <m>wax</m> that serves <pro>goldsmiths</pro> for modeling.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p133r_2</id>
 
<head>Casting the feet of small <al>lizards</al> in <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m></head>
 
<ab>Because the feet of these <al>[lizards]</al> that are very small are [also] very fine, once you have molded the top and you have uncover the vents and underneath the feet are  covered lightly with <m>wax</m>, and then cast a second mold. And the <m>wax</m> that one removes, it leaves a little cast for these said feet, and again such that the underneath [part] comes out in one piece that you can repair well, And the scales on top of the toes come [out] well.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Around the big <al>lizard</al> nails, put on each a small round of <m>wax</m> to make the cast like this.</ab>
 
<figure>
<id>fig_p133r_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5V2JZcWtNeEJmYWs</link>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
</figure>
</div>
<div>
<id>p133r_3</id>
 
<head>Marks [made by] the [pin] points of <m>iron</m> thread which one finds on the head of an animal</head>
 
<ab>With the points [or pins] with which you have dressed [your animal] all over, do same with the head, but [out of] the head which is pierced, a certain moisture seeps out around the wound and this little exudation prevents the sand from covering the point well and there always remain little pinpricks. But to avoid this, you can plant in the <m>plaster</m> of the said blunt pin point and around the upper part of the point, and over this point, there put a little hard <m>wax</m> or a little <m>mastic</m> or <m>cement</m>. And by the medium of the hot thread of <m>iron</m> there you can hold the throat of the animal which one removes [the <m>iron</m>] when you come to uncover the vents and the throat for doing the second cast.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p133r_4</id>
 
<head>Clamps and the broken mold</head>
 
<ab>When you have done the first firing and taken off the clamps and you have opened your mold to clean it by taking off the bubbles with <m>quicksilver</m> which one cannot do with closed molds, reclose the mold and reattach the clamps but not in the same place as the first time. Reapply lute and dry it but if this is for casting <m>silver</m> or <m>gold</m> [use] lute with the rest of sand which has been used because this is the best netting. If your mold is broken in refiring you can augment it with clamps and lute.</ab>
<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<figure>X</figure>
</ab>
</div></root>