<root><page>134v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f274.image</image>


<div>
<id>p134v_1</id>


<head>
To make <m>gold</m> fluid </head>


<ab>
Put as much <m>verdigris</m> as <m>sal ammoniac</m>, as much <m>borax</m> as <m>saltpeter</m>. But don't add a greater quantity of <m>borax</m> and <m>saltpeter</m> than half the quantity of <m>verdegris</m> and <m>sal ammoniac</m>, in fact add as much <m>borax</m> and <m>saltpetre</m> all together as <m>verdigris</m>. Grind into powder the ingredients on the <m>marble</m> slab, then grind again with very good <m>vinegar</m> until it is very fine, like a ground color, grind <m>verdigris</m> with <m>oil</m>, then leave to dry if you have time, if you haven't so much time dry it with the fire of the forge, make so that it is very dry.</ab>


<man>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Grind</man>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
One of the principal things for casting is to cast very hot, especially large metals</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p134v_2</id>


<head>
Casting big works with <m>gold</m></head>


<ab>
Not only should one clamp the mold very well, but also strengthen it with good iron wire links or adequate straps.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Before casting with gold, clean thoroughly your forge with <m>lead</m> and <m>tin</m>.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p134v_3</id>


<head>Secret for soldering small works made of <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m></head>


<ab>
If some little pieces of legs cannot be easily removed from <m>gold</m> or <m>silver</m> casting, it is because you didn't cast <m>wax</m> under these parts. Beat some soldering <m>gold</m> very finely, then cut it into very fine flakes, cut the quantity you need. Take some of this phlegm or white and thick <m>saliva</m> which is on the teeth, put some of this matter to the place you want to solder with the point of a burin, then place your flakes, then put to the opposite part a mixture made of a small quantity of soaked fat <m>earth</m>and <m>saliva</m>, thanks to the mixture the solder will better adhere. Then pulverize a bit of <m>borax</m> on it, and heat up <m>Quince pulp seed water</m> to a boil and others too.</ab>
</div></root>