<root><page>135r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f275.item.r=</image>


<div>
<id>p135r_1</id>
<head>Colors for <m>gold</m>, or sauce</head>


<ab>
Take as much <m>verdigris</m> as <m>sal ammoniac</m>, &amp; <m>saltpetre</m> the size of a bean. Because if you put in too much, it would make the whole thing boil so much that it would all pour out. <m>Saltpeter</m> is only put in to make it boil, so that you know when the material has boiled enough. This color put on sour melted <m>gold</m> makes it soft instantly.</ab>


<margin>left-top</margin>
<head>Softening <m>gold</m></head>
</div>


<div>
<id>p135r_2</id>
<head>Casting</head>


<ab>
It must be lengthened out with respect to the thing you have molded. And at a minimum for large molds it must be four or five fingers in length. You can make it large enough for half the mold &amp; then divide it in three points of such a sort, and so the molded things will <x>each</x> be small. But your points must be small. And in the middle of the casting &amp; of its points, make some holes to impede the fury of the <m>metal</m> &amp; make it run more softly. It is also necessary to fix the bent parts of the animal with little notched lines, and similarly the end of the tail and other fine parts so that the <m>metal</m> goes throughout &amp; flows from one part to the other.</ab>


<ab>
Do not forget to make a wax cast of the paws of <ill/> &amp; things as subtle as this.</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
When you have molded an animal in the first part of the mold, do not let this part dry out before you have removed the said animal, because when the mold dries out it will shrink and it will also make the animal shrink. Keep it therefore in a damp &amp; humid place until you have done it.</ab> 


<figure>
<id>fig_p135r_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5U3BqOGxwTHNPeVk</link>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
</figure>



<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Vine <m>leaf</m> is painted with a green made of <m>scudegrun</m> &amp; <m>verd de terre</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p135r_3</id>
<head><m>Vine leaf</m> and small <m>frog</m></head>
<ab>
To mold, take <m>vine leaves</m> as they are blooming, just as with all <m>herbs</m> &amp; <m>flowers</m>, or a young <m>vine</m> regrowing after it has been cut or when the leaves come off in autumn, because new <m>leaves</m> are knottier &amp; have more evident veins. By contrast, old <m>leaves</m> are smooth all the way through &amp; full of holes in many places. Place therefore your <m>leaf</m>, its back behind it against the <m>clay plaster</m>, and fasten it with little pins. Leave it nevertheless with its natural curling. And make a notch in the clay to hide the stem for the first cast.  And when it's done and dry, take out the stem of the <m>leaf</m> and clean it well with your jacket and press it with a little scoop of clay. Afterwards, make many castings around the <m>leaf</m> with <m>wax</m>, as you know well, &amp; make a slender casting &amp; with many lines &amp; knots.</ab>
 




<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>

You can cast a spider or frog &amp; whatever you like on the leaf.</ab>
</div></root>