<root><page>135v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f276.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p135v_a1</id>
<head>Casting <m>gold</m></head>


<ab>Take a crusol that can contain a certain amount, as you wish to place roughly crushed <m>borax</m> into it. Place <x>the <m>borax</m></x> at the bottom and then the <m>gold</m> on top of it. Arrange the <m>coal</m> in the forge in such a way that the wind of the bellow will blow above the crusol and no on its side as it would cool it down and would not heat it enough. Also, make sure it is three good <ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> away from the wall of the forge so that it is quite surrounded by <m>coal</m>. Allow the crusol to anneal until it is quite red. Then, have your boy strongly blow the bellow with long pushes, as in this manner it heats it better. Meanwhile, once the <m>gold</m> will be melted, blow a small bellow above it. Because <x>otherwise</x> the <m>gold</m> would turn sour and would acquire some kind of coat. As long as there will be some swirling smoke as you blow this way, it means that it is not soft enough for the cast. Therefore, uncover the melting pot and without displacing it and without stopping the bellow, tilt it towards you so you may well see what is inside. Throw a ferue of <m>borax</m> in it and blow wind towards it with the small bellow in a jerky fashion. Should there be <m>coal</m> inside, blow a bit stronger to make them come out. And if the <m>gold</m> still smokes and swirls, add <m>borax</m> again and blow above it. Beware that it is still sour and not soft enough, it will show a coat when you blow it as if it had cooled down. By contrast, if it does not show this sign, it is soft enough. Then, blow strongly so that it <x>the <m>gold</m></x> is quite heated and once you think it is hot enough, throw colour on top of it in the crusol and the colour should be composed as following: <m>verdigris</m>, <m>saltpeter</m>, <m>sal ammoniac</m>, and a bit of <m>borax</m>. And continue blowing with the small bellows, and the <m>gold</m> will turn shiny like</ab>


<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
If you cast in <m>gold</m> some piece of important <x>dimensions</x>, lute your mold with the same <m>sand</m> or put <m>crocum</m> on it.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
If you wish to cast some large work, or of important <x>dimensions</x>, create at the bottom or at an extremity of the forge a  vented furnace where you may hold your mold in the <m>sand</m> so red.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
One may cast two or three pounds of <m>gold</m>.</ab>


<cont/>
</div></root>