<root><page>138r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f281.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p137v_a1</id>


<ab>If you want to cast <m>gold</m>, <m>silver</m>, <m>copper</m> or <m>brass</m>, it is necessary that they be perfectly red, and fired on the inside when you cast, and perfectly reheated twice, if there is something inside to be burnt and cleaned.</ab>
  
<ab>The molds of animals that you burn must be reheated in such a manner that the animal burns up.  But if it has big bones, it is frustrating to take out and <m><figure>☿</figure></m> often breaks delicate things because of its heaviness. One does not put <m><figure>☿</figure></m>in molds that can open.  It is often molds for flowers that do not open because they are cast in one go.</ab>
 
<ab>When you want to reheat your molds, fix cramp-irons on the joints, so that when they reheat they will not bend, contract or break. This is done once the cast is made.</ab>
 
<ab>The scrapings of the mold can also be used instead of <m>bricks</m> after being reheated, and also the leftover bits of the mold that have already been used. You can also pat it over important things, like works in <m>gold</m> or <m>silver</m>. You can also reheat it and blend it with water diluted with <m>sal ammoniac</m>, like <m>spar</m> from Germany, and is excellent <m>sand</m> for box molds for all metals.</ab>
 
<ab>The molds with things that need to be burnt out inside them, those ones will not open until the thing that is inside is burnt, like the molds for crayfish, crab, great-horned beetles. Do not open the molds in which you will burn something, not before the thing is burnt, it could be crayfishes, crabs, stag beetles, pictures, and pieces of wax and <m>black sulphur</m>, which do not come out of the mold [easily].</ab>
 
<ab>You must not mold on <m>brick</m> or <m>wood</m> because they absorb and attract water too early, and do not allow the sand to set. The best place for [the sand] is on a fresh layers of <m>clay</m>.  And yet, I have experienced that <m>grey earth</m> dries out the mold too quickly. <m>Yellow [earth]</m> is better.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
For medals, and flat things, the <m>sand</m> must be quite thick and moistened so that it sets quickly. And when the <m>sand</m> is thusly thick, you can shake and move the table where you mold lies, so that [the movement] makes the <m>sand</m> go everywhere. But when the <m>sand</m> is clear, as for flowers and herbs, you cannot shake it, nor can you do it when there is something attached to <m>wax</m> or other things which are prone to come off, such as the legs of crayfish or other similar things. And if by chance your <m>sand</m> is too thick, you must quickly add some water. And having put the <m>sand</m> in the water, examine it until it is thick on the bottom and clear on top.  The clearest is thrown in immediately and then bubbles and the thickest is thrown in at the end so that it strengthens the mold.</ab>


</div></root>