<root><page>142r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f289.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p141r_1</id>




<ab>are not so uncovered. But since <al>crayfish</al> are troublesome to burn &amp; clean, you have to uncover them as much as you can, even the little legs just until the tips, because they are troublesome &amp; if, in order to not alter them, you have to take them out, you could break something of the mold. Having uncovered it with the point of a knife, like an engraving stick or another fitting thing, clean off the sand at the joints &amp; elsewhere with your little brush really very scrupulously. And if something is loosed from the <al>crayfish</al>, attach it with <m>wax</m>, as is discussed. And also attach the horns this way. And also do the casting the length of the extremes of the little legs with <m>wax</m>. And refill the holes that have been made with the needles of <m>iron</m> wire with it. And everything being quite clean &amp; having uncovered more than half of it, <m>oil</m> your mold after having soaked the back side in <m>water</m>, &amp; do not forget to <m>oil</m> all the fine parts that are between the legs and the little beaks; then rub the <al>crayfish</al> with <m>spirits</m>. And do your second casting after having made the first mold even, so that the cramp-irons join better. Your mold must be larger on the side with the impression than on the back. Do not open your mold after the second casting, so that it not become <m>clayed</m> &amp; reheated &amp; that which is inside not be burned. Do not forget to mix <m>crocum</m> throughout your sand when you mold the <al>crayfish</al>, because you must really reheat it &amp; the <m>crocum</m> withstands this marvelously. To mold a <al>crab</al> &amp; to mold a <al>crayfish</al> are exactly the same. When you have uncovered your <al>crayfish</al> on one side do not delay at all before doing the second casting, because <al>crayfish</al> dry out. It is not enough to uncover the <al>crayfish</al> such that you see the whole half <sup>the half you uncover</sup>, but take heed that your mold, even when you are uncovering, be good and stripped, because if the <al>crayfish</al> gets well burnt, you will not be able to open your mold without breaking it.</ab>
  
<ab><margin>top</margin>Restore it with a pen knife, little chisels, or engraving sticks.</ab>


<ab><margin>left-top</margin>As you see here, but a <m>wax</m> casting all around &amp; at the end of the tail, where you will do the principal casting, two or three more.</ab>


<figure>
<id>fig_p142r_1</id>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Qkh2MDhvUkFnUW8</link>
</figure>
 
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Make the casting with <m>candle wax</m> <sup>shaped</sup> in a thread like a large packthread, the whole length from the end of the claws to the extremity of the tail. If there is also some claw end or other part that is extended past the rank of the others or is raised up higher or turned up all alone, make a <m>wax</m> casting for it from its end just barely not joined to the body or to one of the large claws or to some other place where lots of <m>metal</m> will be wedged in.</ab>


<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>Having uncovered it, attach &amp; secure the two little bearded horns of the crayfish, and anything else that is not secured, with <m>wax</m>.</ab>
</div></root>