<root><page>143v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f292.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p143r_3</id>


<ab>from one leg to another, so that the spread out limbs are in connection with one another due to the aforesaid casting conduits, which you will start in the waxless round parts that you have put at the edge of the legs to attract the metal.  In this way, because you are casting in <m>wax</m>, there is no danger chipping any part of the molded animal.  It's quicker to make the <m>wax</m> casting conduits thus, because in this way <sup>you can</sup> cast the second mold after <sup>the first</sup>, rather than wait to do them <sup>the conduits</sup> after the mold has been recooked, because then, if possible, you will need to have everything ready.  You need to heat well, and even redden the molds where there are <m>wax</m> conduits so that they melt and leave nothing inside.</ab></div>
 
<div>
<id>p143v_1</id>
<head>Openwork carcanets</head>


<ab>You can mold them "en noyau" like <al>crayfish</al>, first with one side being made higher with <m>clay</m>, which is hollow, and then you open <sup>it</sup> from the other side and make the second casting.  You can just as well cast <sup>them</sup> "en chassis", provided that they release well. If they do not, you can do a rough cast in <m>wax</m>, or you can fill up the cavities which do not release well with <m>wax</m> or <m>clay</m>.</ab>
 </div>


<div>
<id>p143v_2</id>
 
<head><m>Iron</m> filings </head>


<ab>Because usually <m>filings</m> are mixed with impurities, it is good to heat them over fire to burn the filth and then wash them in clear <m>water</m>. In this way, the dirt will rise to the top of the <m>water</m>, which you will throw out, and the good filings will go at the bottom.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p143v_3</id>
<head>Carnations</head>


<ab>Because those that you usually cast are generally quite big, they are heavy.  And so for these, you make them with <m>silver</m> leaf or slivers.</ab></div></root>