<root><page>154v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f314.image</image>


<div>
<id>p154v_1</id>
<head><m>Latten</m></head>


<ab><m>Latten</m> is wonderful to cast. It is necessary to be cast very hot. And to master it better, throw in some <m>sal ammoniac</m> to clarify it. You can also add a bit a <m>red copper</m>, and if you wish to, add in a bit of <m>tin</m> to make it runnier.  It always leaves filaments like melted <m>glass</m>. It does not require as long of a cast as others.</ab></div>
 
<div>
<id>p154v_2</id>


<head>Moulding</head>


<ab>It is a good thing that it be cooled on the outside, but nevertheless remain hot on the inside, because when it comes out of the fire, the air and the strong fumes from the fire do not reheat the cast well. </ab></div>
 
<div>
<id>p154v_3</id>
<head>Casting <m>silver</m></head>


<ab><m>Silver</m> requires a long cast, whereas for <m>gold</m> it does not matter. <m>Silver</m>, when soldering, withstands the <m>water</m> you throw at it. Whereas <m>gold</m> sizzles, and because of this one throws its ? on the <m>solder</m>.</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>
Let the mold cool well after the casting, rather than opening it.</ab></div>


<div>
<id>p154v_4</id>
<head>Strengthening flowers and delicate things</head>


<ab>For flowers and small plants, do not use <m>wheat oil</m>. Instead, use some melted <m>butter</m> which you will apply lightly with a small brush on the back of the rose leaves, and pansies and any other flower that needs it. But one reinforces the little feet of <al>flies</al> and other small animals with <m>wheat</m> oil to make them stronger and hold up.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p154v_5</id>
<head>Strawberries </head>


<ab>The leaves are cast separately and then rejoined with solder.  And because the strawberry fruit is cast solid, and because of this it is heavy, and the <m>tin</m> stem is slender, it will not be able to sustain <sup>weight</sup> without breaking quickly. One makes the stems with <m>latten</m> thread and then solder them back onto the fruit.</ab>
</div></root>