<root><page>160v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f326.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p160v_a1</id>
<head>Moulding a foot or a hand</head>


<ab>Mix <m>resin</m> to the <m>wax</m>. Once well blended, soften the mixture in hot <m>water</m> or <m>urine</m>. Then press [the foot or the hand] in the mixture in order to get an impress, then pour <m>plaster;</m> the cast will which will be clean and come off easily.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p160v_a2</id>
<head>Fine work made of <m>gold</m> or <m>silver</m></head>


<ab>You can mold flies by hand,without casting; the wings and the feet can be soldered, which you could not do with fine works of <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m>, because they would melt. You can enamel the work made of <m>gold</m>.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p160v_a3</id>
<head>Catching crayfishes</head>


<ab>On the end of a stick, attach pieces of liver or lung, from beef or mutton. Then hang a basket to the stick with a little string. Put the basket into water where crayfishes eat; they will soon aggregate on the flesh. Pull very gently your stick out of the water; the crayfishes which will try to return to the water will fall into the basket.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p160v_a4</id>
<head>Catching passerines</head>


<ab>If they sleep in the farmyard, like they commonly do, close to the house, let the closest window open, and put a lighted candle close to the window. The candle itself must be hidden, only its glimmer must be seen through the room and through the window; all the passerines will then lock themselves into the room. But the night must be very dark, without any moonlight.</ab>
  
</div>
<div>
<id>p160v_a5</id>
<head>Catching birds</head>


<ab>During winter, when birds have molted, skin them and fill them with cloth and stuffing, or dry them well in an oven. Then arrange your birds on trees, have some [look like they are] singing, [look like they have assembled] and are numerous.</ab>


<ab>the oven must not be too hot. This [method] is good in the summer, because flies would set into the eyes and make works before they [birds] could dry. You can work on the birds more easily in the winter, because they dry by themselves.</ab>
</div></root>