<root><page>162v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f330.item</image>


<div>
<id>p162v_1</id>
<head>Peach trees</head>
<ab>Because they bud and blossom from the outset, and so are caught by the frost. We expose their roots during winter so that the cold slows them down, and they blossom later, which benefits their flowers.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p162v_2</id>
<head>Olive trees</head>
<ab>In <pl>Spain</pl> they expose their roots during winter and in spring they earth them up again.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p162v_3</id>
<head>Foot of <m>bittern</m></head>
<ab>To mold it it is better to extend its fingers and nails on something flat and let them dry this way for a few days, because in drying the scales will be rougher and the nerves and and tendons will be more apparent, and so the molded foot will be more artistic.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p162v_4</id>
<head>Molds of things which have not been<lb/>
pelted</head>
<ab>Animals who have not been pelted can only be molded in a double mold, which can only be opened after they have been refired and after the enclosed animal is completely burnt. Animals with bones or scales which are not reducible to powder thus remain in calcined pieces which will never removed from the cast, however much bellowing or whatever amount of quicksilver is put in, or by using a feather pipe while molding to make a gate. This is why you mold in two halves: so that once the mold is opened after having been refired, the thing you've burnt can be cleaned out. But I advise letting it cool so that in taking off the clamps (being hot) nothing cracks while it is still fragile. While it is hot the crust and cinders which it leaves and which stick to the mold can be more easily removed when it is cold. Also note that on the side of the lower mold when you reheat the animal, which in boiling leaves a crust, in this case, always mark on the mold where the back of the animal is so that in reheating it is to the top and above and will by this method stay cleaner.</ab>
</div></root>