<root><page>165r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f336.item</image>
<div>
<id>p165r_1</id>


<head>To repair</head>


<ab>If in your cast, there appear some little hole, fix it with black or gray filling <m>gum wax</m>.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p165r_2</id>
 
<head><m>Lacquer</m></head>


<ab>If, having been ground, you let it dry without keeping it in <m>water</m>, it will dry out and it will be quite difficult to crush it as before.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p165r_3</id>


<head>Stretching a <m>canvas</m> portrait</head>


<ab>If it is crumpled or folded from when it was rolled up, moisten the back side with a wet sponge. Then stretch it very evenly without damaging it.</ab>
 </div>
<div>
<id>p165r_4</id>


<head><m>Plaster</m> for molding</head>


<ab>When it is long to set and dry, it means that it is too fat and moist, which is what makes it shrink away from the fire and crack. <x>This is</x> where burrs come from.  The one that comes from lean <m>earth</m> is better. You must not store your moulds made of fat <m>plaster</m> for a long time, because they resemble fat <m>earth</m>, which when drying, cracks. The best is to reheat them soon after they have been made and cast. Moulds made of good <m>plaster</m> can  be stored a long time.</ab>
 
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is necessary to <m>oil</m>it well, because it is more difficult to separate the two halves of these moulds than when it is mixed.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p165r_5</id>


<head><m><al>Dragon's</al> blood</m></head>


<ab>It is imitated with <m>lake</m> that surpasses it in beauty if, with this distempered in <m>oil</m>, you glaze on <m>gold</m> or <m>silver</m>. Distempered in <m>varnish</m>, it dies.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p165r_6</id>
 
<head>Repairing <al>snakes</al> and <al>lizards</al></head>


<ab>You could make some marks according to the form of their scales, making some bigger ones and some smaller ones, according to the shape of the neck, the body and the tail. If there is something broken, you can attach it with small <m>iron</m> or <m>steel</m> nails, and glue it with some <m>mouth glue</m>, then cover the whole thing with gray or black <m>wax</m>.  But it is necessary to let the <m>glue</m> dry for one day without touching it.</ab>
</div></root>