<root><page>170r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f345.image</image>
<div>
<cont/>
<id>p169_2</id>


<ab><m>perfume</m> and similar things. But be sure that the <m>black</m> <m>wax</m>with which you cast is hard, so it will come off rapidly when dry so you can see if it has been stamped correctly. It can be made harder by adding more melted <m>sulphur</m> in the melted <m>wax</m>, and a bit of <m>resin</m>.</ab> 
</div>
<div>
<id>p170r_1</id>
 
<head>Common medals</head>


<ab>Relief awls are made of untempered <m>steel</m>, and then it is tempered. With it we beat on a matrice, not red hot on the fire as some people think, but on some steeled <m>iron</m>, reheated and adoulcy, that is then tempered.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p170r_2</id>
 
<head>Casting</head>


<ab>Do not cast all at once because in doing so, the metal overflows and gets cold instead of going to the bottom [of the mold]. Rather, cast it bit by bit, and gently.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p170r_3</id>


 <head><m>Iron</m> clamps</head>


<ab>When you put them for the second time, make sure that the mould does not wobble.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p170r_4</id>
 
<head>Molds</head>


<ab>Those with noyau, when reheated, should be placed on half lit <m>charcoal</m>, without being in contact with the air; like the frame molds, they need to dry in the open, and uncovered.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p170r_5</id>
 
<head>Thick <m>tin</m> pieces</head>


<ab>They should not be casted with <m>lead</m> or <m>red tin</m>, like thin and fragile things. It is enough if they are well melted and hot. Fragile things need to be red hot and made of <m>red tin</m>.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p170r_6</id>
 
<head>How to clean closed molds</head>


<ab>You have to leave them cool down rather than blow inside to clean them, because they hold the ashes when they are hot. Once cooled, they are easier to clean. Have a fine <m>brass</m> wire or a thin straw to thoroughly clean the tail because it is through it that you cast. Blow into it and siphon, bringing it to you. Give it volume before casting the tail with <m>wax</m>, then cut it.
<figure>
<id>fig_p170r_2</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5amQ1YVRWWnFGWUE</link>
</figure></ab>
 
 <ab><margin>left-top</margin>
<figure>
<id>fig_p170r_1</id>
<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5S3FNaEt0QmN1alU</link>
</figure>
make a tail by soldering a <m>latten</m> wire. The grains of a flower are quite little, so they can be removed with the chaple, but the leafs need to be peeled off correctly, then the paint will cover everything.</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>