<root>
<page>129v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f264.item.r=</image>

<div>

<id>p129v_1</id>

<head>Animals oven dried for a long time</head>

<ab>

Stick your animals on a slab of <m>earth</m>, fix them with sharp
pointed iron wires, as if you wanted to mold them, then dry them into an
oven as hot as when <m>bread</m> has been taken out. It is the same for
<al>snakes</al>, <al>birds</al> and other animals. But they have to be
promptly dried.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

Note that you have to arrange them and put them into the sand as for
flowers, and promptly dry them in an oven as warm as when <m>bread</m>
has been taken out. Leave it there one day and one night in order for
them to be very dry, otherwise it would stink. However, be sure that the
oven is not too hot, it should be as warm as the sun in June, otherwise
the animals would cook. Once they are dry, do not soak them; clean them
with a brush or a paintbrush.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129v_2</id>

<head>Animals casted in <m>copper</m></head>

<ab>Once casted in <m>copper</m>, try to burnish them as we do with
leaves made from gem, to see if they will get the same color.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129v_2</id>

<head>Advice about casting</head>

<ab>Be careful that your cast is not too thick, and do not forget to
make 2 or 3 holes and notches in the conduit, when your cast is coming
near the molded thing, divide it between 3 or 4 parts like fingers, and
not deep. Thus the metal will run more gently, without preventing vapors
and smoke.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>right-middle</margin>

Always make the entry of you cast close to the medal and the notch, when
lumpy, it will lessens the metal's fury.</ab>

<ab>

To cast a <al>spider</al> on a leaf, and to prevent the sand from
covering the under belly, fix a bit of melted <m>wax</m> at the end of
its tail, and bottom part of the body, with the help of a warm wire as
you know. Once the leaf has burnt and the <m>wax</m> has melted, two
small holes remain on the leaf, that will be the cast of the
<al>spider</al>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129v_4</id>

<head>Casting a spider on a leaf</head>

<ab>

Usually big spiders have hairy legs, which are difficult to mold if you
do not lay hairs down flat, or if you don't burn them with the flame of
a candle, or if you stiffen them and lay them flat by <m>oiling</m> them
with <m>wheat oil</m>. Kill them into <m>vinegar</m> and <m>urine</m>,
like <al>snakes</al>, or in <m>spirits</m>. Then arrange your them on a
beautiful vine leaf, or another leaf, then you can make the
undisciplined hair look like tamed hair by rubbing them with mouth glue,
or something similar. Their true color is <m>vinegar</m> or greenish.
And season with sulphur in random places. Arrange your slab of
<m>clay</m> and place your vine leaf on it, your dead spider in the
middle. Pierce the middle of the <al>spider</al>'s body with the tip of
an <m>iron</m> or <m>latten</m> wire. Then fix diagonally some small
<m>latten</m> tacks all around the vine leafs in order to secure it.
Then block the end of the legs with a bit of melted wax using a warm
<m>iron</m> wire, and smooth it out with the tip of a pair of small
pincers. do the same with the other edges of the <al>spider</al>.
Return<figure>🜊</figure></ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<figure>🜊</figure>

<figure>🜊</figure>

When the wax is cool, scrape away the superfluous parts with the point
of a penknife, that way the end of the legs will stay neat. Then arrange
the disc of earth around the spider, and cast your soaked sand, as you
did for others. In this fashion you will have to burn the vine leaf in
the mold. Otherwise, you will not have to. To cast your <al>spider</al>
more easily, make sure the animal is dead, avoiding the entanglement of
its legs while agonizing. When you have done your first cast, peel this
side of the leaf, then do the second cast. </ab>

</div>
</root>
