<root>
<page>021v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f48.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p021r_2</id>

<ab>Others place two well-staked poles into the earth in such a way that
the one is as far from the edge of the cannon's mouth as the other. And
underneath they place the above-mentioned ruler. Then when want to fire
the cannon at night, they push their cannon straight towards the
above-mentioned ruler and make it so that the edge of the mouth rests on
the end of the aforesaid ruler. Next, they measure with a ruler, or a
similar tool divided with measured intervals, from one pole to the side
of the cannon and if it is too close or too far, they adjust the canon
and make it the same distance as from the other pole.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p021v_1</id>

<head>Unspiking your cannon</head>

<ab>Some people say that one should remove the cannonball if the cannon
is loaded and introduce fire into the mouth of the cannon. But it is
probable that the fire will leave again through the mouth rather than
seek its exit through the touch hole which is spiked and restricted. The
most reliable way is that the <pro>cannoneer</pro>, who is often a
<pro>founder</pro>, drive in a <m>nail</m> and turn back the point of
the <m>nail</m> that the enemies placed therein, and with a
<tl>trephine</tl>, make another touch hole at the side of the spiked
one, which can be done in an hour. And if with time the violence of the
<m>powder</m> loosens the <m>nail</m> that the cannon was spiked with,
you will make a <tl>nut</tl> in the second touchhole and place a
<m>screw</m> in it, so perfectly that it will never come
undone.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p021v_2</id>

<head>Defense of a town</head>

<ab>There is nothing more efficient for defending a breach than mortars
placed at the front line, as soon as the initial assault. They carry a
lot of ammunition and are filled with cart <m>nails</m>, big
<m>steel</m> dice, bits of <m>chains</m> and similar items. And when one
senses that the enemy is close, one lights everything on fire. Grenades,
well-constructed and thrown at the right moment, also cause much damage.
And to make them worse, one can add some roughly crushed <m>glass</m>,
either in the mold or in the crucible, when one casts them. This worsens
the wounds. The grenades must not be too brittle, but it is good that
they be somewhat alloyed with the material of the grenade so that
instead of breaking up, they resist shock better and inflict more
violence.</ab></div>
</root>
