<root>
<page>039r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f83.image</image>

<div>

<id>p039r_1</id>

<head><pro>Goldsmith</pro></head>

<ab>They assemble <m>silver filings</m> with <m>saltpeter</m> which
refines it &amp; does not make it brittle. But <m>gold filings</m> are
assembled with <m>borax</m> or, to spare the <m>borax</m>, with
<m>lead</m>, which refines the <m>gold</m> &amp; softens it, for the
<m>saltpeter</m> would make it brittle, which <m>silver</m> does not do.
This is why, to save money, <pro>goldsmiths</pro> use it to assemble, in
order to spare <m>borax</m>, which costs viii <cn><fr>sols</fr></cn> per
<ms>ounce</ms>, &amp; <m>saltpeter</m> x <cn><fr>sols</fr></cn> per
<ms>lb</ms>.</ab>

<ab>When <pro>goldsmiths</pro> have thus assembled their <m>silver
filings</m> with <m>saltpeter</m>, a <m>red enamel</m> vitrifies at the
bottom of the <tl>crucible</tl>. I do not know if the <m>copper</m>
mixed in with the <m>silver</m> is the cause. <rub>Try for
<m>enamel</m></rub>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p039r_2</id>

<head><m><pa><fr>Pastel</fr> woad</pa></m></head>

<ab>It is grown in <pl>Lauragais</pl> <env>where the deep soil is so
fertile</env> that if <pa>wheat</pa> was grown there <tmp><ms>every
year</ms></tmp>, it would lie flat for being too vigorous. This is why
one alternately does <pa><fr>pastel</fr> woad</pa> and <pa>wheat</pa>
there. For the cultivation of <pa><fr>pastel</fr> woad</pa>, one works
the soil with <tl><m>iron</m> shovels</tl>, as <pro>gardeners</pro> do.
Next, one harrows it with <tl>rakes</tl>, &amp; breaks it up finely as
for sowing <pa>cooking herbs</pa>. One commonly sows it <tmp>on
<pn>Saint Anthony</pn>'s day in January</tmp>. One makes eight harvests
of it. The first ones are better. The best <pa><fr>pastel</fr> woad</pa>
of <pl>Lauragais</pl> is the one from <pl>Carmail</pl> &amp; the one
from <pl>Auragne</pl>. And sometimes the <pa><fr>pastel</fr> woad</pa>
is good <env>in one field &amp; in the one close by it</env> will hardly
have worth. The goodness of the <pa><fr>pastel</fr> woad</pa> is known
when, put in the <bp>mouth</bp>, it gives a <sn>taste as of
<m>vinegar</m></sn>, or when crumbling &amp; breaking it, it has some
mold-like veins which are as if golden or silver. One assays it in the
<tl><pro>dyers</pro>' vat</tl>, and to fill a <tl>vat</tl> with it, one
needs six <ms>balls</ms> of it. One dyes several <ms>locks</ms> of
<m>wool</m>, and if it dyes fifteen times, it is said to be fifteen
<cn>florins</cn>, if it gives xx dyings, xx <cn>florins</cn>. The good
kind dyes up to 30 times &amp; commonly up to xxv or 26.</ab>

</div>
</root>
