<root>
<page>006v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f18.image</image>

<div>
<id>p006v_a1</id>
<head>For cages</head>

<ab>You can embellish them with <m>thin</m> <m>enamel</m> <m>canes</m>
of various colors by covering the <m>yellow latten</m> or <m>iron</m>
wire with said canes. These you will break neatly into the length that
you want if you make a small notch with a cutting <tl>file</tl> at the
point where you want to break them, and they will not break anywhere
else. You can bend them with a <m>wood</m>en model over a brazier or by
the heat of a <tl>lamp</tl>. A cane can be stretched out as long as you
want in a small <tl>furnace</tl> made like a <tl>reverberatory oven</tl>
but with openings on both sides. And once the large cane is red, they
seize the hot end of it with <tl>small pincers</tl> that have long
beaks, with one end of the beak inside the end of the cane, so that it
may be stretched without becoming blocked. The other end of the cane is
held with the hand, as it is not hot. Once the cane is stretched enough,
the one who is working seated with his <tl>stove</tl>, the size of a
carnation pot, placed in front of him, breaks it off and carries on.
This is for making canes for capes, which may be cut, as already
mentioned, with a <tl>file</tl>. <pro>Glass-button makers</pro> also use
the said <tl>stove</tl>.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p006v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5eVFRYjVCTmczcmM</link>

</figure>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Under the door is a grill that supports the burning <m>charcoal</m>. The
<m>ash</m> is emptied by turning the <tl>stove</tl> upside down.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p006v_a2</id>
<head>For stamped ornaments used for embellishing and inserting into or
covering the edges of mirrors, the tops of chests, or the friezes of bed
valances</head>

<ab>Etch with <m>aqua fortis</m> on <m>iron</m> or <m>copper</m>
whatever you have pounced and drawn there, next make it neat with a
<tl>burin</tl> or <tl>chisel</tl>. Then pour <m>soft</m> <m>tin</m>, yet
unused, onto polished <m>marble</m> and flatten it, making it quite
thin, with a <m>wood</m>en board. Or else pour it on a table as is done
with <m>lead</m>, or put it through a <tl>roll-press</tl>. Next lay your
<m>tin</m> plate over the engraving, and over the <m>tin</m> plate put a
piece of <m>felt</m> and strike it with a <tl>hammer</tl>. Then gild it
in the following manner.</ab>

</div>
</root>
