<root>
<page>153r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f311.image</image>

<div>

<id>p153r_1</id>

<head>Moulding the hollow part of a mold for seals or other
things</head>

<ab>Firstly fashion your figure in <m>wax</m> on an even slab of
<m>glass</m> or <m>slate</m>. After, mold it with our aforesaid sand,
having beforehand lightly smeared with <m>oil</m> as you know, and
having rubbed it with <m>spirits</m>, while tempering your sand with
<m>hot water</m>. Having made the hollow part, cast it in <m>lead</m>,
using the same alloy as you do for other figures that come out very
neatly. However, if it does not release cleanly, repair it. And then
mold with <m>wax</m> on the <m>lead</m> relief &amp; you will have a
very neat cavity in the <m>wax</m> that comes out very neat in
<m>lead</m>. After, in your <m>wax</m> hollow part, throw in your
tempered sand which will give you a relief, upon which you will cast
your hollow part with <m>silver</m>, or any other metal used for seals.
But note that you must not make your hollow part with melted <m>wax</m>,
but only with <m>wax</m> warmed in hot <m>water</m>, or even better in
hot <m>urine</m>. Or else, if you have a relief in <m>gold</m> or
<m>silver</m>, or any other very neat and flawless metal, mold your
<m>wax</m> hollow part directly upon it, and throw your sand in it
<sup>wax hollow</sup>, which will form your relief, upon which you will
cast your hollow part to make your seal or any other work. You could
also cast a hollow part directly from the main part of your metal, even
<sup>should you want to cast</sup> in <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m>, which
will not make the main part of your metal melt, if it has been lightly
brushed with <m>crushed chalk</m>, or covered with <m>candle soot</m>,
or with dried <m>glair of egg</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>When you have the <m>wax</m> imprint of
your seal, mold in a noyau this piece of <m>wax</m>, which is hollow
like your seal, and your noyau will make a mold similar to the imprint
and the seal.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Your <m>wax</m> must be mixed with a
color that has little body, so that you may better see your imprint. The
<m>lamp black</m> or <m>soot black</m> is good for this. <m>White
wax</m> to do this is even better.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p153r_2</id>

<head>Giving a medal the thickness that you wish</head>

<ab>Having cast your first mold, mix some <m>crocum</m> or well-ground
<m>iron scales</m> to make it <sup>your mould</sup> firmer. And having
taken hold, and made your hollow part very neat, take some paste made of
fine</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
