<root>
<page>94v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f194.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p094r_1</id>

<ab>The <m>gold</m> handles are made with some <m>yellow thin cloth</m>
set below or other kind of <m>chalk-yellowed fabric</m>. And this
<m>cloth</m> is set on with <m>glue</m> or aforesaid <m>gum</m>. This is
in order to make the <m>thread</m> hold better on it. These latter are
made of cordons like the <m>silk</m> ones and between two cordons are
put one or two <m>threads</m> to enhance it. The <m>silver</m> one is
identically made. And there is as much difficulty as for the <m>silk</m>
one, not because <m>silk</m> is difficult to twisted, but it needs to be
twisted twice. A fine <m>gold</m> handle is worth 28 or 20 cents.</ab>

<ab>The best sword point is of <m>sage foliage</m>.</ab>

<ab>This long stick on which the sword is laid down and attached in
order to furbish is called the chameau. It is commonly made from
<m>rowan</m> which is hard and even.</ab>

<ab>The stick underneath which is folded bow-like is called the
arch.</ab>

<ab>The stick above is called stick of the fustée.</ab>

<ab>And this square piece, used on the sword to burnish it, is called
the fustée.</ab>

<ab>There are two horns, one is called the <m>oil</m> hornet and the
other the <m>emery</m> hornet. </ab>

<ab>There is an <m>iron</m> tool with the shape of a halberd point,
square and made of very even and well limed <m>steel</m> called the
grateau which helps to soften lime strokes on swords hilts and to
sharpen blades once they are softened which is better than with
<m>stone</m> or other tools which leave some scratches.</ab>

<ab>To make the swords cut better, the edge from the point is also
sharpened.</ab>

<ab><pro>Those who create sword hilts</pro> are different craftsmen than
<pro>furbishers</pro>.</ab>

<ab>The fustée is a three-finger-thick, square <m>wood</m> tool, made of
<m>boxwood</m> which fit in the middle of the fustée stick to
furbish.</ab>

<ab>The fresil stick is made of <m>willow wood</m> which is to <x>…</x>
weapon with some <m>clinker</m> which is the <m>iron scale</m> falling
from the <pro>blacksmiths</pro>' forge.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p094v_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Q29MTEVLUGE5RGs</link>

<caption>le banc <lb/>

des fourreaux</caption>

</figure>
<figure>

<id>fig_p094v_2</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5OEQ3OEFSNnEzeE0</link>

</figure>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<figure/> a<figure/> <figure/>b<lb/>

D<lb/>

<figure/><lb/>

le baston <lb/>

a felinder<lb/>

<figure/><lb/>

c<lb/>

le <m>flin</m> ou <m>pierre<lb/>

de fouldre</m></ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
