<root>
<page>017v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f40.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p017r_1</id>

<ab>The large canon is for great batteries and usually weighs fifty five
or 60 <ms>quintal</ms>s. The breech is two cannonball and three quarters
each. The mouth is one cannonball and three quarters each. It is
thirteen or fourteen <fr><ms>pan</ms>s</fr> in length. But they are very
uneasy to drive. The proper battery, to be used rapidly and to have
great impact, is a hundred fifty to two hundred <ms>pace</ms>s. It is
true that a fair impact can be had from three or four hundred
<ms>pace</ms>s, but more <m>powder</m> is needed. Its usual load is 20
<ms>pound</ms>s of <m>powder</m>; its cannonball weighs 40
<ms>pound</ms>s, and 25 <al>horses</al> are required to carry it. When
one needs a longer range than the usual one, half a
<ms><tl>linstock</tl></ms> of canon <m>powder</m> is added. 80 or a
hundred shots can be made with this canon per day, but it needs to be
cooled down after each nine or ten shots if the battery is continuously
used; if there are some breaks, it is not necessary to refresh it as
often. For each <ms>quintal</ms> of <m>copper</m> - or one
<ms>quintal</ms> and a half for big cannons - a <ms>quintal</ms> of
<m>metal</m> is added. The <m>metal</m> is composed of eight
<ms>pound</ms>s of <m>tin</m> for each <ms>quintal</ms> of
<m>rosette</m> and even less for big bells for which we use only six
<ms>pound</ms>s of fine <m>tin</m> for a <ms>quintal</ms> of
<m>rosette</m>, to give it a louder voice. Because the more <m>tin</m>
there is, the clearer the sound is. For canon founding, if the material
and <m>charcoal</m> is provided as it is usually done because
<pro>master</pro>s cannot afford it, it costs 10 to 12 <cn>pound</cn>s
per <ms>quintal</ms>. And when the <pro>master</pro> provides
everything, you give him 40 <cn>pound</cn>s per <ms>quintal</ms> for big
pieces such as cannons, according to the King's ordinance. And 50
<cn>pound</cn>s for smaller pieces. For the more matter there is, the
more the <pro>master</pro> makes profit. Another kind of 30
<ms>quintal</ms>'s fowler is founded which is longer than the others,
and usually 8 <fr><ms>pan</ms>s</fr> long, which is used to attack
fortifications and <fr>cassemattes</fr> by displaying them, at night, in
groups on the moat's edge.</ab>

<figure>◯</figure>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

Each side of the breech's opening is half a cannonball thick, plus a
third of a cannonball.</ab>

<ab>We give it two <ms><tl>linstock</tl></ms> of cannon <m>powder</m>
for its load, and half a <ms><tl>linstock</tl></ms> of arquebus
<m>powder</m> and the same for the others.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<figure>#</figure>

The alloy of cannons from <pl>France</pl> is made of one
<ms>quintal</ms> of metal for two of <m>rosette</m>. But those of
<pl>Toulouse</pl> and <pn>Ponce</pn>t put 3 <ms>quintal</ms>s of
<m>rosette</m> for one of metal.</ab>

<ab> The <m>rosette</m> used to remelt is better than <m>rosette</m> for
cauldrons, for the latter get all dirty.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

The older pieces are composed of almost as much of each, that is to say
a part of <m>rosette</m> and one of metal. This alloy can be recognized
with a <tl>burin</tl> because the matter is acid and the part scraped
off with the <tl>burin</tl> is yellow and white.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
