<root>
<page>137v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f280.image</image>

<div>
<id>p137v_a1</id>
<head>Wetting <m>sand</m> to mold flat medals</head>

<ab>Flat medals, made of <m>wax</m> or <m>metal</m>, must be oiled very
lightly and then touched with a brush of <m>spirits</m>. So that the
already moistened mold takes well the oiled thing without rejecting it,
one warms the water well in order to wet the <m>sand</m>, because with
cold water it would be rejected. It is necessary to <m>oil</m> medals,
because they do not expand and in this way would break the mold.
Animals, which expand, do not need oiling. The hot water much be of such
a heat that you cannot keep your figure in it without it becoming too
warm. Wet the thickest <m>sand</m> for flat and solid medals rather than
<x>for</x> lizards and finer things. Once your sand has set, clean and
scrape your mold on one side and the other, and on the bottom edge of
the thrown side of the medal, make a notch so that it is easier to take
out. Lower the mold, scraping what surrounds the medal, so that on all
sides you can take it out easily without it damaging the mold. Then make
some gashes around the first mold used to throw so that the second time
that you throw in it, it will be identical to the first one, and in the
same way, make a notch at the bottom of the mold, where the held of the
item cast lies. Also make some <x>gashes</x> in the sides of the cast.
This done, wet the back of the first mold in <m>oiled water</m>, and
after the second casting moisten it with warm <m>water</m> if you have
molded your medal in a noyau mold. Having done the first cast, and this
one having set, cut around the edge of the medal with the point of a
knife so that it comes out of the throw and is not buried in it. Then
having made the second cast, and having opened your mold, take away the
medal in one go, with two knife points, one on the side of the cast
object and one on the side of the head, which is at the opposite
end.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Take care not to oil your medal too much because if the seeps out, it
prevents the <m>sand</m> from serving its purpose and coming together
and renders it wavy and lumpy. You must only touch the middle of the
medal with the tip of your oil brush and then smear the <m>oil</m>
everywhere.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>

Make especially sure that the throw is as wide as you can on the medal
and holds it together well. The gate of your cast must always be big and
always narrowing as you go towards the medal. Also do not forget to
notch the gate of your cast.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
