<root>
<page>150v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f306.image</image>

<div>

<id>p150v_1</id>

<head>Molding hollow</head>

<ab>This <m>iron</m> thread needle which you put thusly in the mold, is
to better secure the noyau and keep it from shifting. All of this having
been thusly arranged, lay your mold on the table, hole facing upwards,
as it is explained at the side. And then fashion a circle made of soft
<m>clay</m>, of about two fingers high around the hole, as you have done
with other molds. And then temper your molding sand to an average
thickness, and throw it in the hole until it <sup>mold</sup> is very
very full, that is to say until you reach the <m>clay</m> circle. Be
advised not to throw it <sup>sand</sup> in the middle of the hole, but
from the sides, because the already made mold, will drink and suck the
moisture. And the new sand that you throw on the sides of the mold,
because drying quickly, will plug the mold and not <sup>leave you enough
time</sup> to fill up. Whereas if you throw it <sup>the sand</sup> from
the side, when you realize <sup>it is drying too quickly</sup> and plugs
up, you can make a path for it. Having thrown it in, blow on the
tempered sand, and insert the tip of your finger in the hole a few
times, or some kind of pointy thing to keep it moist, in order to make
sure that the hollow <m>wax</m> does not fill up. At the end throw in
the thicker tempered sand to strengthen the mold, because when
<m>water</m> rises up to the edge of the mold, it always makes it
softer. Having taken hold, get rid of the <m>clay</m> circle and any
raised parts that relate to the hole through which you threw the noyau,
and you will not even realize the process took place. Once your mold has
been thusly prepared, lute its outside with the same sand that you used
to make the mold. Then reheat it on with a low heat to begin with, slant
the mouth of the cast downwards so that the <m>wax</m> trickles out
slowly, because if you reheat it over very high heat to make the
<m>wax</m> come out, it will boil inside it <sup>the mold</sup>, and
will leave blisters and lumpy bits on it <sup>the cast</sup>, as long
as</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

This <m>iron</m> thread needle is placed in the middle and the hole of
the cast, when the mold is in many pieces, as is the one for
<al>turtles</al>. And you do this so that the noyau does not shift. But
when the mold is made out of only two pieces, it is not necessary to put
needles in the middle.

<figure>

<id>fig_p150v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5eVVJSjUwSFhpUzg</link>

</figure>

<figure>

<id>fig_p150v_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SUk5cUNtNnpqbXc</link>

</figure>

</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>Rather than cast the noyau, make some
notches around the edge of the hole through which you would like to
cast, so that your mold is even more secure.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>Mixed <m>tallow</m> means that when you
empty your <m>wax</m> when you are emptying the mold of <m>wax</m>, it
does not clog.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>You will need half <m>tallow</m> and
half <m>black wax</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Every thick piece comes out better when
molded hollow, because a thick mass of mostly lead will stay warm for a
long time and eat away at the mold.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>After the cast, you can mold the part of
the shell of the belly where you made your hole on the real thing
<sup>animal</sup> and fix it with <m>solder</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>

<figure>X</figure>Note that after your noyau has been cast, it is better
to put your mold in hot <m>water</m> to open it, so that you can take
away as much <m>wax</m> as you can, always softening it in the hot
<m>water</m>. Because the less <m>wax</m> you have on it, the better it
is, because it will reboil when you reheat your mold, and you will get
blisters and lumps. And if you have little <m>wax</m> left <sup>in the
mold</sup> you will not need to reheat it as much. When you open your
mold the cast will break. But it can easily be repaired as long as you
cast<figure>A</figure>

</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
