<root>
<page>053v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f112.image</image>

<div>

<id>p053v_1</id>

<head><al>Silkworms</al></head>

<ab>They are produced from grain, that is eggs, which are sold by the
ounce, which is commonly sold in Languedoc 3 lb. and 5 s. The one from
Spain brought by merchants is considered to be the best, because the
worms coming from it are not so subject to illnesses and produce more
silk. In Spain, one ounce of grain gives worms that commonly make 15 lb.
of silk. But from one once produced in France, they do not make but 10
or 12. Three ounces of grain are to produce such a quantity of worms,
with which you will be able to furnish a room with three or 4 shelves of
wide boards. They begin to shed their skin on their own around Easter.
And to do this, one has to put them in a pine box, like the ones in
which we put pellet, warmly among feather cushions. And in the
beginning, they shed their skin as little black ants, and as soon as
there are two or three without skin, they have to be given white
mulberry leaves. And then arrange them on the boards. And three times
per day, it is necessary to change the leaves for fresh ones. And if
during the day there is any storm or rainy weather, cloudy and cool, one
needs to keep in the room three or 4 embers and with glowing coal, and
to light incense until the room is filled with its smoke. And when the
weather is warm and serene, they produce more and better silk. Some
worms make it whiter, others more yellowish. And even if it is white, it
can be yellowed when it is extracted with hot water. From their birth
until the moment they make their cocoons and prisons, worms sleep and
rest 4 times, and each time they remain 4 or five days resting without
eating, as if they were dying so as to be born again, because each one
sheds their skin and begins by uncovering the head, then consequently,
on different days, the rest of the body, and they go from white to grey,
and from grey to white. And if one of them has some sickness and does
not have the strength to shed, one needs to help it and to be careful
not to squash it, because if it gives off a yellow liquor, it is no
longer worth anything. And they do not even serve much if one handles
them. Around Pentecost, they begin to want to climb on the dry heather
branches that we prepare and attach</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

See Marco Girolamo Vida, Bishop of Alba and Cremonesi, wrote a poem on
the nature of silkworms.

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

How they are <ill/>

</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
