<root>
<page>156r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f317.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p156r_1</id>
<head>Quickly molding and reducing a relief to a hollow
<x>mold</x></head>

<ab>Make an impression in colored wax of the relief of your medal. And
you will get a hollow mold, in which you can cast en noyau a relief in
sand. In this, you will cast your hollow in lead or tin. In this, you
you will cast your wax relief. And then on this <m>wax</m>, you will
make your hollow moule en noyau, in order to cast in it the relief in
<m>gold</m> or <m>silver</m> or any other metal you would like. But to
make this process go faster, if you are in a hurry, make the first
impression and the first hollow out of the inside portion of the
<m>bread</m> loaf, prepared as you know, and which will cast neatly. And
inside this, cast in the melted <m>wax</m> which will give you a nice
relief on which you can make your noyau.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p156r_2</id>
<head>Work of <m>gold</m>, very light and hollow</head>

<ab>Cast a lizard or any medal you would like in <m>silver</m>, of low
quality, then gild it lightly and once the first gilding is done and
dried up in the fire, burnish it, brush it with a wirebrush. Apply
another layer of light gilding, repeating the whole process. Do this
three or four times or even more depending on how thick you want your
<m>gold</m> to be. Then, in the most discrete place you can find, make a
small opening, and submerge your entire work in some good <m>aqua
fortis,</m> which will penetrate into the <m>silver</m> through the
opening and will corrode the <m>silver</m> without damaging the
<m>gold</m>. In this way, you will have a lizard that is hollow until
the tip of its nails or any type of work that is so light that when you
blow into it, it moves. But be advised not to apply a thick layer of
<m>amalgamated gold</m> in one go, or apply layers that are too thin
each time, because this will block the finer details, but if you proceed
as I have said, <x>i.e.</x> lightly and in many goes, and cleaning it
well, then you will be fine.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
If you want the aqua fortis to corrode well, you must cast in low
quality silver.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p156r_3</id>
<head>Chiseling</head>

<ab><m>Lead</m> is so fat and soft that one cannot hammer it harshly,
one should have a light touch. Other big metals are easier to work with.
With a graver called an onglete, you make and retool the finest of
details. With the ordinary graver, you make the larger ones, and with
the chaple, you can remove the bits that have run, and with the <x>…</x>
soften <x>…</x> some lines you flatten or raise the lines.</ab>

</div>
</root>
