<root>
<page>050r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f105.image</image>

<div>

<id>p050r_1</id>

<head>Preserving fruit for the entire year</head>

<ab>Take a rounded <m>glass</m> phial, with a large enough opening to
receive cherries and plums and whatever fruit you want. Put in some
<m>hot water</m> <sup>and leave it</sup> for two hours, and once your
<m>water</m> is cold, throw it out and turn the phial upside down onto
its opening on a perfectly even table and in a room where there is not a
bit of draft or wind. Then prepare a stopper of fresh <m>wax</m>,
wrapped in <m>oilcloth</m>, and adapt it precisely to the <m>glass</m>
phial so that it will be ready to stop it once you have put in the
fruit. And once you have hand-picked the fruit, only the non-rotten
fruit, and on a warm and dry day, withdraw to the room, well closed so
that no wind or draft can get in, and put it gently and deftly in the
bottle. Then stop the bottle well with the stopper and lute it, making
your lute, if you want, with some <m>quicklime</m> and <m>oil</m>, so
that no <m>water</m> gets in. Then put your bottles into a tub full of
<m>water</m>, in a cellar, during the summer, and in the winter put your
bottles into a basket filled with some weights and lower it to the
bottom of a deep well. Because in the winter the <m>water</m> in the tub
would be too cold if your cellar is not warm enough, because the
<m>water</m> needs to be like <m>river water</m>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>po50r_2</id>

<head>Molding</head>

<ab>If you want to promptly mold something in <fr>demy relief</fr> that
comes to hand, fold some <tl><m>paper</m></tl> in five or six doubles,
&amp; place it on the <tl>medal</tl> &amp; make sure the
<tl><m>paper</m></tl> is folded on the back of the <tl>medal</tl> so
that it is well secured. Next take a <tl>stick</tl>, broad at one end
&amp; pointed at the other, well softened and rub well on the
<tl><m>paper</m></tl>, &amp;with the point of the <tl>stick</tl> retrace
the lines &amp; proceed until you recognize that your impression is well
done. Then, at your convenience, slightly rub <m>oil</m> with a
<tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> <del><fr>lemp</fr></del> on the
<tl><m>>paper</m></tl> impression and cast in <m>tallow</m> or
<m>wax</m> or <m>sulphur</m>, &amp; the <tl><m>paper</m></tl>, without
it burning, will render your design neat, so that you will be able to
mold it later in <m>plaster</m> or <m>tripoli</m>, and then in
<m>lead</m> &amp; other <m>metal</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>Polished <tl><m>cardboard</m></tl> of
little thickness &amp; a little moistened is proper. Then if you want,
strengthen it with <tl><m><fr>papier collé</fr></m></tl> on the
back.</ab></div>
</root>
