<root>
<page>050r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f105.image</image>

<div>

<id>p050r_1</id>

<head>Keeping fruit for the entire year</head>

<ab>Take a <m>glass</m> ampul with an opening capable of receiving
cherries and plums or whatever fruit that you want. Put in some <m>hot
water</m> for the space of two hours. And when your <m>water</m> will be
cooled, throw it &amp; turn the opening upside down on a quite even
table, &amp; in a room where there is not a bit of air &amp; of wind.
Then prepare a stopper of new <m>wax</m>, wrapped in <m>waxed
canvas</m>, and adjust it to the ampul quite precisely in order that it
will be all ready to stop it when you will have put in the fruit. And
when you will have delicately picked with your hand only the fruit that
is not rotten &amp; on a warm &amp; dry day, return to the well-closed
room, where neither wind nor draft may enter, &amp; put it gently &amp;
with dexterity in the bottle. Then stop the bottle well with the stopper
&amp; lute it &amp; making the lute if it seems good with some
<m>quicklime</m> &amp; <m>oil</m>, &amp; such that no <m>water</m> may
enter in. Then put your bottles in a vat full of <m>water</m>, during
the summer, in a cellar, and in the winter put your bottles into a
basket furnished with some weights &amp; lower it to the bottom of a
deep well. For in the winter the <m>water</m> of the vat would be too
cold if your cellar is not quite warm, for one needs the <m>water</m> to
be like <m>river water</m>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>po50r_2</id>

<head>Molding</head>

<ab>If you want to promptly mold something in <fr>demy relief</fr> that
comes to hand, fold some <tl><m>paper</m></tl> in five or six doubles,
&amp; place it on the <tl>medal</tl> &amp; make sure the
<tl><m>paper</m></tl> is folded on the back of the <tl>medal</tl> so
that it is well secured. Next take a <tl>stick</tl>, broad at one end
&amp; pointed at the other, well softened and rub well on the
<tl><m>paper</m></tl>, &amp;with the point of the <tl>stick</tl> retrace
the lines &amp; proceed until you recognize that your impression is well
done. Then, at your convenience, slightly rub <m>oil</m> with a
<tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> <del><fr>lemp</fr></del> on the
<tl><m>>paper</m></tl> impression and cast in <m>tallow</m> or
<m>wax</m> or <m>sulphur</m>, &amp; the <tl><m>paper</m></tl>, without
it burning, will render your design neat, so that you will be able to
mold it later in <m>plaster</m> or <m>tripoli</m>, and then in
<m>lead</m> &amp; other <m>metal</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>Polished <tl><m>cardboard</m></tl> of
little thickness &amp; a little moistened is proper. Then if you want,
strengthen it with <tl><m><fr>papier collé</fr></m></tl> on the
back.</ab></div>
</root>
