<root>
<page>0121r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f248.item</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p0120v_4</id>

<ab>a sign that it has some humidity, &amp; if the flower also had some
aquosity, it would rot. It also ought not to be <del>too</del> coarse,
for with its heaviness it would weigh down the flower &amp; make it lose
its form. Having thus chosen it as is needed, take a <tl>box</tl>, in
which you first make a mound of the said sand, on which you will place?
the stalk of your flower <del>so that</del> laid down so that the flower
touches neither the bottom nor the sides of the <tl>box</tl>, but
remains in the air. Then apply more <del>on</del> sand on the stalk in
order that it remains firm &amp; fixed. Finally take the same sand &amp;
with two <tl><bp>fingers</bp></tl> pulverize &amp; throw it delicately
on the flower, <del>e</del> imitating in this the flow of an
<ms><tl>hourglass</tl></ms>. And when the flower is as if
<del>half</del> covered, strike your <bp><tl>fist</tl></bp> on the table
where the <tl>box</tl> is set in order that the sand drops &amp; enters
everywhere. Finally cover it all over and lay it thus, in the order of
the other flowers, one over the other, as many as your <tl>box</tl> will
hold within. This being thus arranged, expose it in <env>hot sun</env>
for <ms><tmp>several days</tmp></ms>. And when the flower is dried, the
sand that has always accompanied it &amp; tightened around it allows it
only to contract, it shrivels &amp; shrinks. On the contrary, it needs
to dry remaining in the same state as when you put it there. But to that
effect take care you chose <pa>knapweed</pa>s, <pa>marigold</pa>s, the
<pa>yellow meadow flowers</pa> called <la><pa>ranunculus</pa></la> or
<la><pa>palta lupina</pa></la>, <pa>amaranth</pa>s, and similar flowers,
such as <pa>broom</pa> and others that you will know from
experience.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

The sand that <pro>goldsmiths</pro> use to rub <m>enamel</m>s and the
white one that <pro>glassworker</pro>s use and any thin sand that does
not set, you put through a <tl>sieve</tl> made of <m>horsehair</m>
because it needs not be too thin. Then dry the sand well in the
<env>sun</env> for <ms><tmp>several days</tmp></ms> in order to remove
its humidity, and ventilate it as you would do with <m>wheat</m> so that
the dust becomes separated from it. After taking that dust, well dried,
use it as you know.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<pa>Pansies</pa> are preserved in the same way.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p121r_1</id>

<head>For keeping fruits all <ms><tmp>year</tmp></ms></head>

<ab>One needs to pick them in <fr>serain</fr> &amp; <del>s</del> quite
dry weather &amp; by the stem without <del>en</del> <sn>touching</sn>
the fruit with your <bp>hand</bp>, and put them in <tl><m>glass</m>
bottles</tl> that have a wide opening, like tall <m>glass</m>
<tl>jars</tl> for preserves. Protect them with <m>straw</m> or something
else so that they may not break, and seal them well with <m>wax</m> so
that they may not breathe. And if they have <m>glass</m> lids well
sealed with <m>wax</m>, it will be all the better. Put them in a
<tl>case</tl> and put this in the <env>well</env>, or in the
<env>cellar</env>, or in a vat or plot of <m>earth</m> full of
<m>water</m>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

Because wherever the <bp>hand</bp> <sn>touches</sn> them they will rot,
and it is even best not to breathe on them. You can also put <m>vine
leaves</m> with them.</ab>

</div>
</root>
