<root>
<page>133v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f272.image</image>

<div>

<id>p133v_1</id>

<head> Porosity and little holes which are in the mold</head>

<ab>

It oftens happens when you cast two or three molds one after the other
using the same dish, because the last casting comes from the bottom of
the dish and is thicker, and then often the last cast which comes from
the bottom and which is the thickest of the dish, may easily become
porous. Cast thinner and neater, as long as you blow very strongly on
the soaked sand while casting in order to clear the little air
bubbles.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

When the sand is casted thick, it often becomes porous

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p133v_2</id>

<head>Thing that cannot be released from the mold</head>

<ab>

You must cut it inside the mold in order to burn it. Cut it with
scissors at once, that way <m>blood</m> doesn't flow on the mold, and
doesn't make dirty. Because this dirt would be removed with difficulty
when reheated. Then place your mold into a furnace, or something
similar, in order to quickly dry the mold which must be removed before
the forming of crusts or molds.@ </ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<figure>+</figure>

When you mold small <al>lizards</al>, and when you want to peel away the
first molded part, start to peel away the heads, you will know its place
thanks to the needle.

Don't peel away the legs before peeling away the entire body, to avoid
that the naked body, moving,doesn't remove the legs from their place,
which would not be easy to put back into place. When you remove the
small needles fixing the legs, block the legs or press the legs with
something, that way while removing the needles the legs won't move;
finally, you can fix the legs again with <m>wax</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p133v_3</id>

<head>Various animals entwined</head>

<ab>

You can entwine a <al>snake</al> with a <al>lizard</al>, each one biting
the other, or a <al>snake</al> eating a <al>frog</al>, or a <al>wall
lizard</al> or something similar. But since these interlacings cannot be
stripped, cut what's possible, and allow the rest to burn. To make the
mouth of the <al>snake</al>, which must stand high, hold a <al>wall
lizard</al>, which is small and would need to be held in the air,
because the <al>snake</al>'s head is higher, put under the <al>wall
lizard</al> a mound of earth suitable to support it. And if you place
the mold in a furnace, the animal drying quickly, it will quickly
shrink, then it will burn more easily. These interlacings are also made
to mask wounds or defects on the animal which happen when we catch them.
Do not forget to join with <m>wax</m>, applied carefully with a hot
<m>iron</m> wire, all the parts of the animal which are one on top of
the other, or those which are not well pressed on the slab of clay, so
that the soaked sand does not remove them. Do that in order to </ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
