<root>
<page>132r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f269.item.r=</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p131v_1</id>

<ab>to not open your mold too hott, for this sours it, makes it porous
&amp; contracts the tin &amp; makes the molded thing break. Also, do not
quench your hot mold in water, for this makes the <del>le met</del> tin
or lead contract.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p132r_1</id>
<head>Mold made in two casts</head>

<ab>It opens once reheated to be cleaned, next, one puts the clamps on
again, one lutes the mold &amp; especially the joints, then one slowly
dries the earth. And then, as it no longer smokes, one leaves the mold
to cool until you hold it without harm. Next, put in the presses or in
the sand in a <fr>terrine</fr>, &amp; cast in tin. For if you were to
cast in silver or gold, it would be necessary that your mold be reheated
twice &amp; cast, as it would be red.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
If your mold <del>f</del>, through the fault of the plaster, retracts in
the fire, one needs to open it, after the first reheating, to tighten it
again &amp; clamp it and lute again and tighten again. </ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p132r_2</id>
<head>Method for reheating the molds</head>

<ab>Light <m>charcoals</m> in the forge, &amp; then arrange them in rows
in a corner of it, according to the size of your mold, in such a way
that it can be furnished with three or 4 fingers all around, and
especially at the bottom of the mold, which is the thickest, <del>and
which</del>. Your charcoals thus arranged, place your molds on top of
them, &amp; not on a <fr>grille</fr>, as some do, because they would
take the fire too harshly. And leave for some time thusly, &amp; little
&amp; by little warm your oven, always adding some lit charcoal. And as
long as the mold is damp, the charcoals will be as if died down from
below. But as it dries, they will light themselves. And when it is dry
on one side, turn it to the other. And when it is dry on both, &amp; it
no longer smokes. At that moment, invigorate the fire &amp; cover it
with lit charcoals. And as it begins to redden, do not blow the
charcoals with a little bellows, for this would make it <del>blow</del>
burst. And similarly, when it is red, keep it well covered with lit
charcoals &amp; do not uncover it, for it would break. Make sure wind
from a window does not beat on it. Let cool</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
When you want to reheat your molds, <del>&amp;</del> be they luted or
not, mark the place on the belly to put it under, against the lit
charcoals <del>que</del> because if the ardor of the fire would make
them crack, it would be better that this be at the belly &amp; from
underneath, than on the back.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
@If your mold is small, one ought not to leave it <del>rest</del> so
much in the fire, for it corrupts and breaks there, for it reheats more
quickly than a big one.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
