<root>
<page>080r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f165.item</image>

<div>

<id>p080r_1</id>

<head>Mortar</head>

<ab>They make them of fine material and fine copper in the shape of
reinforced barrel, and which can hold 50 pounds of powder, and having
made a clean hole in the ground at the foot of a wall, they embed the
said loaded mortar in this hole, with the mouth on top, which will make
a large breach.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p080r_2</id>

<head>Very hard white <m>stucco</m></head>

<ab><m>White wax</m>, <m><pl>Venice</pl> turpentine</m>,
<m>eggshell</m>, &amp; <m>ceruse</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p080r_3</id>

<head>Fountains</head>

<figure>

<id>fig_p080r_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5c3dLNVNsem9nTjQ</link>

</figure>

<ab>If you wish to raise <m>water</m> higher than its source, make a
pipe descend as in A. to B. to give it push <del/>, then from B. to C.
make the pipe ascend, but not quite to the height of the source, here
represented by the dotted line, and then make it descend again in a pipe
from C. to D., and then let it rise higher than the line demarcating the
height of the source, and do this successively until you reach the
desired height. Remark nonetheless that the length of the descending
pipe is always twice as long as the ascending pipe. This cone also fills
itself and demonstrates a perpetual fountain which you can adapt into a
rock, attracting the water with which it is filled by the tip here
marked, by sucking and breathing in. You can also make a watering can
pipe in this way, so long as the bent pipe is just as long as the
straight pipe, but does not extend as far down.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p080r_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5N2U2RXB5UFc3TUE</link>

</figure>

<figure>

<id>fig_p080r_3</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5R2ZBNWRseEpQdnc</link>

</figure>

</div>
</root>
