<root>
<page>094r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f193.image</image>

<div>
<id>p094r_a1</id>
<head><pro>Furbisher</pro></head>

<ab>The parts of a sword are the tang, the tail of the sword, what comes
next is the heel, the rest is the blade. The sides are the edge &amp;
the point. Some blades, acute in point, have only one side filed in the
middle &amp; along the whole length, and are easy to break. The other
blades are called of three molds or three grips, which do have a rise in
the middle, but it is flat as if it were acute in point but flattened,
and <del><fr>s</fr></del> these ones are the safest. The others
<del>are</del> are called fluted, which are notched in the middle, &amp;
when it is along the whole length, they are just as easy to break as
those acute in point &amp; are more troublesome to furbish because the
burnishing stick cannot get in. But one makes one in particular which is
narrow.</ab>

<ab>Of the hilt of the sword are the pommel, the branches of the hilt
&amp; the cross-guard, which is this <m>iron</m> strip which closes off
the branch which is at the end of the heel to stop thrusts from sliding
down the hilt. The rings are these two branches in half-round which
start from the eye of the guard up to the branch of the cross-guard. The
branch that crosses the hilt is called the body. And this escutcheon, by
which the sword tail enters and to which all the branches return &amp;
are held, is called the eye of the guard.</ab>

<ab>Then follows the <m>wood</m> of the handle which one <m>glue</m>s,
or according to the most competent, with <m>gummed wax</m> which is of
<m>wax</m> &amp; <m>pitch</m>, because <m>resin</m> would be too hard.
They heat it lightly, then rubs the <m>wood</m> of the handle in order
that the tang takes hold there, otherwise, if a <m>thread</m> were to
come loose, the whole <del><fr>d</fr></del> would break immediately. On
<m>iron</m> wire or <m>dog skin</m>, one also puts <m>glue</m> on it.
The trimming <del>of</del> which is put on the <m>wood</m>
<del>of</del>, which is of <m>silk</m> or <m>thread</m>, is called the
cord, which is made from two <del>thr</del> or three <m>threads</m>
t<del>wisted</del> twined on the spinning wheel, or 4 if the <m>silk</m>
is thin. The slightly bigger cord holds better. The rivement, which is
also made of <m>silk</m> at both ends of the handle, are called the
buttons.</ab>

<ab>Some handles are made of <m>silk</m>, <m>dogfish skin</m>, reheated
<m>iron</m> thread, threads of <m>gold</m> &amp; of <m>fine</m> <m>&amp;
false silver</m> &amp; of <m>velvet</m>. <m>Iron</m> thread has a lower
price &amp; is the most durable. Next is the handle of <m>silk</m>, if
one does not have the convenience of being close to the sea to procure
some <m>dogfish skin</m>, which is quite convenient. <del>To</del> The
beautiful <m>skin</m> costs fifty or lx <cn><fr>sous</fr></cn> &amp; 4
or five dozen handles are made from it. This kind gives a good grip even
if the hand is sweating. To put it to work, if it is too hard, one soaks
it for one or two hours in not quite lukewarm <m>aquafortis</m>, for if
it were too hot, it would cook &amp; spoil the <m>skin</m>. It is sewn
with <m>black thread</m>.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p094r_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5YTlFNHRBSVRrOEU</link>
</figure>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
