<root>
<page>130v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f266.item</image>

<div>
<id>p130v_1</id>
<head>Molding a crab</head>

<ab>It is a secret and a masterpiece to mold it well, because one needs
to proceed differently than with other animals, because its shell is
very difficult to <del>mold</del> burn &amp; in this case, one
<del>le</del> needs to sometimes reheat the mold three or four times.
And with all of this, it leaves a hard crust, grey like ash. But because
it does not mold in one piece &amp; one cast, like plants, but rather in
two casts like snakes that release well, one removes this crust, not
with quicksilver, which would do nothing, after it is open, with the
very fine point of a pen-knife with dexterity, as with the little crusts
of the second cast, which enter in the nooks that the sand or the molded
animal made. But, <del>la</del> because it has curved legs, here is the
cunning way &amp; secret for releasing it. Therefore, as you have molded
it on one side, which is on the back, in the same way as others, uncover
its belly, &amp; all its curved legs. Make your second cast in the same
way as others, but, as it will have set, keep from opening the mold
until you have first reheated it well. Otherwise, because of its curved
legs, you would break everything. In this lies the dexterity. If you
recognize, after having reheated &amp; opened it, that the crust is not
burned enough, reheat until it does.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
It is painted like a crayfish.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<del>Know that</del> For opening the mold, there is no need to soak it,
for once reheated, it will open by itself.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p130v_2</id>
<head>Stag beetle</head>

<ab>It is as difficult to burn as a crab, therefore do for it as you did
for the crab.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p130v_3</id>
<head>For molding thin</head>

<ab>After you have molded in <fr>noyau</fr> <del>la</del> the first
<del>e figur</del> mold, let it dry well before taking away the figure
of wax, <del>order</del> in order that the mold does not corrupt. Next,
make a small lasagna of paste of such thickness that you would like, and
having smeared with butter <del>your</del> the hollow of your first
hollow mold, adapt the paste to it and then make your second mold on
top. If you were to smear with oil, it would be absorbed &amp; would not
be as appropriate as butter.</ab>

</div>
</root>
