<root>
<page>120r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f245.image</image>

<div>
<id>p120r_1</id>
<head>Stamped medals made from <m>wax</m></head>

<ab>You can mold your relief with <m>wax</m> mixed with a bit of
<m>resin</m> to make it harder and firmer, whatever relief that you
wish, either an animal or a medal. And then, fashion a hollow out of
this relief in <m>brass</m> or <m>copper</m>. Or mold your
<x><m>wax</m></x> in relief and strike it in a sheet of <m>tin</m>. And
fill <x>your final product</x> with <m>lead</m>, and heat it. Try <x>to
use</x> blades of <m>stone leaf</m> to make the hollow for lizards
&amp;</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p120r_a2</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> for casting <m>gold</m></head>

<ab>Take <m>common sand</m> made of <m>alum, plaster</m> and
<m>brick</m>, according to the composition above-mentioned. Add to it
some more <m>feather alum</m>. And add as well something a third part of
<m>crocum ferri</m>. However whatever quantity is never harmful, because
<x><m>crocum ferri</m></x> is the one that makes <m>gold</m> shiny and
makes it come out of its cast easily. But it is best if your
<m>crocum</m> has previously been left for three days and three nights
in the furnace of <pro>glassworkers</pro>, in a flat box, where it is
not very thick so that it will reheat better.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
You can easily cast <m>gold</m> with the <m>common sand</m> of
<pro>goldsmiths</pro>, but <x>make sure</x> that you add some substance
that makes it runny. Before the invention of <m>crocum</m>, one cast
flowers in <m>silver</m>, but not in gold. This has only been known in
Germany for forty years.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<m>Sublimate</m> is often used by <pro>goldsmiths</pro> for <m>gold</m>.
Some people add <m>sulphur</m>, but they are all wrong, because
<m>sulphur</m> makes things sour, even if it heats <x>well.</x>, And
<m>sublimate</m> gets agitated,boils and bubbles. It is very good to
clean <m>gold</m> because its exaltation draws <x>the bad stuff</x> out
that disappears in the smoke. But to heat up <m>gold</m>, and to keep
the heat, there is only the color of <m>verdigris</m>, <m>salt of
ammoniacum</m>, <m>saltpeter</m>, and <m>borax</m>. This makes it runny
and you will be able to throw in a branch from the Santoinge.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p120r_a3</id>
<head>Nightingale</head>

<ab>It is necessary for the cage, made like those for larks found in
barns and lined with green fabric, to be made with something that slides
out from underneath, so that you can refresh the dirt everyday, because
the nightingale loves it, and mix in some ants. You can carry an
ant-hill with its dirt in a barred full of earth, and keep them there
and they will lay their eggs and in this way, you can always have access
to them when you need them, should you enjoy feeding nightingales. When
you caught it, it was fat and full. And to keep it in such good shape,
on the first day, you must take it in you hand and open its beak and
place in it, using a sharp twig, some mutton heart or other delicate
flesh, chopped up not too finely, so that the belly does something, and
make sure that it does not get smaller or thinner, until it has gotten
used to it. And feed it in this way three or four times a day, and also
give it something to drink. The next morning, you will give him in his
cage some well-minced flesh mixed with the yolk of a hard-boiled egg,
and change this mixture two or three times a day, because it will not
eat it if it is hard and not fresh. And If it goes half a day without
eating, you must feed it as before and do so until</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
