<root>
<page>015r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f35.image</image>

<div>
<id>p015r_a1</id>
<head><m>Damasked Cloth</m></head>

<ab>You can damask a <m> cloth</m> of two different colours and imitate
embroidery without adding anything else to it, as follows. Once it is is
<m>dye</m>d yellow, pounce onto it such a pattern as will please you.
Then you will sew some <m>string</m> or a bigger <m>cord</m> loosely
onto the pattern and throw it into a <m>dye</m> of <m>woad</m> or
<m>pastel</m> and it will become green, except that which is beneath the
<m>string</m>, which will remain yellow because the <m>green dye</m>
will not have penetrated there. And you can do the same with other
colours and, instead of <m>string</m> or <m>cord</m>, add some pieces of
poor quality <m>cloth</m> cut in Moorish shapes on top of the first
colour. In that manner, you will have cheap embroidery.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p015r_a2</id>
<head>Casting molten <m>metals</m></head>

<ab>One casts candlesticks and small works in a <tl>frame</tl> with
sand. And after having imprinted the work, one sprinkles the frame with
<m>flour</m> in order to make the <del><fr>e metal</fr></del>
<m>copper</m> or <m>latten</m> run better. When the sand has been used
for a <ms>month</ms>, it is necessary to take some new sand, because the
one that was used, having been reheated <del>in fire</del>
<figure>+</figure>, dries out &amp; loses its ability to bond. However,
it is used to mix with the new sand, for it makes the work not so
porous. One casts large works such as artillery, bells &amp; similar
things in <m>earth</m>, &amp; <m>copper</m> cast in <m>earth</m> makes
less of a <fr>chappe</fr>, and is whiter than the one cast in sand. The
<m>earth</m> is <m>sandy clay</m> mixed with <m><al>horse</al> dung</m>
&amp; <m>cloth</m> waste. The <m>earth</m> that <del>is</del> has been
used for casting, which is black, baked &amp; as if burnt, is used to
cast, <del><fr>gecte</fr></del> mixed with <m>artificial sand</m>, &amp;
is very good. <add>To soften &amp; make the <m>copper</m> run, throw in,
once it is melted, a little <m>lead</m>, which does not form an alloy
but is found on the surface of the cast.</add></ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<figure>+</figure> by the heat of molten <m>metal</m></ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p015r_a3</id>
<head>Casting <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m></head>

<ab>The sand must be from something very dry &amp; arid &amp; reheated
well in the <tl>frame</tl>, because, if it were humid, like
<m><pro>founder</pro>'s sand</m>, the <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m>
would spatter, &amp; cause damage. It is also necessary for the
<m>earth</m> to absorb the <m>metal</m>, for cast <m>gold</m> or
<m>silver</m> <del>is</del> become very spongy. That is why it must be
beaten again, otherwise it is brittle, as one sees in spoon
handles.</ab>

</div>
</root>
