<root>
<page>159r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f323.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p159r_a1</id>
<head>

Portraits in <m>Wax</m></head>

<ab>

If you do not mix your <m>wax</m> with any color <m>dye</m>, and if you
paint some colors on the <m>wax</m>, these colors would fade if you cast
it en noyau. But the representation is not damaged, rub it very lightly
with spirits diluted with hot <m>water</m>. If your representations are
varnished, repeat the molding process two or three times in order to
remove this <m>varnish</m> which sticks to the mold. When the
<m>varnish</m> is removed, your mold is very clean. If your
representation is set on <m>wood</m>, it is necessary to pour very hot
melted <m>wax</m> on the <m>wood,</m> otherwise the mold sticks to the
<m>wood</m>. It is much better to mix your white <m>wax</m> with
<m>white lead</m> than <m>ceruse</m>, because <m>white lead</m> is
whiter and more firm.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p159r_a2</id>
<head>

Chasing tool</head>

<ab>

If a chasing tool has passed through any part of the representation, it
is necessary to rework the whole thing and follow it all again.
Otherwise it would look like an additional piece.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p159r_a3</id>
<head>

<m>Fish glue</m></head>

<ab>

Beat it very finely &amp; thinly on a well-cleaned anvil, &amp; next wet
it with <m>eau-de-vie</m> over <del>ch</del> hot ashes &amp; a low fire,
&amp; it will be quickly melted; &amp; if it is not strong &amp; thick
enough, add <m>eau-de-vie</m>. And take heed <del>them</del> not to put
it in a fatty <m>vessel</m>, but in a new one, if you can. It is melted
on the fire &amp;is also dried quickly on the fire, but it may be warmed
from a distance once on the work. It holds strongly. One adjoins with it
flowers &amp; delicate things of <m>gold</m>, of <m>silver</m>, of
<m>tin</m>, &amp; other materials which are in danger of spoiling if
soldered.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p159r_a4</id>
<head>

<m>Tin</m> and <m>lead</m></head>

<ab>

They must be beaten out very finely and <m>tin</m> will not get brittle
or break, <m>lead</m> is a bit fatter. But that is why it is necessary
to reheat it under hot ashes, and to beat several leaves together.</ab>

</div>
</root>
