<root>
<page>163r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f331.image</image>

<div>

<id>p163r_1</id>

<head><pro>Perfume maker</pro></head>

<ab>They readily put half of <m>amber</m> &amp; half of <m>musk</m>,
&amp; a very little <m>civet</m>, because <m>amber</m> always overtakes
the principal scent of <m>musk</m>.</ab>

<ab>To spare the <m>amber</m>, they readily put a little <m>musk</m> in
the white layers, which gives a more severe scent. But to remove or hide
the blackness of the <m>musk</m>, they put in a little of <m>wheat
starch</m> from <pl>England</pl>, which is perfectly white.</ab>

<del>When the <m>amber</m></del>

<ab>To make a perfume of <m>white amber</m> in the fashion of those in
<pl>Portugal</pl>, take a <fr>huchau</fr> of <m>amber</m> well broken
up. And having put in a small <m>silver</m> bowl a
<del><m>silver</m></del> <ms>spoonful</ms> of <m>flower oil</m>, or
lacking that, <m><fr>Ben oil</fr>l</m>, that is to say, a <m>silver</m>
spoon that one uses at the table, put in your <m>ambergris</m> &amp;
place all on a low fire, and it will melt quickly if your <m>amber</m>
is good, &amp; it will remain there without lumps. Once all melted, put
in the amount of a <fr>pinon</fr> of <m>civet</m>, &amp; make it melt
&amp; mix it well together. Next take your gloves, well-cleaned &amp;
well-dried, &amp; dipping the tip of your finger very lightly
<del>on</del> on the edge of the <m>oil</m>, spread it on the glove
little by little &amp; with patience &amp; rub the glove between your
hands, &amp; trace the fingers &amp; the stitches, one after the other.
And leave it to dry. Next trace again as before until the <m>amber</m>
is all laid down.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p163r_2</id>

<head><m>Spirits</m></head>

<ab><m>Spirits</m> are excellent for making molds clean, in such a way
that where you do not apply some, common sand will attach to the figure.
But it needs to be passed three times. And because it does not take well
on oiled things, I believe it may be best to put some into the
<m>water</m> with which you have moistened your sand.</ab>

</div>
</root>
