<root>
<page>120v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f246.image</image>

<div>

<id>p120r_3</id>

<ab>eats by itself. And to entice it better, you could add amongst the
meat &amp; the egg some live mealworms, for it is very fond of
them.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p120v_1</id>
<head><m>Crocum ferri</m></head>

<ab>It is excellent plastered on wounds to stop the blood. The best is
made of <m>needle filings</m>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<m>Crocum ferri</m> hardens molds, being reheated, &amp; <m>alum de
plum</m>, as much as there is some, renders them softer &amp;
<fr>doulx</fr>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p120v_2</id>
<head>Anatomy</head>

<ab> One needs to skin the animal &amp; boil it, or else skin it &amp;
put it into good <m>quicklime</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p120v_3</id>
<head>Making <m>silver</m> run</head>

<ab><del>If it is for a large work, <m>arsenic</m> &amp; pulverized
<m>tartar</m> &amp; thrown on the melted <m>silver</m>, makes it run
<del>If it is</del> and it suffices. But for fine work, one needs <m>aes
ustum</m>, small filings <del>of latten</del> of copper, <del>du</del>
<m>antimony</m>, <m>sublimate</m>, finely pulverized. <del>This</del>
All of this makes a mass that does sour at all. If the <del>s</del>
<m>plaster</m> is good, one ought not add <m>crocum</m> for
<m>silver</m>, but one puts more <m>alum de plume</m>.@ It needs also
some melted <m>common salt</m>, &amp; some <m>saltpeter</m> with the
aforementioned drugs: <m>arsenic, tartar, aes ustum, copper filings,
antimony</m> &amp;</del></ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<la>Doubtful question</la></ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
A little <m>tallow</m> and <m>arsenic</m>.</ab>

<figure/>

</div>
<div>
<id>p120v_5</id>

<figure><margin>left-middle</margin>+</figure>

<ab>See the second folio following</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>
Flowers can also be kept in their same beauty in distilled
<m>vinegar</m> in a well-sealed vase which does not admit any wind,
which should be well sealed with <m>wax</m> &amp; &amp; <m>mastic</m>.
The residue of common <m>vinegar</m> makes carnations &amp; roses rot.
If the <m>sand</m> makes dust, &amp; clings to the flowers &amp; does
not easily come off with a <fr>pinceau</fr>, it is no good. The leanest
is the best.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p120v_6</id>

<head>Keeping dry flowers in the same condition all year</head>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
<m>River sand</m> washed by the current of the waters, is good once
passed through a linen cloth to shake the powder.</ab>

<ab>This is a rare secret, &amp; which gives pleasure for adorning
tables, rooms, &amp; cabinets out of season when winter denies flowers.
Take heed, therefore, to <del><fr>ce</fr></del> pick them when they are
in full vigor &amp; growing. For if you were to take them when their
season is past, or when they are starting to wilt, they would not keep.
Having thus chosen them, therefore, take <m>sand</m>, the leanest &amp;
driest you can find, which should be very fine, like that which
<pro>goldsmiths</pro> <del>use</del> use to work <m>enamel</m>, or like
that for impressions. But above all it must not make dust, nor remain on
the hand or leave a mark on it when you have pulverized it &amp; then
poured it from your hand. For it is</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<figure>+</figure>

Make sure your box is well joined in order that the <m>sand</m> does not
trickle out. Keep it uncovered in sunlight and remove it from the
<fr>serain</fr>, &amp; the humidity of the night, &amp; cover it &amp;
keep it in a dry place.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<del><fr>Que</fr></del>Take heed not to put the said flowers in big
vases, for when one pulls out one, one needs to pull out all. </ab>

<ab>
<margin>bottom</margin>
Take good heed not to pick your flowers <del>w</del> in rainy and humid
weather, but when the sun has been shining on them.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
