<root>
<page>131v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f268.item.r=</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p131r_5</id>

<ab>in a round form to cast it in <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m>, put
only in your wax what you prepare for this effect <del>sino</del> from
all these drugs, except casting with melted sulphur, since it is melted
&amp; candle smoke. The melted sulphur goes to the bottom and
nevertheless leaves its quality in the wax, making it melt readily in
the fire &amp; giving it firmness. In this way, you can melt in the fire
this roughed out <del>ci</del> figure of wax. But if it is composed of
ceruse or similar things, it is necessary that you put your mold in
boiling water.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
For figures of flat wax, there is no need for all this, for the wax
releases &amp; does not stay in the <del>la</del> mold.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p131v_1</id>
<head>When the cast of <m>tin</m> or <m>lead</m> becomes porous</head>

<ab>

If your cast work has become porous, it can be repaired with very hard
wax, that you can gilt afterwards with silver or gold. To prevent this,
if you cast thin, the alloy of one <ms>℥</ms> <del>d’est</del> of lead
for one <ms>lb</ms> of tin is good. But if you cast with lead for a
thick thing, one needs for one <ms>lb</ms> of the latter, two <ms>℥</ms>
of tin, for the lead being fat &amp; weighty, carries more. From this
alloy, I cast a large lizard, as if natural. In thick things,
<del>if</del> which keep their heat a long time, if there is little tin,
it makes it porous. Your mold must not be cold, but of such a heat that
you can handle without harm, or that you can keep your finger in the
cast without burning it. It also necessary that your lead or tin be like
red.Melt firstly the lead, &amp; then the alloy of tin on top. And as
you want to cast, put a piece of resin &amp; then a little looking-glass
tin. @If you put into the tin too much lead, it does not run very thin.
And to know this, if <del>l</del> the tin shouts loudly, it is a sign
there is not enough lead. If it shouts slowly, that means that is there
is too much. Take heed</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
You can solder with the <del>l’es</del> same substance, then repair it
with the burin, file, <fr>chaple</fr> &amp; similar things.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>

<m>Tin</m> is a metal that penetrates, that becomes porous &amp; burns,
and is fanciful to us, more than gold and silver.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<m>Lead</m> wants not only to be red, but also lively &amp; runny &amp;
liquid as water, which is a sign of its perfect heat &amp; the mold
<del>ch</del><del>f</del> is so hot that you suffer with your finger in
it. Do not open until it is cooled. It is a sign of a good cast, as much
for it as for gold &amp; silver when it exits by the vents.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
