<root>
<page>017r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f39.image</image>

<div>

<id>p017r_1</id>

<head>On <pro>cannon-makers</pro></head>

<ab>

The cannon <fr>tire de poincte en blanc</fr> five to six hundred
<ms>paces</ms>. But not for making battery, for which it is only able to
make a good execution of two hundred paces, or three hundred at the
most, it should not be any farther. Its ball usually weighs 40
<ms>lb</ms> of the King's standard. There is a fowler, which weighs xxv
<ms>quintals</ms>, which is a small, short cannon. It is for fighting
the cassemattes des fossés &amp; for close fighting. It bears large
cannonballs of 40 <ms>lb</ms> of the King's standard like the others. It
bears in the breech only the width of two balls &amp; a quarter of a
ball. The front only bears the width of one ball &amp; the a third of a
ball. Its load is similar to those bigger, namely xx <ms>lb</ms>. And
when one wants to try them, one ought not to overload it, for this
damages the piece. And for the first time &amp; until it has been fired
five or six shots, it is better not to give its whole load, for the
piece is stabilized. And the test that one can do is to give it a load
of xx <ms>lb</ms> of fine arquebus <m>powder</m> instead of ordinary
cannon <m>powder</m>. And four good <al>horses</al> are sufficient to
carry it. They are easy to use &amp; close up they make as much force as
the big ones, particularly for private houses &amp; small towns &amp;
fortresses of little importance. They are not more prone to bursting
than the others because they are short. For that which gives great
strength to the <m>powder</m> &amp; endangers the piece of breaking is
the length of the piece, because the <m>powder</m> is burned entirely
before it goes out, &amp; its energy is held in containment longer in a
long piece than a short. The fowler is usually seven to eight
<fr><ms>pan</ms></fr>s long. It is true that this is a <ms><fr>pan</fr>
of <pl>Montpellier</pl></ms> &amp; not a <ms>pan</ms> of the King's
standard, which is not used in casting cannons for making them good. For
the <ms><fr>pan</fr> of <pl>Montpellier</pl></ms> being shorter, the
cannons proportioned there are shorter also, &amp;compensate in
thickness the length that they would have by the <ms><fr>pan</fr> of the
King's standard</ms>, by which measure they will be found longer. But
also they will be thinner. The strength of the fowler for making battery
is 80 <fr><ms>paces</ms></fr>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

The great cannon, because of the weight of its ball, carries a range of
only a thousand or xii hundred <ms>paces</ms> without landing, &amp;
doing good, it usually does iii good.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

The fowlers do not have a large range if not close.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

One knows the good alloy of a piece by seeing it. For if, with the
energy that they expel into the area around them, they redden, that is
to say that they are composed of a sufficient quantity of
<m>rosette</m>. If not, they are only of <m>metal</m>, which appears
whitish. If they themselves do not make this demonstration, scratch
&amp; you will see. </ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

The good alloy for pieces is of three <fr><ms>parts</ms></fr> of
<m>rosette</m> &amp; one of the fine <m>metal</m> from a big bell, where
there is more <m>rosette</m> than in the <m>metal</m> of small bells.
The <m>metal</m> usually costs xv <cn>lb</cn> &amp; fine <m>rosette</m>
xv or xvi.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

The <ms><fr>pan</fr></ms> of <pl>Montpellier</pl> is equivalent to six
<ms>poulces</ms> of the King's standard, which holds two common. </ab>

<ab>

<margin>bottom</margin>

It is necessary, for aiming a piece well, that it be as high at the side
of the opening as the breech. Otherwise, one does not aim well.

</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
