<root>
<page>123v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f252.item.r=</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p123r_1</id>

<ab>Your lute once dry, put your crucible in an <fr>four a vent</fr> in
the early morning, &amp; at the beginning, give low fire, as much as you
need to heat your crucible as to let the fury of the <m>saltpeter</m>
pass gently. Then, little by little &amp; with judgement intensify the
fire. And <fr><del>y</del></fr> leave in the fullness of this your
ingredients for 12 hours, or a natural day. Make at each go a good
quantity of this mixture to not have to repeat it too often, because the
fumes, which are dangerous, could hurt you. And before working with it,
take a good piece of buttered toast in the morning, and hold in your
mouth the said <m>butter</m>, or <m>zedoary</m>, or <m>gold</m> coins,
and <fr><del>ada</del></fr> cover your face with a towel from the eyes
down. From this mass, the crust will serve to <del>make run</del>
clarify <del>the great works of</del> the <m>silver</m> from the
metallic mass <del>like <al>snakes</al> &amp; similar things</del> when
it starts to melt. <del>But</del> And then, the grain that will be at
the bottom of the <tl>crucible</tl> should be reserved for
<del>principally delicate flowers and herbs</del> putting a little in
the melted <m>silver</m> when you want to cast it, <del>However it is
necessary to always put a little of this grain in the <m>silver</m> when
<del>you want to cast</del> it is melted and when you are ready to
cast</del> as you do thus for fine <m>tin</m> on <m>copper</m>, &amp;
for <m>looking-glass tin</m> on <m>lead</m> and on <m>tin</m>. And just
as <m>looking-glass tin</m> makes <m>lead</m> and <m>tin</m> too brittle
if you put in too much, likewise the grain composed of the
above-mentioned ingredients would make your silver too brittle if
<del>l</del> you were to put in too much, and obscure it. This
above-mentioned composition will suffice you for a long time, when it
has been on a <del>low</del> low fire for a whole day at the beginning
&amp; intensified degree by degree until the end. Having thrown one load
of charcoal, let it consume itself, &amp; let your <tl>crucible</tl>
cool down. Then break it. You will find two sheets &amp; hard cakes in
the <tl>crucible</tl>. The upper one looks stoned <del>Once</del>, once
composed of <m>salts</m>,sublimated &amp; mixed together. The lower one
is metallic, composed of fillings, <m>aes ustum</m> &amp;
<m>antimony</m>, having very small grain. Pulverize the upper cake, made
from <m>salts</m>, &amp; put some in to lighten &amp; clean the
<m>silver</m> and the metallic grain can be used to put into the melted
metal.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<m>Charcoal</m> fire</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Or, after you have pestled your <m>drugs</m> by a rustic, and having put
them in your crucible, &amp; the latter luted &amp; dry as said &amp;
place into the furnace, have the fire managed by a <fr>boutique</fr>
boy, familiar with <m>charcoal</m>. </ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
One sells this metallic mass to <pro>silversmiths</pro> to soften their
solder, because when melting <m>brass</m> exhales. And with a little of
this mixture, they solder over the other solder.</ab>

</div>
</root>
