<root>
<page>036r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f77.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p035v_2</id>

<ab>

so that it cannot be seen, &amp; you will cunningly and with grace cast
all of it into the bag or pouch.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p036r_1</id>

<head>For transmuting a ball into a thin thimble</head>

<figure>

<id>fig_p036r_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5UmZaWjV2VE82QjQ</link>

<caption>de cuir</caption>

</figure>

<ab>Make a small case of plain <m>cow leather</m> or <m><pl>Spanish</pl>
goat's leather</m> quite thick, as high as three fingers, sewn like the
finger of a glove and large enough that two fingertips can fit inside
and which, at the tip, is a little creased, and has a round hole as
large as a double liard. Take two <m>boxwood</m> balls that look the
same, and one should be hollowed and opened by a round hole only on one
side so that the thimble can enter. Thus, when you want to perform, you
will place your <m>leather</m> case on the table with the ball that is
not hollow. Put a stick into the <m>leather</m> case to show that there
is nothing inside it, also show the round ball, and hold the hollow one
which has the thimble inside it between your little and ring finger, and
do this with your right hand with which you hold the stick. After, take
the <m>leather</m> case and place it over the hollow ball which is
between your fingers and pretend you put some <m>goldibus powder</m>
upon it, and replace the <m>leather</m> case that contains the ball on
the table, then you take the large round ball remaining on the table,
and order it to enter from upon the table into the <m>leather</m> case.
Then, lifting the <m>leather</m>, it will seem to be the same, although
it is the hollow one. Then, cover it and command that it should become
invisible, and lifting the case while pressing it, you will remove it at
the same time as the ball, and meanwhile discreetly put it back in the
case. In its place will be found a thimble for the ladies whose bottom
hurts, that is the bottom of the needle.</ab>

</div>
</root>
