<root>
<page>148r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f301.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p147v_4</id>

<ab>not come out as clear as I wanted. I reheated it again, let it cool,
put it into the <m>bleach</m> again, and brushed <x>it</x>. It came out
very clear. In this way, you will do <x>the same</x> for <m>copper</m>
and <m>silver</m>. And if you want to give...</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p148r_1</id>

<head>Beautiful color for <m>brass</m></head>

<ab>Having cleaned it well, as is stated, and brushed it well, boil it
in water with <m>curcuma root</m> or <m>terra merita</m>, and it will
become very beautiful.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p148r_2</id>

<head><m>Bleach</m></head>

<ab>If it is for <m>silver</m>, do not grind your <m>tartar</m> with
<sup>something made of</sup> <m>iron</m>, but with the handle of a
hammer, because if you touch <x>your tartar with iron</x> and <x>end
up</x> getting some <m>iron</m> in your <m>bleach</m>, the <m>silver</m>
will come out red, like <m>copper</m>, and you will need to reheat it
and put it back in the <m>bleach</m>. Mix in nothing with your
<m>tartar</m> that should not enter the <m>bleach</m>, because this
ruins it. Do not let it spill out when it first starts to boil because
all its strength is in it <x>at this point</x>. <m>Bleach</m> is made
with one part pulverized <m>tartar</m> and a half part of common
<m>salt</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p148r_3</id>

<head>Moulding the foot of the bittern, or eagle, or other birds for the
base of saltcellars or vases</head>

<ab>One commonly molds the foot and the legs up until the calf. And for
this effect, one molds it in five pieces: the leg in two pieces, the top
of the foot in two, and the bottom in one piece.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>with three pieces</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p148r_4</id>

<head><m>Crocum Ferri</m></head>

<ab>To make this quickly, redden the <m>filings</m> in an <m>iron</m>
ladle, stirring it often. Then sprinkle it with some good <m>vinegar</m>
and let it evaporate. And without taking it away from above the fire,
let it redden and take flame. Having been cooled, pulverise <x>it</x> on
the <m>marble</m> and return it to the heat, sprinkle with
<m>vinegar</m>, and then set it on fire. In this way it will soon be
colored and made fine.</ab>

</div>
</root>
