<root>
<page>019r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f43.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p017r_1</id>

<ab>

of campaign. The <fr>faulconneau</fr> is commonly loaded with a
<tl>linstock</tl>, and one commonly gives it only one linstock. There
are also other <fr>faulconneaux</fr> weighing three
<fr><ms>quintals</ms></fr>, and which are nine <fr><ms>pans</ms></fr>
long. Their cannonball weighs half a pound. Their load is a quarter
pound of <m>powder</m>. They can be loaded with a <tl>linstock</tl>, but
more commonly they are loaded with a charge. The breech is three
cannonballs thick and the front two. The small pieces which are under
three <fr><ms>quintals</ms></fr> are at least three cannonballs and a
twelfth of a cannonball thick at the breech, and the front thickness is
sometimes reduced to get the proportion according to the length.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

The strength of the piece is at the level of the <fr>tourillon</fr>,
where the lighted <m>powder</m> starts.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

The strength of the <fr>berche</fr> is at the <fr>maslée</fr>, behind
the breech.

</ab>

<ab>

A double musket weighs 2 <fr><ms>quintal</ms>s</fr> and is seven
<fr><ms>pan</ms>s</fr> long. Its cannonball is a quarter of a pound or
less. The breech is three cannonballs thick, and the front two. It is
loaded with as much <m>powder</m> as cannonballs, to the top of the
touch line, which is equivalent for such small pieces to 3 or 4 arquebus
<m>powder</m> cannonballs, because if cannon <m>powder</m> is used, it
can be loaded five cannonballs high.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

This has to be understood as <m>iron</m> cannonballs. When a metal
cannonball is fired, we overload it with a quarter of
<tl><ms>linstock</ms></tl> because if a cannonball weighs 40 pounds, a
metal one weights 60 pounds. This is why the sight is higher when a
metal cannonball is fired. Because if an <m>iron</m> cannonball is fired
point-blank, a metal cannonball is shot from six lines higher. A metal
cannonball, mixed with <m>copper</m> to make it more brittle, is more
effective at close range than the <m>iron</m> one. But an <m>iron</m>
one is more effective at long range. </ab>

<ab>

A simple musket weighs one <fr><ms>quintal</ms></fr> and is six
<fr><ms>pan</ms>s</fr> long. We disregard the ones that are less than
two <fr><ms>quintal</ms>s</fr>, and which usually throw lead cannonballs
by its weight, and <x>concentrate on those</x> which are loaded by
caliber. However, those <x>muskets</x> that can be loaded with metal or
<m>iron</m> cannonballs will work better, for they will do more damage
than the <m>lead ones</m>. It is loaded up to the touch line, which is 4
cannonballs thick. </ab>

<ab>

Arquebus à croc weighs 60 pounds, the bigger one is five
<fr><ms>panel</ms>s</fr> long, it is loaded up to the touch line, which
is 4 cannonballs thick; it is loaded with <m>lead</m> cannonballs, and
is for house's defence. These great and small arquebuses are used for to
make <fr>orgues</fr>, appropriate for an assault outside and inside.They
are casted separately in order to be used in various ways. See the 4th
leaf marked.

<figure>

<id>fig_p019r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5WWY3VjdlVktqZVk</link>

<!--Philip Cherian: Continues into p022v-->

</figure>

</ab>

</div>
</root>
