<root>
<page>025r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f55.item</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p024v_1</id>

<ab>a hundred feet away from the battery and should be surrounded with
barricades or trenches. And this is where they go and get <m>powder</m>
in bags or baskets. And each piece has its own basket to it three or
four times. Then, when the cannon is placed on the platform, one puts a
board that is proof of an arquebus between two gabions. Then, with a
ladle, a <pro>gunner</pro> loads it, and with the ramer which is at the
other end of the ladle, two men press as hard as they can, nine or ten
pushes, until the <m>powder</m> is dense &amp; and well compacted. Then
another one adds some <m>hay</m> or <m>straw</m> and the others ram for
a while. Another one loads the cannon ball. And the one with the
<m>hay</m> adds the same amount and presses again. Another one adds a
<m>wood</m> bung but this might damage the piece. And if one has to
shoot a lot, one would need many bungs, which are heavy to bring. When
the cannon is loaded, xx or xxv <pro>workers</pro> push it forward with
the sticks by the side, behind the gabions without taking off the board
until the cannon reaches it. Once the cannon is forward, the
<pro>gunner</pro> adjusts it with the wedges at the back, taking the
sight on each side and then in the middle. Then another one nearby sets
fire. Each cannon needs 3 <pro>gunners</pro>: one to load, one to sight,
and one to set fire. Sometimes, against a field where breaches are made,
one shoots a cartridges, as you find elsewhere, or one may use a sheep’s
leather full of <m>stones</m>, <m>cars' nails</m> or similar things. A
cannon must not be carried unless it is with two carriages, either of
<m>wood</m> or <m>iron</m>. And you need seven quintals and a half of
<m>iron</m> to fill the cannon's wheels, powder box, and other equipage.
The best battery is, according to some people, made as a curtain wall
which is on the bias, because by doing so you unsettle more stones.</ab>

<figure>----------------------------------------</figure>

<ab>

<margin>bottom</margin>

Some add small wheels and a thick board to the end of the piece so it
can be moved quicker and without noise. Others wrap some leather around
the wheels and also add soles or leather shoes to the horses' hooves so
they cannot be heard.</ab></div>
</root>
