<root>
tri6/30/2017p<page>037v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f80.image</image>

<div>

<id>p037v_1</id>

<head><pro>Gardener</pro></head>

<ab>

To sow melons properly, it must be the end of a moon <x>cycle</x>,
because otherwise they would sprout too many leaves and not bear much
fruit. Every two fingers, make small holes with a small pickaxe and, in
each, put two or three seeds. Then, take very fine <m>earth</m> and
lightly fill the holes with it. Afterwards, spread the thickness of one
thumb of 'havets,' that is wheat chaff, over everything, so that when
the rain comes, it does not beat the earth and prevent their birth.
'Hanets' attract <al>field mice</al> that eat the seeds, and to prevent
this, they must be moistened with a decoction of <m>wormwood</m>.

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p037v_2</id>

<head><pro>Glassmaker</pro></head>

<ab>

Some do not lay <m>gris d'escaille</m> on the <m>glass</m> to work on
it, but trace straight on the <m>glass</m> with <m>noir à huile</m>.
However, it is important that the <m>wood</m> be degreased, because if
it has even a little <m>grease</m> <sup>on it</sup>, the color will not
take at all. And even, if the working <pro>glassmaker</pro> has a
<sn>stink</sn> from his <bp>nose</bp> or his <bp>mouth</bp>
<del><fr>la</fr></del>, &amp; he <bp>breathes</bp> on the <m>glass</m>,
the color will not take on it. Those who came up with the invention of
working in small works of softened <m>enamels</m> use only <m>azure
enamel</m>, which is blue, &amp; <m>esmail colombin</m>, which is the
color of purple, which they soften with <m>rocks</m> or <m>lead
glass</m>. As for yellow, they make it from <m>silver</m>, red from
<m>sanguine</m>, as is said elsewhere, black &amp; gray &amp; shadows
from <m>scale black</m>, either strong or weak, carnation from <m>light
sanguine</m>. Green is made first from yellow, then they overlay
<m>azure enamel</m>, either strong or weak, depending on whether they
want to make it bright or dark.

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p037v_3</id>

<head><m>Yellow Amber</m></head>

<ab>

It is cut with a <tl>file</tl>, then one passes a certain <m>pulverized
salt</m> across the surface, which an <pl>Englishman</pl> called
<fr>desramonet</fr>. But I believe that this was <m>pulverized pumice
stone</m>, for it had the harshness of <m>arène</m>. And with a taut
<tl>cord</tl>, he polished his <m>amber</m>, then passed <tl><m>tripoli
from <pl>Bretagne</pl></m></tl> on it with the <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl>;
others used a piece of <tl><m>leather</m></tl> or a <tl>cane</tl>.
<m>Amber</m> loses its color if an unhealthy person wears it, &amp;
becomes whitish. But to restore it, it needs to be soaked for one
<ms><tmp>night</tmp></ms> in <m>urine</m>, then boiled a little in it.

</ab>

</div>
</root>
