<root>
<page>124r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f253.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p124r_1</id>
<head>Hairy animals and very fragile and thin <pa>flowers</pa></head>

<ab>Hairy animals are difficult to mold because hairs raise up &amp;
come out looking intermingled &amp; in clumps. At the beginning, it is
necessary to keep it flat with a drying agent &amp; that makes it
firmer. And in this, the best thing to use is <m>wheat oil</m>, with
which you will dawb it. Once cast, you will be able to repair it. The
bodies of <m>butterflies</m> and <m>herbs</m> that have a <m>stem</m>
&amp; <m>leaves</m> that are flocked with capricious &amp;
downy<m>hairs</m> need to be daubed with the same <m>oil</m> to keep
these flocks flat; likewise <m>flowers</m> that have very delicate &amp;
thin <m>leaves</m> because dry <m>wheat oil</m> makes them and rigid and
firm. And if someone brags about molding anything presented to them,
give them the downy head of the herb called <m>dandelion</m> to cast or
a <pa>pappus</pa>, which comes from the seeds of <pa>burdock</pa> &amp;
takes flight at the slightest sigh of wind.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p124r_1</id>
<head><fr>Noyaulx</fr> for molding hollow</head>

<ab>Animals of <m>gold</m> &amp; <m>silver</m> are generally cast hollow
to avoid weightiness, and costs as well, if they are not quite small.
But in order to make the core &amp; the <fr>noyau</fr>, the mold needs
to be freshly molded and not dry.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p124r_3</id>
<head><al>Spider</al> web</head>

<ab>It comes undone in <m>water</m> &amp; because of this, cannot be
molded in a <fr>noyau</fr>, but one casts the <m>spider</m> and then one
draws the web <m>filaments</m> that they make in the fields stretched
between blades of <m>grass</m> on some <m>carton</m> with a stylus. One
makes around it an edge of <m>paper</m>, glued to the <m>carton</m>
&amp; one casts with <m>tin</m> mixed with very little <m>lead</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p124r_4</id>
<head>Fine <m>gold</m> </head>

<ab>There is a kind of <m>gold</m> which, even though it is very fine
&amp; unalloyed &amp; has been passed through <m>aqua fortis</m> &amp;
<m>antimony</m>, is however so brittle that it hardly withstands the
hammer. And the composition of <m>verdigris</m> mentioned above to make
<m>gold</m> flow, makes it as <fr>doux</fr> as <m>lead</m>.</ab></div>
</root>
