<root>
<page>145r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f295.image</image>

<div>

<id>p145r_1</id>

<head>Casting in three frames</head>

<ab>You can cast <m>bronze</m> mortars and similar things which release
well in three frames. That is to say the body of the mortar in one, its
noyau in the other, and the base of the mortar in the third one, because
otherwise the cast which is there will not release well.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>Inquire

<figure>

<id>fig_p145r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5MXRaSldvRzY2UTg</link>

</figure>

A</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p145r_2</id>

<head><m>Cuttlefish bone</m></head>

<ab>You must not heat the <m>tin</m> or <m>lead</m> too hot, otherwise
they will burn the <m>bone</m> and become lumpy. And to know when it is
the right temperature, dip in it a little piece of twisted <m>paper</m>.
If it turns black without catching fire, it is the right temperature.
But if it burns &amp; catches fire, it is too hot. You can cast
<m>gold</m> &amp; <m>silver</m>, but it never comes out neatly. To cast
something delicate well, it is necessary that the <m>bone</m> not be
extremely dry, because it is rough &amp; does not release as well &amp;
crumbles &amp; is brittle. In any case, before you cast, dry them
<sup>the <m>bones</m></sup> &amp; especially for <m>gold</m>, which does
not react well to humidity. You will know that they are dry enough when,
after having exposed the insides and the imprint to the fire, they hiss
&amp; crackle when you bring them near your ear. Now join the
<m>bone</m>s &amp; daub the joints with a little <m>lute</m> and slowly
dry it near the fire &amp; cast &amp; then shake the mold or scratch the
rough crannies and let it cool down before opening it. Usually one cuts
the <m>bone</m> in the middle, and the dull part that does not have half
circles <figure/> is more delicate and smoother to mold with, and
therefore one always uses it to do the main part of the casting, the
other <sup>part of the <m>cuttlefish bone</m></sup> is crumbly on the
inside as on the outside. Therefore one does not use this to cast
delicate things which need to be molded in two places. One evens out
&amp; flattens these two halves on some piece of wood, then one rubs
some <m>charcoal</m> on top so that it releases well. And to make sure
the <m>charcoal</m> is evenly spread everywhere, tap the side of the
hand which is holding the half <m>bone</m>. Both having been covered in
<m>charcoal</m>, take the first <m>bone</m> that has been prepared &amp;
rounded on the edges, and having placed the medal above it, press the
medal down strongly.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
