<root>
<page>117r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f239.image</image>

<div>
<id>p117r_a1</id>
<head>A way to mold <pa>flower</pa>s and <pa>herb</pa>s</head>

<ab>It is necessary to choose them in full bloom and color, and not pick
them, if possible, until the time one wants to mold them so that they
will not wilt. Or if you need to carry them from afar, put their stems
in a bottle of <m>water</m>, or better still <m>wine</m>. First make a
<m>wax</m> stick pointed like a big peg, of a size appropriate to what
you want to cast, as you see in the margin, marked A. At the bottom of
this peg, put and prick a bit of <m>iron</m> wire, rather thick and
strong. And at the point of this <sup>peg</sup>, you will fit your
<pa>flower</pa> stem or your <pa>herb</pa>. This done, set it aside.
Arrange your <m>clay</m> circle and outline as you did for the
<al>snake</al>s, in the shape of a <mu>mandore</mu> according to the
size of your <pa>herb</pa>. Then take the <pa>herb</pa> you have
prepared to be cast, as we have taught you, and wet and moisten it
carefully with good <m>eau de vie</m> with a <tl>pinceau</tl>. Then
place the wire end through the end of the <m>earthen</m>
<mu>mandore</mu>, so that the <m>wax</m> peg, where the <pa>herb</pa>
is, joins itself to the edge of the <m>earthen</m> <mu>mandore</mu>. And
arrange your <pa>herb</pa> lying flat so that it remains in the middle
of said <mu>mandore</mu>, without touching on any side, such that the
sand that you pour in it will be of equal thickness everywhere, and will
be <add>more than</add> two good <ms>finger</ms>s higher than your
<pa>plant</pa> everywhere on top. And having secured the wire well,
quickly pour your <m>wet sand</m>, much clearer than the one used for
snakes, in the <mu>mandore</mu>, and the sooner the better, so that the
<m>eau de vie</m> does not dry. And be sure to put in a little more
<m>water of sal ammoniac</m> among the common than you do for the
snakes. And if you were to make sand especially for casting your
bouquets, where you would mix in a little more <m>feather alum</m>, it
will be all the better. In this way, your mold will be in one piece and
it will not be necessary to disassemble it, but to separate it from the
<m>clay</m> once it will have set. Let it dry. And then fire it again
until the herbs are burnt. Note that if the herb you want to cast has a
strong stalk and stem, you can cast it lying down, as said. But if it is
fine and delicate, plant it standing up with the <m>wax</m> peg so that
the sand will always raise it up, it being very clear. Do not forget to
arrange two vent holes with two small <tl>stick</tl>s, which will start
at the bottom of the cast, which is the pointed end of the <m>wax</m>
peg.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
If the <pa>plants</pa>s are so delicate that they rise to the top when
you pour the <m>wet sand</m>, one can stop and contain them with a
<m>thread</m> passed through the circle of the mold with a
<tl>needle</tl>.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p117r_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5WnpBbm8wN2gyTWs</link>

</figure>

<figure>

<id>fig_p117r_2</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5VURRYzlWOFByNzQ</link>

</figure>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The more delicate the <pa>flower</pa> is, the clearer the sand must
be.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p117r_3</id>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dVB5bzVUWWJuS0U</link>

<caption>This is a core mold.</caption>

</figure>

</div>
</root>
