<root>
<page>134r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f273.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p133v_3</id>

<ab>

avoid putting pins that should not be put, only on the top of the head,
the thickest parts of the body, and on the delicate parts like the
middle of the <al>lizard</al>'s feet, the nails of which you will drive
into the <m>clay</m>, thus they won't move. Once your first mold is
casted, peel away the belly of the animal, but do not forget to put some
tenuous little pieces of <m>wax</m> at the tip of the <al>lizard</al>'s
feet. But if it is from a <al>wall lizard</al>, lightly cover all the
sole of its feet with <m>wax</m>, which will be removed with the second
cast. A cavity is left which will be fill these little fingers with
metal. then rework it. Make sure that wax is fixed well on the parts of
the animal which are one on top of the other, so that the soaked sand
which comes in does not make them move. If that happened your jacket of
<m>clay</m> would be spoiled and your mold wouldn't get the right
thickness, would have holes, and would be spoiled. To obviate that you
can make a thicker mold. If this occurs you could rework it in this
fashion.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p134r_1</id>

<head>To repair a pierced mold</head>

<ab>

If the molded animal pulls of in certain places, moves from the place
you had fixed it, or has not completely died, or if you didn't fix it
well with the <m>iron</m> pins or with the melted <m>wax</m>, or if the
animal hasn't the right thickness on the outside at the relief, or if it
is pierced, instead of removing the animal from the mold, peel away the
weak parts, or the pierced part, and make holes all around these parts,
then dip the back side of the mold, quickly cast onto this place with
the same soaked sand which will go into the holes, the cast will adhere
to the first cast. But you will have to lute this spot afterwards.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p134r_2</id>

<head>Sand made of <m>crocum <x>ferri</x></m></head>

<ab>

You can use the mixture made of <m>crocum ferri</m> to cast
<m>silver</m> or <m>gold</m>, this mixture will make these casts firm,
and prevent these from cracking and making burrs. And I believe that for
flat things, it would withstand severa casts. Which however is not
commonly done for <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

Try <m>crocum ferri</m> for <m>lead</m> and <m>tin</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
