<root>
<page>111r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f227.image</image>

<div>
<id>p111r_a1</id>
<head>Reheating molds</head>

<ab>The frames readily dry out &amp; do not reheat. For reheating is
actually to redden &amp; inflame the molds in the fire, and drying out
is to let the molds dry themselves, or to make their dampness evaporate
by placing them in front of a flaming fire or a charcoal one.
<fr>Noyau</fr> molds readily reheat &amp; frame molds dry out.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p111r_a2</id>
<head><m>Latten</m> <m>smoke</m></head>

<ab>

It is good to reheat in it the molds for casting <m>latten</m>, for this
yellow <m>filth</m>, which appears nevertheless to refill the molds,
casts very neatly, being of the same nature.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p111r_a3</id>
<head>For <m>red copper</m></head>

<ab>When it is melted, it is good to throw in a little fine <m>tin</m>,
for this makes it run.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p111r_a4</id>
<head><m>Clay earth</m></head>

<ab>This one, moistened &amp; well beaten &amp; kneaded as you know, is
necessary for you to make the contour for containing your molds. But
take heed that it not be too soft, but rather as if half dry, that it
does not attack your hands, because otherwise it would attack your work.
Always keep it in a damp place, and make holes in it, and fill them with
water, to keep it fresh.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The gray one is best, which does not crack at all.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is more appropriate than a blade of <m>lead</m>.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p111r_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5X085N09VejNheTQ</link>

</figure>

</div>

<div>
<id>p111r_a5</id>
<head><m>Iron</m> wire</head>

<ab>You need to have enough provisions of different thicknesses,
according to the molds that you want to make, some large like cord, some
<ill/> &amp; some thin, like the large cords of a spinet, for small
works. You make, once reheated, clamps from it to close the molds &amp;
the points, like needles of different lengths, according to your need,
to pierce the animal to be molded &amp; keep it subjected. Needles would
not be good for this because it is necessary that their points be empty
&amp; of the same thickness throughout, except at the point. And then,
one must make them as long as you have need of. <m>Iron</m> wire is
firmer than that of <m>latten</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
