<root>
<page>111v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f228.image</image>

<div>

<id>p111v_1</id>

<head><m>Essence of sal ammoniac</m></head>

<ab>The size of two <m>chestnuts</m> of pulverized <m>sal ammoniac</m>
suffices in a pot of <m>water</m>, and to the tongue you find the water
moderatly salty, for too much is not good. </ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p111v_2</id>

<head><m>Sanguine</m></head>

<ab>To clean the various colors of <m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m>, one
pulverizes <m>sanguine</m> &amp; with some cloths, one rubs the molded
work.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p111v_3</id>

<head><al>Crab</al> and <al>crayfish</al></head>

<ab>

These are the hardest to mold &amp; whoever molds them well will mold
many other very delicate things.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p111v_4</id>

<head><al>Lizards</al></head>

<ab>When one takes them with two fingers from the sides of the head, at
the level of the ears, one makes them open their mouth, then one takes
the end of its lower mandibule, with the end of the fingernail, &amp;
after with the one from above it bites the nail, but it cannot pass
through, but it bites very well. And if it were to bite living flesh it
would not let go, &amp; there would be no better remedy than to promptly
cut off his head. In the spring, as they have changed skin, they are
more beautiful.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

The small <al>lizards</al> that one takes in the summer, the size of
small <al>female lizards</al>, grey on the back &amp; green on the
belly, are very appropriate to cast in silver, &amp; gold, or other
metal, because their have rougher scales than the of <m><al>female
lizards</al></m> &amp; show better.

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

like pincers

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p111v_5</id>

<head>Composition of <m>sand</m></head>

<ab>Everything once reheated as it said here above, take four 4 full
crucibles of <m>plaster</m>, two 2 of <m>brick</m>, &amp; one of
<m><fr>alum de plume</fr></m>. Do not pass through the sieve to mix,
because the <m><fr>alum</fr></m> would not pass. Mix with your hands,
until neither one nor the other, neither white nor red, is recognised
among the other. If your <m>plaster</m> was not strong, do not mix at
all so much <m><fr>alum de plume</fr></m>, because it softens the molds.
Take head also that your <m>sand</m> is not hot (since it has
immediately been reheated) when you will want to mix it with
<m>water</m>, for this makes molds too soft &amp; breakable.

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

You may sometimes diminish the quantity of <m>plaster</m> if you do not
find it strong enough to withstands, with the <m>alum de plume</m>,
which you can also increase so that it creates a better bond.</ab>

</div>
</root>
