<root>
<page>133v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f272.image</image>

<div>

<id>p133v_1</id>

<head>Bubbles and little molds which are found in the mold</head>

<ab>

This readily comes about when you cast two or three small molds, one
after the other, in the same bowl, for the last one is cast from the
bottom &amp; thickest part of the bowl, which readily becomes porous.
The lightest casts more finely &amp; more neat, provided that one blows
strongly enough when casting on the wet &amp; cast sand in order to
dissipate these small bubbles.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

When the sand is cast thickly, it readily becomes porous

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p133v_2</id>

<head>Thing that does not release</head>

<ab>

One needs to cut it to make it burn in the mold, but cut it with chisels
in one go, in order that the blood does not fall on the mold &amp; does
not create filth, which, once reheated, is difficult to remove. Next,
put your mold in the oven or similar heat, in order that it quickly
dries &amp; retracts, before making a crust or mold on the mold.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<figure>+</figure>

When you mold small <al>lizards</al>, and you want to uncover the first
molded part, begin to uncover the heads &amp; you will recognize its
place by the pin. Do not attempt to uncover the legs until you have
uncovered the rest of the body, in order that the bared body, when
moving, does not remove the legs from their place, where it is difficult
to put them back. When you remove little points which hold the legs, fix
them &amp; press them with something, in order that, when removing the
pin, they are not removed from their place, or, in the end, you can put
them back with some wax.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p133v_3</id>

<head>Various animals entwined</head>

<ab>

You can entwine a <al>snake</al> <del>entwine</del> with a
<al>lizard</al>, one biting the other, or a <al>snake</al> that eats a
<al>frog</al> or a <al>wall lizard</al> <del>s</del> &amp; similar
things. But because these entwinings can in no way make a good release,
cut what you can &amp; leave the rest to burn. And to keep a wall
lizard, which is small, in the mouth of the snake, which is raised &amp;
needs to be supported in the air, <del>po</del>, because the head of the
snake is placed raised, put underneath the wall lizard <del>se</del> an
elevation of earth suited to support it. And if you put your mold in the
oven, the animal, drying quickly, retracts &amp; burns better after.
<del>if you see</del> These entwinings are also made to cover a wound or
fault in the animals, that one usually wounds when one catches them.
Also, do not forget to attach &amp; join, with some wax, finely applied
with hot iron wire, all the parts of the animal which pass one on top of
the other or those that you notice are not well fixed on the slab of
<del>wax</del> earth, in order that the wet sand does not remove it. And
it is to</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
