<root>
<page>017v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f40.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p017r_1</id>

<ab>The large canon, which is for great batteries, usually weighs
fifty-five or lx <ms>quintal</ms>s. At the breech it carries the
thickness of <del>b</del> two bullets &amp;<del><fr>l</fr></del> a third
of one bullet. At the front, it carries <del>ba</del> the thickness of
one bullet &amp; two thirds. It is thirteen or fourteen
<fr><ms>pan</ms>s</fr> in length. But they are very troublesome to
drive. The head-on battery, to accomplish its task quickly <del>is</del>
&amp; batter with great force ranges at <del>a</del> hundred fifty paces
&amp; at two hundred. <del>And</del> It is true that one batters well
from three or 4 hundred <ms>pace</ms>s, but it is necessary to give it
more <m>powder</m>. Its common load is of xx <ms>lb</ms> of
<m>powder</m>, its bullet of 40 <ms>lb.</ms>. One needs xxv
<al>horses</al> to drag it. When one drags it farther than its usual
range, one puts in a half <ms><tl>linstock</tl></ms> of canon
<m>powder</m> more. A cannon can be shot 80 or a hundred shots per day,
but one needs to refresh it every time after one has shot <del>te</del>
nine or ten shots, if the battery is continuously used. For if there is
a break, it is not necessary to refresh it as often. For two
<ms>quintal</ms>s of <m>copper</m>, or two <ms>quintal</ms>s &amp; a
half if it is for large cannons, one puts one <ms>quintal</ms> of
<m>metal</m>. The <m>metal</m> is composed at the beginning of eight
<ms>lb.</ms> of <m>tin</m> for one <ms>quintal</ms> of
<m><fr>rosette</fr></m>, and also for big bells one only puts six
<ms>lb.</ms> of fine <m>tin</m> for one <ms>quintal</ms> of
<m><fr>rosette</fr></m>, to give it a bigger voice. For the more
<m>tin</m> there is, the clearer the sound is. <del>Its</del> For gun
founding, if one provides the material &amp; <m>charcoal</m> as one
usually does for <pro>master</pro>s do not have the means, one gives x
to xii <cn>lb.</cn> per <ms>quintal</ms>. And <del>for the mat</del>
when the <pro>master</pro> provides everything, one gives him 40
<cn>lb.</cn> per <ms>quintal</ms> for large pieces such as cannons,
according to the King's ordinance, and l <cn>lb.</cn> for small pieces.
<del><fr>T</fr></del> For the more material there is, the more profit
the <pro>master</pro> has of it. One founds another kind of fowlers of
xxx <ms>quintal</ms>s which are longer than the others, and easily eight
<fr><ms>pan</ms>s</fr> long, &amp; they are for battering defenses &amp;
casemates <del><fr>s</fr></del> by placing them par trenchees at night
the edge of the ditch.</ab>

<figure>◯</figure>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

On each side of the breech's opening they give the thickness of half a
ball. And then they also add on each side the third part of a ball.</ab>

<ab><del><fr>Ain</fr></del> one gives it two <ms><tl>linstocks</tl></ms>
of cannon <m>powder</m> for its charge, &amp; one &amp; a half of
arquebus <m>powder</m>, &amp; the same for the others.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<figure>#</figure>

The composition for cannons from <pl>France</pl> is one <ms>quintal</ms>
of metal for two of <m><fr>rosette</fr></m>. But those of
<pl>Toulouse</pl> &amp; <pn>Poncet</pn> put iii of
<m><fr>rosette</fr></m> &amp; one of metal.</ab>

<ab>The <m><fr>rosette</fr></m> for re-melting is more profitable than
cauldrons, which turn entirely into filth.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

Old pieces are composed of almost <del><fr>de dem</fr></del> as much one
as of the other, namely one part of <m><fr>rosette</fr></m> &amp; one of
metal. One recognises this composition with a <tl>burin</tl>. For its
substance is found to be sour &amp; the particle taken from the
<tl>burin</tl> is found to be mixed with yellow &amp; white.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
