<root>
<page>050v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f106.image</image>

<div>

<id>p050v_1</id>

<head><al>Little Birds</al></head>

<ab><al>Buntings</al> sing during the night if they are left in the cool
open air, but they are better suited to fattening for fine tables than
for singing. <al>Chaffinches</al> are prone to blindness, and their eyes
swell at the beginning of August. <al>Goldfinches</al> love <m>lettuce
seeds</m>, and you can catch them in gardens on seedy lettuce using two
<m>lime-twigs</m>. But because such a daily fayre would be too expensive
for them, they are usually fed with <m>hemp-seed</m>. The
<al>owsell</al> is purged with a <al>spider</al>, which you must give it
once a week, so that it doesn't become too strong. The <al>lark</al> is
purged with <m>dry mortar</m>, composed of <m>lime</m> and sand, to keep
it from becoming too strong and fat. Small young birds are purged with
the same <m>dry mortar</m>, by placing small lumps of it in their cages.
The <al>cuckoo</al> lays its eggs in the nest of the <al>bunting</al>,
otherwise know as <al>verdaule</al>. This bird is very simple-minded, I
have previously let two go, which after a few days returned to their
cage. To feed young <al>goldfinches</al>, it is necessary to crush
<m>almonds</m> with very fine <m>breadcrumbs</m>, and <m>lettuce
seeds</m> or <m>hemp seeds</m>. For <al>linnets</al>, some
<m>rapeseed</m>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p050v_2</id>

<head>Curried <m>steel</m> and <tl>files</tl></head>

<ab>The <m>steel</m> that <pro>blacksmiths</pro> &amp; <pro><m>iron</m>
workers</pro> commonly use is not refined like that from
<pl>Germany</pl> or <pl>Biscay</pl>, which is reduced in hardness
<del><fr>p</fr></del> in a bath of a <m>molten iron</m>, but
<del>only</del> among the <m>iron bars</m> which are transported in flat
ingots from the <env>forges of <pl>Foix</pl></env> &amp; elsewhere,
there is a harder &amp; whiter &amp; finer kind than the other, as it
comes from the <env>mine</env>. And the <pro>workers</pro> choose it
&amp; use it like the other <m>steel</m>. And because it comes from
<m>common iron</m>, they call it <m>strong iron</m>. But it is not as
excellent as <m>purified steel</m> like that from <pl>Germany</pl> &amp;
<pl>Biscaye</pl>, which is sold in <ms>small beads</ms>. Some curry
<m>steel</m>, giving it a heating, then temper it <del>&amp;
<m>water</m></del> in a large quantity of <m>water</m>, then forge it.
&amp; <m>fine steel</m>, which is brittle, breaks and crumbles, &amp;
<m>iron</m> allows itself to be stretched. Thus they separate <m>the
finest steel</m> <del>&amp;</del>, which with another heating they
reduce to a mass. The <pl>Germans</pl> make their <tl>files</tl> from
<m>strong iron</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>One applies <m>steel</m> to tools
<del><fr>dess</fr></del> not on both sides, but underneath the part
where one sharpens &amp; whets them. &amp; in this part, they must be of
<m>very <fr>doulx</fr> iron</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin><pl>Levantines</pl> refine our
<m>steel</m> because their country does not provide them with any. And
they reheat it in a <tl>pot</tl> with <m>bitumen</m>, &amp;c.</ab></div>
</root>
