<root>
<page>095r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f195.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p094r_a1</id>

<ab>The <pro>furbisher</pro> buys his blades by the dozen which are not
fully drawn by the tang because he does this himself to adjust them them
well to the pommels &amp; guards.</ab>

<ab>Spanish ones are deemed better for being of better <m>steel</m>
&amp; <m>iron</m> but they are not as well-forged as swords from Vienne
in <del><fr>pro</fr></del> Dauphiné. The Spanish ones are not as well
whetted coming from the forge because they whet them with the foot &amp;
this is what makes them wavy.</ab>

<ab>Blades from Vienne commonly cost xviii or 19 lb a dozen.</ab>

<ab>The first thing the <pro>furbisher</pro> does when he gets his new
blades is to draw out their tang, which he does himself, or has done by
<pro>locksmiths</pro> or <pro>farriers</pro>, giving him some
<cn>liard</cn> for his <m>charcoal</m>. Next they pass it over a
grindstone to make it cut, then lay it down on the chameau<m>,</m> and
with some pulverized <m>emery</m>, fine &amp; soft as flour, &amp; mixed
with <m>oil</m> to make it hold, they furbish the sword with the stick
used to remove the traces of the grindstone and then <del>the</del>
clean <del><fr>po</fr></del> the sword well with the <m>emery</m>, and
give it a drop or two of <m>oil</m> which they spread with the finger to
give it luster. Having put the <m>oil</m>, they furnish the sword again
on the <fr>chameau</fr> with the <fr>felin</fr> which is a thunderstone
mounted in the middle of a stick like the <fr>fustée</fr>, and this
stick is called the felindel stick. Next, having passed it on the
<fr>felin</fr>, they furnish it with <m>chalk</m> &amp; the <m>oil</m>
which is on the sword. After they wipe it &amp; go over it again, &amp;
furbish with dry <m>chalk</m>. And at the end, when they ready mounted,
one gives them the edge with the <fr>gratteau</fr>.
<del><fr>Ai</fr></del></ab>

<ab>Once furbished, one mounts it on the guards which one presents to
know if they are quite suitable. And taking hold of a blade such that
the whole tang is held in the hand, one conjectures that it will be just
as heavy once mounted.</ab>

<ab>One puts the blade in a vice between two pieces of <m>wood</m>, then
with a file they enlarge the opening of the hilt if it is necessary.
Then to rivet it, one places on the rivet <del>a piece of</del> &amp;
the pommel a piece of <m>wood</m> &amp; with a hammer, one beats on it
to straighten &amp; secure the pommel well. Then with the hammer, one
finishes the rivet when the hammer is well secured &amp; does not
wobble. The <m>wood</m> is put there so as not to spoil the pommel.
Next, one fits the rivet with a file or chisel. And some make <del>the
<fr>b</fr></del> the rivet in a square diamond-shape but it is not as
good as the round one, for at the edge rivet is cut.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
