<root>
<page>094v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f194.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p094r_1</id>

<ab>The <m>gold</m> handles are made by putting underneath <m>thin
yellow canvas</m> or a different canvas yellowed with <m>chalk</m>. And
this <m>canvas</m> is set with <m>glue</m> or the aforesaid <m>gum</m>,
this is in order that the <m>thread</m> holds better on it. These are
made of cords like the <m>silk</m> ones &amp; between two cords one sets
one or two <m>threads</m> to make it show up better. The <m>silver</m>
kind is made similarly, and there is not as much trouble as with
<m>silk</m>, and even less because it takes more to twist <m>silk</m>,
because one needs to twist it twice. A handle of fine <m>gold</m> is
worth 18 or 20 <fr><cn>sols</cn></fr>.</ab>

<ab>The best sword point is the <m>sage leaf</m> form.</ab>

<ab>This long stick on which the sword is attached &amp; laid down to
furbish it is called the <fr>chameau</fr>, it is commonly of
<m>rowan</m> which is hard &amp; even.</ab>

<ab>The lower stick which is folded like a bow is called the
<fr>arson</fr>.</ab>

<ab>The upper is called the stick of the <fr>fustée</fr>.</ab>

<ab>And this small square piece, which is pu<del><ill/></del>t
<del><fr>l</fr></del>on the sword to burnish it, is called the
<fr>fustée</fr>.</ab>

<ab>There are two horns: one is called the <m>oil</m> cornet and the
other the <m>emery</m> cornet. </ab>

<ab>There is an <m>iron</m> which is made like a halberd point, square,
&amp; of very even <m>steel</m>, &amp; well filed, which is called the
<fr>grateau</fr> which serves to <del>to</del> soften the traces of the
file on sword hilts &amp; to give an edge to swords after they have been
whetted, which is better than with a <m>stone</m> or a <m>sharpening
stone</m>, which quite often makes scratches.</ab>

<ab>To make <del><fr>coupp</fr></del> swords cut better, one gives them
the edge by pulling upwards from the point.</ab>

<ab><pro>Those who create sword hilts</pro> are artisans separate from
the <pro>furbisher</pro>.</ab>

<ab> A is the <fr>bruisson</fr><lb/>

B is the bloodstone</ab>

<ab>The <fr>fustée</fr> is a square piece of wood three fingers in
thickness, of <m>boxwood</m>, which is fitted in the middle of the stick
<add>of the fustée to furbish</add>.</ab>

<ab>The fresil stick is of <m>willow wood</m> which is to clean the rust
off weapons with <m>slag</m> which is the <m>iron scale</m> falling at
the <pro>farrier</pro>s' forge.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p094v_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Q29MTEVLUGE5RGs</link>

<caption>le banc des fourreaux</caption>

</figure>
<figure>

<id>fig_p094v_2</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5OEQ3OEFSNnEzeE0</link>

</figure>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<figure/> a<figure/> <figure/>b<lb/>

D<lb/>

<figure/>

le baston a felinder<figure/>c le <m>flin</m> ou <m>pierre de
fouldre</m></ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
