<root>
<page>107v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f220.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p107v_1</id>

<ab>Molds can only be used once for fine things, like <m>wormwood</m>
&amp;others, one needs to break them, but before one needs to dip them
into <m>water</m> in which the twice reheated things dissolve easily.
Otherwise, you would not be able to release your work without danger of
spoiling it.</ab>

<ab>Good <m>alum de plume</m> is white and as shiny as white silk. It is
made of long pieces, as long as a finger, &amp; is very breakable &amp;
cottony as down. The one made of <m>stone</m> is harder &amp; not so
good. The best of the above mentioned quality can be found in France
near <pl>Rouan</pl>. The <m>alum de plume</m> for other sand is pestled
into a mortar, and is ground on the <m>marble</m> again, as one cannot
grind it through the sieve, as it is so fat &amp; cottony, it would not
pass through it. It is it, with its small soft filaments, which gives
the <m>sand</m> binding effect than natural <m>wool</m> or even the
<m>filler</m> the <pro>foundry owner</pro> uses for big works, because
natural <m>wool</m> &amp; <m>filler</m> burn and <m>stone feather
alum</m> resists fire.</ab>

<ab>When you cast surround the <m>sand</m> of your mold with very beaten
greasy <m>earth</m>. Make a circle &amp; around your mold with this
<m>earth</m>.</ab>

<ab>Archanum omnibus fere reconditum est in re fusoria,<lb/>

v<exp>idelicet</exp> res exprimenda formis, sive <m>herba</m> sit sive
<m>animal</m><lb/>

ut <m>lucerta</m>, inmergatur primum in <m>vini spiritum</m><lb/>

aprime rectificatum, deinde pulvere composito aspergatur<lb/>

sive illinatur (si pulvis in formam pultis redactus sit, ut<lb/>

assolet)</ab>

<ab>When you want to mold something hollow, the core must be made of the
same matter, if the snake or the animal is curved or folded you must do
your core in several pieces.</ab>

<ab>Try <x>to see</x> if distilled <m>vinegar</m> is good for eating
away, &amp; it will dissolve the <m>animal</m> inside the hollow
mold.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
If you know that your <m>plaster</m> cannot endure fire without
breaking, do not take the recipe of the mixture literally, sometimes you
can add less <m>stone alum</m> than above. Because <m>stone alum</m>
soften molds. Once reheated do not grind the <m>stone alum</m> again,
leave it ground as the <pro>apothecaries</pro> did. It will not prevent
the cast from being neat, &amp; will give more binder to your cast. When
the mold holds the color of the brick and is reddened then it will be
harder.</ab>

</div>
</root>
