<root>
<page>110v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f226.image</image>

<div>

<id>p110r_3</id>

<ab>When it has eaten something, by tormenting it, it will render it.
And if, after having eaten something, it is thusly pressed underfoot,
this pains it a lot &amp; hurts it. If it is wounded, it will not eat
willingly.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p110v_1</id>
<head><tl>Molds</tl></head>

<ab>There is nothing better for opening them up than to smear them with
<m>olive oil</m>, &amp; nothing else. And afterwards, when you want to
disjoin them, soak them in cold <m>water</m>, which is the secret. And
you will see that the <m>oil</m> although it seems to be imbued, will
detach itself, like grease. Molds become stronger in cold <m>water</m>.
And hot <m>water</m> would dissolve them uneasily, although once
reheated, they are more handleable &amp; easier to dissolve in the
<m>water</m>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p110v_2</id>

<head><m>Wheat oil</m></head>

<ab>Is made on a blade of <m>iron</m> reddened in the fire. And the
<m>oil</m> drips off, which is appropriate for smearing the hair of a
butterfly or similar thing, for this <m>oil</m> is instantly dry &amp;
makes the remainder dry out. It is necessary that the hair or down of
any animal that you want to mold be flat, for it were upright it would
elevate the sand and become porous.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><figure>#</figure> If you want to mold
something delicate, like a pansy, some, to give it a little thickness,
more than what is natural, rub it with <m>butter</m>. But it is best to
smear it with <m>wheat oil</m> for it has no body &amp; does not
obstruct the small lineaments as much, and makes the flower
firm.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p110v_3</id>

<head>Cast of <m>lead</m> and <m>tin</m></head>

<ab>Because <m>tin</m> wants to be cast very thinly, if your medal,
plant or other thing for molding is thin &amp; fine, do it so that there
is more <m>tin</m>, much more than <m>lead</m>, namely less than the
fourth part <m>lead</m> for three parts <m>tin</m>. And still, one puts
lead only to form an alloy. On the contrary, if you want to mold
something strong &amp; thick, put a lot more <m>lead</m> in than
<m>tin</m>. And in one &amp; the other you can put a little
<m>looking-glass tin</m>, but only a little, with a little <m>resin</m>,
when you want to cast. Since then, when molding with fine &amp; new
<m>lead</m>, I put into one <ms>lb</ms> two <ms>ounces</ms> of fine
<m>tin</m>. And when molding with fine <m>tin</m>, I put in two ounces
of fine <m>lead</m> for one pound. I made plants &amp; snakes just like
nature.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>

I cast <m>tin</m> almost red, and <m>lead</m> the same, which however
had not remained in the fire for too long, for it becomes brittle and
calcines.</ab>

</div>
</root>
