<root>
<page>151v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f308.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p150v_1</id>

<ab>However, do not remove it before you have prepared the whole
<al>turtle</al>, because you will use this <m>earth</m> as
<m>cement</m>, should you need embed something or make repairs with a
chisel. If you have some metal overflow at the joints of your mold, you
will remove it, either with a burin, called a chaple, or with a very
sharp pen-knife, or with a small file followed by the chisel. Always
keeping in front of you the real thing to do as best you can. You can
curl on a file a chisel point, which is not at all moistened, to make
something lumpy. For these <al>turtles</al> and any other hollow things
which you can assume are quite big, create a <m>ligue</m> of half
<m>lead</m> and half <m>refined tin</m>. There is more to do when
molding a <al>turtle</al> than when molding a dozen flowers. If there is
<m>crocum</m> in your sand, there will be no metal overflow and if you
are unfortunate enough that there should be some on the sides, these
will be as thin as <m>paper</m>, as long as your mold is very tightly
pressed together. And to make the scales of <al>turtles</al> and other
animals, you can make little chisel marks in the shape of round punch
cutters, others in the shape of a gouge, or shaped like a <al>snake</al>
or <al>lizard</al> scale, and other using a file used to make twisty
bits and lumps. <al>Turtles</al> that do not need to be molded hollow
are not as much work, because they are molded in two pieces and repair
them with little chisels <sup>that make</sup> punch cutters, little
couge, and serrated chisels.

<figure>

<id>fig_p151v_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bk1US2QxRTVwa2s</link>

</figure>

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p151v_1</id>

<head><m>Wheat oil</m></head>

<ab>One needs to make it between two quite sparkling hot <m>iron</m>
blades, especially the lower one, which will be sloping, on which you
will put some wheat, quite even &amp; uniform. And then you will place
the other, all red, on top, &amp; you will press it until you see the
black <m>oil</m> drip well. Reiterate that until you have enough of it.
This <m>oil</m> dries immediately. It gives gold color to
<m>silver</m>-plated &amp; burnished things, augments the color of
gilded things, serves as a <m>varnish</m> on <m>iron</m> for engraving
it later, for varnishing sword guards tawny. And could also serve
<pro>makers of gilded <m>leather</m></pro> well. </ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>One needs to use it when it is newly
made. And for things to be molded, it must not be as thick as for
coloring.

</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>It is not for oiling hairy animals, for
it is too strong &amp; rigid, but it is good to give form to the legs of
a small animal, like a <al>fly</al> &amp; suchlike. It is also excellent
for coloring white false stones.</ab></div>
</root>
