<root>
<page>014r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f33.image</image>

<div>

<id>p014r_1</id>

<head>For <m>earth</m> walls and rustic construction</head>

<ab><al>Swallows</al> have taught us this craft, making their nests out
of <m>mud</m> mixed with <m>wisps</m> &amp; stalks of <m>hay</m> or
<m>straw</m> to make it bond. Therefore, in places where <m>stone</m>
&amp; <m>brick</m> are lacking, one can use <m>earth</m> to make thin
&amp; thick walls. And for this, light <m>earth</m>, which does not form
clumps when plowed, but which is somewhat intermixed with <m>arene</m>,
holds first rank, because it can be most easily beaten &amp; tamped
down. It is true that it needs to be moistened &amp; cut into clods with
a <tl>ditch-spade</tl>, and thus place &amp; arrange it. This one lasts
longer and does not require as much effort, and dryness doesn't make it
split &amp; crack. But, because such kinds of earth are not found
everywhere, those who live on good &amp; fertile land, after marking out
with a measuring line the width &amp; length of their foundations, drive
<del>into the ground</del> in along the foundation edges, on this side
&amp; that, long <tl>poles</tl> <del>&amp;</del> or <tl>chevron
beams</tl> to support boards between which they throw the <m>earth</m>,
making each layer one foot thick or about, intermixing it with
<figure>S.S.S</figure>-like branches of <m><pa>heather</pa></m> or
similar things, then with beaters of three different forms they tamp it
&amp; beat it down. One is called the mallet, which has a triangular
form like A, and this is used firstly to tamp down the <m>earth</m>.
Then one uses another made of pointed <tl>woodblocks</tl> fitted onto a
thick <tl>stick</tl>, and this one is used to properly press the
<m>earth</m> at the wall’s ends and edges where they adhere to the
boards, and is called <gap/>. The other one is called the bat and is
used to flatten and beat the <m>earth</m> for the last time, as shown in
C. Then one makes another layer of <m>earth</m> and
<m><pa>heather</pa></m> and beats as has been said, and continues thus
until completing the wall, which one covers with <m><pa>heather</pa></m>
and then with <m>earth</m>. Some intermix the said wall with rows of
<m>bricks</m>. They also make walls with a sloped foot, adding width to
the foundations according to how high they want to build the wall. When
it is old it whitens, showing that it has <m>saltpeter</m> in it. Which
is why, when they fall down, <pro>gunpowder makers</pro> profit from
them.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p014r_1</id>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5b2lVN19SU1Z6UkU</link>

<!--A-->

<!--Nicolas Misery:text refers also to a "C" part of the figure, which
is absent in the actual figure.-->

</figure>

</div>
</root>
