<root>
<page>054r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f113.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p053v_1</id>

<ab>on some of the high shelves, &amp; at that time, one knows when they
want to climb up when, on the leaf, they lengthen &amp; raise the head
&amp; a part of the body. At that time one carries them to the heather
branches where they stop &amp; begin to spin their prison, which one
calls cocoon, commonly the size of a pigeon egg, although one finds many
much bigger because it sometimes happens that two or three &amp; up to
xi <al>worms</al> are put in a cocoon, which is hairy &amp; downy all
around, the hair of which is ferret-silk or <fr>floret</fr>; &amp; from
the cocoon, which is a white, solid, continuous &amp; firm skin,
<m>silk</m> is made. The cocoon is so hard that one only cuts it with
difficulty with a fingernail. And, however, for leaving its prison, the
<al>worm</al> gnaws it at one end, &amp; after having stayed inside
living on its own sap for three weeks, it comes out, diminished by half.
For when it begins to spin, it is as long as a ring finger &amp; has
eight feet, &amp; coming out it shorter by half &amp; only has 4 feet.
On the other hand, it has become a butterfly &amp; has wings, without
flying however. And there are male &amp; female. As soon as they come
out of the cocoon, the male charges the female &amp; one puts them on a
white linen, where they make their eggs. Which female would not be good
&amp; profitable if the male was not given to her. And when the male has
detached himself from a female, one needs to throw it, for it would not
be good to give it to another. They have completed spinning &amp; making
their eggs in three weeks &amp; around Saint John's Day. And at that
time one keeps their eggs &amp; seed until Holy Week, as is said. Some
<x>worms</x> spin among the leaves &amp; make their cocoon there without
climbing high.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>

The <m>silk</m> of the cocoons where there are</ab>

</div>
</root>
