<root>
<page>005r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f15.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p004v_a3</id>

<ab>or <m><pa>linen</pa></m> &amp; leave it thus for xx4
<ms><tmp>hours</tmp></ms> &amp; it will be engraved. But if you should
want to engrave quickly, varnish all your work &amp; boil it in the
aforesaid liquor, and it will engrave quickly.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p005r_a1</id>
<head><m>Steel</m> mirrors</head>

<ab><figure>+</figure>They are called <m>steel</m> <sup>mirrors</sup>
because in the past they were usually made of <m>steel</m> polished with
<m>emery paste</m>. But more easily, various kinds are made of <m>cuivre
franc</m>, which is <m>rosette</m> and <m>tin</m>, because these can be
cast in a mold and made round, concave, convex or in whatever various
shapes you want to represent.</ab>

<ab>So take half <m>copper de rosette</m> and half soft <m>tin</m>, i.e.
fine and yet unused. Place them in a crucible, and first melt the
<m>copper</m>. Once it has been well melted, add the <m>tin</m> and mix
them together and cast that in a <m>white stone</m> mold with no hole,
and grease the mold, which should be moderately warm, with <m>oil</m>.
Then, once your mirror has been molded, you can polish it in this
manner.</ab>

<ab>Set one <sup>mirror</sup> in <m>plaster</m> to hold it firmly, then
put the other one over it with fine sand between them, and rub one
against the other, whether they are hollowed or flat, and thus you will
polish both at once. If you want to polish them on both sides, you only
have to switch them, which means putting the one that was polishing in
the <m>plaster</m> and <x>using</x> the one which was in the
<m>plaster</m> to polish. Once they have been polished with <m>arene</m>
you can soften them with <m>tripoli of Venice</m> that should not be
<m>sand</m>y, and then with <m>paste</m>. You use <m>water</m> with
<m>arene</m> to polish, but polishing with <m>tripoli</m> and
<m>paste</m> is done dry. Once <sup>the mirror</sup> has been polished,
you can set it.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p005r_a2</id>
<head>Concave mirrors</head>

<ab>A concave mirror shaped in the aforesaid form produces an endless
number of illusions which seem like magic. If one wants to see oneself
from behind, you have to place the concave mirror on the ground on its
foot, at a slant, and then look at it one step further. But if you look
at it from a closer position, it shows you the right way up but with the
face quite large and the hairs of your beard as thick as</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
