<root>
<page>096v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f198.image</image>

<div>
<id>p096v_a1</id>
<head>Grey hilts</head>

<ab>Once they are white, one only needs to clean <del>we</del> them
well, then put them in the fire, &amp; make them turn blue. And one
needs to take good care that they do not go too far beyond blue, for
neither gold nor silver nor any color would take on it. To do this,
which is called <fr>les faire passer</fr>, one takes a <tl>cauldron full
of <m>ashes</m></tl> which one covers with thoroughly kindled charcoal,
&amp; thus one heats them quite strongly for an <ms><tmp>hour</tmp></ms>
or two, and when the <m>ashes</m> are very hot, one pulls the charcoal
to one side &amp; one puts the hilt where the charcoal was, &amp; one
covers it completely with <m>ashes</m>. And when the body of the hilt,
which is the main thing, is completely <fr>passé</fr>, one turns the
hilt onto the other side, and in this manner, the grey cannot
<fr>passer</fr> too much, unless some <m>hot charcoal</m> touches it.
The grey can be done well in the <add>ordinary</add> fire <env>in the
fireplace</env>, but there is a danger that it may <fr>passer</fr> too
much &amp; produce <m>filth</m> which will prevent it from taking color.
Blue is obtained as soon as the <m>ash</m> has heated the hilts a
little, but it is still grey in some places. After blue comes grey.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p096v_a2</id>
<head>Color of water</head>

<ab><add>For</add> the color of water, pass a <tl><fr>lime
doulce</fr></tl> on the guards to whiten them, then the
<tl>burnisher</tl>. Next, one makes them pass blue until they become
grey. Next, when they are still moderately hot, pass the
<m>bloodstone</m> over them, and when they cool, one turns them to
reheat them, for the color of water is made only by several goes. And if
the guards were not warm, the <m>bloodstone</m> would scrape &amp; undo
the color. One needs to heed that guards do not pass too grey, for they
would give off filth that would prevent the color from taking. One needs
almost one <ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms> for preparing, softening, &amp;
setting the color of water, but as they pass a little blue, it is enough
for grey &amp; another color. Grey is the lesser color after
<m>varnish</m> which is of two colors, either yellow or black.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p096v_a3</id>
<head><m>Yellow varnish</m></head>

<ab>One whitens very well &amp; one cleans the guards well. Next, one
with a feather, one coats them cold with a <tl>feather</tl> all of
<m><pa>walnut</pa> <del><pa>olive</pa></del> oil</m>, and next turn them
over a good <m>charcoal</m> fire that is in the
<tl><pro>furbishers</pro>' furnace</tl>, without them touching the
<m>charcoal</m> or the <m>ashes</m>. And when they do not smoke anymore,
it is done.</ab>

</div>
</root>
