<root>
<page>152r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f309.image</image>

<div>

<id>p152r_1</id>

<head>Molding a <al>rat</al></head>

<ab>The hairs of his whiskers are difficult to come out of the mold, you
can therefore shave them with fire, as did the tyrant of
<pl>Syracuse</pl>, which you can always replace with life-like
<m>silver</m> ones. The tail comes out beautifully because it is made of
little scale-like circles, almost like the ones of a <al>lizard</al>.
And to make sure that the hair does not keep you from molding well, burn
them away with a little candle. The rest of the body must be oiled with
<m>wheat oil</m>, which will keep the hair rigid and flat, so that it
will not be removed when it mixes with the sand, which will keep you
cast from releasing cleanly. <m>Wheat oil</m>, being dry, will dry
quickly, you will therefore be able to comb the hair with a very fine
comb, so that the hair will be visible when cast. On a small
<al>mouse</al> you can use <m>common oil</m> to flatten the hair. Rather
than molding these animals immediately (except for <al>snakes</al> and
<al>lizards</al>), keep them dead for a day a two so that they become
easier to handle. Because they are very stiff after they die and cannot
be shaped into a life-like looking position unless they are softened.
However, if you mold it straight after it dies, and give it its shape
before it becomes stiff, that will be good. And because the eyes die
unless you mold them immediately, you can replace them with half a round
<m>pea</m> taken out of its shell. Some cast their <al>rats</al> without
any added preparations; others oil them with <m>olive oil</m> which
suits the purpose, because <m>wheat oil</m> is thick and has too much
body. This is why we only use it <sup>wheat oil</sup> in light strokes
on <m>fly</m>'s feet or beneath a wing, to keep them stiff. Others
flatten the hair with an <m>egg yolk</m>, which dries quickly and does
the job. Arrange it <sup>the <al>rat</al></sup> on its <m>clay</m> base
before oiling it. Raise its head with an <m>iron</m> needle, and also
secure its feet with needles, and it tail. Rub it with <m>spirits</m>
after the <m>oil</m> has dried. Then throw in your sand. Uncover it as
you would other animals, then do your second casting. You must not open
the mold until it is completely reheated and the <al>rat</al> has burned
away.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin><figure>+</figure>If it is a big
<al>rat</al>, it is better to cast it hollow, because it is thick. A
<al>mouse</al> is easier to mold because it has shorter hair. It is
impossible to mold an animal with big bones well, such as a bird or
<al>rat</al>, without opening the mold to clean it well, because bones
do not burn well.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>All kinds of feathers and hairs are
difficult to mold realistically.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>It is better to use <m>butter</m> to
grease hairy animals than <m>wheat oil</m>, because it is better suited
to the purpose.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>If the <al>rat</al> is big, it is better
to remove its entrails, or having molded it, let it dry in an oven,
because the large amount of moisture it contains would boil inside the
mold, which would ruin it and make it lumpy.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>Only put your mold in the oven after it
has cooled, drying slowly, otherwise it will absorb the moisture and
break.</ab></div>
</root>
