<root>
<page>052r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f109.item</image>

<div>

<id>p052r_1</id>

<head>The Work done in Algiers</head>

<ab>Have a <al>colt</al> of three of four years and feed it on
<del><m>rye</m></del> <m>barley</m> and <m>straw</m> cut in the same way
as that which they use to feed horses in <pl>Spain</pl>. Let it drink
<m>water</m> from a good fountain or river <sup><m>water</m></sup>. I do
not know if it would be good sometimes to let him drink the <m>water</m>
of <m>sulfur</m> springs, and to sometimes give him <m>fenugreek</m> or
other hot foods, for the intention of the <pro>worker</pro> is to use
the heat of his <m>manure</m>, and the climate here is cooler than that
of Algiers. Keep it in a warm place and use it and make sure it loses
none of its <m>manure</m> or <m>urine</m>, of which you will make a mass
or two so that while one cools the other will keep its heat and be
suitable to continue. Also have a large flask as thick as possible, one
finger thick if it can be so made, and with a capacity of one pitcher or
<m>clay</m> jug, and around the feast of St John place a dozen and a
half <m>chicken eggs</m>, that is to say, the <m>egg</m> without the
<m><sup>egg</sup> white</m> and the <m>germ</m>. Others say sixty
<m>yolks</m>. And with this dozen and a half of <m>chicken egg yolks</m>
put one half ounce (others say sixty <m>eggs</m> and a half pound) of
<m>female silk worm eggs</m>. And after carefully luting the flask (I do
not know if air will be needed for the generation) and bury it in the
heat of the <m>manure</m> up to the neck, and leave it there until
several <al>worms</al> are engendered and then remove the flask and do
not bury it in the <m>manure</m> anymore. But put it on the hot layer of
the <m>manure</m> until all the <al>worms</al> are eaten and consume one
another by shriveling and stirring, and only one remains. Once this has
happened, you must lure it at regular intervals, day and night, with the
assistance of two men, who will care for it in shifts, and you will lure
it with an <m>egg yolk</m> covered in <m>gold</m> leaf or with a liquid
<m>yolk</m> into which the <m>gold</m> leaf has been incorporated. And
be careful that it does not miss such fodder (some say one <m>egg
yolk</m> per hour, others say three, but the thing itself will
demonstrate the practice). So nourished in this way it will grow in two
month or seven weeks and will become like a <al>serpent</al>, one span
and four fingers long, and one pound in weight, and as the wings will
begin to develop, you must kill it, doing so with a <m>charcoal</m> fire
in a ring around the bottle one span away from it, and at that time lute
the bottle well so that it does not exhale.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
