<root>
<page>147r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f299.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p146v_1</id>

<ab>Be warned to make an edge of <m>wax</m> melted with a warm
<m>wire</m> all around the edge of the top shell which is close to the
tail in order to make a better cast. And make it so that two small
strings of the same <m>wax</m> goes from the end of the shell of the
belly to the aforesaid <m>wax</m> edge, which is around the backbone of
the shell, and the <al>turtle</al>'s tail should stay in between those
two strings. This to make a better cast. This done, <m>oil</m> your mold
and what you can see of the shell. Put the circle around this, and cast
with <m>hot water</m> as before, and doing what you have done in the
same manner to mold the third part which is the tail. And having taken
hold, take away the <m>clay</m> contours, clean your mold, bring it
together, and flatten it on all sides with a knife as you have done with
other molds. Lightly dip it in <m>water</m>, then try to release it.
Usually, one starts by the shell of the back, which is to say the top
mold that is made of two halves. And this one is easier to release. The
other follows directly after, but because it is next to the
<al>turtle</al>'s shoulders which are deeply entrenched, it is sometimes
troublesome to do this when lightly shaking and pulling the mold. Be
advised to pull the easiest one first, because you will need to release
them one after the other. The hardest one of all is the one molding the
throat, the underside of the legs, and the cavities of the shoulders,
which are so difficult to release, that if you do not plan accordingly
by filling it with wax rather than molding what cannot been released, it
will be difficult to take the pieces without breaking something. But if
it happens to you again, there is a solution, provided that you keep the
broken pieces, because you can reassemble them with stong iron needles,
and fill whatever crack or flaw you have with some melted wax and hot
iron as you have with others so that the noyau to mold hollow is easier
to do. After</ab>

<ab><margin>bottom</margin>See the second page</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>To prevent breaking while releasing, be
advised to uncover up to the point where it can still hold.</ab>

</div>
</root>
