<root>
<page>146v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f298.image</image>

<div>

<id>p146v_1</id>

<head>Molding<al>turtles</al></head>

<ab>This page is the continuation of the preceding second page.Since you
have cleanly uncovered the part of the belly of <al>turtle</al>, its
underparts, its throat, and its legs, and having cleaned it all well, do
not forget to neatly uncover the cavity that these animals have in their
shell between the neck and the shoulders. <al>Turtles</al> do not have
as deep of a cavity as <al>tortoises</al>, which are more scraggly, and
even amongst those, there are some that have a deeper cavity than
others. Do not therefore forget to neatly uncover all of this in order
to better represent its likeness. But if there is a cavity which spirals
too much inside, and is not visible, nor releases well, apply some small
lumps of <m>wax</m> and with heated needles of thick <m>iron</m> and
work the aforesaid <m>wax</m>. Then plug the entrance to all of these
cavities with <m>soft clay</m>. Put the circle of <m>clay</m> around the
mold, which has already been made of two pieces and contains the back of
the <al>turtle</al>. And to mold its belly, you must separate it in
three as you can see. That is to say, you will put a roll of <m>clay</m>
on top of the throat and another one on the edge of the shell of its
tail, so that only the shell of the entire stomach will be accessible to
be molded on its own. Having <m>oiled</m> the shell of the belly and
having rubbed it with <m>spirits</m>, thrown you slightly thick sand,
which has been tempered with <m>hot water</m> as before. Having taken
hold, remove the rolls of <m>clay</m>, then uncover the front and back
legs, that is to say the bottom bit, and the throat and the tail, and
remove the clay of all the cavities in one go if you can, because this
will show you if the cavity will release well. And if the removed
<m>clay</m> carries with it some of the <m>wax</m> you have applied, put
it back into the places that did not release well, as has been said. And
if some bit of the <al>turtle</al> has come away with the <m>clay</m>,
or fallen off, attach and rejoin it to the mold with some <m>wax</m>,
using a heated <m>iron</m> needle. Do not forget to put some melted
<m>wax</m> at the edge of the <al>turtle</al>'s nails when you cast.
Having molded and uncovered the shell of the belly, you will see the
mold in this way.<figure>#</figure></ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p146v_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bUk2c1E3LWtOTDA</link>

</figure>

<figure>

<id>fig_p146v_2</id>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5WGEzek5peHJ6VDA</link>

</figure>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
