<root>
<page>141v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f288.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p141r_1</id>

<ab>Let your <al>crayfish</al> dry a little in the sun, by itself. If it
has spawns, they will shrink while drying, and be all the more beautiful
for it. Make your paste out of yellow <m><pro>potter</pro>'s earth</m>,
just like for the other representations. Lay your <al>crayfish</al> on
it, the back side down, and the other parts which are more tricky to
mold -- legs, belly, eggs - side up. Drive in the back side in the
<m>clay</m> paste up to the legs, which is about the half part <sup>of
the crayfish's body</sup>. Fix the body with a pointy <m>iron</m> thread
in the middle and, if you feel you need it, you can also drive another
one at the edge of the tail. And in order that the big legs be lower
than the head, which is lower because it is linked from below, add a
little <m>clay</m> <sup>under the head</sup>. Then add a bit of
<m>clay</m> under the jacket in order to raise it. Hide the feelers
under the <m>clay</m> and under the crusher claws, then arrange it as
you like. Stretch out the walking legs to the joints, and for the first
cast, bend the second part of the walking legs. Fix the joints of the
legs with <m>wax</m> and a warm <m>wire</m> so they will not move. If
you want to mould something fancier, fix the end of one walking legs on
the body or on a crusher claw , using the same <m>wax</m>. If the female
has spawns, bent half the tail over the spawns, and keep the shape by
fixing the tail with a <m>wire</m>. Be sure that you will be able to
clean this part. Finally rub your <al>crayfish</al> with <m>spirits</m>,
and cast your sand. Once the sand is hardened, uncover the back side,
the head, the eyes, and the small legs close to the crusher claws, and
the walking legs all along. One must uncover these parts as much as
possible. Then bend and cover the spawns again. The other animals</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>Fix what may raise <sup>the two padded
edges on each side of the mouth</sup> with melted <m>wax</m> under
them.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p141v_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5R0NIbHoyNTNQRlk</link>

</figure>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Uncover as many parts as possible, but
be sure the channels you make are well stripped.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Incline your mould to the thickest side
of the animal.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>To paint the crayfish, one paints the
middle of the back with <m>vermilion</m><m>,</m> mixed with a bit of
<m>lacquer</m>. The sides, the belly, and below the legs with a mixture
made of <m>vermilion</m>, <m>ceruse</m>, and a bit of yellow
<m>ochre</m>. As with all things, always keep the real one in front of
you in order to copy it <sup>as realistically as possible</sup>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>Lay the feelers on the crusher claws, or
solder this part with a wire made of bleached <m>brass</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>bottom</margin>When you arrange the legs, be sure that they
do not get over the belly, and that they are well set against the belly
otherwise <ill/></ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
