<root>
<page>105r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f215.image</image>

<div>

<id>p105r_1</id>

<head><al>Turtles</al></head>

<ab>Males have shells that turn down at the end near their tails, and
their underbelly shells have lined marks along the bottom from their
tails to their head. And the females have neither the turned down shell
near the tail nor the marks.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p105r_2</id>

<head>Drying colors</head>

<ab><m>Soot black</m> &amp; others would not dry in <m>oil</m> if one
did not put <m>verdigris</m> with it.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p105r_3</id>

<head><pro>Painter</pro></head>

<ab>Colors laid down twice are more gritty in and of themselves, if they
are not managed. Otherwise, one paints on <m>wood</m>; otherwise on
<m>canvas</m>; otherwise on walls.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p105r_4</id>

<head>Gardening</head>

<ab>To graft, it is necessary to take the new growth that was produced
within the year by the tree you wish to graft. And cut off a branch in
which you can see that beside the place where the leaves join the stem,
there are little buttons we call buds, the initial stages of a sprout.
With dexterity you must, with a very sharp pen-knife, cut in the shape
of a graft a small bit of the skin <sup>of the tree</sup>, which
contains a bud or a sprout with the leaf, as you can see in B. Then on
the tender wood, which is full of sap, and on which you wish to graft,
cut quickly two lines as you can see <figure/>, then add in the middle a
slit thusly

<figure>

<id>fig_p105r_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5T1FZYTdOT1U4Qzg</link>

</figure>

. Then with the point of your pen-knife separate the bark <sup>from the
tree</sup>, and open it from the slit in the middle, and having neatly
lodged your graft so that nothing is sticking out, only the sprout,
binding everything well and wrap the whole thing with a bit of
<m>linen</m> or soft string. In this way, there will be nothing
uncovered but the leaf, which in three or 4 days will indicate whether
the graft has taken hold, by being green. Keep your graft in this way
for seven or eight days. Then unwrap it, and join it to the bark,
keeping the sprout itself straight, and then rewrap the whole thing
gently, but not as strongly as before. And if there is any growth, leave
it some room to grow and then three or four times</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p105r_1</id>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5UWpzdGVweGVvQTg</link>

</figure>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
