<root>
<page>114r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f233.image</image>

<div>

<id>p114r_1</id>

<head>Second Casting</head>

<ab>When you have well molded the first part of the animal, that is to
say the back, the spine, and the entire top part, and when the half-mold
where the part is encased is hard enough <figure>

<id>fig_114r_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SWVndzB0aEk5MWs</link>

</figure> turn over the bottom &amp; the sides of the belly, sometimes
using a knife <del>&amp; tanto</del> for the thicker parts, &amp; then
with a pen-knife for the places where the more fragile parts are
encased, like legs, tail, &amp; similar things. Because the head is
higher, you will have to dig deeper to expose it &amp; do a deeper notch
that has to be well exposed, by enlarging it from the outside, in order
for the second mold that you cast on top of it releases well. A process
for which the animal himself can be useful because his nature so
permits. However, make sure that you reveal the <al>lizard</al>'s throat
more than you would do a <al>snake</al>, because the <al>lizard</al> has
big jaws &amp; big bones that do not cast as easily, and has deep ears
in which the wet sand is not as easy to remove. But you will avoid all
of this if you expose half of the head and those things that you know do
not release easily. When everything is well exposed, blow over it &amp;
wipe each part again with a cloth made of <al>swine</al> hair, slightly
dampened into salt <m>water</m> or clear <m>water</m>, do that gently,
that way the lower part of your uncovered animal will be very neat.
<figure>#</figure> <figure>🝋</figure> Once it is done, dip the covered
side of your mold into <m>water</m> for a pater noster. It will suck
water inside, that way when you'll rub with <m>oil</m> the uncovered
side, the <m>oil</m> will remain on the top, &amp; to prevent the second
cast which you will cast on top from sticking. Dip your mold into
<m>water</m>, take a particularly fine brush &amp; rub with <m>oil</m>
the entire mold but the animal; it should not be touched with
<m>oil</m>. &amp; Make sure to use you brush between the parts &amp; on
all the fragile parts. And if by mistake <m>oil</m> is soaked, dip the
mold into <m>water</m>, as it is said above, &amp; drop by drop the
<m>oil</m> will come back to the top.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

Mold small animals as big ones, however, for small animals, use very
fine tacks made of cords of cittern, short &amp; long ones.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<figure>

<id>fig_p114r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NVR5Y2FtZHM0ck0</link>

</figure>

remove all the little tacks with the help of very small flat
pincers.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<figure>#</figure>

then

<figure>+</figure><del><ill/></del></ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<figure>#</figure>However, leave the tack which is pinned into the
throat so that it will help you to turn the head over, because it is
sunk deeper than any other part, because when you drew the plan, you put
higher up. It is at the level of the head that you must make the biggest
notch &amp; you should start at that notch to expose and then keep
following by looking at the traces left by the tacks. </ab>

<ab><figure>#</figure> and if a small piece of nail, or piece of tail,
or other fine things separate from the mold, put a little piece of
<m>wax</m>between them, &amp; join them with the tip of a hot
<m>iron</m> wire, then smooth it in your mold with a knife, &amp; make
notches on the sides in order for the other half of the mold to adhere
to it. <figure>🝋</figure>

<figure>

<id>fig_p114r_6</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5TTRuWU8yVktnc3M</link>

</figure>

</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
