<root>
<page>107r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f219.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p106v_2</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p107r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5RFFFT3hSbnlGaVU</link>

</figure>

as heavy as before, and like a moderately thick paste &amp; that it is
not so easy to handle, as when it is liquid. It is a sign that it is
cooked enough, which you will know when it also throws big bubbles or
exhalations in the middle &amp; around, as long as a finger. Seeing it in
this state, remove it from the fire for it is heated enough, because if
you were to reheat more, it would be too much &amp; would not set as
well. For, when it becomes red &amp; overheats &amp; it loses its strength
&amp; spoils the sand. Leave it to cool before mixing it within the other
sands. And when it is cold, mix and mold, for as soon as you will use it
after its cooking, the sooner it will set.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p107r_a1</id>
<head>Catching <m><al>lizards</al></m> and <m><al>snakes</al></m></head>

<ab>Take a stick and attach a string at the end, which has a
<del>knot</del> <del>eyelet</del> slip <add>eyelet</add> at the end.
And, being two to three, to distract the lizard while whistling,
approach the eyelet of his neck, and when his head is inside, pull. The
lizard is more tedious to catch by hand than the serpent &amp; bites
without letting go &amp; grips like pincers.</ab>

<ab>Snakes can be caught by hand, provided that it is covered by a thick
woollen cloth, for the teeth of the snake stay in the cloth, &amp;
cannot pierce like they would with a linen. The dangerous ones are
recognisable by their blue eyes &amp; <del>asses</del> deep azur. They
hardly ever bite in water, which crayfish catchers experience.</ab>

<ab>The <m>sand</m> mixture is of two thirds of <m>plaster</m>,
pulverized &amp; reheated as said, &amp; of one part of <m>tile</m>,
reddened <del>et p pre</del> <add>in a good fire</add>, after the first
cooking &amp; then finely pulverized, and of <m><fr>alum de
plume</fr></m>, half of brick, namely two full crucibles of plaster, one
of brick &amp; a half of <fr>alum de plume</fr>. There can never be too
much <fr>alum de plume</fr>,<del>s</del> for this is what gives bond to
the sand, and because it does not burn, it makes sand withstand the fire
without cracking and bursting. Otherwise, without it, the sand would not
withstand. This sand, thus composed, is proper for all metals, but if
you want to use it for gold, it needs more <fr>alum de plume</fr>
<del>&amp;</del>,than the above mentioned composition, and mix in some
crocum ferri, and for it is this one that attracts gold.</ab>

<ab>It is necessary that all <m>sand</m> with which you want to cast,
withstands the fire well, that is to say that it withstands
<del>abon</del> <del>c</del> a great firing without getting
spoiled.</ab>

<ab><fr>Alum de plume</fr> is uneasy to crush, and it does not pass
through the sieve. Thusly one ought to grind it finely on <m>marble</m>.
And the one, white <del>que v</del> in powder form, that
<pro>apothecaries</pro> sell, is good. It is better finely ground
<del>su</del> in the mortar by pestling &amp;dragging the
<fr>pinon</fr>, thus you will render it very fine.</ab>

<ab><m>Crocum ferri</m> must be set ablaze in a <pro>glassworker</pro>’s
furnace for four days.</ab>

</div>
</root>
