<root>
<page>096v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f198.image</image>

<div>
<id>p096v_a1</id>
<head>Grey hilts</head>

<ab>When they are white, it is necessary only to clean them well, and
then to heat them over a fire, and make them turn blue. And take good
care that they do not turn too blue, since neither <m>gold</m> nor
<m>silver</m> nor any color would set. To accomplish this, which is
called <fr>les faire passer</fr>, have a caldron full of <m>ashes</m>
that you cover with some <m>blazing hot charcoal</m>, and heat the
<m>ashes</m> thus very well, for an hour or two. And when the
<m>ashes</m> are very hot, put the <m>charcoal</m> aside and put the
hilt where the <m>charcoal</m> was, and cover it completely with
<m>ashes</m>. And when the body, which is the main part of the hilt, is
completely colored, flip it onto the other side. In that way, the grey
cannot color it too dark, unless some <m>hot coal</m> touches it.
Greying can be achieved in an ordinary fireplace, too, but there is a
danger that it may sit there too long and make a crust which which will
prevent the color from setting. Blue coloring is obtained as soon as the
<m>ashes</m> have heated the hilts a little bit, but it will always be
grey on some sides. After blue comes grey.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p096v_a2</id>
<head>Color of water</head>

<ab><add>For</add> the color of water, pass a <tl><fr>lime
doulce</fr></tl> on the guards to whiten them, then the
<tl>burnisher</tl>. Next, one makes them pass blue until they become
grey. Next, when they are still moderately hot, pass the
<m>bloodstone</m> over them, and when they cool, one turns them to
reheat them, for the color of water is made only by several goes. And if
the guards were not warm, the <m>bloodstone</m> would scrape &amp; undo
the color. One needs to heed that guards do not pass too grey, for they
would give off filth that would prevent the color from taking. One needs
almost one <ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms> for preparing, softening, &amp;
setting the color of water, but as they pass a little blue, it is enough
for grey &amp; another color. Grey is the lesser color after
<m>varnish</m> which is of two colors, either yellow or black.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p096v_a3</id>
<head><m>Yellow varnish</m></head>

<ab>One whitens very well &amp; one cleans the guards well. Next, one
with a feather, one coats them cold with a <tl>feather</tl> all of
<m><pa>walnut</pa> <del><pa>olive</pa></del> oil</m>, and next turn them
over a good <m>charcoal</m> fire that is in the
<tl><pro>furbishers</pro>' furnace</tl>, without them touching the
<m>charcoal</m> or the <m>ashes</m>. And when they do not smoke anymore,
it is done.</ab>

</div>
</root>
