<root>
<page>005v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f16.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p005r_a2</id>

<ab>string &amp; will reflect a <bp>nipple</bp> as large as a plate, and
women can see the secret places that they do not want to show to
<pro>surgeons</pro>. It casts the representation out of itself, and if
you touch with your <bp>finger</bp> the eye of the representation,
another <bp>finger</bp> will come against yours.</ab>

<ab>You will be able to make a light at night for someone quite far
away, if you place the concave mirror behind a candle placed on the
window sill. You can read and write quite far from the candle if you
place it behind the candle &amp; place &amp; turn the concavity towards
you. If you put the mirror at the end of a table &amp; a candle on it,
it will represent two lights on the table for you. To see what is
happening on a street, shutter the window, or the more you can shut the
better, make a hole in the bottom <sup>pane</sup>, the size of your
<ms><bp>little finger</bp></ms>, perfectly round all the way through.
Then apply a sheet of paper onto the window and let the middle of the
sheet be over the hole. Pierce the sheet in the same place as the hole
and of the same size. Then turn the concave face of the mirror towards
the hole, and anyone passing by in the street will be reflected on the
sheet of paper. Do the same with the pierced door of a closed room. You
can make wavy <sup>mirrors</sup> and triangular ones, such as are
described by Ptolemy and Archimedes. The concave sort can also set fire
to straw or light a candle from afar, using the sun. By reverberating
fire too, it can provide warmth.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p005v_a1</id>
<head>For bronzing in yellow and white</head>

<ab>Take <m>mirror tin</m> and melt it. On half a pound of this, put
half an ounce of <m>quicksilver</m>, and remove it immediately from the
fire and grind it until it is like ashes. Wash it thoroughly in <m>clean
water</m>, then grind it on a <tl><m>marble</m> slab</tl> and soak it
with water of <m>glue de retailles</m>. Then apply that on your wooden
candlesticks and any other works you like, and burnish with a
<m>tooth</m>. You can grind <m>pin filings</m> and apply them with the
said <m>glue <sup>de retailles</sup></m>. </ab>

</div>
</root>
