<root>
<page>109r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f223.image</image>

<div>

<id>p109r_1</id>

<head>Modelling with <m>wax</m></head>

<ab>When <m>wax</m> is too hard, one mixes in <m>turpentine</m> or a
little <m>butter</m>, which <del>sont pl</del> renders the <m>wax</m>
more amiable, and more appropriate than the<m>tallow</m> that the
<pl>Italians</pl> put in, because one has to, often, put the tools in
the mouth, which are better in <m>box wood</m> or <m>bone of
hart</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p109r_2</id>

<head><m>Wax</m> for molding</head>

<ab>Since the <m>wax</m> is molten, they have some <m>sulphur</m> in a
spoon or crucible &amp; pour it in the molten <m>wax</m>. And with the
<m>sulphur</m> going to the bottom or staying on top, it stays where it
is &amp; mixes only its substance in the <m>wax</m>, &amp; renders it
more meltable when warming it, in such a way that having molded it,
<sup>the <m>wax</m></sup> gently melts in the mold like <m>butter</m>,
without leaving any blister or boil. Also be warned to not give it too
much heat.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>If</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p109r_3</id>

<head>Molding <m>wax</m></head>

<ab>So that your mold takes hold without repelling any surface on a form
or figure in <m>wax</m><m>,</m> it is necessary to rub the <m>wax</m>
with <m>oil</m> and soak your sand in lukewarm <m>water</m>, because
cold <m>water</m> repels <m>oil</m> even more &amp; will not make a good
layer on the <m>wax</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Rub the <m>oil</m> on very very lightly,
<sup>use</sup> so little that it hardly appears at all. Then rub with
some <m>spirits</m>. After soak your sand in lukewarm <m>water</m> so
that it does not repel the <m>oil</m>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p109r_4</id>

<head>Forge bellows</head>

<ab>It is better that at the end with the air chamber the bellows be set
in some kind of bit of cloven board because they are more secure this
way. Afterwards you can lightly secure them from the top. It is
necessary that the nozzles be four fingers above the bottom of the
forge.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p109r_5</id>

<head>Molding <al>snakes</al></head>

<ab>When you get them for molding, if it is possible, do not remove
their teeth if you <x>think you might</x> want to keep them, because
having had their teeth removed, it hurts their gums &amp; mouths, &amp;
they can no longer eat. You can keep <x>the snakes</x> in a barrel full
of <m>bran</m> or even better of <m>earth</m>, in a cool place, or in a
<m>glass</m> bottle. And give them some live frog or other live animal
because they do not eat anything <sup>that is</sup> dead. Also I have
noticed that</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
