<root>
<page>057v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f120.item</image>

<div>

<id>p057v_1</id>

<head><pro>Sheathmaker</pro></head>

<ab><pro>Sheathmakers</pro>use small <m>skins</m> of <al>lambs</al> and
young <al>goats</al>

very delicate, as it were like <m>parchment</m> and they keep them in
humid places constantly re-wetted. When they want to print some history
they lay them in the hollows of their figure and then on top they spread
some fatty fine <m>earth</m> used for degreasing cloth, well pressed and
beaten and slightly humid and soft and then put on the <m>earth</m> a
small one-piece board and put the whole under a press and leave that dry
there. After the <m>earth</m> the <m>leather</m> only remains very
neatly printed <x>missing word</x> of the size of a pea. And then apply
on the <m>leather</m> two or three <m>black copperas</m> and <m>iron
scale</m> layers one after the other like the <pro>tanners</pro> do. And
since this tincture is astringent and shrinks the leather will be
stronger more more easily printable. Once dried stick on the reverse
some <m>fabric</m> with strong <m>glue</m>, and by doing so one can
quickly imitate big statues and very fine medals and paint them and
<ill/> and are light and can be carried and last for a long time. What
can be printed on a relief can be made differently and can be reheated
with a hot <m>iron</m> tool.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p057v_2</id>

<head><pro>Painter</pro></head>

<ab>Good <tl><m>crayons</m></tl> are not made with <del>good</del>
<m>glue</m> but with <m>women's milk</m>.</ab>

<ab>Images made of <m><fr>carton</fr></m>, once dry, have to be soaked
in <m>thoroughly macerated and clear melted resin</m>. This strengthens
it, otherwise they turn limp in <env>wet weather</env>.</ab>

<ab><pl>Venice</pl> masks are made with a hollow &amp; male face of
<m>copper</m>.</ab>

<ab>The <pl>Flemish</pl> do not use any whites for flesh colors in
<m>oil</m> other than <m>lead white</m> because the <m>ceruse</m> turns
yellow.</ab>

<ab>4 or 5 <tmp>year</tmp>-old <m><pa>walnut</pa> oil</m> which is clear
is the best color, it keeps off dust. The kind which has recently been
drawn with the press in the manner of <m><pa>almond</pa> oil</m> is
white, especially if the <m><pa>walnuts</pa>' skin</m> is removed.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
