<root>
<page>052v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f110.item</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p052r_1</id>

<ab>or to be safer, go away until the fire is completely blown out and
that everything is cold again. Because the exaltation may be dangerous.
And for that moment, when you take it with some tongs, do cover your
mouth with some good <m>vinegar</m> and have a protection and cover
yourself with it. Once it has died out, put it into a cloth or a canvas
made of <m>silk</m> and fold it and hold it to a board exposed to air
and the sun will dry it. Once it is well dry, powder it in a mortar and
keep this powder cautiously Because one ounce of this one thrown on 3
pounds of melted <m>♁</m> transforms it into a finer <m>☉</m> than the
other one. But there is not so much pitch. You also have to choose the
oldest <m>♁</m> possible which has often melted before and finely
hammered into blades or other works, and at first purify it by melting
and throwing it into some <m>honey</m> and <m>vinegar</m>. The
completion time for such work is nine months from Saint John's day until
the 25th April. </ab></div>

<div>

<id>p052v_1</id>

<head><m>Linseed</m></head>

<ab>Who wants to have it beautiful &amp; very delicate, one needs to
pick it before the seed may be perfectly ripe. For if one waits for the
seed to be perfectly ripe, the foot is so dried by the sun that it is
brittle &amp; breakable. It is true that in this way the seed is reduced
by a third.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p052v_2</id>

<head>Colors</head>

<ab>If you want to keep them beautiful in <m>gum</m> and such that they
do not lose any of their natural color, put <m>white wine</m>, the
whitest and clearest you can, in a <tl>bottle</tl> with a little
<m>tragacanth gum</m>. And having <tl>stoppered</tl> the
<tl>bottle</tl>, scramble &amp; shake it very strongly together, &amp;
let it rest until the <m>tragacanth</m> is dissolved. Also put in a
little fine-grained <m><fr>sel blanc</fr></m> to brighten the whole.
Some mix <m>clear water</m> with <m>white wine</m>, and with this
mixture they temper the colors without grinding. And these show very
beautifully on <pro>illumination</pro> works.</ab></div>
</root>
