<root>
<page>154r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f313.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p154r_a1</id>
<head>Removing <m>gold</m></head>

<ab><m>Gold</m> as gilding goes away if the coin is reheated and placed
against a strong fire, even if there is <m>lead</m>, because
<m>lead</m>, which contains much <m>mercury</m> will pierce a
<m>gold</m> coin in a fire.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p154r_a2</id>
<head>Cutting <m>lead</m></head>

<ab>Because it <x><m>lead</m></x> is fat, hard to catch and corrosive to
the knife and the scissors, wet it up and you will <x>be able to</x> cut
it like <m>glass</m>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Sometimes, <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m>, exposed to a certain kind of
smoke, take on a coloration during the casting. But these are neither
flakes nor coat but a colour which will go away during the
whitening.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p154r_a3</id>
<head>Softening <m>silver</m></head>

<ab>When <pro>goldsmiths</pro> who work on a large scale have forged
their plates, to their loss <x>these plates</x> quite often break and
crack because they have been sharpened too much. In order to avoid this,
when it is quite melted, throw in ground dry <m>mortar</m> made of
<m>sand</m> and good <m>lime</m> which has been used before.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<pro>Goldsmiths</pro> do not work with <m>silver</m> from <m>real</m>
because it is rich in <m>lead</m> and becomes sour when forged.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

For small works and things that need to go only once to the fire, some
weld with some old <m>sol</m> or <m>carolus</m> reheated and beaten.
However if the <m>sol</m> is not quite good <x>enough</x>, the welding
will not hold as there is too much <m>copper</m> and one will have to
weld twice. Others weld with <x>an alloy made of</x> half <m>silver</m>
and half fine <m>copper</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p154r_a4</id>
<head><m>Iron</m> flakes</head>

<ab>Once it is quite ground and refined on the <m>marble</m> slab and
mixed with the <m>sand</m> from the core <x>mold</x>, dry it slowing
without reheating it, and it will allow for several casting of
<m>lead</m> and <m>tin</m>. <m>Copper</m> and <m>brass</m> come out fine
of it. But if it is not ground as finely as <m>crocum</m>, it sinks
unless the <m>sand</m> is soaked and quite thick.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p154r_a5</id>
<head><m>Metal file dust</m></head>

<ab>It does not melt by itself if it is not helped with some portion of
similar <m>metal</m> melted to assemble it and bathe it, as it is more
burnt than melted. <m>File dust</m> from <m>tin</m> and <m>lead</m> are
made with <m>tallow</m>, <x><m>file dust</m></x> from <m>gold</m> with
<m>saltpeter</m>, <x><m>file dust</m></x> from <m>silver</m> with
<m>sandever.</m></ab>

</div>
</root>
