<root>
<page>160v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f326.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p160v_1</id>
<head>Molding a foot or hand</head>

<ab>Mix <m>resin</m> among <m>wax</m>, &amp; having incorporated it
well, soften them in hot <m>water</m> or <m>urine</m>, &amp; then make
an imprint by pressing, &amp; next cast in <m>plaster</m>, &amp; it will
come out quite neat &amp; will easily release.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p160v_2</id>
<head>Delicate work of <m>gold</m> or of <m>silver</m></head>

<ab>It can be done with flies by hand without casting, &amp; the wings
&amp; feet can be joined by solder, which is not able to be done with
delicate works of <m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m>, because they would melt.
And the work of <m>gold</m> can be enameled.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p160v_3</id>
<head>Catching crayfish</head>

<ab>Attach to the tip of a stick some liver or lung of a cow or sheep,
&amp; with a small string you make a basket hang from the tip of the
aforesaid stick. Put in water where crayfishes eat, &amp; they will
quickly come to accumulate on the flesh. Extract gently from the water,
&amp;; those who want to go back into the water will fall into the
basket.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p160v_4</id>
<head>Catching passerines</head>

<ab>If they sleep in straw, like they usually do close to the house,
leave the closest window open &amp; put in a lighted candle, but so that
the candle is hidden &amp; that its light only appears throughout the
room &amp; through the window, and all will enclose themselves in the
room. But it is necessary that the night be dark &amp; make no
<figure>☾</figure>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p160v_5</id>
<head>Catching birds</head>

<ab>In winter, when the birds have molted, skin them &amp; fill them
with stuffing cloth <del>&amp;</del>, <add>or</add> dry them in an oven
<figure>#</figure>. Then arrange them on the trees, &amp; have one who
sings, &amp; you will gather them &amp; catch many.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>

in an oven that is scarcely hot <del>The <tmp>winter</tmp></del>.
<del>it</del><add>And</add> in summer this is done because, before they
would be dried, the fly would get into their eyes <add>and make
worms</add>. In winter they are prepared better &amp; are dried by
themselves.</ab>

</div>
</root>
