<root>
<page>130r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f265.item.r=</image>

<div>

<id>p130r_1</id>

<head>Animals dried in an oven</head>

<ab>Small <al>cats</al> are skinned and one removes their eyes &amp;all
their entrails. One puts a small stick vertically between their teeth to
make them open their mouths wide. Then with <m>iron points</m> one
attaches their feet to a small board, giving them the fitting attitude
&amp; gait. Once thus attached by their feet with small <m>rings of iron
wire</m>, one needs to suspend them in the sun with their spines
downwards. In this manner they take <del>&amp; d</del> their shape &amp;
dry, &amp; the belly tightens &amp; the tail remains high or with the
bend that you will have given it. Once a little dry by this means, one
turns the head as one wants, securing it with some tool. Then one
finishes drying it in an oven after the bread is taken out. Next one
places in its eye sockets balls of <m>lead</m> or of <m>wax</m>, painted
according to nature. One paints them with <m>well-gummed ink</m> so that
they seem to be jet. One gives it a painted tongue, horns, wings &amp;
similar fantasies. Thus for <al>rats</al> &amp; all animals.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p130r_2</id>

<head>For reddening live <al>crayfish</al> which will seem as if
boiled</head>

<ab>Rub them in quite good <m>vinegar</m>, in which there should be a
little <m>eau-de-vie</m> and not much, and they can be served as if
cooked and will walk.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p130r_3</id>

<head>Molding a single <al>spider</al></head>

<ab>One needs to plant it on the clay slab, as has been said, on a vine
leaf, and make there your first cast &amp; once it has set, uncover the
spider up to half its legs, then make the second cast.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<corr><del>In order</del></corr> The hairy feet of large
<al>spiders</al>, like any animal hair, does not mold well if it is not
flattened, having smeared it with <m>wheat oil</m>, which stiffens it
&amp; is quickly dry. Hairy things mix with the sand &amp; do not burn
well.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p130r_4</id>

<head>Molding a single <m>vine leaf</m></head>

<ab>Plant it with the points of fine <del>iron</del> latten wire &amp;
place diagonally on the clay slab, then cast the first mold. Having set,
uncover the <del>back</del> reverse &amp; make the second cast, which
once set, you can take away the leaf. And you will need to reheat your
mold only once, because there will be nothing to burn.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<figure>

<id>fig_p130r</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5cHVsNnNVQ1l5RnM</link>

</figure>

which surround the fingers of the paws and which stick in the jacket of
<m>clay</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
