<root>
<page>119r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f243.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p118v_2</id>

<ab> When I saw that they did not smoke anymore, &amp; scratching the
back &amp; the front of the casting &amp; having found that they are
rough &amp; firm &amp; hard on both sides, which is a good sign of their
being quite dry, I leave them to cool down. I took some fine <m>tin</m>,
one lb., &amp; one ounce of fine &amp; new <m>lead</m>. I melted it in a
crucible just until it was a bit red. Being in this way quite hot &amp;
ready to cast &amp; no sooner, I smoked every side of my box frame with
the smoke of a <m>tallow candle</m> &amp; pressed &amp; cast &amp;
everything. I set my box frame, well joined, in the press. I drew my
crucible from the fire. I let it sit a bit to quench the redness of the
crucible's bottom. And wanting to cast, I threw in around two or three
grains of rosin, and about the measure of a bean of <m>looking-glass
tin</m> &amp; blended it &amp; stirred the crucible a little and cast.
And the medal came out as neat as the original. I smoked it with the
candle &amp; cleaned it with my <m>coat</m>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Always cast through the foot of the medal because the head, which is
lower, will come out better, and make the casting somewhat long. And
when you cast several medals in a large box frame, they will come out
better.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p119r_1</id>
<head>Notice about everything above</head>

<ab> Good <m>tin</m> is that which is hard as <m>silver</m> &amp; soft
nevertheless. If your work is fine, it must be almost all <m>tin</m>
&amp; alloyed as is said.</ab>

<ab><m>Looking-glass tin</m> must not be mixed until the instant that
you want to cast.</ab>

<ab> Nor must the forms be smoked until then.</ab>

<ab> If the <m>sand</m> shrinks in the box frame, this means that it
must be reheated &amp; turned red on the fire.</ab>

<ab>Good <m>sand</m> when moistened does not stick at all to the hand
when pressed.</ab>

<ab>The perfect <m>sand</m> for the box frame is the <m>asphalt</m>
found in Germany, which is soft as wet <m>flour</m>, &amp; almost all
the rest are lumpy.</ab>

<ab>

<rub>Nota</rub>that the casting must be fine &amp; hardly thick so that
it does not work the material at all, &amp; must not exceed the
thickness of a grain of <m>wheat</m> taken crossw-wise, likewise for
<m>tin</m> that is going to be cast finely. For <m>lead</m>, a little
thicker. There is no need to make air vents very large &amp; deep
either.</ab>

<ab>
The <m>sand</m> that you use à noyau for the said mixture is excellent
for a box frame. But in washing, crushing &amp; reheating it several
times, its nature will be corrupted &amp; it will no longer be fit to be
taken &amp; molded <pro>en noyau</pro>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
