<root>
<page>115v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f236.image</image>

<div>
<id>p115v_1</id>
<head><m>Tin</m> casting</head>

<ab>If the <m>plant</m> or <m>flower</m> that you want to cast is
delicate &amp; fine, it is necessary that the <m>tin</m> exceeds
<m>lead</m> in the mixture &amp; on the contrary, if it is thick, it is
necessary that lead exceed. Therefore for the fine thing, put in some
fine tin, not all the quarter part of lead. And make sure that your mold
is hottish, such that you can hold it in your hand, when you want to
cast. As for the alloyed <m>tin</m>,the same as mentioned, it is
necessary that it is very hot &amp; almost red for casting, so that it
penetrates. Otherwise, having to run the length of the fine branches of
the plant, it will get cold before arriving there. And no forget to mix
in it a little <m>looking-glass tin</m>, which makes it run better &amp;
firms it up.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
In the <m>lead</m> alloyed with <m>tin</m>, or <m>tin</m> alloyed with
<m>lead</m>, you can put a little bit of <fr>metalline</fr> &amp; it
will seem silver. But do not put too much, for this hardens the
substance &amp; sours it also, so that for a delicate thing like legs
&amp; similar things, it would not be appropriate.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p115v_2</id>
<head>To give vent to the mold</head>

<ab>In addition to your vents, if your plant is very fine, you can pass
a thread through the clay circle, rather than casting with a needle,
&amp; make sure it passes through the plant. And with thread, burning
like the plant, a hole will remain, which will give air &amp; venting,
to help clean.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Do not pull out your reheated molds from the fire, before they have
cooled themselves &amp; take care that neither the wind or the cold hits
them while very hot, for this would make them burst. One must not reheat
them before they are dry and firmed up for they would cast in a
different way, and it is necessary before hand to make gates &amp; vents
&amp; place clamps.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p115v_3</id>
<head>Reheating <fr>noyau</fr> molds</head>

<ab>After your molds have their gate, vents &amp; clamps, as mentioned,
make at the end of the forge, or in some clean place, a surrounding of
bricks, and fill it with large half lit charcoal. And place your molds
on top, and leave the charcoals thusly to light by themselves for a half
hour, so that they heat little by little and not all at once. Finally as
they begin to become white, beat the thusly half-lit large charcoals on
top &amp; blow with your little bellows, until they are warmed. And
thusly, little by little, invigorate the fire, without haste, until you
molds are well red on the outside &amp; the inside. If it is for casting
some plant or some animal which does not release well &amp; in this
case, one needs to burn it in the mold &amp; when you look through the
gate &amp; through it you see the molds are very red &amp; inflamed
inside,this will be your signal that they are reheated enough. But if
you do not see this signal, increase &amp;continue the fire until it is
the case. If there is nothing in the mold that needs burning, it will be
enough that they are dried well on the same fire, if it is for casting
tin, they reheat better in a reverberatory furnace.</ab>

<x>image</x>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<figure>

<id>fig_p115v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dHVja3NnV0dmMlk</link>

</figure>
Take care not to heat the fire in one go, for fear that your molds crack
inside.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
They are reheated enough when the entire hole of the gate is red. When
it is black, it is not enough.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
For casting in silver, one must not reheat two times, if there is
nothing in the mold that needs burning, simply because it does not
release well. All the molds of farriers are reheated two times, first
for</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
