<root>
<page>023r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f51.image</image>

<div>

<id>p023r_1</id>

<ab>A petard is made so that it weighs three <ms>quintals</ms> and
carries a cannonball flat on the side from which it must exit and round
on the side of the cannon, as if it was a cannonball cut in half. It is
two pans long. It has to be loaded with xxv <ms>lb</ms> of powder
because it has to be full to the mouth &amp; has to burst. Its bottom is
not thicker than the mouth &amp; is made of one single piece. Its
substance has to be better than that other artillery piece, and for 4
<ms>quintals</ms> of fine <m>copper</m> there must only be one quintal
of <m>metal</m> so that it absorbs the shock, and so that, when fired
with more force, it is more efficient. It has to be used against a door
with a large <m>iron</m> cross before the bullet, and once loaded, needs
to be covered with a firmly sewed rough <m>canvas</m> which should be
completely smeared with <m>turpentine</m>. Four handles need to be added
to it while it is cast, it <corr>is</corr> thus easier to place. The
<m>iron</m> cross is fixed to the mouth with the <m>canvas</m> covering
it. The handles have to be held at its muzzle's edge, as you can see. To
place it, you need three or four <m>iron</m> <tl>pegs</tl> of one
<fr><ms>pan</ms></fr> long &amp; as thick as a <ms><bp>finger</bp></ms>,
which have their point like a <tl>gimlet</tl>, &amp; the entire leg in
the shape of a screw like an auger, and a ring on the other end to turn
them with a short <tl>stick</tl> that fits into the <tl>ring</tl>. And
the <tl>pegs</tl> are fixed on the door, not straight, for they would
not have any strength, but crooked as if you wanted to fix them towards
the middle of the <m>petard</m>, and to that effect, the hole of the
handles needs to be quite large. In that way, the shooting <m>petard</m>
pushes the <tl>pegs</tl> forward and sideways into the door, and makes
more fracture. Once it is placed, it is necessary to have <fr>saucisse
de <m>buckram</m></fr> @ made in this manner: take eight or nine
<fr><ms>canes</ms></fr> of <fr><m>buckram</m></fr> strip or more if the
ditch is larger, and make the strip four or five
<ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> wide. Have it well sewn in such a way so that
it is like a bowel where a <tl>stick</tl> as thick as a
<ms><bp>finger</bp></ms> could fit. Fill it completely with good</ab>

<cont/>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

This one is to be put below an undermined tower with its muzzle towards
the top. One casts two large <m>iron</m> <tl>rings</tl> &amp; with a
<tl>stick</tl> or two, four men carry it. They are also used for placing
within wall breaches but just half a charge is necessary, that is x
<ms>lb</ms>, &amp; fill it with some <m>pebbles</m> &amp; <m>cart
pebbles</m></ab>.

<figure>

<id>fig_p023r_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5RzRNM284T3Q0eTQ</link>

</figure>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

It is necessary to cover it entirely with a <m>waxed</m> <m>canvas</m>
&amp; rubbed with <m>turpentine</m> and other <m>combustible things</m>.
This cover is made to ensure that the ball does not fall and in order
that when the cover is given fire, the <m>primer powder</m> does not
fail. At the top of the touch-hole, it will be necessary to put in a
good quantity of <m>primer powder</m>. Some put on the ball a cross of
<m>iron</m> which is longer than the mouth of the <m>mortar</m> by two
<fr><ms>pans</ms></fr>. Others only put the ball.</ab>

</div>
</root>
