<root>
<page>115v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f236.image</image>

<div>
<id>p115v_1</id>
<head><m>Tin</m> casting</head>

<ab>If the <m>herbage</m> or <m>flower</m> you want to cast is delicate
and fine, <m>tin</m> must exceed <m>lead</m> in your mixture; on the
contrary, if it the flower or herbage is thick, you must add into your
mixture more <m>lead</m> than <m>tin</m>. For a fine thing<m>,</m> put
to the <m>tin</m> not quite the fourth part of <m>lead</m>. Your mold
must not be too hot, so you can hold it with your hand when you cast.
Your alloyed <m>tin</m> must be very hot and almost red for casting, and
that way it will enter all the small parts of the mold. Otherwise, your
tin will cool down before reaching the thin parts of your
<m>herbage</m>. Do not forget to mix a little <m>bismuth</m> in your
mixture; that way, your tin will run better and be firmer.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
With your <m>lead</m> allied with <m>tin</m>, or <m>tin</m> allied with
<m>lead</m>, you can add a very little quantity of <m>bismuth</m> and it
will look silvery. But do not put too much, because if hardens the
matter and makes it sour, and if your work on fine things -- like legs
and similar things -- it will not cast properly.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p115v_2</id>
<head>Giving ventilation to your mold</head>

<ab>If your herbage is very fine, in addition to vents, you can pass a
thread through the <m>clay</m> contour instead of casting with a needle,
and ensure that it also passes through the herbage. As the thread burns
like the herbage, the hole will remain, which will give air and wind to
help clean.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Do not remove your annealed molds out of the <m>fire</m> before they
have cooled down by themselves. Also make sure that your very hot molds
do not come into contact with wind or coldness otherwise they would
burst. Do not reheat your molds before they are drained and firm again,
otherwise they would cast before the vent holes are made and the clamps
are fixed.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p115v_3</id>
<head>Annealing core molds</head>

<ab>After your molds have their cast vents and clamps, fix the clamps as
above mentioned. Then make a round, made of <m>bricks</m>, at the edge
of your forge, or in a clean place. Fill this round with big,
half-lighted pieces of <m>charcoal</m>. Put your molds on the round, and
leave it during half an hour, that way it will gently heat up and not
all at once. Finally, when <m>coals</m> start being white, add big
half-lighted big pieces of <m>charcoal</m> and blow with your small
bellows until hot. Do as such, slowly, until the molds redden inside and
out. If you want to cast a herbage or an animal which are difficult to
strip, and you need to burn what is in the mold, look into the cast and
see if it is molds are quite red and inflamed inside; this will be a
sign that they are properly annealed. If it is not so, increase the heat
and keep at it until it becomes thus. If there is nothing inside the
mold to be burnt, this heat is good for <m>tin</m> casting. The molds
for <m>tin</m> casting are much better annealed in a reverberatory
furnace.</ab>

<x>image</x>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<figure>

<id>fig_p115v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dHVja3NnV0dmMlk</link>

</figure>
Do not heat too much at first otherwise your molds could break</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
You know that your molds are annealed enough if the hole in the cast is
red, on the contrary if the hole is black the molds are not annealed
enough.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
If you want to cast <m>silver</m>, do not anneal twice, and if something
stays in the mold and that must be burnt because no good <x>…</x></ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
