<root>
<page>131r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f267.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p131r_1</id>
<head><m>Plants</m> which are bad to burn in the mold</head>

<ab>Mold them in two or three castings; being annealed, your mold will
open, and it will be easier to extract the <m>charcoal</m> from inside.
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Try <x>this</x></ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p131r_2</id>
<head>Letters and molded <m>paper</m></head>

<ab>Write with some <m>ink</m> well thickened with gum or any other
<m>color dye</m> which has body, and which is not erased if dampened
with brandy. Then put your paper on the sheet of clay, and dampen it
with <m>brandy</m>. Cast both sides <x>of paper</x>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p131r_3</id>
<head>For adorning beds, mirrors and similar things</head>

<ab>Model any drawing in half relief on a flat <m>slate</m> in order to
set it on round or flat things. Cast with very fine <m>tin</m>, then you
can gild it with <m>gold</m> leaf, and set it wherever you want. Fill
the bottom of the relief with small <m>rubies</m>, <m>orpiment</m>, or
any colored little <m>grains</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p131r_4</id>
<head>To teach a dog well</head>

<ab>You need to keep your dog attached; when it does what you command,
to win its love, give it a piece of <m>cheese</m> that was held under
the armpit. This <m>cheese</m> would be a bad drug if the master, or the
apprentice, is red-haired. </ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p131r_5</id>
<head>Molded <m>waxes</m></head>

<ab>Wax representations made from <m>white lead</m> and <m>cerussite</m>
are not made to be burned and melted in a mold where you want to cast
<m>silver</m> and <m>gold</m>; this would make it brittle. Moreover if
you use such a mold, the <m>wax</m> would be stripped thanks to the
violence of the fire which makes it boil, and the mixture made of
<m>cerrusite</m> or any other metal would attack the mold. That's why if
you want to sketch things</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<figure>+</figure>
<m>White wax</m> is more delicate than the other, and it doesn't leave
any filth when you want to mold it as a core, or to mold hollow.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
