<root>
<page>009r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f23.item</image>

<div>

<id>p009r_1</id>

<head><pro>Plowman</pro></head>

<ab>Since <m><pa><fr>millet</fr></pa></m> is naturally very dry,
<pro>harvesters</pro> thresh it most often in the cool of night and in
moonlight. Which could not be done with another, wetter,
<m><pa>grain</pa></m>, because you must let the sunbeams pass over it,
and one rarely threshes it before midday. Immediately after the
<m><pa><fr>millet</fr></pa></m> is harvested, the earth needs to be
plowed because its roots eat and make lean <sup>the soil</sup> as much
as if the <m><pa><fr>millet</fr></pa></m> was still standing. The ground
where <m><pa><fr>millet</fr></pa></m> will have been sown becomes quite
diminished in fertility, which you can tell next time it is sown. But
more than any other the <m>grain</m> called
<m><pa><fr>pomole</fr></pa></m> in <pl>Gascony</pl>or
<m><pa><fr>baillard</fr></pa></m> in <pl><sup>northern</sup>
France</pl>, makes the earth shake, according to the common saying,
seven years later. <m><pa>Broad beans</pa></m> improve and enrich the
soil, provided that one lets the roots and stems rot in it.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p009r_2</id>

<head><pro>Painters</pro></head>

<ab>Some, having laid down their color, soften it with the back of a
<tl>feather</tl> but the large <tl>brush</tl> is best.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p009r_3</id>

<head><pro>Merchants</pro></head>

<ab>They commonly have four books. The tiro, which is a formulary for
apprentices, by which they can know how much every item of merchandise
costs and for how much it should be sold. The second is the waste book,
where they put down in rough what they sell daily. The third is the
sales book, where they put down the clean copy and detailed account of
what is contained in the waste book. The fourth is the ledger, which
mentions the sale, the balanced account, the bill and the term of
payment, and this book is accepted as evidence in court.</ab>

</div>
</root>
