<root>
<page>157r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f319.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p157r_1</id>
<head>The mode in which <pro>goldsmiths</pro> mold hollow molds</head>

<ab>

They mold their animal, or another solid work that they have already
made or rough-hewn in <m>wax</m> and cast in <m>lead</m>, in two
cuttlefish bones. When it is good and impressed in the two cuttlefish
bones, they put a piece of <m>paper</m> between the two bones &amp; join
the bones and cast. The work comes in parts by halves. And then with a
chaple they excavate the two half castings of <m>gold</m> or
<m>silver</m> as subtly as they like, and then they solder or braze
them.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p157r_2</id>
<head><m><fr>Rouge cler</fr></m></head>

<ab>

Some <pro>goldsmiths</pro> assay it on <m>thinly beaten
<del><fr>esp</fr></del> gold</m> &amp; that is well <tl>burnished</tl>
with a <tl><fr>chaple</fr></tl>. But it is better to assay it on a
<m>gold ingot</m>. And also assay your substances in large or
fantastical work, since if they appear good &amp; extraordinary in large
work, they will show excellently on a common work.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p157r_3</id>
<head>Flies </head>

<ab>They mold better on a single leaf than on a bouquet or a flower or
the branch of an herb, since the single leaf is molded in two halves
that being reheated can be opened up and cleaned well, &amp; the cast
will be better. In picking up the fly, take heed that you do not break
its legs or let it dry out too much, because then the legs will fall
off. And if this happens to you, glue the same legs back on with <m>fish
glue</m> and <m>wax</m>, or adapt the <m>hairs of a pig</m> or the
<m>cords of a spinet</m>. Fix the leaf on a flat piece of <m>clay</m>
with two pins, and the fly with one pin in the middle of its body &amp;
the feet with wax.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p157r_4</id>
<head>Cleaning and degreasing your cast <m>tin</m> works, and
others</head>

<ab>Make some lye passed through carefully with good <m>ashes</m>, and
it should be new &amp; without any fat; boil your molded work in it. And
the tallow and fat will leave.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p157r_5</id>
<head>Arranging an herb or flower to cast</head>

<ab>

Always put the front side of the thing on the upper side because it will
come out better and neater than the lower side. Make the casting large
&amp; prepare the supraplus, which is the mass, after the
<pro>founders</pro> of large castings, even for <m>silver</m>, which
needs a very hot mold &amp; is cast very hot. Very fine thing must be
cast very hot.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>

When you know that the stem of a flower burned in a mold that will not
open at all is totally reduced to ashes, this is the sign that
everything else is well-burned.</ab>

</div>
</root>
