<root>
<page>122v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f250.item.r=</image>

<div>

<id>p122v_1</id>

<head>Cleaning the <tl>bowl</tl> and the <tl>spoon</tl> that one uses to
temper sand</head>

<ab>Be very careful to clean, vigorously &amp; quickly after casting,
your <tl>bowl</tl> &amp; your <tl>spatula</tl> or <tl>spoon</tl> with
which you temper your sand, because if it dries, it crumbles &amp; falls
into the fresh sand &amp; makes a hole or fault get made. Also, when the
<tl>mold</tl> gets reheated, these little pieces will chip &amp; flake
off &amp; prevent neat casting. </ab></div>

<div>

<id>p122v_2</id>

<head>Molding hollow</head>

<ab><m>Wax</m> on its own cools down too rapidly &amp; does not spread
well everywhere, &amp; <m>tallow</m> holds its heat &amp; spreads
everywhere; but is not good on its own. But when <m>wax</m> and
<m>tallow</m> are mixed the work behaves well. The bodies of
<m>crawfish</m> &amp; other small animals can easily be molded hollow,
but as for the legs, it will be troublesome.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

The first part of the <tl>mold</tl> that is first cast on the plate of
<m>clay</m>, cracks more easily in the fire than the second.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p122v_3</id>

<head>Molding medals and flat things</head>

<ab>You are not limited to making the gate with legs thus

<figure>

<id>fig_p122v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5aTlRdkx2eVdtZXM</link>

</figure>

, but rather in this way

<figure>

<id>fig_p122v_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5WFBpaEV5Ti1hRUU</link>

</figure>

, which embraces the medal well. For the other way with legs is only
done to accommodate more delicate works and the other, which is wide and
in one piece works better for flat medals. But take heed that all gates
need to be very thin close to the medal &amp; so as to say not as thick
as the medal, if it is not very thin like paper. And then, from the
medal out towards the opening of the gate, make it thicker and thicker
for it works better thus. If the gate is thick at the entry to the
medal, the work never comes out very well. Make that <del>despuys</del>
from the middle to the top of the gate be moderately thick, &amp; from
the same middle to the bottom very thin. Do not forget to makes grooves
in <del>au hau</del> the top of your gate to prevent the <m>metal</m>
from spreading furiously.</ab>

</div>
</root>
