<root>
<page>105v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f216.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p105r_4</id>

<ab>Then, when the graft has taken hold, cut the top of the tree, which
is above your tree, three or four fingers above the graft for the first
time. Then, closer so that it serves. But be advised that when you do
your initial grafting there should be no small hole at the back of your
sprout, because this means that root is broken and your graft will never
take. Therefore make sure the back is in tact. This type of grafting can
be done from mid-May onwards, because the trees have budded and made new
growth, until the beginning of August when the trees are full of sap.
Almond trees which are naturally drier lose their sap earlier. Those who
want to graft onto them <sup>the almond trees</sup> mericotons, apricots
and nut-tree grafts, which are the best, should do so usually in
January. Nut trees, such as perches mericotons should be grafted en
fente. It is said that trees graft by the shield-graft method take
longer to bear fruit.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p105v_1</id>

<head>Gardening</head>

<ab>It's not very strange to cultivate in your garden some arnols,
because when your soup or broth goes cold, you get <al>worms</al>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p105v_2</id>

<head>fountain</head>

<ab>Recooked <m>plaster</m> runs when mixed with <m>water</m>, which you
will see in the next recipe about wet molds. When put on the joints of
the fountain conduits, <sup>it</sup> resists as much as any
<m>stucco</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p105v_3</id>

<head>Catching <al>nightingales</al>

<add>See the 15th folio <lb/>

after this.</add></head>

<ab>In order to catch them, you must observe them in real life, the food
that they favor and their mating season. The <al>nightingale</al>, as
long as he is singing, marks his own territory. Therefore approach him
by pretending to look for something on the ground. Take some
<al>worms</al> from old flour or from beneath what you are kneading or
from mills, which <al>nightingales</al> love, and put some on your hat,
fastened with a pin or in any other way, so that it can wiggle. And five
or six steps away from the hedge where it is singing, dig a hole, and
place some <al>worms</al> in it, as well as your device made out of
little criss-crossed sticks. As soon as you leave it will be anxious to
go and see what you have done. And seeing <al>worms</al> it will
enter.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>Some people sell <al>nightingales</al>
on trees.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>It is easier to catch
<al>nightingales</al> in the cool of the morning or evening, near
fountains or shaded areas.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p105v_4</id>

<head><al>Nightingale</al></head>

<ab>The <m>iron</m> wire used for its cage must be the thickest
possible, so that should it try to leave, it will not hurt itself. At
the beginning of its captivity cover its cage in fabric. The first day
you will have to forcibly feed it, moving it from its cage in your hand
and opening its beak and with a small wooden needle, place <sup>its
food</sup> in its throat and make it swallow. And continue to do so
until it is no longer willful. You must do this to keep it alive,
because should it become thin or lose weight it will die.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p105v_5</id>

<head><al>Nightingale</al></head>

<ab>It will need a cage made in the shape of a barn, like the ones for
<al>larks</al>, lined with green fabric, because it feels the cold. And
to get it to eat when it is first put in the cage, you must give it
<al>ants</al> mixed with <m>earth</m> in the bottom of the cage to get
it used to pecking, and you can give it minced <al>sheep</al>'s heart,
and sometimes eggs, and sometimes <al>mealworm</al>.</ab></div>
</root>
