<root>
<page>168r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f341.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p167r_1</id>

<figure>

<id>fig_p168r_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5RUdzVWVNM3l6QVU</link>

</figure>

<ab>rod that we put into the touch-hole, and then, with a rope wrapped
around the end of a baston, we ignite it and promptly retreat to take
cover. The small mortars of 16 or 17 lb. are attached promptly with a
short, hooked rod made like a wimble, and if it is of a good alloy, we
can ignite it by hand. It is done in this way for mortars of 27 lb., but
then we only put three lb. of powder. The door really needs to be strong
so as not to be blown off for seventeenth lb. mortars. Some people use
little bells worn by oxen or mules as an door for the mortars. Others
load two canons of guns and, with a gimlet and a string, tie them with
the opening against the door. If the mortars are good and do not
explode, they only recoil and cannot harm if one is next to them.</ab>

<ab>A is a small rod, hooked like the hinge of a door and made as a
biron on one end in order to quickly attach a small mortar with handles
of fifteen or xvii lb. for a common door or window.</ab>

<ab>B is a small mortar with handles.</ab>

<ab>C is a common mortar of 27 or 30 lb. pierced at the bottom, where a
large <m>iron</m> rod passes, button-like on one end made like a biron
on the tip so as to quickly hang the mortar against a door that will not
be covered with <m>iron</m> plates.</ab>

<ab>D These are slabs of <m>wax</m>, <m>cork</m> and <m>wood</m> for
loading the mortar and well packing the powder.</ab>

<ab>E <m>iron</m> fork made in the form of pincers as tall as a man,
used to quickly set the mortar without a rod. It must be of soft
<m>iron</m> so that the sides fold easily, if needed, and to accommodate
the height or width of the door.</ab>

<ab>F is another <m>iron</m> fork of the same height that supports the
fork made as pincers and also sustains the mortar, and with its low claw
prevents the pincers from recoiling.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
