<root>
<page>120r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f245.image</image>

<div>
<id>p120r_1</id>
<head>Medals stamped from the <m>wax</m></head>

<ab>You can mold in <m>wax</m>, mixed with a bit of <m>resin</m> so it
will be harder &amp; firmer, the relief of whatever you please, either
an animal or a medal, &amp; then, from it, make a hollow of latten or
copper. Or <del>hit it</del> mold it in relief and hammer it in a sheet
of tin, <del>Et pu</del> and then fill with lead &amp; heat it. Try
sheets of gemstone leaves molded in hollow for lizards &amp;.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p120r_a2</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> for casting in <m>gold</m></head>

<ab>Take <m>common sand</m> of <m>alum</m>, of <m>plaster</m> &amp;
<m>brick</m>, according to the composition as said above. Add to it some
more <m>alum de plume</m>. And mix in not the whole of a third part of
<m>crocum ferri</m>. However its quantity cannot be harmful, for it is
that which receives the gold, &amp; thanks to which it comes out very
neatly. But it is good that your <m>crocum</m> will have been previously
in the furnace of <pro>glassmakers</pro>, three <del>or four</del> days
and <del>three days</del> and three nights, in a flat box, where it will
be not very thick, so that it will reheat better.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
You could cast well <m>gold</m> in <m>common sand</m> of
<pro>goldsmiths</pro>, should you add some substance that makes it run.
Before the invention of <m>crocum</m>, one would cast flowers in
<m>silver</m>, but not at all in gold. It has not been forty years that
one knows this in Germany.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<m>Sublimate</m> is commonly employed by <pro>goldsmiths</pro> for
<m>gold</m>. Some add <m>sulphur</m>, but they &amp; others are wrong,
for <m>sulphur</m> sours, even as it heats. And the <m>sublimate</m> is
agitated, boils and bubbles. It is very good to clean <m>gold</m>
because by its exhalations, it draws everything out as it goes up in
smoke. But to warm <m>gold</m>, &amp; conserve its heat, there is only
the color, which is <m>verdet</m>, <m>sal ammoniac</m>,
<m>saltpeter</m>, &amp; <m>borax</m>. This makes it run &amp; you can
throw in a branch of wormseed.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p120r_a3</id>
<head><del>Il</del>Nightingale</head>

<ab>One needs for the cage, made like those for larks in barns &amp;
lined with green fabric, to be made with a drawer underneath, to refresh
its fresh earth everyday, for it takes much delight in this, &amp; mix
in it some ants. You can carry an ant-hill with its earth in a barrel
full of earth, &amp; keep them there &amp; they will lay their eggs
there, in order to always have some at hand when you want them, should
you take pleasure in feeding nightingales. When you caught it, it is fat
&amp; full, &amp;, thusly, to keep it in its strength, one needs to, for
the first day, <del>luy</del> take it in their hand &amp; open its beak
&amp; put in its beak with a sharp twig some mutton heart or other
delicate flesh, chopped up not too finely, in order to fill its stomach
&amp; keep it from diminishing &amp; growing leaner, until it has gotten
over its fancy. <del>The next day you will give him</del> And you will
feed it in this way three or four times a day, &amp; will also make it
drink. The next morning, you will give it in his cage some well-minced
flesh with the yolk of a hard-boiled egg, and change it two or three
times a day, for it will not eat it if it is hardened &amp; if it is not
fresh. And if it goes half a day without eating, one needs to feed it as
before &amp; do so until it</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
