<root>
<page>148v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f302.image</image>

<div>

<id>p148v_1</id>

<head>Molding <al>turtles</al></head>

<ab>Next, reassemble the parts of your mold and cramp carefully all the
joints, as much as above &amp; bellow as on the sides, having not
forgotten to notch the joints of the molds, as with others. Having
cramped it all, undo the cramps on the side &amp; not the others. And
thusly, your mold of several pieces <del>sem</del> will open as if it
were only in two halves. If you want to mold hollow, make in the middle
of the <del>of the part</del> belly mold a hole, from side to side,
which, inside, is of such capacity that the end of a little finger can
almost enter it, widening like a <fr>clervoise</fr> the outside of the
hole. This is to cast the <fr>noyau</fr>. But, note that all these
difficulties would be nothing if you wanted to mold hollow because you
could mold your turtle in two pieces <del><ill/></del> and burn it
inside, as with other animals, and it would be done quickly. But since
the turtle is massive &amp; that it is weighty, without being hollow,
one considers better molded in this way, hollow, and in <del>cha</del>
this way, to make well a mold, one really needs three days. Take heed,
for hollow &amp; fanciful molds, to have some strong plaster, which
endures the fire without bursting, if it is possible. But, if you cannot
have any such, mix a little more <fr>alum de plume</fr> &amp; add to it
also some crocum, which fortifies it &amp; makes the flaws, if there are
any, come out so finely that they are easily undone. Also do not forget
to tighten well, with a press, your molds, to avoid flaws which are made
either when the mold is not well joined or when it bursts. To repair, if
the features are not apparent enough, retrace them lightly with a burin,
then soften them with a small chisel. The flaws are removed with the
<fr>chaple</fr>, a type of burin. For the lumps &amp; scales, they are
made either with a little gouge or a little round cutter, or with the
point of a small chisel, not tempered &amp; struck on a small file.
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>Make this hole before <del>molding</del>
joining your molds.</ab></div>
</root>
