<root>
<page>022v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f50.image</image>

<figure>

<id>fig_p022v_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NkNrYkVZTlVnbDQ</link>

<!--Philip Cherian: Continues from p019r-->

</figure>

<div>

<id>p022v_1</id>

<head>Orgues</head>

<ab>Then they are affustés on a rather thick board close to each other
and notches are made onto the board this way
<figure><id>fig_p022v_2</id><link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5RnQ2Ri1PenA1aDA</link></figure>.

And through these notches is fit the harquebus’s hook which has a hole
through which we pass, from under, <m>iron</m> pegs. When you want to
aim, you affuste the middle and side ones. If you want to make double,
triple or four ranks or more, you have to put similar board rank one on
the other, like the first one. This manner of making an orgue fait faute
@ and makes it very stable. Because the other ones made of one massive
and solid piece have cannons of only one and a half pan long. They
therefore are used only for a salvo at an entrance or to protect a
gate.</ab>

<ab>

A small hooked harquebus a-crocke weighs 40 <ms>pounds</ms> and is 4
<fr><ms>pans</ms></fr> long, and is to be loaded to the touch hole, its
breech is three cannonballs thick, its front two.</ab>

<ab>

The double cannon is nothing different from the big ordinary cannon,
apart from the fact that its cannonball has one <ms>line</ms> of
thickness - or of diametre - more. A <ms>line</ms> is a <ms>twelfth
part</ms> of a cannonball. At the breech, it has a thickess of one
<ms>line</ms> more than the cannon, and the mouth is half a
<ms>line</ms> thicker. Its load is six or seven <ms>lbs</ms> of
<m>powder</m>, more than a cannon, that is to say of two big linstocks.
Its cannonball weighs 56 <ms>lb</ms>. Thirty <al>horses</al> are
necessary to carry it. It weakens the walls more than a cannon. But it
is very uneasy to drive. This is why it is unused today and is more
appropriate to be brought to a nearby place for close combat or for a
<x>ceremonial</x> entry, rather than for an ordinary execution. They are
called basilics, and they are unmovable pieces.</ab>

</div>
</root>
