<root>
<page>033v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f72.image</image>

<div>

<id>p033v_1</id>

<head>To make it seem to someone that he has a piece of silver on his
forehead</head>

<ab>Take a token or piece of <m>silver</m> and wet it and make it hold
against your forehead. Then say to the bystander that if you put it thus
on his forehead, he will not be able to make it fall without lifting his
hands to it, no matter how he shakes his head. And making it seem as if
you are placing it on his forehead, retain it in your hand &amp; amp; wet your
thumb with your <m>saliva</m> then press it quite strongly on his
forehead. And thinking he has the piece on his forehead due to the
coolness of the <m><bp>saliva</bp></m>, he will shake his ears &amp;  will
get nowhere.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p033v_2</id>

<head>For making blood or wine issue from someone's forehead or from a
wall</head>

<figure>

<id>fig_p033v_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5MXk2RzNQdF9aeDg</link>

</figure>

<ab>Take an “<oc>ambu</oc>” or funnel of <m>white iron</m> which is
double-walled in the body but not in the spout. Make a small hole at the
top edge &amp;  another slightly bigger on the inner wall that will be a
little above the spout, just as you can see in the adjacent example.
Then when you want to use it, put in <m>wine</m> or <m>liquid rosette of
Brazilwood</m> or <m>black cherry juice</m>, and blocking the hole of
the spout with your little finger, make sure that the funnel is well
filled so that the <m>wine</m> can enter between the double walls
through the hole at the side, &amp;  if it does not enter well, making it
seem as if you are tasting the <m>wine</m>, suck &amp;  draw in a little air,
drinking where the little hole is. After, make one of the close
bystanders drink the rest of the <m>wine</m> or cast it aside or let it
flow through the tip, but before, you must have pressed your thumb well
over the hole on the top edge, because in this way, by the compression
of air, the wine will be retained between the double walls. Then with a
bodkin rounded at the tip &amp;  that goes into its handle, you make it seem
as if you pierce the forehead of someone who holds a glass in his hand,
and while you pierce, you cover what you are doing with the funnel that
you hold close to</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<figure>#</figure>

his forehead. Then removing your thumb from over the hole on the top
edge, the air, being free, will make the <m>wine</m> issue from between
the double walls through the hole marked B, &amp;  fall through the tip
marked C into the glass. But you must make the fellow bend his head
enough in order to do it well.</ab>

</div>
</root>
