<root>
<page>129v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f264.item.r=</image>

<div>

<id>p129v_1</id>

<head>Animals dried in the oven for a long time</head>

<ab>

Plant them on a slab of <m>earth</m>, arranging them with points of iron
wire, as if you wanted to mold them, and <del>they</del> dry them in an
oven, after the bread is taken out. And they always remain thus, as much
for snakes, as birds, and other things. But, it is necessary that be
quickly dried.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

Note that one needs to give them their shape &amp; put them in the sand,
as with flowers, &amp; promptly dry them in the oven, which is hot
enough, as when one pulls out the bread. And it should stay there a day
&amp; a night, in order that it is <del>chau</del> dry, for otherwise it
would stink. However, take heed that the oven not be too harsh, but
rather like the heat of the sun in june, otherwise the animals cook.
Once dry, do not wet them, but clean them with a <fr>pinceau</fr> or
clean them with a brush.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129v_2</id>

<head>Animals cast in <m>copper</m></head>

<ab>Try, <del>d</del> having cast them in copper, to burnish them with
gemstone leaves, to see if they take the same color.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129v_2</id>

<head>Advice about casting</head>

<ab><del>Ne</del> Be careful to not make your gate very wide, and do not
forget to make in its conduit two or three holes and notches, &amp; as
your gate approaches the <del>ch</del> molded thing, divide it into
three or four parts like fingers, which are pointed, &amp; are not very
deep. For the metal runs more gently, without being hindered by vapors
&amp; smoke.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>right-middle</margin>

Always make the entry of your gate near the medal, notched &amp; lumpy,
to draw out the medal's fury.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129v_4</id>

<head>Spider molded on a leaf</head>

<ab>

The very big ones usually have hairy feet, which are difficult to mold
if you do not keep them flat <del>with some</del>, or burn them with a
candle, or stiffen them &amp; lay them flat, <m>smearing</m> them with
<m>wheat oil</m>. Kill them in <m>vinegar</m> &amp; <m>urine</m>, like
<al>snakes</al> <del>&amp;</del>, or in <m>eau-de-vie</m>, and then
shape them on a well-made vine leaf, or other thing. Next, you can give
them back their capricious hair with <del>bourr</del> the sieved fine
hair of cloth waste, by smearing them with <del>dun</del> fish glue, or
similar things. Their true color is of <m>vinegar</m> &amp; greenish,
&amp; then fumigate them in various places with sulphur. Having made
your <del>tourt</del> clay slab, place on it your vine leaf, and the
dead spider in the middle, &amp; pierce with a point of iron or latten
wire the middle of the spider’s body &amp; the leaf together. Next,
place diagonally somal points of latten wire around the vine leaf to
secure it well. Then fix, with a little melted was and the point of a
hot iron wire, the end of the legs, adapting them with the end of small
pincers. Do the same thing with the end of the spider’s small brows.
Return<figure>🜊</figure></ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<figure>

<id>fig_p129v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Sk9tdno1ODBqdms</link>

</figure>

To make the gate for the <al>spider</al> on the leaf, and to prevent the
sand from covering the spider from underneath the belly, furnish the end
of the tail &amp; the bottom of the body with a little melted wax, &amp;
applied with the hot iron wire, as you know. In this way, the leaf
burning &amp; the wax having melted, there will remain two little holes
in the meaf which will be the gate of the the spider.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<figure>🜊</figure>

The wax once cooled, scrape the excess with the point of a pen-knife, in
order that the end of the legs stay neat. Next, place the circle of
earth around &amp; cast your wet sand, like for other things. In this
way, one will need to burn the vine leaf in the mold, otherwise not. And
to cast more easily, let the animal die fully, in order that, when
struggling in does not mix up its legs. Having made your first cast,
uncover the reverse of the leaf, and make the second cast.</ab>

</div>
</root>
