<root>
<page>096r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f197.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>094r_1</id>

<ab>

round <tl>plane</tl>, also mounted with two handles, then with a small
narrow <tl>plane</tl>, one hollows &amp; scours it half a foot towards
the end of the heel. And shorter is better when it comes to scouring,
<sup>otherwise</sup> the sword would always cut the scabbard.</ab>

<ab>

The opening of the scabbard is called the mouth &amp; on top is the
shape of the knife.</ab>

<ab>

The stitch which is a <m>leather</m> rim set on the edge of the knife
shape is made to stop the sword frogs.</ab>

<ab>

When the <fr>estelles</fr> are well levelled, one lays the sword on top
&amp; with a <tl>black stone</tl> one marks the width of the blade,
&amp; the length, &amp; then with a <tl>chisel</tl> one cuts the excess.
And one passes a <tl>joiner’s plane</tl> to even it well along the
mark.</ab>

<ab>

Next, one glues the two <fr>estelles</fr> edge to edge <add>and all
around</add> only as far as the shape of the knife extends &amp; not
elsewhere. And this is to make the <m>velvet leather</m> of the scabbard
hold.</ab>

<ab>

Then one puts the sword into the <fr>estelles</fr>. And precisely thus
they set it in the scabbard which is sewn, and rub what is glued along
the knife shape with <m>tallow</m> to make it run into the
scabbard.</ab>

<ab>

The scabbard is made of <al>calf</al> or <al>sheep</al> <m>leather</m>,
the <al>calf</al> ones are in all one piece, but not the <al>sheep</al>
ones. But, when the swords are long, one makes them in pieces which are
sewn between <m>leather</m> &amp; <m>flesh</m>, &amp; then they rub the
stitching thoroughly with a piece of <m>boxwood</m> to cover &amp; even
it. From a good <al>calf</al> <m>skin</m>, viii or 9 or x scabbards can
be taken, from a <al>sheep</al> <m>skin</m>, v or vi. A
<pro>workman</pro> can easily make vi a day. If they are too thick, one
thins them a little with a plane. If the <m>skin</m> is hard, one wets
it in lightly lukewarm <m>water</m>, and one does not leave it there for
long. Next, the same worker who made the <m>wood</m> piece has to adjust
the scabbard to be well made. It is true that for common people, one may
well get ones which are ready made, but they are never as good to wear.
When the scabbard is made &amp; sewed with black <m>thread</m>, one rubs
it with a piece of <m>boxwood</m> or with a linen cloth, having daubed
it a little in <m>oil</m>. The scabbard of a good <al>cow</al> is better
than any and also costs more, except the <m>velvet</m> kind. Under the
<m>velvet</m> one commonly puts plain <m>canvas</m> or a <al>sheep</al>
scabbard or a <m>parchment</m> cover. But the best scabbard of all is a
waxed scabbard, of either <m>velvet</m> or <al>calf</al>. It is because
one covers the wood with thin canvas, which one waxes, then covers in
<m>velvet</m> or <al>calf</al> . A <m>waxed</m> scabbard is worth at
least xxx <cn><fr>sols</fr></cn>, a <al>cow</al> one xx
<cn><fr>sols</fr></cn>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

From a <al>sheep</al> <m>skin</m>, v or vi.</ab>

</div>
</root>
