<root>
<page>050v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f106.image</image>

<div>

<id>p050v_1</id>

<head><al>Little Birds</al></head>

<ab><al>Buntings</al> sing during the night if they are left in the cool
open air, but they are better suited to fattening for fine tables than
for singing. <al>Chaffinches</al> are prone to blindness, and their eyes
swell at the beginning of August. <al>Goldfinches</al> love <m>lettuce
seeds</m>, and you can catch them in gardens on seedy lettuce using two
<m>lime-twigs</m>. But because such a daily fayre would be too expensive
for them, they are usually fed with <m>hemp-seed</m>. The
<al>owsell</al> is purged with a <al>spider</al>, which you must give it
once a week, so that it doesn't become too strong. The <al>lark</al> is
purged with <m>dry mortar</m>, composed of <m>lime</m> and sand, to keep
it from becoming too strong and fat. Small young birds are purged with
the same <m>dry mortar</m>, by placing small lumps of it in their cages.
The <al>cuckoo</al> lays its eggs in the nest of the <al>bunting</al>,
otherwise know as <al>verdaule</al>. This bird is very simple-minded, I
have previously let two go, which after a few days returned to their
cage. To feed young <al>goldfinches</al>, it is necessary to crush
<m>almonds</m> with very fine <m>breadcrumbs</m>, and <m>lettuce
seeds</m> or <m>hemp seeds</m>. For <al>linnets</al>, some
<m>rapeseed</m>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p050v_2</id>

<head>Hot-worked <m>steel</m> and files</head>

<ab>The <m>steel</m> that <pro>blacksmiths</pro> and other
<pro><m>iron</m> workers</pro> commonly use is not refined like that
from <pl>Germany</pl> or <pl>Biscay</pl>, which is hardened in a
<m>molten iron</m> bath, but among the <m>iron</m> in bars which is
transported by flatboat from the forges of <pl>Foix</pl> and elsewhere,
some is harder, whiter and more refined than the rest, as it comes from
the mine. And the <pro>workers</pro> choose it and use it like the other
<m>steel</m>. And because it consists of <m>common iron</m>, they call
it strong <m>iron</m>. But it is not of such good quality as purified
<m>steel</m> like that from <pl>Germany</pl> and <pl>Biscaye</pl>, which
is sold in small beads. Some hot-work their <m>steel</m>, giving it a
heating and then dipping it into a large quantity of <m>water</m>, then
forging it. And fine <m>steel</m>, which is brittle, does break and
crumble, whereas <m>iron</m> can be pulled out. Thus they separate the
finest <m>steel</m>, which with another heating they make into a mass.
The <pl>Germans</pl> make their files from strong <m>iron</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin><m>Steel</m> is applied to tools not on
both sides, but underneath the part where one sharpens and whets them,
and this part must be made of very soft <m>iron</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin><pl>Levantines</pl> refine our own
<m>steel</m> because their country provides them with none, and they
reheat it in a pot with <m>bitumen</m> etc.</ab></div>
</root>
