<root>
<page>170v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f346.item</image>

<div>

<id>p170v_1</id>

<ab>In the year fifteen hundred seventy-eight, the second of July, the
heirs of the late Sr. Ouvryer received (two hundred and five ecus), the
rent of Saint-Frajou, amounting to twelve hundred and thirty
livres.</ab>

<ab>They have also received, as part of the revenue of the year fifteen
hundred seventy nine, three hundred forty three and one third ecus.</ab>

<ab>And for the first year, they remain <x>to be paid</x> eighty livres
and fifteen sous, | and for the second settlement, they have not yet
received anything.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p170v_2</id>
<head>Against plague</head>

<ab>Against pestilential fever or poison or plague, take an ecu's weight
of your <m>opiate</m> soaked in <m>scabious</m> or <m>bugloss
extract,</m> or heavily diluted <m>wine</m>, if you are already ill.
After taking it, you must make yourself sweat.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p170v_3</id>
<head>To preserve oneself</head>

<ab><m>Acetum</m> paratum ex <m>ruta</m> <m>baccis juniperi</m> simul
tusis Eo <m>aceto</m> extinguantur <m>lateres</m> igniti. Et vapor
excipiatur ore &amp; naribus. <m>Rue</m> <m>vinegar</m> together with
crushed <m>juniper berries</m>. Pour the <m>vinegar</m> over red hot
<m>bricks</m> and inhale the vapor through the mouth and nostrils. This
is to preserve oneself when going into noxious air: a garment can be
perfumed with this vapor in order to remove infection from a room,
house, etc. And if you find yourself in a place where you do not have
this preparation, carry <m>rue</m> and <m>berries</m> crushed together,
then, if need be, boil them in <m>vinegar</m> and use as described.</ab>

<ab>Ottonis episcopi | Frisigensis | Ab orbe condito</ab>

<ab>Abbatis | Urspergensis | Chronicon</ab>

<ab>Hieronymus | Mercurialis, | Variarum</ab>

<ab>Rerum Scoticarum Historia, Georgio Bucanano authore</ab>

<ab>Rembertus Dodonæus, Mechliniensis medicus, | De stirpium
historia</ab>

<ab>De L'Orme, De l'invention de bien bastir, and other works</ab>

<ab> Telesius, De coloribus, Vascosan</ab>

<ab>Marbodius, De lapillis prætiosis</ab>

</div>
</root>
