<root>
<page>016r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f37.image</image>

<div>
<id>p016r_a1</id>
<head><fr>Fonte</fr> of <m>soft iron</m></head>

<ab>Most people consider that <m>iron</m>, once melted, cannot be melted
again because they only heat it in small <tl>forge</tl>s, in which it
only becomes red-hot. <pro>Alchemists</pro> undertake to melt it with
<m>realgar</m> or <m>lead</m> or mixed <m>orpiment</m>. But without all
that, some have found a way to <del>the</del> melt not only brittle
<m>iron</m>, such as <del><fr>d</fr></del> the kind used for <m>iron</m>
pots, but also soft <m>iron</m> such as that of pigs &amp; ingots, which
is the most difficult kind. And to this effect they make a
<tl>furnace</tl> in this manner which has a width of one
<ms><fr>pan</fr></ms> &amp; a half &amp; <del>one <ms><fr>pan</fr></ms>
&amp; a half of</del> a depth of two <ms><fr>pan</fr></ms>s. And the
<fr>tuelle</fr>, which is the barrel <del>through</del> marked A through
which the <tl>bellows' pipes</tl> enter, has to be placed in the middle
of the depth of the furnace such that there is one <ms><fr>pan</fr></ms>
of the mouth of the <tl>furnace</tl> above the <fr>tuelle</fr> &amp; one
<ms><fr>pan</fr></ms> underneath.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Each <ms><fr>pan</fr></ms> of the mouth of the square <tl>furnace</tl>
contains one &amp; a half <ms>quintal</ms>, &amp; the
<ms><fr>pan</fr></ms> of the round <tl>furnace</tl> holds two
<ms>quintals</ms>.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p016r_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5aUw0eThJNEVTelk</link>

<!--José Beltrán Coello: Drawn before the writing of at least the second
half of the first paragraph-->

</figure>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
The <pro>miners</pro>, to make the <m>iron</m> run, put at the mouth of
the <tl>forge</tl>, two or three handfuls of <m><pa>wallwort</pa></m>
whenthey want to make the <fr>fonte</fr> run, and this renders the
<m>iron</m> wonderfully ductile and flowy.</ab>

<ab>It is also necessary that the <fr>tuelle</fr> enters through to the
middle of the mouth of the<tl>furnace</tl>, which is a principal part of
the secret because the wind will hit the edge &amp; the wall which makes
up the belly of the <tl>furnace</tl> &amp; by such means, it spreads
equally everywhere &amp; above, like the flame in a reverberatory
furnace, &amp; by such means heats much more; for if the wind were to
hit directly from above, the substance which is melted or ready to be
melted, it would cool it down &amp; prevent it from running &amp;
melting. It is also necessary for the <tl>bellows</tl> to be driven by
the falling &amp; running of <m>water</m> as in <tl>forges</tl>, because
in this manner, the <tl>bellows</tl> run with measure &amp; compass
&amp; with great speed, which the strength of <pro>workers</pro> could
<del>d</del> not do. Therefore one raises the wall as you see &amp; the
furnace on the surface of the ground at the edge of which you make a
channel as with other <fr>fontes</fr>, to put the molds of that which
you want to cast &amp; to do this, you unstop the opening that you had
made at the bottom of the <tl>furnace</tl> to make the melted substance
run. You will be able to melt two <ms>quintals</ms> of <m>iron</m> each
time and to do this, you will choose the biggest <m>charcoal</m> you can
find &amp; put a load of it at the bottom, on the plane and surface of
the furnace &amp; with the bottom piling up <del>as if</del> to a point,
up to the top of the wall

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Some make a mould of the calibre of the piece, &amp; temper it, then
beat a soft <m>iron</m> piece cut to size, &amp; when this piece is very
red, they beat it into the mold &amp; round it off with a large
<tl>file</tl>, considering these balls to be stronger than the melted
ones which, being britlle, are more subject to breaking.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
