<root>
<page>129v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f264.item.r=</image>

<div>

<id>p129v_1</id>

<head>Animals dried in the oven for a long time</head>

<ab>

Plant them on a slab of <m>earth</m>, arranging them with points of iron
wire, as if you wanted to mold them, and <del>they</del> dry them in an
oven, after the bread is taken out. And they always remain thus, as much
for snakes, as birds, and other things. But, it is necessary that be
quickly dried.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

Note that one needs to give them their shape &amp; put them in the sand,
as with flowers, &amp; promptly dry them in the oven, which is hot
enough, as when one pulls out the bread. And it should stay there a day
&amp; a night, in order that it is <del>chau</del> dry, for otherwise it
would stink. However, take heed that the oven not be too harsh, but
rather like the heat of the sun in june, otherwise the animals cook.
Once dry, do not wet them, but clean them with a <fr>pinceau</fr> or
clean them with a brush.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129v_2</id>

<head>Animals cast in <m>copper</m></head>

<ab>Try, <del>d</del> having cast them in copper, to burnish them with
gemstone leaves, to see if they take the same color.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129v_2</id>

<head>Advice about casting</head>

<ab><del>Ne</del> Be careful to not make your gate very wide, and do not
forget to make in its conduit two or three holes and notches, &amp; as
your gate approaches the <del>ch</del> molded thing, divide it into
three or four parts like fingers, which are pointed, &amp; are not very
deep. For the metal runs more gently, without being hindered by vapors
&amp; smoke.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>right-middle</margin>

Always make the entry of your gate near the medal, notched &amp; lumpy,
to draw out the medal's fury.</ab>
</div>
<div>

<id>p129v_4</id>

<head>Spider molded on a leaf</head>

<ab>

The very big ones usually have hairy feet, which are difficult to mold
if you do not keep them flat <del>with some</del>, or burn them with a
candle, or stiffen them &amp; lay them flat, <m>smearing</m> them with
<m>wheat oil</m>. Kill them in <m>vinegar</m> &amp; <m>urine</m>, like
<al>snakes</al> <del>&amp;</del>, or in <m>eau-de-vie</m>, and then
shape them on a well-made vine leaf, or other thing. Next, you can give
them back their capricious hair with <del>bourr</del> the sieved fine
hair of cloth waste, by smearing them with <del>dun</del> fish glue, or
similar things. Their true color is of <m>vinegar</m> &amp; greenish,
&amp; then fumigate them in various places with sulphur. Having made
your <del>tourt</del> clay slab, place on it your vine leaf, and the
dead spider in the middle, &amp; pierce with a point of iron or latten
wire the middle of the spider’s body &amp; the leaf together. Next,
place diagonally somal points of latten wire around the vine leaf to
secure it well. Then, Then block the end of the legs with a bit of
melted wax using a warm <m>iron</m> wire, and smooth it out with the tip
of a pair of small pincers. do the same with the other edges of the
<al>spider</al>. Return<figure>🜊</figure></ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<figure>

<id>fig_p129v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Sk9tdno1ODBqdms</link>

</figure>

To cast a <al>spider</al> on a leaf, and to prevent the sand from
covering the under belly, fix a bit of melted <m>wax</m> at the end of
its tail, and bottom part of the body, with the help of a warm wire as
you know. Once the leaf has burnt and the <m>wax</m> has melted, two
small holes remain on the leaf, that will be the cast of the
<al>spider</al>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<figure>🜊</figure>

<figure>🜊</figure>

When the wax is cool, scrape away the superfluous parts with the point
of a penknife, that way the end of the legs will stay neat. Then arrange
the disc of earth around the spider, and cast your soaked sand, as you
did for others. In this fashion you will have to burn the vine leaf in
the mold. Otherwise, you will not have to. To cast your <al>spider</al>
more easily, make sure the animal is dead, avoiding the entanglement of
its legs while agonizing. When you have done your first cast, peel this
side of the leaf, then do the second cast. </ab>

</div>
</root>
