<root>
<page>117v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f240.image</image>

<div>
<id>p117v_a1</id>
<head>To make the ashes of <pa>flowers</pa> and <pa>herbs</pa> leave
<tl>molds</tl></head>

<ab>Some people put <m>quicksilver</m> inside. But, if it is a little
work, or fine &amp; delicate foliage, that only has a slender issue,
they make two errors: the first, that <m>quicksilver</m> by its
heaviness can destroy some delicate tract inside in coming out, the
other, that some bit will always linger inside that will make
<x>other</x> <m>metals</m> sour &amp; inhibit the perfection of the
casting. It is true that if it is to empty the <tl>mold</tl> of some
large animal that has big conduits &amp; passages through which the
<m>quicksilver</m> can easily exit, like of a bird or a serpent, one can
indeed put some amount of <m>quicksilver</m> to break the calcinated
bones of the animal in escaping, because of which the said <m>☿</m> will
empty out &amp; not remain at all.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
The <pa>asparagus</pa> stalk is so hard that most often it perseveres as
charcoal. Because of this, do it rather dried out or wet it with
<m>sulfur oil</m> &amp; <m>turpentine</m>, or indeed cast the little
branches separately &amp; solder them onto a fat stalk drawn through
with a wire.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
If the burnt thing has left behind some filth or ash, let it cool down a
little, &amp; with an <m>iron</m> <m>wire</m> wrapped in <m>cotton</m>
that can bend with the cavities that you have, investigate. Clean &amp;
blow to a fault, either with a soft <tl>brush</tl> or a clipped
<tl>brush</tl>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p117v_a2</id>
<head><pa>Daisies</pa></head>

<ab>They can be cast well in <m>gold</m>. But if you want to
<m>enamel</m> them, you have to make them by hand &amp; <m>enamel</m>
them &amp; then attach them. Otherwise, the <pa>leaves</pa> would be so
pressured that it would encrust the <m>enamel</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p117v_a3</id>
<head><m>Sand</m> that has already been used</head>

<ab>Do not cast it. But because it is mixed with <m>stone allum</m>, you
can use it in the mixture of other things &amp; it can serve in place of
<m>brick</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p117v_a4</id>
<head>Core <tl>molding</tl> <m>wax</m> figures or <m>lead</m>
medals</head>

<ab>Rub them with <m>oil</m> with a <tl>brush</tl>. But be sure that it
be so softly that your medal be barely wiped with it &amp; that it
hardly appear to have been greased. After rub it with <m>spirits</m> and
heat the <m>water</m> with which you will wet your <m>sand</m>, that of
<m>plaster</m>, <m>brick</m> &amp; <m>alum</m>, so that being sort of
lukewarm when you cast it, the <m>oil</m> will not refuse it, as it does
with cold water, &amp; do not forget to moisten your <m>sand</m> with
it, mixing it always with a little <m>sal ammoniac</m>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Medals <tl>molded</tl> in this way are very fine.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p117v_a5</id>
<head><m>Snakes' blood</m></head>

<ab>If you have to cut some snake inside a <tl>mold</tl> in order to
burn it, cut it far from the intake of the <tl>mold</tl> so that no
<m>blood</m> at all remains, because it makes a crust that afterwards
would not be taken away by the same <m>quicksilver</m> &amp; removes
impressions from your <tl>mold</tl>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
