<root>
<page>023v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f52.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p023r_1</id>

<figure>

<id>fig_p023v_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Tm4ySC1wcUx6Yzg</link>

</figure>

<ab><m>powder</m>. When the sausage is filled, dip it gently in two
<ms>parts</ms> <m>vinegar</m> and one of <m>spirits</m>, to moisten the
<m>canvas</m> but not the <m>powder</m>. Next, leave the aforesaid
<m>canvas</m> to dry completely, and then you need to attach to the
sausage a long <m>string</m> or <m>cord</m> <ms>twice as long as the
sausage</ms>, but you must not tie it to the sausage but make it touch
the two ends and sew it to the sausage in a few places in the middle.
Next you need to smear all of the sausage with very good
<m>turpentine</m>, and at one end, where you will want to join to the
<m>mortar</m>'s fuse for firing, you can sew or tightly attach with a
selvage of <m>canvas</m> as large as one <fr><ms>empan</ms></fr> which
should also be well soaked in <m>turpentine</m>, and this selvage should
be cut in the middle so that it can be fastened and wrapped around the
<m>mortar</m>, and you must attach it so that the tip of the sausage
that is open will be joined to the fuse of the <m>mortar</m>. Then you
need to place a lot of tightly-packed <m>powder</m> onto the fuse of the
<m>mortar</m>. And next, the person outside of the ditch should draw the
small <m>string</m> and <m>cord</m> that is joined to the sausage so
that it is extended mid-way, but not so much that it is detached. And if
there is <m>water</m> in the ditch, it will be necessary to support the
sausage with a fork. Then, having placed himself and others in safety,
the person who holds the tip of the sausage will be able to fire.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p023v_1</id>

<ab><m>Mortars</m> that one wants to fix on doors or <m>iron</m> gates
are sufficient if they weigh 40 or 50 <ms>lb</ms>. For the rest, for its
charge, cannonball, and process, you need to do all just as was already
said before concerning the one of 3 <fr><ms>quintals</ms></fr>. One man
can carry it.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p023v_2</id>

<ab>The cannonball needs to be be round on one side and flat on the
other like a <ms>half</ms> of a cut cannonball. The cross also needs to
stick to the ball - the latter melting if it is made with <m>metal</m> -
and is enveloped in the middle of the cross.</ab>

</div>
</root>
