<root>
<page>129r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f263.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p129r_1</id>

<head>Painting metal herbs</head>

<ab>If you are in a hurry it would be better to mix your color with a
not-too-thick <m>gum</m> because oil takes a long time to dry, and it
runs if it is transparently layered, as the herbs require. And if you
still want it done quickly, mix your color with <m>glair</m> beaten with
<m><pa>fig tree</pa> rind</m>, and your work will soon be dry. But layer
it transparently.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129r_2</id>

<head>Wormwood</head>

<ab> The pallid white of this herb is made from <m>green verditer</m>,
<m>white lead</m> or <m>ceruse</m>, a bit of <m>massicot</m>,
<m>scudegrun</m>, and <m>cendré d'azur</m>. Mix and arrange your color
with a branch you have. </ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129r_3</id>

<head><al>Viper color</al></head>

<ab>

It is the most beautiful <al>snake</al> to mold, because it has very
beautiful scales, round and transparent. Its natural color is made from
good <m>verdigris</m> well ground, with good <m>vinegar</m>, if it is
made of <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m>. And in the darkest parts, season this
first color with a little <m>sulfur</m>, as you know. And if you need to
lighten and whiten, like under the throat, rub these parts with a rough
cloth. Because of its nature, the male ejects a kind of small lump from
its backside when pressed, like a half arquebus ball, made in its
genitals, and full of highly poisonous prickles.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<figure>+</figure> Add a bit of <m>looking-glass tin</m> in your
<m>tin</m>; your <al>lizard</al> will look as if made of
<m>silver</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129r_4</id>

<head>Molded roses</head>

<ab>

Roses are molded with difficulty because of their petals, which are very
delicate, weak, and doubled. To avoid this, rub them with <m>wheat
oil</m> which is very dessicative, and once dried it stiffens and firms
up the leaves to separate them and for them to withstand soaked sand. Do
the same thing with <al>flies</al>, pansies, and other delicate things
like capers.</ab>

</div>
</root>
