<root>
<page>039r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f83.image</image>

<div>

<id>p039r_1</id>

<head><pro>Goldsmith</pro></head>

<ab>They assemble <m>silver filings</m> with <m>saltpeter</m> which
refines it &amp; does not make it brittle. But <m>gold filings</m> are
assembled with <m>borax</m> or, to spare the <m>borax</m>, with
<m>lead</m>, which refines the <m>gold</m> &amp; softens it, for the
<m>saltpeter</m> would make it brittle, which <m>silver</m> does not do.
This is why, to save money, <pro>goldsmiths</pro> use it to assemble, in
order to spare <m>borax</m>, which costs viii <cn><fr>sols</fr></cn> per
<ms>ounce</ms>, &amp; <m>saltpeter</m> x <cn><fr>sols</fr></cn> per
<ms>lb</ms>.</ab>

<ab>When <pro>goldsmiths</pro> have thus assembled their <m>silver
filings</m> with <m>saltpeter</m>, a <m>red enamel</m> vitrifies at the
bottom of the <tl>crucible</tl>. I do not know if the <m>copper</m>
mixed in with the <m>silver</m> is the cause. <rub>Try for
<m>enamel</m></rub>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p039r_2</id>

<head><m><pa>Dyers’ woad</pa></m></head>

<ab>It is grown in <pl>Lauragais</pl> where the deep soil is so fertile
that every year wheat was grown there, it would lie flat for being too
vigorous. This is why <m>dyers’ woad</m> and wheat are grown there
alternately. For cultivating <m>dyers’ woad</m>, the soil is ploughed
with <tl><m>iron</m> shovels</tl>, as <pro>gardeners</pro> do. Next, it
is harrowed with <tl>rakes</tl>, &amp; broken up finely as for sowing
some <pa>kitchen herbs</pa>. It is commonly sown on <tmp>Saint Anthony's
day in January</tmp>. Eight harvests are made. The first ones are
better. The best <m>dyers’ woad</m> of <pl>Lauragais</pl> is the one
from <pl>Carmail</pl> &amp; the one from <pl>Auragne</pl>. And sometimes
the <m>dyers’ woad</m> is good in one field &amp; in the one close by it
will hardly have worth. The goodness of the <m>dyers’ woad</m> can be
recognized when put in the mouth it gives the taste of <m>vinegar</m>,
or when crumbling &amp; breaking it, it has some mold-like veins which
are as it were golden or silver. It is assayed in the
<tl><pro>dyers</pro>' vat</tl>, and to fill a <tl>vat</tl> with it, six
<ms>bales</ms> of it are needed. There several flocks of <m>wool</m> are
dyed, and if it dyes fifteen times, it is said to be worth 15
<cn>florins</cn>, if it gives xx dyings, xx <cn>florins</cn>. The good
kind dyes up to 30 times &amp; commonly up to xxv or 26.</ab>

</div>
</root>
