<root>
<page>170v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f346.item</image>

<div>

<id>p170v_1</id>

<ab>In the year fifteen hundred seventy-eight, the second of July, the
heirs of the late Sr. Ouvryer received (two hundred and five ecus), the
rent of Saint-Frajou, amounting to twelve hundred and thirty
livres.</ab>

<ab>They have also received, as part of the revenue of the year fifteen
hundred seventy nine, three hundred forty three and one third ecus.</ab>

<ab>And for the first year, they remain <x>to be paid</x> eighty livres
and fifteen sous, | and for the second settlement, they have not yet
received anything.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p170v_2</id>
<head>Against plague</head>

<ab>Take, against pestilential fever or poison or plague, an ecu's
weight of your <m>opiate</m> soaked in <m>scabious</m> or <m>bugloss
water</m>, or thoroughly tempered <m>wine</m>, if one is afflicted.
After taking it, one needs to make oneself sweat.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p170v_3</id>
<head>For preserving</head>

<ab><m>Vinegar</m> made from <m>rue</m> <m>juniper berries</m> crushed
together. With this <m>vinegar</m> burning <m>bricks</m> shall be
extinguished. And the vapor shall be received through the mouth &amp;
nostrils. This is to preserve oneself when one goes into corrupt air: a
garment can be thus perfumed &amp; remove infection from it, from a
room, house, &amp;c. If you find yourself in a place where you do not
have this preparation, carry <m>rue</m> and <m>berries</m> pestled
together, then, according to your need, boil them in <m>vinegar</m> and
use as above.</ab>

<ab><rub><la>Rerum Scoticarum Historia, Georgio Bucanano
authore</la></rub></ab>

<ab><rub><la>Rembertus Dodonæus, Mechliniensis medicus, | De stirpium
historia</la></rub></ab>

<ab><rub>De L'Orme, De l'invention de bien bastir, and other
works</rub></ab>

<ab><rub><la>Telesius, De coloribus, Vascosan</la></rub></ab>

<ab><rub><la>Marbodius, <del>go</del> De lapillis
prætiosis</la></rub></ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><la>Ottonis episcopi | Frisigensis | Ab
orbe condito</la></ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><la>Abbatis | Urspergensis |
Chronicon</la></ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><la>Hieronymus | Mercurialis, |
Variarum</la></ab>

</div>
</root>
