<root>
<page>014r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f33.image</image>

<div>

<id>p014r_1</id>

<head>For walls of <m>earth</m> and rustic construction</head>

<ab><al>Swallows</al> have taught us this craft, making their nests out
of <m>mud</m> mixed with <m>wisps</m> &amp; stalks of <m>hay</m> or
<m>straw</m> to make it bond. Therefore, in places where <m>stone</m>
&amp; <m>brick</m> are lacking, one can use <m>earth</m> to make
partitions &amp; walls. And for this, light <m>earth</m>, which does not
form clumps when plowed, but which is somewhat intermixed with
<m>arene</m>, holds first rank, because it can be beaten &amp; tamped
down better. It is true that it needs to be moistened &amp; cut into
clods with a <tl>ditch-spade</tl>, and thus place &amp; arrange it. This
one lasts longer and does not require as much effort, and dryness does
not make it split &amp; crack. But, because such kinds of earth are not
found everywhere, those who are on good &amp; fertile land, after
marking out with a measuring line the width &amp; length of their
foundations, drive <del>into the ground</del> in along the foundation
edges, on this side &amp; that, long <tl>poles</tl> <del>&amp;</del> or
<tl>chevron beams</tl> to support boards between which they throw the
<m>earth</m>, making each layer one foot thick or thereabouts,
intermixing it with <figure>S.S.S</figure>-like branches of
<m><pa>heather</pa></m> or similar things, then with beaters of three
different forms they tamp it &amp; beat it. One is called the mallet,
which has a triangular form like A, and with this, one first tamps the
<m>earth</m>. Next one uses the one made of <tl>blocks of wood</tl>
pointed at the tip &amp; helved to a thick <tl>stick</tl>, &amp; this
one is for pressing the <m>earth</m> well at the extremities and edges
of the wall, which adhere to the boards, &amp; is called <gap/>. The
other one is called the bat, which is for flattening &amp; beating the
<m>earth</m> for the last time, as shown in C. Then one makes another
layer of <m>earth</m> &amp; <m><pa>heather</pa></m> and beats it as was
said, &amp; continues thus until the wall is complete, which one covers
with <m><pa>heather</pa></m> &amp; then with <m>earth</m>. Some intermix
the said wall with rows of <m>bricks</m>. They also make the wall
tapering, giving width to the foundations according to how high one
wants to raise the wall. Which, when old, whitens, &amp; thereby shows
that it has <m>saltpeter</m> in it. That is why, when they fall down,
<pro>gunpowder makers</pro> profit from them.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p014r_1</id>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5b2lVN19SU1Z6UkU</link>

<!--A-->

<!--Nicolas Misery:text refers also to a "C" part of the figure, which
is absent in the actual figure.-->

</figure>

</div>
</root>
