<root>
<page>110v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f226.image</image>

<div>

<id>p110r_3</id>

<ab>When <sup><al>a snake</al></sup> has eaten something; when
tormenting it, it will vomit <sup>the food</sup>. And if, after having
eaten something, <sup>the snake</sup> is pressed underfoot, this
troubles <sup>the snake</sup> a lot &amp; makes it sick. If <sup>the
snake</sup> is wounded, it will not eat voluntarily.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p110v_1</id>
<head><tl>Molds</tl></head>

<ab>There is nothing better for opening them up than to oil them with
<m>olive oil</m>, &amp; nothing else. And afterwards, when you want to
separate them, soak them in cold <m>water</m>; that is the secret. And
you will see that the <m>oil</m><m>,</m> although it seems to be imbued,
will separate itself <sup>from the water</sup> as <sup>does</sup>
grease. <al>Mussels</al> become stronger in cold <m>water</m>, and warm
<m>water</m> would dissolve them with difficulty, although having been
reheated, <sup>the mussels</sup> are <sup>then</sup> more handleable
&amp; easy to dissolve in the <m>water</m>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p110v_2</id>

<head><m>Wheat oil</m></head>

<ab>Is made on a blade of <m>iron</m> reddened in the fire, and the
<m>oil</m> turns into drops, which is appropriate to oil the hair of a
butterfly or similar thing, because this <m>oil</m> is instantly dry
&amp; makes the rest dry out. It is necessary that the coat or down of
any animal that you want to mold be flat, because <sup>if left</sup>
standing up, it will make the sand raise up &amp; form bubbles.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><figure>#</figure> If you want to mold
something delicate, like a pansy, some, to give it a little thickness,
more than what is natural, some rub it with <m>butter</m>. But it is
best to oil it with <m>wheat oil</m> because it has no opacity &amp;
does not block the smaller features as much, and makes the flower
firmer.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p110v_3</id>

<head>A cast of <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m></head>

<ab>Because you want to cast <m>tin</m> very thinly, if your medal,
plant or other thing <sup>you want</sup> to mold is thin &amp; fine,
make <sup>sure</sup> to include more <m>tin</m>, much more than
<m>lead</m>, namely less than the fourth part of <m>lead</m> for three
of <m>tin</m>. And moreover, one only puts <m>lead</m> in as an alloy.
Contrarily, if you want to mold something strong &amp; thick, put a lot
more <m>lead</m> in than <m>tin</m>. And for the one &amp; the other you
can put in a little <m>looking-glass tin</m>, but only a very little,
with a little <m>resin</m>, when you want to cast. Since then, when
molding with pure new <m>lead</m>, I put in two ounces of pure
<m>tin</m> for every pound <sup>of <m>lead</m></sup>. And when molding
with pure <m>tin</m>, I put in two ounces of pure <m>lead</m> for every
pound <sup>of <m>tin</m></sup>. I made some plants &amp; snakes as if
they were real.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>

I cast <m>tin</m> <sup>when it was</sup> nearly red, and the same thing
with <m>lead</m>, which however had not remained in the fire for too
long, because it becomes brittle and burns up.</ab>

</div>
</root>
