<root>
<page>036v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f78.image</image>

<div>

<id>p036v_1</id>

<head><pro>Founder</pro></head>

<ab>Kitchen pots are made well, in order not to give a <sn>bad taste to
the meat</sn>, with the same <m>metal the bells are made of</m>. It is
true that <pro>foun<del><fr>ables</fr></del><add>ders</add></pro> mix in
more <m>latten</m> to make them yellower, in order to sell them better.
But the <m>latten</m> by itself, &amp;simply by touching it, is
<sn>stinking</sn> &amp; <sn>bad smelling</sn>.</ab>

<ab><m>Latten</m> does not lose, or very slightly, its <m>calamine</m>
in an <tl>air furnace</tl> when it is melted in a <tl>crucible</tl>, nor
does it lose it in a <tl><m>wood</m> furnace</tl>, but it does in a
<tl>bellows furnace</tl> because <tl>bellows</tl> give intense
flames.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p036v_2</id>

<head><tl>Air furnace</tl></head>

<ab>It is necessary that the mouth be narrower than the bottom. And it
is enough if the <tl>crucible</tl> can enter in it, &amp; if there is
enough space to remove &amp; take it with <tl>pincers</tl>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p036v_3</id>

<head><m><pro>Glassmakers</pro>' glass</m></head>

<ab>It is said that in <pl>Lorraine</pl> &amp; <pl>Flanders</pl>
<m>linking glass</m> is made of <m><pa>fern</pa> ashes</m> &amp;
<m>pebbles</m>. First they blow up a long still that another worker
breaks off and cuts vertically with big shears. Then this long still
expands by being placed on a <tl><m>stone</m></tl> or large
<tl>platine</tl> in a <tl>furnace</tl> slightly colder than one for
melting. Furthermore, they flatten it by rolling <sup>over</sup> it a
big &amp; long <tl><m>iron</m> stick</tl>. Then they take it out of the
annealing <tl>furnace</tl>. Similarly, they make some in
<pl>England</pl> that are quite beautiful. Close to <pl>Rouen</pl> in
<pl>France</pl>, <m>flat glass</m> is made with some <del><fr>sel
de</fr></del> <m><pa>saltworth</pa></m> &amp; <m>pebbles</m> and is
whiter &amp; softer than the <pl>Lorraine</pl> one, because it can be
melted with a <tl>candle</tl>, unlike the <pl>Lorraine</pl> one. This
<m>flat glass</m> is blown up in a long still -- the end of which
someone else cuts and blows up whilst turning it, then flattens it using
a <tl>plane</tl> which is on the ground, <del>A</del> and then reheats
it. Thus the middle of the still, where it began, always stays the
same.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The <m>glass</m>, when wet, can be
broken again with the flame of a <tl>candle</tl>, but not as precisely
as with <tl>hot <m>iron</m></tl>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
