<root>
<page>130v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f266.item</image>

<div>
<id>p130v_1</id>
<head>Molding a crab</head>

<ab>It is a secret and a masterpiece to mold <x>a crab</x> well because
it is necessary to proceed differently <x>than you would</x> with other
animals, because its shell is quite difficult to <x>...</x> and that is
why it is necessary to reheat the mold three or four times. And on top
of all that, it leaves a hard crust <x>that is</x> gray like <m>ash</m>.
It is not molded from one piece and one cast, like plants. Rather, in
two casts as with serpents which are easily stripped. After it is
opened, nimbly remove this crust with the very fine point of a
pen-knife, <add>not with <m>quicksilver</m> which would do nothing</add>
and likewise those small crusts of the second cast which get into the
cavities that the <m>sand</m> or the molded animal made because it has
curved legs. Here is the subtlety and the secret of stripping it. As you
molded it <x>the crab</x> from the back side in the way <x>that you did
for</x> the others <x>animals</x>, remove the stomach and all the curved
legs from it. Make your second cast in the way <x>that you did for</x>
the other <x>animals</x>, but as it will have set, take care that you
not open the mold unless you have first reheated it well. Otherwise,
because of its curved legs, you would break the whole thing. Herein lies
the subtlety. If, after it has been well reheated and opened, you see
that the crust is not burned enough, reheat <x>it</x> until it is burned
<x>enough</x>. </ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
It <x>a crab</x> can be painted like a crayfish.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
For opening the mold, it is not necessary to soak it because, once
reheated, it will open itself by itself.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p130v_2</id>
<head>Stag beetle</head>

<ab>Like a crab, it <x>a stag beetle</x> is also difficult to burn,
therefore do <x>stag beetles</x> as you did crabs.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p130v_3</id>
<head>For molding thinly</head>

<ab>After you have molded the first mold as the core, leave it to dry
well before removing the figure from <m>wax</m>, so that the mold is not
ruined. Afterwards, then make make a small <m>lasagna of paste</m> as
thick as you like, and, once you have greased the cavity of your first
hollowed mold with <m>butter</m>, apply the <m>paste</m> to it <x>the
cavity of the first concave mold</x> and then the upper part of the
second mold. If you grease <x>the mold</x> with <m>oil</m>, it will be
soaked up <x>into the mold</x> and it will not be as clean as
<m>butter</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
