<root>
<page>109v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f224.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p109r_5</id>

<ab>when they want to bite or to eat something, they <x>snakes</x> do
not go at it head on, but sideways &amp; by sinuous coiling, as do Satan
&amp; his henchmen. The snake has a small head, but a very large body;
the entryway to sin seems small &amp; inconsequential, but the
consequences are great indeed. A snake can abstain from eating for seven
or eight days, once he has swallowed a frog, and can swallow three or
four frogs, one after the other, and what it has devoured does not rot
&amp; is not digested all at once in its stomach, but each part little
by little, i.e. the bones and everything. The rest is just as fresh as
when the snake ate it, such that when one bothers &amp; torments it, it
spits out what it swallowed up, which, in part, is totally digested,
&amp; with the other part as fresh as if the frog were alive. It can
hold a swallowed frog down for two or three hours &amp; spit it out
alive.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p109v_1</id>
<head>Toad</head>

<ab>If by chance you want to mold this ugly animal &amp; if it should
piss in your hand, it will sting your hand &amp; cause it to itch, as if
you had been holding nettles. But the very best remedy for this is to
put your hand into fresh <m>dirt</m>, &amp; to cover it as if you wanted
to bury it. Frogs are not so beautiful when molded because they have
shiny skin, &amp; toads have lumpy skin.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
You can mold the toad hollow, and leaving a notch open on the
underbelly, you will make it jump with the twisted cord of the saw. If
it is a small, put it on a <m>magnet</m> cut small to the size of the
toad, then put it in good <m>vinegar</m>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
If it is big, mold hollow, &amp; if you want to mold it with its mouth
open, put some <m>cotton</m> therein, &amp; then put some melted
<m>wax</m> on the <m>cotton</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p109v_2</id>
<head>Killing snakes for molding</head>

<ab>Some put a drop of <m>aqua fortis</m> into their mouths, which
stupefies them, so that the head &amp; the body look dead. But the head
is still alive, and when you stick it with a needle in order to fix it
to your mold, it moves &amp; spoils &amp; undoes everything. Therefore,
to kill your snake, put it into a bottle filled with good <m>vinegar</m>
&amp; some <m>spirits</m>. Do the same with lizards &amp; other similar
animals.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
If you want to keep them, you can put them in a pipe full of <m>dirt</m>
in a garden outdoors, but it is necessary that the pipe be covered with
<m>latten wire</m>, because otherwise, the snakes will crawl &amp; climb
up quite high.</ab>

</div>
</root>
