<root>
<page>135v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f276.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p135v_1</id>
<head>Casting in <m><figure>☼</figure></m></head>

<ab>Take a crucible with a capacity suitable for what you want to put in
it, crush a little borax coarsely &amp; put it at the bottom, then the
<m><figure>☼</figure></m> on top. Arrange the crucible on the charcoals
of the forge in such a way that the wind of the bellows blows on it from
underneath and not at the side, for this cools it &amp; does not heat it
enough. Make sure also that it is distanced three fingers from the wall
of the forge, in order that it can be surrounded with charcoal. Let the
said crucible reheat, until it is well red. Then, make your boy blow on
it with long and strong pushes, for in this way it heats <del>well</del>
better. And nevertheless <del>blow by</del> when the gold is melted,
blow on top with a little bellows, for the gold will become brittle
&amp; take on a <fr>chappe</fr>. And as long as it makes a swirling
smoke, as you blow thusly, it means that is not <fr>doulx</fr> enough
for the cast. Uncover therefore the crucible &amp; without moving
<del>ch</del> it from its place and without interrupting the blowing,
make it lean towards you in order to see well inside. Throw in it the
size of a bean of borax &amp; blow inside in jolts with the little
bellows. But if there is charcoal inside, blow a little stronger to make
it go out. And if the gold smokes &amp; swirls, put some more borax in
and <del>note</del> blow on top, making sure that, if it is still
brittle &amp; not softened enough, it does not cover itself when you
blow, as if it had cooled. But if it does not make this sign, it is
<fr>douls</fr> enough. @At that point blow very strongly in order to
heat it well, and as you think it is hot enough, throw in on top, in the
crucible, the color composed, as said beforehand here, of verdet,
saltpeter, sal ammoniac &amp; a little borax. And <del>let rest</del>
blow always with the small bellows, and the gold will become shiny
like</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
If you cast in <m>gold</m> some important piece, lute your mold with the
same <m>sand</m> where <del>there is</del> there is some crocum.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
If you want to cast some large work in gold, or which is important, make
at the foot of the forge, or at one end of it a <fr>four à vent</fr>,
where you can hold your mold in the completely <del>n</del> red sand.
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
One can cast two or three <ms>lb</ms> of <m>gold</m>.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
