<root>
<page>005r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f15.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p004v_a3</id>

<ab>or <m><pa>linen</pa></m> &amp; leave it thus for xx4
<ms><tmp>hours</tmp></ms> &amp; it will be engraved. But if you should
want to engrave quickly, varnish all your work &amp; boil it in the
aforesaid liquor, and it will engrave quickly.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p005r_a1</id>
<head><m>Steel</m> mirrors</head>

<ab><figure>+</figure>They are called of <m>steel</m> because in the
past they were commonly made of <m>steel</m> polished with <m>potée of
emery</m>. But more easily, various kinds are made of <m>cuivre
franc</m>, which is <m>rosette</m>, and <m>tin</m>, because this can be
cast in a mold &amp; made round, concave, convex &amp; however you like,
to produce various forms.</ab>

<ab>So take half of <m>rosette copper</m> &amp; half of soft <m>tin</m>,
that is to say fine, which has not yet been used. Put them in a
crucible, &amp; first melt the <m>copper</m> well. And once it is well
melted, put in the <m>tin</m> and mix together. Then cast in the mold,
of <m>white stone</m> with no eyelets, &amp; grease the mold with
<m>oil</m>, &amp; let the mold be moderately warm. Then, having molded
your mirror, you can polish it in this manner.</ab>

<ab>Set one of these in <m>plaster</m> in order that it holds firmly,
&amp; then put the other one over it with thin sand in between, &amp;
rub one against the other, whether hollow or flat, &amp; thus you will
polish two at once. And if you want to polish them on both sides, you
only need to switch them, which means putting the one that was polishing
into the <m>plaster</m> &amp; using the one that was in the
<m>plaster</m> to polish. After having polished them with the
<m><fr>arene</fr></m> you can soften them with <m>tripoli of Venice</m>,
which should not be sandy, &amp; after with <m>potée</m>. You polish
with <m>arene</m> using <m>water</m>, but polishing with <m>tripoli</m>
&amp; <m>potée</m> is done dry. Once polished, you can set it.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p005r_a2</id>
<head>Concave mirrors</head>

<ab>The concave mirror composed in the aforesaid form produces an
endless number of illusions which seem magic. If someone wants to see
oneself from behind, it is necessary to place the concave mirror on the
ground on its foot, &amp; let it be at a slant; after, look at it one
step away. But if you look at it closer up, it will show you the right
way up but with your face quite large &amp; the hairs of your beard as
thick as</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
