<root>
<page>095v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f196.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p094r_1</id>

<ab>The end is bought ready-made by the dozen which costs of six
<cn><fr>sols</fr></cn> for the small ones, but for the the big ones 2
<cn><la>caroli</la></cn>.The end <del>this</del> is put either with
nails which are put on the sides of the cutting edge, but this only
spoils the sword &amp; destroys the scabbard because the water enters
through the join of the nail. It is best to apply <m>resin</m> or
<m>glue</m> on it, but the <m>resin</m> is better. And it is best is
when the end is well adjusted &amp; set so hot that the pulverized
<m>resin</m> melts on the end. In this way, it does not fall and cannot
be undone unless it is put in the fire.</ab>

<ab>Guards are of several kinds:<lb/>

Worked<lb/>

Guttered which is with round mouldings<lb/>

Pearled<lb/>

Scarfed when the bands are crosswise<lb/>

Onioned which is with a flat head<lb/>

In the King's manner, which are plain</ab>

<ab>The <pro>furbishers</pro> buy them by dozens, the dozen of plain
ones commonly costs x lb. The worked piece, 30 <cn><fr>sols</fr></cn> or
depending on its style.</ab>

<ab>The first thing the <pro>apprentice</pro> does is to furbish as
said.</ab>

<ab>And next to garnish the sword &amp; make a scabbard which is the
height of the art.</ab>

<ab>They buy <m>wood</m> pieces for scabbards which are ready made, of
<m>beech wood</m>, a hundred for xv or xx or 30 <fr>sols</fr>, depending
on the distance to the place where they are made.</ab>

<ab>Theses <m>wood</m> pieces are thus called <fr>estelles</fr>, and
have to be very neat &amp; without any knots &amp; are one finger’s
thickness across.</ab>

<ab>Then the <pro>furbisher</pro> puts them on a small bench, called a
scabbard bench and with a <del>a plane</del> small <m>iron</m> tool
similar to that of the <pro>joiners</pro>' bench, they hold it firmly.
Then with a <del>plane</del> plane which is like a knife with two
handles, one works the <m>wood</m> roughly from the top, next one passes
the <pro>joiner</pro>'s plane on it the better to even it. Next, one
scours it on the inside with a</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
