<root>
<page>117r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f239.image</image>

<div>
<id>p117r_a1</id>
<head>A means to mold <pa>flowers</pa> and <pa>plants</pa></head>

<ab>One needs to choose them in their full verdure &amp; vivacity, &amp;
<del>les mou</del> not pick them, if possible, until the time one will
want to mold them, so that they do not wilt. Or if you need to carry
them from afar, soak their stems in a bottle of <m>water</m>, or better
still <m>wine</m>. Make, firstly, a <m>wax</m> stick pointed like a big
peg, of a size appropriate to what you want to cast, as you see in the
margin, marked A. Put &amp; prick at the foot of this small peg a bit of
<m>iron</m> wire, rather thick &amp; strong. And at the point of this,
you will fit your <pa>flower</pa> stem or your <pa>plant</pa>. This
done, set it aside neatly. And arrange your <del>mold of t</del> circle
and shape of <m>clay</m> as you have done for the <al>snakes</al>, in
the form of a <mu>mandore</mu> <del>in such a way that</del> according
to the size of your <pa>plant</pa>. Then take the one that you have
prepared to be cast, as we have taught you, &amp; wet &amp; moisten it
very carefully with good <m>eau de vie</m> with a <tl>pinceau</tl>. Then
pass the wire stem through the end of the <m>earthen</m>
<mu>mandore</mu>, in order that the <m>wax</m> peg, where the
<pa>plant</pa> is fastened, joins to the end of the <m>earthen</m>
<mu>mandore</mu>. And arrange thusly your <pa>plant</pa> in such a way
lying down that it remains in the middle of aforesaid <mu>mandore</mu>,
without touching on either side, so that <del>a</del> the sand that you
will pour in it will be of equal thickness <del>as</del> everywhere,
&amp; <corr><del>is</del></corr> exceeds everywhere by the height of two
good <ms>fingers</ms> the top of the <del>such</del> <pa>plant</pa>. And
having secured the wire stem well, pour quickly <del>wet</del> your
<m>wet sand</m>, much clearer than the one for snakes, in the
<mu>mandore</mu>. And the sooner the better, in order that the <m>eau de
vie</m> does not dry. And take heed to put in a little more <m>water of
sal ammoniac</m> among the common than you would do for the snakes. And
when you will make sand especially for your bouquets, where you would
mix in a little more <m>feather alum</m>, it will be that much better.
Thus your mold will be in one piece and it will not be necessary to
unjoin it, but rather <del>leave</del> separate it from the <m>clay</m>
once it will have set, let it dry, and then reheat it again until the
plants are burnt. And note that if the plant you want to cast has a
strong stalk &amp; stem, you can cast it lying down, as had been said.
But if it is some weak &amp; delicate flower, <del>cast</del> plant it
upright with the <m>wax</m> peg because the sand will always
<del>cast</del> lift it up, it being very clear. Do not forget to adapt
two vent holes with two small <tl>sticks</tl>, starting at the foot of
the cast, which is the pointed end of the <m>wax</m> peg.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
If the <pa>plants</pa>s are so delicate that they rise to the top when
you pour the <m>wet sand</m>, one can stop and contain them with a
<m>thread</m> passed through the circle of the mold with a
<tl>needle</tl>.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p117r_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5WnpBbm8wN2gyTWs</link>

</figure>

<figure>

<id>fig_p117r_2</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5VURRYzlWOFByNzQ</link>

</figure>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The more delicate the <pa>flower</pa> is, the clearer the sand must
be.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p117r_3</id>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dVB5bzVUWWJuS0U</link>

<caption>Mold <fr>en noyau</fr>.</caption>

</figure>

</div>
</root>
