<root>
<page>053v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f112.image</image>

<div>

<id>p053v_1</id>

<head><al>Silkworms</al></head>

<ab>They are produced from seed, that is to say eggs, that which is sold
by the ounce, which is commonly sold in Languedoc iii lb v s. The one
from Spain that merchants bring there is considered the best because the
worms which come from there are not so subject to illnesses &amp; make
more silk. In Spain, one ounce of seed, they produce there worms which
commonly yield xv lb. of silk. But from one once of seed produced in
France, they only return x or xii. Three ounces of seed are for
producing such a quantity of worms, that with them you will be able to
furnish a room accomodated with three or 4 shelves of large slabs.
Willingly they begin to unskin themselves around holy week. And for
doing this, one puts them in a fir box, like those where one puts
<fr>dragée</fr>, warmly among feather cushions. And at the beginning,
they unskin themselves skin like little black ants, &amp; as soon as
there are two or three unskinned, one needs to give them white mulberry
leaves, and then arrange them on the slabs. And three times per day, one
needs to exchange fresh leaves. And if during the day there is some
thunder or rainy weather, cloud-covered &amp; cool, one needs to keep in
the room three or 4 chafing dishes and with glowing charcoal, &amp; put
in incense until all the room would be filled with smoke. And when the
weather is warm &amp;<fr>serain</fr>, the silk abounds more &amp; and
then it is better. Some worms make it whiter, others more yellowish. And
even if it may be white, it yellows when one draws it with hot water.
From their birth until the moment they make their cocoons and prisons,
worms sleep and rest 4 times, and each time they remain 4 or five days
resting without eating, as if they were dying so as to be born again,
because each one sheds their skin and begins by uncovering the head,
then consequently, on different days, the rest of the body, and they go
from white to grey, and from grey to white. And if one of them has some
sickness and does not have the strength to shed, one needs to help it
and to be careful not to squash it, because if it gives off a yellow
liquor, it is no longer worth anything. And they do not even serve much
if one handles them. Around Pentecost, they begin to want to climb on
the dry heather branches that we prepare and attach</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

See Marco Girolamo Vida, Bishop of Alba and Cremonesi, wrote a poem on
the nature of silkworms.

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

How they are <ill/>

</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
