<root>
<page>157v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f320.image</image>

<div>

<id>p157v_1</id>

<head>Ash in the molds</head>

<ab>One needs to let the mold cool before blowing to make the ashes go
out. For when the mold is hot, they adhere against it &amp; once cold,
they separate from it more easily, &amp; go out from it by blowing with
air <fr>en vapeur</fr>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p157v_2</id>

<head>Molding a <al>bird</al></head>

<ab>One needs to give it its shape. And to do this, place it on its side
on a <m>clay</m> slab, and hide &amp; sink within it half the aforesaid
<al>bird</al>, <add>in order</add> that it only shows one leg &amp; one
foot, then you will grease it with <m>butter</m> to make it hold the
feathers down, finally <del>of<m>oil</m></del> <m>eau-de-vie</m>. And
then cast. And having made this take, clean &amp; uncover whatever needs
it. Next mold the other side in the same way. But because the feet,
being of bone that is difficult to burn, &amp; are not able to be
cleaned with either by <m>quicksilver</m> <del>If</del> or by any other
means, if the mold would not open, uncover the bottom of the feet &amp;
the toe or the little finger of the claw, &amp; mold as a separate
piece. Reheat &amp; open your mold &amp; clean the bones. The feet
usually remain too weak to support the mass of a solid <al>bird</al>.
And for this reason one applies an <m>iron</m> thread in the mold of the
feet, which passes into the body before casting, thus they are
reinforced. Some mold the wings in a frame. Others mold the head
&amp;the said wings separately <fr>en noyau</fr>, then join &amp; repair
them, to first rough out a form that will be rigid &amp; withstand the
wet sand.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>They are skinned &amp; fill up <m>cotton
cloth</m>. &amp; even better, one needs to dress them in the way that
<pro>curriers</pro> do, in order that they do not lose a feather, weight
it. The dressing is <m>alum</m> &amp; paste of <m>flour</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p157v_3</id>

<head>For making h<exp>…</exp> wine f<exp>…</exp>rs <x>?</x></head>

<ab>Take a sock from the right <del>d</del><add>t</add> foot that has
been worn and make it soak in <m>water</m>, and make that same person or
someone else drink the <m>water</m> that comes out from it, and you will
see marvels.</ab>

</div>
</root>
