<root>
<page>109v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f224.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p109r_5</id>

<ab>when they want to bite or eat something, they do not bite with a
direct attack, but with sinuous turns &amp; from the side, as do
<pn>Satan</pn> &amp; his <pro>disciples</pro>. It has a small head, but
a very long body. The entryway to sin seems small &amp; inconsequential,
but the consequences of it are very great. It abstains from eating seven
or eight <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms>, once it has devoured some
<al>frog</al>. It can swallow three or four of them, one after the
other, and what he devoured is neither corrupted nor consumed in one go
in its stomach, but <del><fr>p</fr></del> any part little by little,
that is to say bones and everything. And the remains are found as fresh
as when it had devoured them, such that sometimes, when one presses
&amp; torments it, it renders up what it has engulfed, parts of which
are found totally consumed &amp; others as fresh as if it were alive. It
can keep for two to three <ms><tmp>hours</tmp></ms> a <al>frog</al>
engulfed &amp; renders it up completely alive.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p109v_1</id>
<head><al>Toad</al></head>

<ab>If by chance you want to mold this vile animal &amp; if it were to
<m>piss</m> in your <bp>hand</bp>, it would burn your <bp>hand</bp>
&amp; itch, as if you had handled <pa>nettles</pa>. But the most
powerful <md>remedy</md> for this is to put your <bp>hand</bp> <env>into
fresh <m>earth</m></env>, &amp; to cover it as if you wanted to bury it.
A <al>frog</al> is not so beautiful molded because it has lively skin,
&amp; the other has a lumpy one.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
You can mold it hollow, and leaving under its belly an open notch, you
will make it jump with the <tl>twisted cord of the saw</tl>. Or else, if
it is a small, put it on a <m>magnet</m> of its size, cut thinly, then
put it in <m>good vinegar</m>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
When it is big, one needs to mold it hollow, &amp; if you want to make
it have an open mouth, put some <m>cotton</m> inside, &amp; then on the
<m>cotton</m> some <m>melted wax</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p109v_2</id>
<head>Killing <al>snakes</al> for molding</head>

<ab>Some put a <ms>drop</ms> of <m>aquafortis</m> in their mouths,
which makes it really drunk, such that the head &amp; the part behind
seem to be dead, but the mouth remains alive, and when you pierce it
with a <tl>needle</tl> to fit it to the <tl>mold</tl>, it moves &amp;
spoils &amp; undoes everything. Therefore, to kill them entirely, put it
in a <tl>bottle</tl> of <m>good vinegar</m> &amp; some <m>eau-de-vie</m>. And do thus with <al>lizards</al> &amp; other similar
beasts.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
If you want to keep them, you can put them in a <tl>pipe</tl> full of
<m>earth</m> <env>in a garden outdoors</env>. But your <tl>pipe</tl>
must be covered with <tl><m>archal wire</m></tl>, for otherwise it would
climb &amp; go up very high.</ab>

</div>
</root>
