<root>
<page>163v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f332.image</image>

<div>

<id>p163v_1</id>

<head><al>Crayfish</al></head>

<ab>The hairy cornicles that it has under its beak tend to come out
lumpy &amp; not neat because, being burnt, it is difficult to remove
them &amp; clean their ash, which, staying in the mold, prevents the
<m>metal</m> from running well therein; &amp; for that reason, one makes
a small gate of <m>wax</m> thread at the tips of them, both to hold them
up and to blow out the clogging ash.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>Spare no pins, placing them not only in the
middle of the body, but also on the big legs, and two or three at the
tail, according to the stance that you want to give it.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p163v_2</id>

<head><m>Crocum</m></head>

<ab>That which is rusty by itself, being showered with <m>salt water</m>
or <m>vinegar</m> or <m>urine</m>, and then very dried out <add>and
reddened in fire</add>, is very red ground on <m>porphyry</m> and is of
the color of <m>Levant bole</m>, &amp; approaching <m>minium</m>. But
that which is showered with <m>urine</m> &amp; dried out acquires a
deeper tincture &amp; approaches <m>crushed <lt>aes ustum</lt></m> or
<m>vermillion</m>. But the first one, finely ground, acquires a bright
red color, <del>in</del> like <m>cinnabar</m>, in <m>eau-de-vie</m>. And
the ones and the others, prepared as said, and finely ground &amp;
rendered very hot, give off a red smoke like a volatile spirit if, being
thus hot and fine, one throws on top <m>vinegar</m>, <m>urine</m>, or
<m>eau-de-vie</m>. <m>Urine</m> gives much tincture, and
<m>eau-de-vie</m> also.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p163v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5anJvd0FQQ3BkRFE</link>

</figure>

</div>

<div>

<id>p163v_3</id>

<head>Repairing</head>

<ab>It is better to repair little with the burin called <fr>onglet</fr>,
or with that which one calls <fr>chaple</fr>, or some small file. But
above all, avoid touching your work, but only the fin or lump that will
have occurred during the cast. And while repairing, wet &amp; rub with
your <tl>small <m><al>piglet</al>-bristle</m> brushes</tl>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
