<root>
<page>060r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f125.item</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p059v_6</id>

<ab>and to prevent it from breaking, mix in a little <m>oil</m> &amp;
melt them together &amp; fill the cracks &amp; make them even and paint
on them. And the <m>oil</m> mixed with <m>wax</m> will
<del><fr>q</fr></del> help colors to hold since they are also
distempered with <m>oil</m>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p060r_1</id>

<head>First whitening of a panel</head>

<ab>One layers two or three times with <m>chalk</m> tempered with
<m><fr>colle <add>de destrempe</add></fr></m> on the panel, not with a
<tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> but with a <tl><fr>broisse</fr></tl> in such a
way as if you wanted to pounce, &amp; leave to dry. And reiterate up to
two or three times, then even out the last ground well with a
<tl>knife</tl>, <add>then give coat of <m>glue</m>on top</add>, upon
which you will next be able to make your impression and then paint. But
make sure that your first white is not too thick for it would break
easily. <pl>Flemish</pl> <pro>painters</pro> have such panels
<comment>c_060r_03</comment> made by the dozen.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p060r_2</id>

<head>Neat work</head>

<ab>When you are working, make sure not to stir up dust, &amp; when you
leave your work, cover it in order that the said dust will not fall upon it.
Also layer your colors as thinly as you can, for if they are thick you
will be not be able to soften them thoroughly.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<render>tall</render>

Also do not layer color on color if they are not similar, such as white
on black, but rather flesh color on flesh color, &amp; thus with the
others. And leave blank the space for shadow or a different color.
<del><fr>Ains</fr></del> in this way, layering each manner of color only
on the impression, they will not die &amp; you will work
neatly.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p060r_3</id>

<head><m>Oil</m></head>

<ab><m><pa>Walnut</pa> oil</m> extracted like<m>peeled
<pa>almonds</pa></m> is very white. This one of <m><la>Palma
christi</la></m>. And when the <m>oil</m> has had a little body, the
colors soften. For if the <m>oil</m> is too clear, the colors run &amp;
do <corr>not</corr> bind, even those that do not have body. <m>Fatty
oil</m> that is not easily imbibed is appropriate for <m>varnish</m>.
The <m>oil</m> is desiccative enough when it dries out as quickly as
<m>common varnish</m>. <m>Oils</m> do not dry as quickly in cold
countries as in hot countries. <m>Oil</m> <env>exposed to the sun</env>
is clarified well. But it fattens. If you put in <m>ceruse</m> or
<m>lead filings</m> or <m>lead white</m> or <m>calcined pulverized
<del><fr>p</fr></del>glass</m>. To avoid this, put the <tl>vial</tl> in
<m>clear water</m>.</ab>

<ab>Colors in <m>oil</m>, once dry, sometimes do not easily receive the
second colors, to prevent this, breathe on them &amp; the color will
take.</ab>

</div>
</root>
