<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="012v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f30.image">




<div id="p012v_1">



<head>Molding <m>stucco</m> promptly</head>

<ab>Grind &amp; pulverize finely <m>brick</m> or <m><pl>Armenian</pl>
bole</m> or <m>sanguine</m> &amp; incorporate it with <m>melted wax</m>,
&amp; thus melted, cast like the others on a <tl>relief medal</tl>,
&amp; thus you will have a hollow form where you will be able to cast with
<m>plaster</m>, <m><tl>pestled</tl> paper</m>, or <m><fr>terre chimolée</fr></m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



Finely sieved <m>brick</m> is better, because the <m>bole</m> is too
fat.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p012v_2">



<head>Cleaning <m>yellow pearls</m></head>

<ab>Gently boil them in the <tl><pro>goldsmiths’</pro> <fr>bouteure</fr></tl><comment rid="c_104r_01"/> then, with <tl><m>tripoli</m></tl> &amp; a piece of
<tl><m>leather</m></tl>, sprinkled on the flesh side with the <tl><m>powder of the
said tripoli</m></tl>, rub &amp; polish the <m>pearl</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p012v_3" continued="yes">



<head>For whitening <m>enilanroc</m><comment rid="c_012v_02"/></head>

<ab>Some think that the <m>ceruse</m>-colored crust which is on top
is natural, others say that it is a secret of <pro>ancient lapidaries</pro>
that is lost, others say that it is <m>refired enamel</m>. And by means
of the said crust, several ciphers, letters, circles
<del><fr>st</fr></del> &amp; other bizarre things can be formed. As for
the method, I have practiced it thus. Once I wished to give it a layer of
<m>arsenic</m> ground on <tl><m>marble</m></tl>. However, I experimented
without this, and I put the above said thing, <m>enilanroc</m>, in a
small <tl><m>iron</m> casket</tl> on the fire of my
<tl><pro>goldsmith</pro>’s forge</tl> with three or four small
half-burnt <m>charcoals</m>, and blew only with my <bp>mouth</bp>. And
nonetheless the thing came to <del>redden &amp;</del> ignition &amp; turned
completely white, not only on its surface but also inside, &amp; then I
let it cool on its own <env>near the fire</env>, for otherwise, exposing
it suddenly to cold air, it would have burst. Once all white, I passed
it through my <tl><add><m>lead</m></add> <del><m>tin</m></del>wheel</tl>, 
where I found it as hard as before, &amp; uncovering the white
a little, I found it a fair flesh color. Finally, I polished it &amp;
saw that it took a very beautiful polish &amp; could paragon a
very beautiful <m>agate</m> for cutting some beautiful face on it &amp;
bringing it on <del>the</del> a table of

</ab>



</div>
</root>
