<root>
<page>113v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f232.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p113r_1</id>

<ab>such that while reheating the two casts will unjoin. <del><fr>Et
pour pl</fr></del> Therefore, for this effect, take several <tl>bowls of
different size, which have a lip</tl>, to cast better. In these pour
some <m>common <env>fountain</env> water</m>, &amp; mix into it <ms>as
much <m>essence of sal ammoniac</m> as can be held in an
<m>egg</m></ms>, <add><mark>#</mark></add> composed as mentionned.
If you want to cast in <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m> - because one would
need more for casting <m>gold</m> &amp; <m>silver</m> - the
<m>essence</m> once in your <tl>bowl</tl>, <del><fr>mesles</fr></del>
put <del><fr>y</fr></del> your sand in it &amp; not the <m>essence</m>
in the sand &amp; add it <del><fr>a dista dista</fr></del>with such
discretion that <del><fr>il</fr></del>, while stirring &amp; mixing it
promptly with a <tl><m>wooden</m> spoon</tl>, it does not become thicker
than <m><del>clear</del> mustard</m>. And thus throw
<del><fr>le</fr></del> first the non-thick part, <del><fr>qui
es</fr></del> as is always at the surface, in shakes &amp;
<del><fr>da</fr></del> at the top of your <tl>mold</tl>. And doing so,
since your animal is nearly covered, blow strongly everywhere in order
to dissipate the small and big bubbles that the wet sand makes &amp;
continue without delay to put all the rest which is at the bottom, &amp;
a little thicker than the top, until everything is filled, up to the
mark for thickness that you made.

<figure>

<id>fig_p113v_4</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bEE5QmFaQWxUYm8</link>

</figure> And do not forget to shake the <tl>mold</tl>
<del><fr>affin</fr></del> while throwing, in order that the wet sand runs
&amp; enters well everywhere. Also tip your <tl>mold</tl> up on the side
of the head, which is higher than the body, and thus your <tl>mold</tl>
will have the same thickness, &amp; you will spare sand. All of this
being carefully done <del><fr>fai</fr></del>, let it set, which will
take a <ms><tmp>quarter of an hour</tmp></ms>. Then release the
<m>clay</m> circle, which can be used another time. And leave it to dry
a little bit, &amp; separate your <tl>mold</tl> from the
<fr>tourtelle</fr> <m>earth</m>, which also <del><fr>de</fr></del> will
be appropriate for molding right away, and pare the excess with a big
<tl>knife</tl>, giving to it the long shape of a <mu>mandore</mu>.
<del><fr>Rasche</fr></del> Scrape &amp; cut also away the back <add>of
the <tl>mold</tl></add>, which is always the weakest, and adapt it
cleanly thus. And do not forget to make notches around, in order that the
second cast anchors itself there &amp; binds better

<figure>

<id>fig_p113v_5</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5V29QdUxZVmxCUDQ</link>

</figure> without changing.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<del>If you can, fill</del> your half <tl>mold</tl> in one go &amp; with
<del><fr>la pre</fr></del> one wet batch it is the best.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<mark>#</mark>

<ms>or two <m>eggs</m></ms>, because there is no risk if there is more.
<del><fr>Et l’<m>eau</m></fr></del>If you cast in two goes, it is enough
to put <m>essence of sal ammoniac</m> at the first bowlful. </ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

Make it clear like a <m>broth of juices</m>, or like <m>starchy
water</m>, that <pro>women</pro> use to make their <m>starch</m>. For
there is no risk in it being very clear, because sand always settles in
the bottom &amp; <m>water</m> separates &amp; remains on top. The same
that one scrapes since it is too weak &amp; soft. And it will not let
itself set quickly, for all things calcined dry out promptly from mixed
<m>water</m>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<figure>

<id>fig_p113v_3</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dEdzS040X3RjbkU</link>

</figure>

If you don't fill in one go your <tl>mold</tl>
<del><fr>destrempe</fr></del> with wet sand, take head to stir your
second cast with the <del><fr>e p</fr></del> surface of the first,
<del><fr>p</fr></del> by mixing with the <tl>spoon</tl> or a
<tl>spatula</tl> with which you wet it.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<m>Essence of sal ammoniac</m> is not necessary for small
<tl>molds</tl>, which do not require neither a big nor a long fire to be
reheated, however, when you put some in it will only be better. <ill/>

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p113v_1</id>

<head><del>Second cast</del></head>

</div>
</root>
