<root>
<page>153r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f311.image</image>

<div>

<id>p153r_1</id>

<head>Molding hollow for seals or other things</head>

<ab>Firstly, model your representation in <m>wax</m> on a piece of
<tl><m>glass</m> or smooth <m>slate</m></tl>. Next, mold it with our
above-said sand, <del><fr>l’</fr></del> having firstly anointed lightly
with <m>oil</m>, as you know, &amp; then rubbed with <m>eau-de-vie</m>,
<del>having</del> and wetting your sand with <m>hot water</m>. Having
the hollow, cast it in <m>alloyed lead</m>, in the same format as other
representations that you make very neatly. However, if it did not come
out at all neatly, repair it. And then, <del>cast some</del> <add>mold
with some</add> <m>wax</m>, on the relief of <m>lead</m>, &amp; you will
have a very neat hollow in the <m>wax</m>, which comes out very neatly
on the <m>lead</m>. Next, in the hollow of <m>wax</m>, cast your wet
sand, which will make for you a relief, on which you will cast your
hollow in <m>silver</m> or another <m>metal</m> for seals. But, note
that one ought not make your hollow with <m>melted wax</m>, but rather,
only heated in <m>warm water</m>, or, even better, in <m>warm
<bp>urine</bp></m>. Or else, if you have a relief of <m>gold</m> or
<m>silver</m>, or other <m>metal</m>, very <del><fr>faço</fr></del> neat
&amp; repaired, imprint on top your hollow of <m>wax</m>, &amp; then in
the latter, cast your sand, which will come out in relief, on which you will next cast your hollow for seals or other works. You could even
cast a hollow on the principal part of the <m>metal</m> relief, &amp;
even with <m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m>, which will not melt at all the
principal part if it is with a <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> lightly anointed
with <m>crushed chalk</m>, or smoked with <m><tl>candle</tl> smoke</m> or with
<m>glair of dried egg</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>When you have imprinted your seal of
<m>wax</m>, mold in <fr>noyau</fr> this piece of <m>wax</m>, which is
hollow, like your seal, &amp; your <fr>noyau</fr> will render it molded,
similar to <del><fr>u</fr></del> the imprint &amp; the seal.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

It is necessary that your <m>wax</m> be mixed with some color which
hardly has body, in order that you see the imprint better. <m><tl>Candle</tl>
smoke</m> or <m>soot black</m> is good for this. <m>White wax</m> , for
this effect, is <del><fr>exc</fr></del> better.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p153r_2</id>

<head>Giving the thickness that you wish to a medal</head>

<ab>Having cast your first <tl>mold</tl>, mix <del><fr>d</fr></del>
<m><la>crocum</la></m> or <m>well-ground iron scales</m> to firm it up.
And having set, &amp; rendered your hollow part very neat, take some
paste of fine</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
