<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="049v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f104.image">
    
    
    
    
<div id="p049v_1">
        
        
        
<head><al>Birds</al></head>
        
<ab><al>Calandra larks</al> &amp; all
<al>birds</al> taken from the nest &amp; which have not had freedom are
better, for these which are taken by net never sing so well. However,
the wild ones give <del><ill/></del> much pleasure with their
chanting, but they ought be taken <ms><tmp>before <pn>Sainct Michel</pn></tmp></ms>,<comment rid="c_049v_09"/>
otherwise they scarcely live. A small impostume occurs on all on the
fork of their tail, occasionally, which some call <df><fr>gaillardise</fr></df>,<comment rid="c_049v_06"/>
which makes them sick &amp; sometimes makes them die, especially
<al>calandra larks</al>. One knows this when they are sad &amp; do not sing.
One must pierce it <del><fr>av</fr></del>, not with a <tl>pin</tl>,<comment rid="c_049r_04"/> but
very gently by turning with the tip of <tl>quite pointy feather</tl>.
The <al>calandra lark</al> does not want to be without <del>grey</del>
<m>river sand</m>, &amp; the grey is the best, a little coarse. It rubs itself in it
&amp; purges itself with it.
            
</ab>
        
</div>
    
<div id="p049v_2">
        
        
        
<head>Grain of <m>lead</m></head>
        
<ab>Take a <del>pierced</del> <tl>playing card</tl>, pierced with a
<tl>pin</tl> or <tl>needle</tl>, folded on all four sides. Hold it with
the end of a small <tl>cleft stick</tl> and, holding the said
<tl>stick</tl> by <del>one end</del> <add>the other</add> end,
put your <tl>card</tl> three or 4 <ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> away from
the <m>water</m> that you will have put in a <tl>dish</tl> or similar
<tl>vessel</tl>. Then pour your <m>lead</m>, which should not be too
hot, into the <tl>card</tl> &amp; continually tap on the <tl>stick</tl>
that holds it. And thus your <m>lead</m> will granulate itself roundly.
And pass it through a coarse <tl>sieve</tl> to separate the largest grain
from the smallest. The largeish one will reach 25 to 30 <ms>paces</ms>.<comment rid="c_049v_08"/>
            
</ab>
        
</div>
    
<div id="p049v_3">
        
        
        
<head><al>Birds</al></head>
        
<ab>Those that <del>can</del> are taken <tmp>at <pn>Sainct Michel</pn></tmp> are
good for keeping, but those that are taken in <tmp>March</tmp> die,
because they are starting to fall into love. <oc><al>Ortolans</al></oc>
are fed on oats <tmp>all summer</tmp> in order that they are nourished without becoming
fat, to be more appropriate for hunting &amp; catching others.
Then, when one wants to fatten them for selling, one gives them
<pa>millet</pa>. They sing <tmp>at night</tmp>. One needs to
<del><fr>c</fr></del> take them <ms><tmp>after mid-July until
<pn>Sainct Michel</pn><comment rid="c_049v_09"/></tmp></ms>, for after that time when they have their young in
this country, they go away like <al>turtledoves</al> do. <al>Siskins</al>
should also be taken <ms><tmp>from All Saints’ Day until
Christmas</tmp></ms>, for after that they go to the <env>mountains</env> to
brood.
            
</ab>
        
<ab margin="left-middle">
            
            
            
<oc><al>Ortolans</al></oc> are ventriloquists, such that singing without
opening the beak, one would say that they are.<comment rid="c_049v_05"/>
            
</ab>
        
</div>
</root>
