<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="115r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f235.image">




<div continues="yes" id="p114r_1" categories="casting">


<ab margin="left-middle" render="tall">
        
<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p115r_1" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NmVuVUloTy0zNWc">
</figure><comment rid="c_115r_01"/><lb/> 
    
if you want, which will be enough, or else on the two halves.
But because one needs to cast by the tail or from the back of the
animal, make it so that the vents come from the head &amp; the middle of
the body to join to the said tail, where the gate is done, which is the
end of the mandore.</ab> 
    
<ab margin="left-middle"><del><fr>N</fr></del><comment rid="c_115r_03"/> And having done your cast, do not forget to make in
it some holes and <del><ill/></del>notches<comment rid="c_115r_02"/> because the metal will run more neatly thus than if
the cast were even, for it gets corrupted in its notches &amp; holes,
&amp; does not go so much at once, &amp; does not become as porous. This
done, <del>put</del> join <del><fr>t</fr></del><comment rid="c_115r_04"/> the two halves of your <tl>mold</tl> &amp; strengthen the joints,
putting around these some small <tl>clamps</tl> of iron wire of this shape<lb/>
<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p115r_2" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5aVlsV1BuajVVejQ">
</figure>. They
prevent<lb/> 
the <tl>molds</tl> from deforming &amp; corrupting while reheating.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p115r_3" size="small" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5aS1ZeHc2dGxJTE0">
</figure>
    
<figure id="fig_p115r_4" size="small" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Xzg4WTZ2NFNkOHM">
<caption>This is the shape of the <tl>clamps</tl></caption>
</figure>

</div>


<div id="p115r_1" categories="casting">

<head><del>Making the cast, reheating the <tl>molds</tl>, &amp;c</del><lb/>
Note about everything<lb/>
above <figure size="x-small" id="fig_p115r_5" link="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ObYzhoh2aRo0KXj3zbaJ08g2z-oNd5CR"></figure></head>

<ab>If your <al>snake</al> has been without eating for a <tmp>long time</tmp>, it
happens that, when you want to put it to death in <m><bp>urine</bp></m> &amp;
<m>vinegar</m>, it fills with a lot of <m>water</m> &amp; swells, and
next it dries out as you fix &amp; arrange it on the <m>clay</m>
<po>cake</po>, and next it happens that when you have cast your
<del><tl>mold</tl></del><comment rid="c_115r_05"/> <m>tempered sand</m> on it, &amp; it has set, it
ends up coming out such that between the <al>snake</al> and animal there
is a <ms>line</ms> of distance <del><fr>D</fr></del>, in which enters
the second batch of cast <m>tempered sand</m> <del><fr>M</fr></del>. Avoid this,
therefore, if you can. But if this cannot be, do not let this prevent
your second cast, for the <m>sand</m> which will enter in this void will be so
weak that it will easily be removed with a <tl>small point</tl> &amp;
will not have set with the first hardened one.</ab>

<ab>Note that one needs more <m>feather alum</m> for
<tl>molds</tl> that should be reheated, like those for <m>gold</m>
&amp; <m>silver</m> &amp; things that one needs to burn inside than for those which release well &amp; that are only for casting
<m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m>. However, do not put too much in either one. </ab>

</div>


<div id="p115r_2" categories="casting">

<head>Animal after release</head>

<ab>If, by chance, you gave your <al>snake</al> such a curled shape
that the place of the belly cannot easily come out, especially
since the head &amp; the tail, which are the two ends, are
thinner, cut everything which is outside, &amp; reheat the
<tl>mold</tl> so well that what remained inside burns, then pass some
<m>quicksilver</m> inside, &amp; attracting <del>that which</del>
the <m>ashes</m> &amp; the <m>burnt bones</m> from the inside, it will
also come out, because the conduit is big, &amp; thus will not sour at
all your material. You can pull really strongly the molded
<al>snake</al>, because it is soft &amp; malleable &amp; obedient, &amp;
the <tl>mold</tl>, having set, is so firm that, because of this, the
imprint will not be spoiled. </ab>

</div>

<div id="p115r_3" categories="casting">

<head>Reheating of <tl>Molds</tl></head>

<ab>After your <tl>molds</tl> have been reheated <del><fr>le p</fr></del>
&amp; cleaned, casting soonest is best, because if you keep them, they
get corrupted and moistened. Reheat the thickest part, where the body of the animal is, 
at the top, so that, if there is something inside to burn, it falls to the bottom.
Mark the part on top to recognize it.</ab>

<ab>It can only be good to let the <tl>mold</tl> die down a little from the outside 
<del>so long as</del>, being well reheated, so long as it remains red on the inside when you will cast.</ab>


</div>
</root>
