<root>
<page>063r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f131.image</image>

<div>

<id>p063r_1</id>

<head><pa>Amaranth</pa> color</head>

<ab>Although it is said to be immortal, it is nonetheless the case that
<m>white wine</m> removes its tint &amp; turns claret-colored, &amp; the dry <m>flower</m> ends up white afterwards. Note that thus
<m>wine</m><comment>c_063r_01</comment>, &amp; I have tried it. <m>Eau-de-vie</m> does as much.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p063r_2</id>

<head>Drying of <m>oil</m></head>

<ab>If the <m>oil</m> does not dry out, put in <m>massicot</m> &amp;
<m>minium</m>. There is no better <m>oil than <pa>walnut</pa></m>, for
it does not dry out too soon nor too late.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p063r_3</id>

<head>Casting</head>

<ab>The <pl>Germans</pl> use <m>lead from <pl>Flanders</pl></m> because
it is very soft. And to cast better they take <m>lead ore</m> &amp; melt
it, &amp; separate what is melted from the from the <m>filth</m> &amp;
<m>ore</m>, &amp; pour it into a separate <tl>vessel</tl>, then <del>the
bottom</del> they cast with it. For the <m>lead</m> must not have been
put to work before, but rather completely new. Some cast into <tl>molds
of <m>iron</m> &amp; <m>copper</m></tl>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

or new <m>lead</m> coming from the <env>mine</env>. They melt it twice
in a <tl>crucible</tl>. In the first one, they purge it of
<m>filth</m>. In the second, they <del>en</del> cast.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p063r_4</id>

<head>Shadows</head>

<ab><pl>German</pl> <pro>painters</pro> make their shadows on flesh
colour of people with ground <m>jet</m>, <m>stil de grain yellow</m>
&amp; <m>ochre</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p063r_5</id>

<head><m>Bistre</m></head>

<ab>It is only used in <m>distemper</m>, &amp; with this wood color is
made.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p063r_6</id>

<head><m>Verdigris</m> and another very beautiful bright green</head>

<ab>One ought not to grind it with <m>water</m> alone, for that makes it
die. To render it beautiful in <m>distemper</m>, some grind it with
<m>vinegar</m>, but that makes it turn pale &amp; become whitish. To
render it beautiful, grind it with <m><bp>urine</bp></m> &amp; leave to dry.
Then, whenever you like, grind it with <m>oil</m>. And after you have
collected it with the <tl>spatula</tl>, before finishing to clean the
<tl><m>marble</m></tl>, grind <m>stil de grain yellow</m> on it. And you
will have a very beautiful green.</ab>

</div>
</root>
