<root>
<page>052v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f110.item</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p052r_1</id>

<ab>Or to be safer, retire from there until the fire has died down &amp;
all is cooled, <del><fr>Ap</fr></del> for <md>its exhalation would be
dangerous</md>. And for the occasion when you
feed<comment>c_052v_01</comment> it with <tl>pincers</tl>,
<del><fr>b</fr></del> wash your <bp>mouth</bp> with <m>good vinegar</m>
&amp; take some preservative &amp; plug yourself up well. Once it is
dead, put it in a <m>linen</m> cloth or a canvas of <m>silk</m> &amp;
fold it &amp; hang it <env>from the ceiling, where the air
<del><add>or</add></del> &amp; sun dry it</env>. Once it is quite dry,
pulverize it in a <tl>mortar</tl>. And keep this powder carefully,
because one <tl>℥</tl> of this thrown on iii <ms>lb</ms> of <m>molten
♁</m> reduces it to <m>finer ☉ than the other one</m>. But it does not
have as much <comment>c_052v_02</comment> weight. For this work you also
need to choose the <m>oldest ♁</m> that you can, which has often been
melted &amp; finely hammered into sheets or other works, &amp; purify it
before by melting &amp; throwing it into <m>honey</m> &amp;
<m>vinegar</m>. The term of the work is nine <tmp>months</tmp> <tmp>from
the feast of <pn>Saint John</pn> until the 25th of April</tmp>.
</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p052v_1</id>

<head><pa>Linseed</pa></head>

<ab>Who wants to have it beautiful &amp; <del><fr>p</fr></del> very
delicate, one needs to pick it before the <del><fr>f<ill/>d</fr></del>
seed may be perfectly ripe. For if one waits for the seed to be
perfectly ripe, the foot is so dried by the sun that it is brittle &amp;
breakable. It is true that in this way the seed is reduced by a
third.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p052v_2</id>

<head>Colors</head>

<ab>If you want to keep them beautiful in <m>gum</m> and such that they
do not lose any of their natural color, put <m>white wine</m>, the
whitest and clearest you can, in a <tl>bottle</tl> with a little
<m>tragacanth gum</m>. And having <tl>stoppered</tl> the
<tl>bottle</tl>, scramble &amp; shake it very strongly together, &amp;
let it rest until the <m>tragacanth</m> is dissolved. Also put in a
little fine-grained <m><fr>sel blanc</fr></m> to brighten the whole.
Some mix <m>clear water</m> with <m>white wine</m>, and with this
mixture they temper the colors without grinding. And these show very
beautifully on <pro>illumination</pro> works.</ab></div>
</root>
