<root>
<page>115v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f236.image</image>

<div>
<id>p115v_1</id>
<head>Cast of <m>tin</m></head>

<ab>If the plant or flower that you want to cast <del>in tin</del> is
delicate &amp; fine, it is necessary that the <m>tin</m> exceeds
<m>lead</m> in the mixture &amp; on the contrary, if it is thick, it is
necessary that <m>lead</m> exceed. Therefore for the <del>mixture</del>
fine thing, put in some <m>fine tin</m>, not all the <ms>quarter
part</ms> of <m>lead</m>. And make sure that your <tl>mold</tl> is
<ms>hottish, such that you can hold it in your
<tl><bp>hand</bp></tl></ms>, when you want to cast. As for the
<m>alloyed tin</m>, the same as mentioned, it is necessary that it is
very hot &amp; almost red for casting, so that it penetrates. Otherwise,
having <add><fr>a</fr></add> to run the length of the fine branches of
the plant, it will get cold before arriving there. And do not forget to
mix in it a little <m>looking-glass tin</m>, which makes it run better
&amp; firms it up.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
In the <m>lead alloyed with tin</m>, or <m>tin alloyed with lead</m>,
you can put a little bit of <m><fr>metalline</fr></m> &amp; it will seem
<m>silver</m>. But do not put too much, for this hardens the substance
&amp; sours it also, so that for a delicate thing like legs &amp;
similar things, it would not be appropriate.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p115v_2</id>
<head>For giving vent to the <tl>mold</tl></head>

<ab>In addition to your vents, if your <del><fr>es</fr></del> plant is
very fine, you can pass a <tl>thread</tl> through the
<add><m>clay</m></add> circle, rather than casting with a
<tl>needle</tl>, &amp; make sure it passes through the plant. And with
<tl>thread</tl>, burning like the plant, a hole will remain, which will
give air &amp; venting, to help clean.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p115v_3</id>
<head>Reheating the <tl><fr>noyau</fr> molds</tl></head>

<ab>After your <tl>molds</tl> have their gate, vents &amp;
<tl>clamps</tl>, as mentioned, make at the end of the <tl>forge</tl>
<del><fr>en</fr></del>, or in some clean place, a surrounding of
<m>bricks</m>, and fill it with large half-lit charcoal. And place your
<tl>molds</tl> on top, and leave the charcoals thus to light by
themselves for a <ms><tmp>half hour</tmp></ms>, so that they heat little
by little and not all at once. Finally as they begin to become white,
beat <del><fr>little by little</fr></del> the thus half-lit large charcoals
on top &amp; blow with your <tl>little bellows</tl>, until they are
warmed. And thus, little <add>by little</add>, invigorate the fire,
without haste, until you <tl>mold</tl>s are well red on the outside
&amp; the inside. If it is for casting some plant or some animal which
does not release well &amp; in this case, one needs to burn
<add>it</add> in the <tl>mold</tl> &amp; when you look through the gate
&amp; through it you see the <tl>molds</tl> are very red &amp; inflamed
inside, this will be your signal that they are reheated enough. But if
you do not see this signal, increase &amp;continue the fire until it is
the case. If there is nothing in the <tl>mold</tl> that needs burning,
it will be enough that they are dried well on the same fire, if it is
for casting <m>tin</m>, they reheat better in a <tl>reverberatory
furnace</tl>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>figure/>
Do not pull out your <tl>reheated molds</tl> from the fire, before they
have cooled themselves &amp; take care that neither the <env>wind or the
cold</env> hits them while very hot, for this would make them burst. One
must not reheat them before they are dry and firmed up for they would
cast in a different way, and it is necessary beforehand to make gates
&amp; vents &amp; place <tl>clamps</tl>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<figure>

<id>fig_p115v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dHVja3NnV0dmMlk</link>

</figure>
Take care not to heat the fire in one go, for fear <del><fr>f</fr></del>
that your <tl>molds</tl> crack inside.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
They are reheated enough when the entire hole of the gate is red. When
it is black, it is not enough.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
For casting in <m>silver</m>, one must not reheat two times
<del>&amp;</del>, if there is nothing in the <tl>mold</tl> that needs
<del><fr>despouiller</fr></del> burning, simply because it does not
release well. All the <tl>molds of <pro>farriers</pro></tl> are reheated
two times, first for <figure/></ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
