<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="019r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f43.image">




<div continues="yes" id="p017r_1" categories="arms and armor">





<ab>

<wp>pieces</wp>. The <wp>falconet</wp> is loaded with a <tl>ladle</tl>, and one
commonly gives it only one <tl><ms>ladle</ms></tl>. There are also
other <wp>falconets</wp> weighing three <ms>quintals</ms>, and which
are nine <ms><fr>pans</fr></ms> long. Their ball weighs <ms>half a
lb</ms>. Their charge is a quarter of <m>powder</m>. It is loaded
either with a <tl>ladle</tl>, but more commonly with a charge. <ms>At the
breech, 3 balls, &amp; 2 in front</ms>. To the small <wp>pieces</wp> which
are under 3 <ms>quintals</ms> one gives them at least <ms>3 balls
&amp; a twelfth part of a ball</ms> at the breech, &amp; sometimes
takes away from the front to make this addition to the breech, according
to the length one gives them.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



The strength of the <wp>piece</wp> is at the level of the trunnion, which is the
point of departure of the lit <m>powder</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



The strength of the <fr>berche</fr> is at the
<fr>maslée</fr><comment rid="c_019r_01"/>, &amp; at the back of the
breech.

</ab>

<ab>

A <wp>double musket</wp> weighs 2 <ms>quintal</ms>s, is seven
<ms><fr>pans</fr></ms> long, carries a ball of a quarter of a

<ms>lb</ms> or a little less. <ms>At the breech 3 <ms>balls</ms>, two in
front</ms>. One loads it with as much <m>powder</m> as <ms>ball</ms>, <ms>up to the top of
the escutcheon</ms>,<comment rid="c_018v_02"/> which in these <wp>small pieces</wp> can amount to <add>3

or</add> 4 <ms>balls</ms> of <m><wp>arquebus</wp> powder</m>. For if one uses
<m><wp>cannon</wp> powder</m>, one can load it to a <ms>thickness of <del><fr>c</fr></del>
five balls</ms>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



One needs to understand all of this as <m>iron</m> balls. When one
shoots a <m>metal</m> ball, one over-charges by a quarter
<tl><ms>ladle</ms></tl> because if a <wp>cannon</wp> ball weighs 40
<ms>lb</ms>, the <m>metal</m> one weighs lx <ms>lb</ms>. One also takes
the gun-sight higher when shooting a <m>metal</m> ball. For if one
shoots an <corr><del><m>iron</m></del></corr> <m>iron</m> ball point-blank, one takes six <ms>lines</ms>
higher when shooting <m>metal</m> balls. A <m>metal</m> ball <del>makes</del>
alloyed with <m>copper</m>, in order that it is not frangible, is more
effective hitting at close range than that of <m>iron</m>. But the
<m>iron</m> one hits more fiercely from afar. </ab>

<ab>

A <wp>simple musket</wp> weighs one <ms>quintal</ms>, is six
<ms><fr>pans</fr></ms> long. <del>carries a ball weighing <ill/>
<fr>qu</fr></del> One has no consideration for those which are under two
<ms>quintal</ms>s, which readily carry <m>lead</m> balls
<del><fr>un</fr></del> of the weight of the ball, but of the caliber.
However, those which can receive balls of <m>metal</m> or <m>iron</m> do
better because they will penetrate more than six <m>lead</m> ones. Its
charge is <ms>up to the escutcheon</ms>, namely the <ms>thickness of 4
balls</ms>. </ab>

<ab>

<fr><wp>Arquebus à croc</wp></fr> weighs lx <ms>lb</ms>, that is to say the large one is
five <ms><fr>pans</fr></ms> long, its charge is <ms>up to the
escutcheon</ms>, namely <ms><add>the length of</add> 4 balls</ms>, it

carries <m>lead</m> balls, and is for the defence of houses. Of these
<fr><wp>arquebus à croc</wp></fr>, both the large &amp; the small ones, one makes <wp>orgues</wp>
which are <del>or</del> appropriate for an assault, both outside &amp;
inside the place. They are founded separately as if to serve for uses
other than <wp>orgues</wp>. See the marked 4th leaf following.

<figure id="fig_p019r_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5WWY3VjdlVktqZVk">



    <comment rid="c_019r_02"/>

</figure>

</ab>

</div>
</root>
