<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="114v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f234.image">




<div continues="yes" id="p114r_1" categories="casting" continued="yes">

<ab><lb/><lb/><lb/>This thus prepared, place your <del><fr>de</fr></del> first
half-<tl>mold</tl> on the <po>cake</po> of <del><m>earth</m></del>
<m>clay</m>, &amp; put the circle also around, &amp; make the mark for
the thickness similar to the first. Then, with another rather thickish
<tl>paintbrush</tl>, moisten well everywhere the uncovered half
<del>&amp; the belly</del> of your animal
<del>And</del> <add>with <m>eau-de-vie</m></add>,
without leaving anything, if it is possible, which is not moistened, for
this is the secret which makes it come out neat. And next, as promptly
as will be possible for you, before the <m>eau-de-vie</m>
<del>not</del> evaporates, wet your <m>sand</m> and cast it in thrusts and by blowing &amp; moving the <tl>mold</tl> as you did
for the first one, making sure that the <del>first <fr>q</fr></del>
beginning of that which you pour on the animal should be a little lighter than the
next one so that it moistens everywhere &amp; closely follows the more delicate
parts. So, leave it for a <ms><tmp>quarter of an hour</tmp></ms> to set, then
remove the circle &amp; the <m>clay</m> <po>cake</po>. And, with a
<tl>knife</tl>, arrange your two <tl>molds</tl> uniformly together in a
long shape of a <mu>mandore</mu>, as mentioned, because of the cast.
Then, dip a little the whole <tl>mold</tl> evenly, at the level of the
joints, in <m>water</m>, for this is another secret to unjoin them,
otherwise you will break everything.</ab>

<ab>Separate them nimbly, therefore, by
this means, and next, extract gently &amp; with patience and method
the half of the animal remaining in one of the <tl>molds</tl>,
<del>for</del> pulling it sometimes from one side &amp; sometimes from
the other, to avoid breaking any of it, or also spoiling something from
the <tl>mold</tl>. <del>And</del> The latter being empty,
<del>extract</del> rejoin the two halves so that no dust
enters it, &amp; put them aside until you want to reheat them, make the
gate &amp; vents, &amp; place the <tl>clamps</tl>. As for the animal, so
that it does not dry &amp; that you might be able to mold it four of
five times, put it in <m>water</m>. And I think that it would keep even
better in <m>eau-de-vie</m>. However, the best would be to mold
in the same <tmp>day</tmp> the 4 or 5 <tl>molds</tl> that you can do,
because these corrupt animals in themselves <sn>stink</sn> within one <ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms>. Having left your <tl>molds</tl> one or two
<del><fr>es</fr></del> <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms> to dry, for they stay
humid for a good <ms><tmp>month</tmp></ms>, make the vents on one
half <figure size="x-small" id="fig_p114v_3" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dkk3MW10YzNIbDg">
</figure><comment rid="c_114v_01"/></ab>


<ab margin="left-middle">
<figure size="small" id="fig_p114v_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dmlRQm1lTjc4aXc">
</figure><lb/>
<mark>+</mark><lb/> Note that when you have made your second
<add>cast</add>, were you to leave your <tl>mold</tl> for one
<ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms> or a <ms><tmp>night</tmp></ms> without opening
it, you would need to then dip it in <m>hot water</m> or else reheat it
before opening it, as for <al>crabs</al>.</ab>


<ab margin="left-middle">

If, after both halves of the <fr>noyau</fr> have made a strong &amp; hard set, you
would not dip your <tl>mold</tl> in <m>water</m>, it would not unjoin at
all. But as you dip the reverse of the <tl>mold</tl> in <m>water</m>,
the imbibed <m>oil</m> collects at the top &amp; at the level of the
joints &amp; makes it separate.</ab>


<ab margin="left-middle">

However, take heed your second <tl>mold</tl> is of good thickness &amp;
that it is hard enough because if it is lacking in this, after having
dipped it in <m>water</m>, &amp; you want to open it, there is a risk
that it breaks. Take heed therefore to avoid this, and wanting to open
it, dip all of it in <m>water</m> <add>and rub it everywhere</add>,
where it will harden if it has set well. Then, take your two
<tl>molds</tl>, joined with a <tl>rough <m>linen</m> cloth</tl> in
order to have a better grip, and separate them with strength as if you
wanted to tear apart a loaf of <m>bread</m>. But if it happens to break, join
it &amp; on the reverse, strengthen the joints with <tl>clamps</tl>.

<figure size="x-small" id="fig_p114v_4" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NmZxVUxKTmhYSXM">
</figure>

</ab>


<ab margin="bottom">

Next, you can repair the faults with small <tl>chisels</tl>.

</ab>

</div>
</root>
