<root>
<page>132r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f269.item.r=</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p131v_1</id>

<ab>to not open your <m>mold</m> too hot, for this sours it, makes it
porous &amp; contracts the <m>tin</m> &amp; makes the molded thing
break. Also, do not quench your hot <tl>mold</tl> in <m>water</m>, for
this makes the <del><fr>le met</fr></del> <m>tin</m> or <m>lead</m>
contract.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p132r_1</id>
<head><tl>Mold</tl> made in two casts</head>

<ab>It is opened, once reheated, to be cleaned, next, one puts the
<tl>clamps</tl> on again, one <m>lutes</m> the <tl>mold</tl> &amp;
especially the joints, then one slowly dries the <m>earth</m>. And then,
as it no longer smokes, one leaves the <tl>mold</tl> to cool until you
hold it without harm. Next, put in the <tl>presses</tl> or in the sand
in a <tl><fr>terrine</fr></tl>, &amp; cast in <m>tin</m>. For if you
were to cast in <m>silver</m> or <m>gold</m>, it would be necessary that
your <tl>mold</tl> be reheated twice &amp; cast, as it would be
red.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
If your <tl>mold</tl> <del><fr>f</fr></del>, through the fault of the
<m>plaster</m>, retracts <add>in the fire</add>, one needs to open it,
after the first reheating, to tighten it again &amp; <tl>clamp</tl> it
and <m>lute</m> again and tighten again. </ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p132r_2</id>
<head>Method for reheating the <tl>molds</tl></head>

<ab>Light <m>charcoals</m> in the <tl>forge</tl>, &amp; then arrange
them in rows in a corner of it, according to the size of your
<tl>mold</tl>, in such a way that it can be furnished with three or 4
<ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> all around, and especially at the bottom of
the <tl>mold</tl>, which is the thickest, <del>and which</del>. Your
<m>charcoals</m> thus arranged, place your <tl>molds</tl> on top of
them, &amp; not on a <tl><fr>grille</fr></tl>, as some do, because they
would take the fire too harshly. And leave for some time thus, &amp;
little &amp; by little warm your <tl>oven</tl>, always adding some lit
<m>charcoal</m>. And as long as the <tl>mold</tl> is damp, the
<m>charcoals</m> will be as if died down from below. But as it dries,
they will light themselves. And when it is dry on one side, turn it to
the other. And when it is dry on both, &amp; it no longer smokes. At
that moment, invigorate the fire &amp; cover it with lit
<m>charcoals</m>. And as it begins to redden, do not blow the
<m>charcoals</m> with a <tl>little bellows</tl>, for this would make it
<del>blow</del> burst. And similarly, when it is red, keep it well
covered with lit <m>charcoals</m> &amp; do not uncover it, for it would
crack. Make sure <env>wind from a window</env> does not beat on it. Let
cool</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
When you want to reheat your <tl>molds</tl>, <del>&amp;</del> be they
<m>luted</m> or not, mark the place on the belly to put it under,
against the lit <m>charcoals</m> <del><fr>que</fr></del> because if the
ardor of the fire would make them crack, it would be better that this be
at the belly &amp; from underneath, than on the back.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
@If your <tl>mold</tl> is small, one ought not to leave it
<del>rest</del> so much in the fire, for it corrupts and cracks there,
for it reheats more quickly than a big one.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
