<root>
<page>035r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f75.image</image>

<div>

<id>p035r_1</id>

<head>For telling someone that you will <del>show</del> teach him something
he does not know, and neither do you</head>

<ab>Take a <tl>string</tl> or a <tl>small stick</tl> and take the
measurement <ms>from the tip of his <bp>ear</bp> to the tip of his
<bp>nose</bp></ms> and show it to him. Thus you will teach him something
you did not know, and neither did he.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p035r_2</id>

<head>For supporting a <tl>bucket</tl> of water on the tips of three
<tl>knives</tl> laid down without touching the ground</head>

<figure>

<id>fig_p035r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SGstUTZ6TFRnUjg</link>

</figure>

<ab>According to the strength of your <tl>knives, either
<env>kitchen</env> or table</tl>, you will make them support a large
weight on their tips laid down &amp; arranged in a triangle, edge to
edge, as you can see, &amp; they would not touch the ground. And if,
after arranging them this way, you turn them the other way without
unjoining them, the tips of the handles can also support a large weight
without touching the ground. You can just as well adapt this to another
use with <tl>pikes, with joists</tl>, or to promptly make a tripod in a
camp with three <tl>halberd points</tl>. If the edge of the
<tl>knife</tl> marked A faces from right to left, the butts of the
handles will rise, but if the edge of the same <tl>knife</tl> faces from
left to right, the tips will rise.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p035r_3</id>

<head>For boiling an <m>egg</m> in <m>cold water</m> without fire</head>

<ab>Empty an <m>egg</m> from both ends so that nothing remains inside,
then fill it with <m>quicklime</m> &amp; <m>natural sulphur</m>, then
stop the holes with <m>wax</m> &amp; put it in <m>water</m> so that it
floats by two or three <ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p035r_4</id>

<head>For making <al>rabbits</al> come out of a <env>burrow</env></head>

<ab>Take some <m>embers</m> in a <tl>pot</tl>, &amp; having put
<m>sulphur</m> on top, put it in the <env>burrows</env> &amp; block it
with something light.</ab>

</div>
</root>
