<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="007r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f19.image">




<div id="p007r_1">

<head>For gilding with <m>gold color</m> and <m>tinsel</m></head>

<ab>Once you have <del>gilded</del> <add>colored</add>, make your
stamping either in <m>tin</m>, as is said,<comment rid="c_007r_01"/> or
in <m>iron</m> <del><fr>dest</fr></del> or <m>copper</m>. You ought not
to put a layer of <m>glue</m> there as on <m>wood</m>, but take only
<m>fatty oil</m>, which is made in seven or eight <ms>days</ms> <env>in
the sun</env> with <m>walnut oil</m> and <m>lead white</m> <del>&amp;
with</del>, stirring it often, or cooking it on the fire if one is in
haste. Then, with the <m>oil</m> thus made fatty, grind a little <m>lead
white</m>, <m>massicot</m> &amp; <m><fr>mine de plomb</fr></m><comment rid="c_007r_04"/>
<del><ill/></del>, at discretion, as much of one as of the other.
<m>Minium</m> gives color to the <m>gold</m>. Next, with this, you make
a layer of it evenly on your stamping, taking care not to fill the hollows.
And once it is almost dry, lay the <m>gold</m> leaf on it with
<m>cotton</m>. Such <m>gold</m> will hold up <env>in the rain</env> on
houses &amp; elsewhere. And if you have gilded with <m>tinsel</m>, color
it with <m>smoke of partridge<comment rid="c_007r_05"/> or of yellow or red
<m>cloth</m></m>, &amp; it will be beautiful like fine <m>gold</m>. You can
cover trunks, mirrors, valences &amp; bedposts with colored
<m>velvet</m> or <m>satin</m>, then apply the gilded stampings
on top with <m>strong glue</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p007r_2">

<head>For coloring stamped trunks</head>

<ab>The stampings of <m>sheets of copper or latten</m> is made on engraved &amp; carved
<m><pa>service tree</pa><comment rid="c_007r_02"/> wood</m>, if one wants to spend less. And next, the stamped object is
colored with the aforesaid colors of <m>lake</m>, <m>verdet</m>,
<m><fr>azur d’esmail</fr></m>, &amp; tempered in <m>turpentine varnish</m>.
But in the place you want to <m>azure</m>, lay down <m><fr>fer
blanc</fr></m>, which is more appropriate for an <m>azure</m>
background.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p007r_3">

<head>Doublets<comment rid="c_007r_06"/></head>

<ab>Good <m><al>dragon</al>’s blood</m> soaked in <m>eau-de-vie</m>
carries its <m>mastic</m> or <m>glue</m> in itself, as do
<m>sap-green</m> &amp; <m><pa>saffron</pa></m>.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p007r_4">

<head><m><al>Fish</al> glue</m> or <m>isinglass</m> <add>and
<m><bp>mouth</bp> glue</m></add></head>

<ab>It is made from <m><al>codfish</al> skin</m>, boiled rather than
being <m>salted</m>. <pro>Joiners</pro> <m>glue</m> their masterpieces
with it and <pro><mu>guitar</mu> makers</pro> use it for delicate works.
It wants to be strongly beaten, then soaked gently in <m>barely boiling
water</m>.</ab>

<ab><m><bp>Mouth</bp> glue</m> is made of <m>parchment scrapings</m> and
one uses it without fire, for <m>glueing</m> <m>paper</m> or similar things, 
wetting it with the <tl><bp>mouth</bp></tl>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

One beats it and soaks it in <del>in <m>eau-de-vie</m></del> <del>of
<m>vinegar</m></del> <m>white wine</m> <ms>for one
<tmp>night</tmp></ms>, then one melts it on a slow fire. Others soak
it in <m>eau-de-vie</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
