<root>
<page>130r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f265.item.r=</image>

<div>

<id>p130r_1</id>

<head>Animals dried in an <tl>oven</tl></head>

<ab>Small <del><fr>s</fr></del> <al>cats</al> are skinned and one
removes their eyes &amp;all their entrails. One puts a <tl>small
stick</tl> vertically between their teeth to make them open their mouths
wide. Then with <tl><m>iron points</m></tl> one attaches their feet to a
<tl>small board</tl>, giving them the fitting attitude &amp; gait. Once
thus attached by their feet <add>with <tl>small rings of <m>iron
wire</m></tl></add>, one needs to suspend them <env>in the sun</env>
with their spines downwards. In this manner they take
<del><fr>&amp;d</fr></del> their shape &amp; dry, &amp; the belly
tightens &amp; the tail remains high <add>or with the bend that you will
have given it</add>. Once a little dry by this means, one turns the head
as one wants, securing it with some tool. Then one finishes drying it in
an <tl>oven</tl> when the bread is drawn. Next, one places in its
eye sockets <tl>balls of <m>lead</m> or of <m>wax</m></tl>, painted
according to nature. One paints them with <m>well-gummed ink</m> so that
they seem to be jet. One gives it a painted tongue, horns, wings &amp;
similar fantasies. Thus for <al>rats</al> &amp; all animals.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<figure>

<id>fig_p130r</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5cHVsNnNVQ1l5RnM</link>

</figure>

which surround the fingers of the <corr>paws</corr> and which stick in
the jacket of <m>clay</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p130r_2</id>

<head>For reddening live <al>crayfish</al>, which will seem
boiled</head>

<ab>Rub them in <m>quite good vinegar</m>, in which there should be a
little <m>eau-de-vie</m> &amp; hardly any, &amp; they can be served as
if cooked &amp; will walk along.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p130r_3</id>

<head>Molding a single <al>spider</al></head>

<ab>One needs to plant it on the <tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl>, as has been
said, on a <pa>vine</pa> leaf, and make there your first cast &amp; once
it has set, uncover the <m>spider</m> up to half its legs, then make the
second cast.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<corr><del>In order</del></corr> The hairy feet of large
<al>spiders</al>, like any animal hair, does not mold well if it is not
flattened, having anointed it with <m><pa>wheat</pa> oil</m>, which
stiffens it &amp; is quickly dry. Hairy things mix with the sand &amp;
do not burn well.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p130r_4</id>

<head>Molding a single <pa>vine</pa> leaf</head>

<ab>Plant it with the <tl>points of fine <del>iron</del> <m>latten
wire</m></tl> &amp; place diagonally on the <tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl>,
then cast the first <tl>mold</tl>. Having set, uncover the
<del>back</del> reverse &amp; make the second cast, which once set, you
can take away the leaf. And you will need to reheat your <tl>mold</tl>
only once, because there will be nothing to burn.</ab>

</div>
</root>
