<root>
<page>062r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f129.image</image>

<div>

<id>p062r_1</id>

<head>Perspectives</head>

<ab>Perspectives in <m>oil</m> <tmp>take a long time</tmp> because of
several lines that need to be done with a <tl>ruler</tl>, and for this
reason one usually does them in <m>distemper</m>. One takes the points
<add>at</add> one’s discretion. The main thing in having the knowledge
of the point. One usually makes two or three of them, sometimes
five.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p062r_2</id>

<head><m>Ochre</m></head>

<ab>It is put for faces, hair, skulls and rocks.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p062r_3</id>

<head>Distant people and animals</head>

<ab>One first does them roughly in gray or in purple, which is made of
<m><fr>cendre d’azur</fr></m> &amp; <m>lake</m>. Once dry, one
highlights &amp; finishes with flesh tones &amp; other colors &amp;
white. And it looks better &amp; is sooner done than in white &amp;
black. Armies<ill/> are painted thus.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p062r_4</id>

<head>Drawing</head>

<ab>After you have primed your panel &amp; scraped with a <tl>knife</tl>
to render it quite even, you will start drawing with the longest piece
of <tl><m>charcoal</m></tl> you can find, for with a short one you would
not see your line so well &amp; would do it more roughly. Let the tip of
the <tl><m>charcoal</m></tl> be thin, &amp; in order not to render it
dull &amp; blunt soon, drag the tip flat, thus you will constantly
sharpen it. Also, hold your <tl><m>charcoal</m></tl> as far at the end
as you can, <del>&amp; do it</del> &amp; accustom yourself
<del><fr>af</fr></del> make a light line. For if you accustom yourself
to drawing delicately with <tl><m>charcoal</m></tl>, you will do
likewise with colors. And he who is rough<comment>c_062r_02</comment>
with <tl><m>charcoal</m></tl> is never excellent with colors. And by a
line of <m>charcoal</m>, <pro>masters</pro> pass judgement on their
<pro>apprentices</pro>. First make the outline of your drawing, that is
the contour, lightly &amp; without any too careful work, but boldly. In
so doing, you will teach yourself to be an <pro>artist</pro>, and if you
need to to undo anything, you will not waste as much time as if you had
elaborated it. Next, re-work all the distinctive lines, &amp; do not keep
too close to your panel, but occasionally step away from it to better
judge the proportions. Once the first drawing seems good to you, retrace
all the lines with the <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> in rose color or
another color in <m>gum</m> or <m>distemper</m>. Thus you will work more
confidently with colors, and with less <add>effort</add>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
