<root>
<page>060v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f126.item</image>

<div>

<id>p060v_1</id>

<head><m>Varnish</m> dry in an <ms><tmp>hour</tmp></ms></head>

<ab>Take <m>white <add>turpentine</add> oil</m> <add>&amp;</add>
<m>turpentine</m> &amp; <m>mastic, pulverized &amp; passed delicately
through a <tl>sieve</tl></m>, &amp; boil them together, stirring
continuously with a <tl>stick</tl> until it is dry. And put in two
<ms><fr>liards</fr></ms> of good <m>eau-de-vie</m>. And if you extract
the tear of <m>mastic</m>, it will be whiter &amp; clearer. There is no
need to put in <m>turpentine</m>, but only its <m>white turpentine
oil</m> &amp; <m>mastic pulverized</m> at your discretion, until it has
enough body. <mark>+</mark></ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>+</mark>

which you will know when, being placed on a <tl>knife</tl> <env>in the
wind</env>, it does not run. This one is excellent for panels and is dry
within an <ms><tmp>hour</tmp></ms> and does not stick like the
<m>turpentine</m> one.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p060v_2</id>

<head>Cleaning panels</head>

<ab>Some clean them with <m>soapy water</m>, others with <m><bp>urine</bp></m>,
others with <m>white wine</m>, for dust spoils the colors.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p060v_3</id>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>

<render>tall</render>

<head><m><pa>Spike lavender</pa> oil</m></head>

One ought not to not put any into colors for it is so brisk and
penetrating that it makes the colors flake, which next come off. And for
this reason, <pro>painters</pro> use it to clean their <tl>oil
<fr>pinceaulx</fr></tl> when they have become hard, for it renders them
soft &amp; clean immediately, penetrating the dry color which encrusts
them. Also, <pro>painters</pro>, sometimes envious of the work
undertaken by another, <tmp>in the evening</tmp> secretly pour a few
drops of <m><pa>spike lavender</pa> <del>on the</del> oil</m> on the top
edge of the panel such that, running down, it makes a stain that
penetrates as far as the <m>wood</m> &amp; destroys the colors such
that, to make the work even &amp; of an equal composition, they are
forced to do everything again and thus lose their work.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p060v_4</id>

<head><m>Wood</m> color</head>

<ab>

One gives a layer of <m>bistre</m>, then a coat of
<m>varnish</m>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p060v_5</id>

<head>Work of the <pl>Flemish</pl></head>

<ab>They do all their works in <m>oil</m> with the <tl>tip of the
<fr>pinceau</fr></tl>, in <del><fr>f</fr></del> the fashion of good
<pro>illuminators</pro>, and grind their colors very finely, protect
against dust, and often clean from their <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> the
bits of <m>hair</m> which they sometimes leave there, for if these
should remain on the work <del>it this</del>, it would prevent neat
working, which they are very careful about. In this way their work
appears very soft, especially in small work, in which one needs to apply
more diligence because one looks at them more closely. They
<corr>usually</corr> finish the forehead, then the eyes, next the nose,
finally the mouth and the rest. But they do not proceed like some others
who <del><fr>fo</fr></del> layer two or three different flesh tones, one
yellowish &amp; the other darker, because the colors always mix &amp;
finally die. They simply <del><ill/></del> make their underlayer
<corr>properly</corr>.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
