<root>
<page>125v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f256.item</image>

<div>
<id>p125v_1</id>
<head><al>Vipers</al> and <al>snakes</al></head>

<ab>

I molded a <al>viper</al>, which, for casting, is more appropriate than
any other <al>snake</al>, because it has scales beautiful &amp; very
visible on all the body &amp; principally on the head and under the
throat. It has a flat head, the snout reddish, tending towards
carnation, &amp; snubbed like the <al>horned aspic</al> or like
<del><fr>un</fr></del> the top of a <al>pig</al>'s snout, big jowls, the
eyes very close to the snout, and the mouth wide open, where it
<add>has</add> double canine teeth on each side, all coming out of a
strip of flesh that covers and clothed them. It also has, in the throat,
a tube of flesh, made like a <al>dog</al>'s penis, from which comes its
stinger. Other <al>snakes</al> have a double row of teeth.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>

If you want <del>cut</del> <del>the</del> to mold the <al>snakes</al>
their mouths open, you must cut off the head &amp; leave it inside, for
it will not be released.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p125v_2</id>
<head>Molding <al>turtles</al></head>

<ab>

It is a particular manner than the casting of <al>snakes</al> &amp;
plants and flowers, because the cavities that are between the two shells
require several pieces. They are molded in <m>plaster</m> to be cast in
<m>sugar</m> without making a gate, as do all other things, that you
want.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p125v_3</id>
<head><m>Plaster</m> for casting in <m>wax</m></head>

<ab>

When you want to cast in <m>wax</m> in the <tl><m>plaster</m> mold</tl>,
you must know as secret that there is need for your <tl>mold</tl> to be
in <m>hot water</m>. Never does the animal come out so neatly than in
<m>metal</m>, because the <m>wax</m> sticks. But it is to model an
animal as close to the natural <del><fr>et</fr></del>, to repair
it afterwards. One needs to smooth well away all the scales, <del>when</del> for
<m>wax</m> would enter there, &amp; not release well. In molding thus
the animal, flatten down the scales <add>for</add> <m>wax</m>, &amp;, on
the contrary, rub them in reverse in order that they stand up, for
animals, for they will only be more visible. Also, do not wait for the
<m>wax</m> to <del><fr>un peu</fr></del> cool completely to release it,
but do so when it is still a bit warm. When you have also molded the
first cast of the animal, uncover well the half, in order that, in its
release, there is as much of it in one half than in the other. Make also
strong wide gates, close to the animal, in order that it is fortified
when it is released, &amp; afterwards you cut this off.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<mark>+</mark> <m>Alabaster</m>, commonly called so, is nevertheless
<m>plaster</m>, is very hard, but it shrinks a lot. It is very good to
make medals, but it wants to be very finely sieved.</ab>

</div>
</root>
