<root>
<page>109r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f223.image</image>

<div>

<id>p109r_1</id>

<head>Modelling in <m>wax</m></head>

<ab>When <m>wax</m> is too hard, one mixes in <m>turpentine</m> or a
little <m>butter</m>, which <del><fr>sont pl</fr></del> renders the
<m>wax</m> more amiable, and more appropriate than the <m>tallow</m>
that the <pl>Italians</pl> put in, because one has to, often, put the
<tl>tools</tl> in the <bp>mouth</bp>, which are better in <m><pa>box
wood</pa></m> or <m>bone of <al>hart</al></m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p109r_2</id>

<head><m>Wax</m> for molding <mark>-</mark></head>

<ab>As the <m>wax</m> is melted, they have <m>sulphur</m> that is
melted, in a <tl>spoon</tl> or <tl>crucible</tl>, &amp; they pour some
in the <m>melted wax</m>. And the <m>sulphur</m> going to the bottom or
remaining on top, it leaves &amp; mixes only its substance amongst the
<m>wax</m>, &amp; renders it more meltable when warming it, such that
having molded, it melts in the mold gently, like butter, without leaving
any gently melts in the <tl>mold</tl> like <m>butter</m>, without
leaving any pustule or bubble in it. Also be warned to not give it too
much fire.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>If</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p109r_3</id>

<head>Molding <m>wax</m></head>

<ab>In order that your <tl>mold</tl> grips, without repelling in any place, on
a shape or image of <m>wax</m>, one needs to anoint it with <m>oil</m>
and moisten your sand with <m>lukewarm water</m>, for the <m>cold
water</m> would furthermore repel the <m>oil</m> &amp; would not make a
good ground on it.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

Anoint well, very lightly, with <m>oil</m>, so little that it hardly
appears. Then rub with some <m>eau-de-vie</m>. Next, moisten your sand
with <m>lukewarm water</m> so that it does not repel the
<m>oil</m>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p109r_4</id>

<head><tl>Bellows</tl> of the <tl>forge</tl></head>

<ab>It is best that they be fixed in on some piece of
<fr>membreure</fr>, through the <fr>portevent</fr>,
<del><fr>q</fr></del> for they are more secure, next you can lightly
secure them from above. It is necessary that the <fr>tuelle</fr> be 4
<ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> on the sole of the <tl>forge</tl>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p109r_5</id>

<head><al>Snakes</al> for molding</head>

<ab>When you take them for molding, if it is possible, do not remove
their teeth if you want to keep them. For, having had their teeth
removed, they get sore gums &amp; mouth, &amp; can no longer eat. You
can keep them in a <tl>barrel</tl> full of <m>bran</m> or even better of
<m>earth</m>, <env>in a cool place</env>, or in a <tl><m>glass</m>
bottle</tl>. And give them some live <al>frog</al> or other live animal
for they eat nothing dead. Also I have noticed that</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
