<root>
<page>057r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f119.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p056v_1</id>

<ab>

<m>Lake</m> takes long to dry in <m>oil</m> and for that reason one must
grind <m>glass</m> in it. But one needs to choose <m>crystallin</m>
because it is neater. And because it would be too difficult to grind by
itself, one must redden it on the fire, then when entirely red throw it
into cold <m>water</m>, &amp; it will crumble &amp; pulverize
easily for grinding afterwards. Being well ground <del>it</del> with a lot of
<m>water</m>, it resembles ground <m>lead white</m>, but for this it has
no body. I think it would be good for casting.</ab>

<ab>

<m>Lead white</m> is made with <m>sheet lead</m> beaten subtle &amp; put
under the <m>dung</m>.</ab>

<ab>

<m>White varnish of <m>turpentine</m> or of <m><pa>spike lavender</pa>
oil</m> and <m>turpentine</m></m> is colored with <m>pulverized
<fr>terra emerita</fr></m>, making it boil together. It gives agold
color on <m>silver</m> and more beautiful if it is burnished. It is dry
in <tmp>a quarter of an hour</tmp>. <m>Aloe</m> would make brighter
color, but it takes long to dry &amp; the other is dry in <tmp>a quarter
of an hour</tmp>, <tmp>in winter</tmp> as well as
<tmp>summer</tmp>.</ab>

<ab>

Good <m>lake</m> moistened with <m>saliva</m> is promptly rendered dark.
That from <pl>Florence</pl> is too gummed.</ab>

<ab>

If you make a layer of <m><pro>printers</pro>' ink</m> on <m>velvet</m>
and there apply <m>gold leaf</m> and then stretch the <m>velvet</m>, it
will appear grainy as if there were <m>gold powder</m> disseminated on
it.</ab>

<ab>

<m>Vermilion</m> ground by itself is wan and pale, but ground after
<m>lake</m>, it is more beautiful.</ab>

<ab>For taking the fattiness from <tl><m>marbles</m></tl>, one grinds
<m>ordinary ashes</m> on it, which is good afterwards to make the first
primer coat of a panel that is prepared in <m>oil</m> in order to seal
the cracks &amp; chinks of the <m>wood</m>. It has more body than
<m>chalk</m> &amp; it has <del><m>chalk</m></del> a certain fattiness.
One mixes it with the aforesaid <m>chalk</m> or <del><fr>ra</fr></del>
with the colors collected from the <tl>vessel</tl> where one cleans the
<tl><fr>pinceaulx</fr></tl>. It is desiccative and spares colors.
<del>On</del> Once this primer coat is made on the <m>wood</m>, one
scrapes with a <tl>knife</tl> to even it. Next, one makes a second coat
of <m>ceruse</m> or of the <add>poorest</add> colors mixed together. In
a painting in <m>oil</m> <add>on <m>canvas</m></add>, one applies only
one coat, and the same <m>ashes</m> can be used there. Also, after one
has ground a color, one grinds some <m>pith of coarse bread</m> on it to
remove the fattiness from the <tl><m>marble</m></tl>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
