<root>
<page>033r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f71.image</image>

<div>

<id>p033r_1</id>

<head><tl>Knife</tl> for cutting the <bp>nose</bp> or a
<bp>finger</bp></head>

<figure>

<id>fig_p033r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5RWlDQlc4cU5HN3M</link>

</figure>

<ab>This is a <tl>well-furbished knife</tl>, <tl>nailed</tl> through the
middle in such a way that it easily moves to one side &amp; the other
&amp; the side <del><ill/></del> A, is hidden inside its <tl>handle</tl>
marked C as readily as the side B. The two tenons you see at the tip of
the <tl>knife</tl> are for locking it on one side or the other against a
<tl>nail</tl> which is at the butt of the aforesaid <tl>handle</tl>, in order 
that, when one wants to press hard <add>on</add> something to
cut it, it does not come out from the <tl>handle</tl>. You may allow the
side marked B to cut for demonstration purposes, <add>but not
much</add>, but the side that is notched <del>A</del> and marked A must
not cut. <del>It</del> It is sufficient that it be furbished well. And
also the notch needs to be as thick as <ms>the back of a
<tl>knife</tl></ms> in order that it cannot cause <sn>pain</sn>. And you
will only show the part of the <tl>knife</tl> which is not notched, for
the side with the notch needs to be <del><fr>mar</fr></del> hidden
inside the <tl>handle</tl>. And when you want to cut the <bp>nose</bp>
or a <bp>finger</bp>, pretend to sharpen your <tl>knife</tl> on the
<bp>thigh</bp> and, while <del>while</del> doing this, turn the
<tl>knife</tl> deftly. &amp; the part with the notch, which you will
cover <del><fr>l</fr></del> with one <bp>finger</bp>, will come into
your <bp>hand</bp>, and you will place the notch, colored with
<m>brazilwood rosette</m> or <m><pa>black cherry</pa> juice</m>, upon
the <bp>nose</bp>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

The <pro>conjuror</pro> ought not to amuse himself by watching what he
is doing, but look at the <pro>spectators</pro> and give them plenty of
good hocus-pocus words so that they look at his <bp>face</bp> &amp; not
at his <bp>hands</bp>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p033r_2</id>

<figure>

<id>fig_p033r_3</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5TXhGbkNoNTFHZ0E</link>

</figure>

<head>For relighting an extinguished <tl>candle</tl> between your
<bp>hands</bp> without blowing</head>

<figure>

<id>fig_p033r_4</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Mm1OS0lQRUpVZGs</link>

</figure>

<figure>

<id>fig_p033r_2</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SFNtME0xWURubzA</link>

</figure>

<ab>Take a small <tl>stick of <m>well dried <del>between</del>
wicker</m></tl> and cut from it a small piece <ms>like a
<tl>toothpick</tl></ms>, &amp; <del><fr>la m</fr></del> put one end
between your <bp>index finger</bp> &amp; <bp>middle finger</bp> and
clasp both your <bp>hands</bp>, <bp>fingers</bp> well joined, and pass
them deftly around the lit <tl>candle</tl> as if you wanted to cover it
with them, &amp; your <m>wicker</m> will light, &amp; immediately remove
your <bp>hands</bp> <del><fr>jo</fr></del> thus clasped, &amp;
immediately put out the <tl>candle</tl>. And then put your
<bp>hands</bp> around it again as if you wanted to cover it, &amp; your
little <corr><del>de lumiere</del></corr> <del><fr>p</fr></del>
<m>wicker</m> light,<comment>c_033r_01</comment> by means of the smoke
that you are holding with your two <bp>palms</bp> the <tl>candle</tl>
will light. Then immediately extinguish your <m>wicker</m> &amp;
secretly cast it aside.</ab>

</div>
</root>
