<root>
<page>041v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f88.image</image>

<div>

<id>p041v_1</id>

<head><pro>Glassworkers'</pro> <m>black</m></head>

<ab><m>Iron scale</m> taken from bars that have been in the fire for a
<tmp>long time</tmp>, &amp; <corr>which</corr> is thick, is much better
than <m>the common delicate kind that falls under the anvil</m> in the
<tl>forge</tl>, because it imitates <m>niello</m>. To said <m>black</m>,
described elsewhere, some add <del><fr>d</fr></del> a little
<m>minium</m> to it.

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p041v_2</id>

<head>Sheared <al>ewes</al></head>

<ab>If the <pro>shearer</pro> sometimes wounds them, he puts
<del><ill/></del> the <m>dung of the <al>ewe</al></m> on top. When they
are fat, they are easier to shear &amp; do not get wounded so easily.

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

If the <pro>shearer</pro> wants to <fr>viscorter</fr> them, that is to
say castrate, when they are one or two <ms><tmp>years</tmp></ms> old, he
must not have been with his wife for this would make the <al>sheep</al>
die.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p041v_3</id>

<head>Colors and <m>gilding</m> on <m>glass</m></head>

<ab>One ought not to give as strong <m>gum water</m> on <m>glass</m> for
the <del><m>gold</m> layer as for</del> <m>silver</m> layer as for the
<m>gold</m> layer because a <m>silver</m> leaf is twice as strong as a
<m>gold</m> leaf. Also, <m>silver</m> is harder and therefore does not
scratch as easily. <del><fr>Q</fr></del> And if the <m>gum</m> was not a
little strong for the <m>silver</m>, the latter would not crack so
neatly. When you work, <del>the humid</del> the exhalation of your
<bp>breath</bp> moistens the leaf layered on the <m>glass</m>, &amp;
therefore it would be good, while working, to heat it up a few times.
You need to be very careful to wash that which you want to be blank
&amp; serve as a background for painting with colors, for if it were not
quite clean of the <m>gum</m>'s greasiness &amp; viscosity,
<del>the</del> &amp; of other things, the colors would not be so brisk
on it. To advance your works, you can <fr>ponce</fr>, or, better still,
layer the <m>gum</m> &amp; leaf on a cut <m>paper</m>. In this way, you
will need to repair very little. If you want to make <m>gold</m> color
there without <m>gold</m>, mix soaked dried <m>saffron</m> with a little
<m>massicot</m>.

</ab>

</div>
</root>
