<root>
<page>114r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f233.image</image>

<div>

<id>p114r_1</id>

<head>Second Cast</head>

<ab>When you have well molded the first part of the animal, that is the
back, the backbone, and the entire top part, and the
<del><fr>len</fr></del> half-<tl>mold</tl> where it is enclosed has set
and is hard enough

<figure>

<id>fig_114r_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SWVndzB0aEk5MWs</link>

</figure> uncover the whole bottom part &amp; side of the belly,
<del>#</del> first with a <tl>knife</tl> <del><fr>&amp; tant</fr></del>
at the thickest places, &amp; then with a <tl>pen-knife</tl>, where the
most delicate parts are enclosed, such as the legs, the tail, &amp;
similar things, and because the head is higher, you will also need to
look for it &amp; uncover deeper, and made a deeper notch there which
ought to release easily. That is to say widening by the outside, in order that
the second <tl>mold</tl> that you will cast on it can come out well,
which even the animal can help with, which is malleable and obedient,
having naturalness. However <del><fr>ad</fr></del>, be more careful
when uncovering the throat of the <al>lizard</al> than with the
<al>snake</al>, for the <al>lizard</al> has large jaws &amp; large bones
that are not malleable, and has hollow ears, where, if the wet sand has
entered, it is not <del><fr>aff</fr></del> easy to release. But you will
avoid all of this, if you uncover half of the head and those things that
you know do not release easily. Once everything is uncovered well, blow
on top &amp; wipe each part, by wiping with little <tl>cloths of
<m><al>swine</al> fur</m></tl>, slightly moistened by the end, with a
little <m>saliva</m>, <add>or with <m>clear water</m>, as you dissolve
it</add>, in order that <del>your</del> the uncovered lower part of your
animal will be very neat. <add><mark>#</mark></add>
<add>🝋</add> With this done, dip <del><fr>le
rev</fr></del> <del>your mold</del> your mold, for the <ms><tmp>length
of a <la>pater noster</la></tmp></ms> in <m>water</m>, not
<del><fr>du</fr></del> <add><fr>le</fr></add> the uncovered side but
opposite, &amp; the reverse of the uncovered thing. And this is in order that,
by sucking the <m>water</m> <add>inside</add>, the <m>oil</m> with which
you next anoint the other side <del>to avoid</del>, is not
imbibed at all, but remains on the surface &amp; prevents the second
cast that you will cast on it from attaching to it. Having therefore
thus dipped <add>the reverse of</add> your <tl>mold</tl> in the
<m>water</m>, take a <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> especially dedicated to
this, &amp; <del>anoint it</del> with it anoint some <m>oil</m>
the whole surface of the <tl>mold</tl>, except the animal, which must in
no way touch the <m>oil</m>, &amp; take head to retrace well &amp; to anoint
with the point of a <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> between the parts &amp;
through all the delicate parts. And if by chance the <m>oil</m> is
imbibed, dip the <del><fr>mo</fr></del> reverse of the <tl>mold</tl> as
mentioned in <m>water</m>, &amp; you will see the <m>oil</m> return to
the surface in little drops.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

Mold small animals like big ones, except that you need to make
<tl>delicates points of <del><fr>fil</fr></del> <del><fr>cist</fr></del>
<m><mu>cittern</mu> strings</m></tl>, both long &amp; short.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<figure>

<id>fig_p114r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NVR5Y2FtZHM0ck0</link>

</figure>

Remove with your <tl>small flat pincers</tl>, all the
<tl>points</tl>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<mark>#</mark>

and then

<mark>+</mark><del><fr>tantost avecq</fr></del></ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<mark>#</mark>

However, leave the <tl>point</tl> of the throat, so that it serves as a
clue to find the head, which is deeper down than any other part, because
when making the arrangement you arranged it higher. It is also at the
level of the head that you should make the biggest notch &amp; start
with this one to uncover, and follow the rest through the trace of the
<tl>points</tl>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<mark>#</mark>

And if some bit of nail from a leg, or from a tail, or from another
should separate from the <tl>mold</tl>, put <del><fr>y</fr></del>
between but a small grain of <m>wax</m>, &amp; with the <tl>point of a
hot <m>iron wire</m></tl>, join it then adapt your <tl>mold</tl> with a
<tl>knife</tl>, &amp; make there notches at the sides, so that the other
half binds to it.🝋

<figure>

<id>fig_p114r_6</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5TTRuWU8yVktnc3M</link>

</figure>

</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
