<root>
<page>108r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f221.image</image>

<div>

<id>p108r_1</id>

<ab>To hold the <fr>noyaux</fr>, some use <tl><m>wire of the same
metal</m> that they cast</tl>, because it reduces <del>with</del> &amp;
melts with its counterpart, but because when melting or folding, the
<fr>noyau</fr> changes, some find it better to <del><fr>r</fr></del> use
<tl><m>iron wire</m></tl>, sharpened at the ends, because it holds
firmer &amp; having delicate ends, it appears as no more than a point of
a needle. And one can apply <m>gold</m> or <m>silver</m>, before using
it for a work. If it makes a hole, one covers it with a small
<tl>chisel</tl>.</ab>

<ab><m>Eau-de-vie</m> prevents the sand from becoming porous &amp; does
not make little holes on the edges of the <tl>mold</tl> if the thing to
mold is well dampened with it. The holes &amp; blisters &amp; bubbles
are not made on the side of the <tl>mold</tl>, which is thick, but at
the edges, which are thinner.</ab>

<ab>One casts with <m>common silver</m> with which <pro>goldsmiths</pro>
commonly work, which forms a mediocre <del><fr>Et que</fr></del> alloy.
And when one would cast with <m>solder</m>, it would run even
better.</ab>

<ab><rub><m><fr>Spalt</fr></m></rub> is a <m>whitish stone</m> which can
be found in <pl>Germany</pl>, &amp; mainly in <pl>Augsburg</pl>, which
one uses for the most excellent sand that can be found for <m>lead</m>,
<m>tin</m>, <m>copper</m>, <m>silver</m> &amp; <m>gold</m>. And the more
it is used, the better it is. It is appropriate for casting flat things
in a <tl>frame</tl>. For round things, it is not as fitting nor does
it hold in the fire as well as the above mentioned made with
<m>plaster</m>.</ab>

<ab>The shreds of <del><fr>cui</fr></del> thick, <m>greasy leather</m>
are <del><fr>p</fr></del><add>b</add> good to cast in the <m>melted
copper and latten</m>, for it cleans it &amp; removes from it all its
<m>filth</m>. </ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p108r_2</id>
<head><m>Spalt</m></head>

<ab><m>Spalt</m> is white like <m>cooked plaster</m> and can be found in
mounds and <m>stones</m> formed in long scales &amp; long veins. It is
very soft, such that with a <tl><bp>fingernail</bp></tl> one can scrape
it &amp; makes a powder like our <m>chalk from <pl>Champagne</pl></m>.
And because everything which comes from the <env>earth</env> is mixed
with some other substance, to purify it, one grinds it, coming from the
<env>quarry</env>, quite coarsely, then one mixes it <m>essence of sal
ammoniac</m>. And, by putting in a piece the <ms>size of a
<pa>walnut</pa></ms> in a large <tl>bottle</tl> of <m>water</m> and</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
