<root>
<page>024v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f54.image</image>

<div>

<id>p024v_1</id>

<head>For bringing a canon over <env>land</env></head>

<ab>

<del>If you have</del> To bring a canon, one needs a hundred
<pro>pioneers</pro> or more to flatten the tracks by levelling ditches
&amp; others obstacles, such as <pa>trees</pa>, <m>stone</m> mounds
&amp; similar things to make gabions on the way. Once one is close to
the place one wants to batter, the <pro>gunner</pro> goes <tmp>at
night</tmp> to reconnoiter the most convenient place to mount the
battery &amp; if he does not see well, one gives a false alarm in order
that those on the inside throw torches. Very often, one batters where it
is strongest so that the assailed do not repair there, disregarding the
battery. Usually, there are not many garrets &amp; other defenses in
that place. And when a breach is made at the strongest part &amp; the
cannon removed, it will surprise the assailed. One approaches
<env>fortified towns</env> <tmp>at night</tmp>, but to <env>poorly
fortified towns</env>, <pro>pioneers</pro> bring gabions and
<del>carry</del> once these are placed, one puts some boards or planks
behind the gabions to keep the <pro>pioneers</pro> safe, while behind,
they fill the gabions with some <m>earth</m> by means of their
<tl>shovels</tl>. And while one does this, one raises some false alarm
on another side. And before, one has fired a volley at the defenses.
<corr><del>The gabions</del></corr> The <pro>pioneers</pro> carry the
boards to make a level ground or a platform of four
<bp><ms>fingers</ms></bp> or half a <bp><ms>foot</ms></bp> thick, and
one sets them into the <m>earth</m>. The platform is five or six
<del>canno</del> <bp><ms>feet</ms></bp> larger than the cannon's wheels
on each side <del><fr>m</fr></del> if there is only one cannon. But if
there are more, the platforms touch. The distance which is between the
pieces is the <ms>width of two gabions</ms>. As long as the battery
lasts, the <pro>gunner</pro>s sleep &amp; eat close to a cannon. In
small spaces, one does not bother to dig trenches to reach the pieces
but one puts plenty of gabions that are high and runs to them. In large
places one digs trenches. There are always in trenches or behind
barricades <del>some</del> companions-in-arms on guard duty to defend
the pieces. One keeps the small <m>powder</m> magazine, of three or four
<ms>kegs</ms>, separately.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

Know the magazines of <pl>France</pl> for the
artillery.</ab><comment>c_024v_01</comment>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

It is good if the platform is slightly inclined toward the front because
the piece is more quickly mounted for battery &amp; holds the blast
better &amp; batters more fiercely.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>

<div>

<id>p024v_2</id>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><rub>Fowlers</rub> are those with a
reinforcement in the space which contains the <m>powder</m>, and the
ball can only <del><fr>a</fr></del> roll up to the opening of the said
chamber. These do not penetrate so much &amp;are irritating to load but
they do not heat up as quickly.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p024v_3</id>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><rub><m>A steel</m> touch-hole</rub>is
put in the canons in the manner of a screw so it will not be damaged
during firing like the others very quickly will be. But these screws
are prone to blow off &amp; cause damage to the <pro>gunner</pro>. There
is nothing for it but to use a proper touch-hole.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p024v_4</id>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><rub>A touch-hole at the level</rub> of
the breach is the best because in this way the cannon hardly pushes
back.</ab></div>
</root>
