<root>
<page>069v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f144.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p069r_2</id>

<ab>The sand <env>near my area</env> is very excellent. But one ought
to, in order to make an excellent work, take it fresh, which has been
used. For it dries out after having been cast several times &amp; is
lean &amp; has no body. If you cast some fine work which has hardly any
thickness, it is necessary that your substance of <m>copper</m> be very
hot so that it penetrates &amp; runs. Some mix in <m>lead</m> with the
<fr>fonte</fr>, but it is for large works &amp; not for small ones.</ab>

<ab><m>Sand from <al>oxen</al> feet twice-burned &amp; finely ground</m>
melts more neatly with <m>copper</m>, &amp; without a <fr>chappe</fr>,
than sand that I have seen. I have cast a high relief medal with it, and
<del><fr>f</fr></del> with a thickness as delicate as a <tl>knife</tl>
blade or a <tl>card</tl>. And being a hollow on one side, opposite the
relief which was on other side.</ab>

<ab>It is necessary that <m>lean sands</m> be more moistened than
others, namely with <m>magistra</m> or good <m>pure wine</m> or
<m>boiled wine with <pa>elm tree</pa> roots</m> &amp; similar things.
But <m>very fine sands</m>, like <m>burned linen</m> which is fat &amp;
soft on its own, want to be applied dry.</ab>

<ab>All moistened sand wants to be very beaten &amp; stirred in order to
be ground finely \&amp; to flatten out the clods that it makes in itself
when it is bathed.</ab>

<ab>The <m><pa>olive</pa> oil</m> that some mix in with <m>beaten egg
white</m> makes it become porous.</ab>

<ab><m>Sand of calcined glass</m> withstands several castings, but there
are only the first ones. It also becomes porous.</ab>

<ab><m>Latten</m> comes out on its own, but it runs too quickly. It is
good to mix it with a little <m>copper</m>, like a <ms>quarter
part</ms>, with the <m>substance of skillets</m>.</ab>

<ab><pro>Founders</pro> do cast <tl>frames</tl> up to 30 or 40 <ms>lb</ms>,
but not more.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is good for big work, but for small ones it is troublesome for
releasing. <del><fr>Il</fr></del> because it crumbles. It is good that
it be alloyed with some fat thing which has bond such as <m>molded
tripoly</m> or <del><fr>ab</fr></del> <m>burned felt</m> or <m>sal
ammoniac</m> or <m>tripoly</m> &amp; similar things.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
