<root>
<page>081r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f167.image</image>

<div>
<id>p081r_1</id>
<head>Sand</head>

<ab>One can find an excellent one <env>on the little hill</env> of
<pl>Puy David</pl><comment>c_081r_01</comment> near <pl>Thoulouse</pl>
for <m>lead</m>, <m>tin</m> &amp; <m>copper</m>. It does not want to be
too reheated much because, drying out all at once, it loses its
stickiness &amp; burns at the first arrival of <m>metal</m>, which makes
the work lumpy &amp; not neat. It is better to reheat from a distance,
rather than with a <m>straw</m> flame, which generates
<del><fr>des</fr></del> some <m>filth</m>. Before filling in the <tl>frame</tl>, you can put in the finest sand you have in a <tl>very fine
<m>linen</m></tl>, &amp; dry pounce the medal and then the moistened sand
that you put on top, which has more body, will grip it.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<m>Tallow</m> makes it porous.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<m>Fixed mercury</m> mixed in when one wants to cast, makes
<del>metal</del> <m>lead</m> run. But if it is pure, one ought to cast
very hot so that it runs, and vents.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p081r_2</id>
<head><m>Earth</m> for molding</head>

<ab><m><pro>Tanner</pro>'s earth, or the one with which
<pro>potters</pro> make a whitening on pots</m> to make <m>lead</m> run
better on them &amp; to prevent the <m>lead</m> from being absorbed into
them, is very good for molding the cavities of things you want mold in
relief. It releases better than <m>plaster</m> or <m>sulphur</m> which
become hard once they have set. For the <m>earth</m> being ready, one
ought to be beat hard so that it does not crack. If the piece is very
large you can mold it in several parts. If you reheat it, it is
necessary that it be over a closed fire. One finds this <m>earth</m> at
<pl>Fosseret</pl><comment>c_081r_02</comment> &amp; in another place
called <pl>Ox</pl><comment>c_081r_03</comment>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p081r_3</id>
<head><m>Plaster</m></head>

<ab>It is necessary that it be well cooked, which you will recognize
when cooking it in an <tl><m>iron</m> or <m>metal</m> skillet</tl>, you
mix it with an <tl><m>iron</m> rod</tl>, &amp; if it attaches to the
<m>iron</m>, it is not cooked enough, if not, it is good. The
<m>water</m> with which you moisten should be a little warm &amp; the
<tl>mold</tl> made with the aforesaid <m>earth</m> also a little hot.
The work of <m>plaster</m> does not last &amp; the faces &amp; delicate
things break if one does not give a coat of <m>glue</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p081r_4</id>
<head><m><fr>Carton</fr></m><comment>c_081r_04</comment></head>

<ab>One ought to take <m>paper from <pl>Florence</pl></m>, which is the
finest, &amp; pestle it &amp; soak it several times &amp; change the
<m>water</m> <tmp>every day</tmp>, so that it does not smell bad, &amp;
since you will have molded it in the cavity, put a
<tl><m>linen</m></tl> over it, &amp; from the back, rub the back of the
<m>paper</m> with a <tl>tooth</tl>, as if you wanted to burnish it, and
it will mold very neatly. Then <m>glue</m> the <m>cloth</m> on the back
with <m>strong glue</m>. </ab>

</div>
</root>
