<root>
<page>018r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f41.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p017r_1</id>

<ab>

Large culverins <del>are</del> for battery <add>&amp; piercing</add>
are forty <ms>quintals</ms> &amp; eighteen <ms><fr>pans</fr></ms> long.
Their ball, of the <ms><pro><pn>King</pn></pro>'s caliber</ms> &amp; for
battery, is 30 <ms>lb</ms> and thus lighter than that of the cannon. And
thus, it does not carry so much ammunition for fifteen <ms>lb</ms>
suffices for its charge. The cannon makes a bigger opening due to the
size of its ball, but the culverin hits more fiercely &amp; propels
faster, having greater force due to its length. At the breech it carries
the <ms>thickness of two of its balls &amp; the <del><fr>es</fr></del>
<add><fr>a</fr></add> <del>three</del> <add>third</add>
<del><fr>s</fr></del> part of a ball</ms>, at the front the
<ms>thickness of one ball &amp; two thirds</ms>. Culverins serve to
batter defenses from afar when one cannot easily make an approach, and
cannons approach more closely. They also serve to support the battery.
One needs fifteen or sixteen <al>horses</al> for moving it. They are
<del><fr>tout</fr></del> of the same alloy as the cannon, as are all
pieces <del>that exceed</del> <add>smaller than</add> average, for to
these, one adds a little more <m>metal</m> in order that the melt runs
better. And for two <ms>quintals</ms> of <m><fr>rosette</fr></m>, one
adds six twenties <ms>lb</ms> of <m>metal</m> for the smaller pieces.
<add>They shoot at point blank 8 or 9 hundred <ms>pace</ms>s &amp; up to
a thousand <ms>pace</ms>s if the <m>powder</m> is strong &amp; at range
half a <ms>league</ms>.</add></ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

Some invented the loading of cannons with cartouches.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

Some <del><fr>po</fr></del> do not put the <m>powder</m> in the cannon
all in one go but in two &amp; ramming each time, saying that each
ramming raises &amp; gives a further <ms><bp>thumb</bp>'s breadth</ms>. But this
is not certain for large pieces which are loaded with a lot of
<m>powder</m>.</ab>

<ab>

The <df><fr>bastarde</fr></df>, which is a <del>culverin</del>
<del>moyenne</del><comment>c_018r_01</comment> middle-sized piece,
weighs thirty <ms>quintal</ms>s and its ball weighs <del>xx
<ms>lb</ms></del> <add>xv <ms>lb</ms></add> and carries as its charge x
or xii <ms>lb</ms> of <m>powder</m>. Its proportion is at the breech the
<ms>thickness of two of its balls &amp; <del>the</del><add>the</add>
th<del>ree</del><add>ird</add> part of of a ball</ms>. At the front, the
<ms>thickness of a ball &amp; two thirds</ms>. <del><add>or</add></del>
They serve to batter defences of little importance such as
<env>gabions</env> and <env>garrets topped with a tower</env> &amp;
similar things. It is thirteen or xiiii <fr><ms>pan</ms></fr>s long like
the large cannon. Ten <al>horses</al> can move it. It accompanies well
the large culverin for point blank because it carries small
ammunition.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

Some give it the <ms>thickness of three balls at the breech &amp; at the
front of two balls</ms>.</ab>

<ab>

The bastard culverin weighs 35 <ms>quintal</ms>s &amp; is xxv
<ms><fr>pan</fr></ms>s long. It carries three balls at the breech &amp;
two in front. Its ball is like that of the <fr>bastarde</fr> piece,
weighing xv <ms>lb</ms>. These are fixed pieces which cannot be moved by
carriage, but are for <env>city</env> defences. Some make these xxvii or
xxviii <ms><fr>pan</fr></ms>s long, like the Cow of <pl>La
Rochelle</pl>. But to such pieces one gives reinforcement at the breech
as of three balls. At range, they can shoot around one <ms>league</ms>,
&amp; <ms>a half league</ms> at point blank. Its charge is like the
<fr>bastarde</fr>. And if one wants to fire at some <pro>cavalry</pro>
quite far off, one increases the <m>powder</m> a little. A tail of smoke
follows the ball which <del><fr>de</fr></del> guides your
<corr>sight</corr> to where the ball is going. This goes for the
cannon and for the culverin, and not for small pieces.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
