<root>
<page>157r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f319.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p157r_1</id>
<head>A means for <pro>goldsmiths</pro> for molding hollow</head>

<ab>

They mold in two <tl><m><al>cuttlefish</al> bones</m></tl> their animal
or other work that they have either already made, or modelled in
<m>wax</m> &amp; cast in <m>lead</m>. Since it is well imprinted in the
two <tl><m><al>cuttlefish</al> bones</m></tl>, they place between these
two <tl><m>bones</m></tl> a <tl><m>paper</m></tl>, &amp; join the
<tl><m>bones</m></tl> &amp; cast. The work comes out split in half. And
then, with <del><fr>ch</fr></del> a <tl><fr>chaple</fr></tl>, they
hollow out as finely as they please the two halves cast in <m>gold</m>
or <m>silver</m>, and then <m>solder</m> or braze them.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p157r_2</id>
<head><m>Rouge clair</m></head>

<ab>

Some <pro>goldsmiths</pro> assay it on <m>thinly beaten
<del><fr>esp</fr></del> gold</m> &amp; that is well burnished with a
<tl><fr>chaple</fr></tl>. But it is better to assay it on a <m>gold
ingot</m>. And also assay your substances in large or fantastical work,
since if they appear good &amp; extraordinary in large work, they will
show excellently on a common work.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p157r_3</id>
<head>Cleaning and degreasing your works cast from <m>tin</m> and
others</head>

<ab>Make some <m>lye</m>, carefully passed through <m>good ashes</m>,
and since it is recent &amp; not fatty, boil your molded work in it. And
the <m>tallow</m> and <m>fat</m> leaves it.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p157r_4</id>
<head>Arranging plants or flowers for casting</head>

<ab>

Always put on the top the principal side of the thing, because it comes
out better and neater than the bottom. Make the gate wide &amp; make sure that
<sup>there is</sup> <df><fr>supraplus</fr></df> (which is the
<fr>masse</fr> for <pro>founders</pro>) for a large gate,
<del><fr>Et</fr></del> especially for <m>silver</m>, which wants the
<tl>mold</tl> quite hot &amp; to be cast very hot. Very thin things want
to be cast very hot.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
When you know that the stem of a flower, burned in a <tl>mold</tl> which
does not open, is reduced well into <m>ashes</m>, it is a sign that the
rest is well burned.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p157r_5</id>
<head><al>Flies</al></head>

<ab>They mold better on a single leaf than <del><fr>n</fr></del> on a
bouquet or a flower or the branch of a plant, because the single leaf
molds in two halves, which, once reheated can open and clean well &amp;
the cast is made better. Take heed when using the <al>fly</al> to not
break the legs &amp; to not let it dry too much, for then the legs fall
off. And if this happens to you, <m>glue</m> with <m><al>fish</al>
glue</m> the same legs and with <m>wax</m>, or fashion some out of
<m><al>pork</al> hair</m> or <m><mu>spinet</mu> string</m>. Fix the leaf
on the <tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl> with two <tl>points</tl>, and the
<al>fly</al> with one <tl>point</tl> in the middle of the body, &amp;
the legs with some <m>wax</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
