<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="084r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f173.image">




<div id="p084r_1">

<head>Impromptu mask</head>

<ab>Mold some <m>paper</m> &amp; put it on the face of somebody who is
making an ugly grimace. Let it dry &amp; take your pattern to paint from
it.<hr/></ab>

</div>

<div continues="yes" id="p084r_5">


<ab><mark>#</mark><comment rid="c_084r_02"/>&amp; swellings. It
is necessary that it not be too wet for the aforesaid reasons. Reheat
little <add>by little</add>. And if, after molding it, you leave it to
dry slowly, in some <env>dry place</env> &amp; not over a big fire, it
would be better, for when one exposes it all at once to intense heat, it
warps. I believe that reheating it at the mouth of the <tl>oven</tl>,
<tmp>after the bread has been taken out</tmp>, would be very proper. One
ought not to complain about the difficulty of preparing it, for it
withstands as many castings as you wish, because it renders itself as
hard as <m>marble</m>, &amp; you can polish it, &amp; the <tl>mold</tl>
cannot be spoiled. Once used, <tl>pestle</tl> &amp; <tl>sieve</tl> it again, yet
without being scrupulous to render it so fine,
<del><fr>I</fr></del> for having been passed only through a <tl>common
sieve</tl>, it has more force <del>than</del> and releases better, than
when it is so fine.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p084r_3">

<head><m><fr>Eau magistra</fr></m></head>

<ab>Dissolve <m>rock salt</m> or <del><m>salt</m></del> finely
pulverized <m>sandever</m> &amp; put on <tl><m>marble</m></tl> in a
<env>cellar</env>, &amp; it will dry out by reheating the <tl>mold</tl>,
&amp; will give it a bond to withstand several castings. <emph>Try to
moisten it with <m>tartar oil</m>.</emph></ab>

</div>
<div id="p084r_4">

<head><m>Flour</m></head>

<ab>Ground during <tmp>Advent</tmp>, keeps for the <tmp>whole
year</tmp>.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p084r_5" continued="yes">

<head><m>Sand from a <env>mine in <pl>Thoulouse</pl></env></m></head>

<ab>The <m>sand from <pl>Thoulouse</pl></m>, which is taken, from the
<env>depths of the earth, from the small hill of <pl>Puy
David</pl></env>, is excellent in itself, but to make it withstand
several castings, I mix it with <m>pulverized sandever</m> &amp;
moistened, which hardens it, &amp; takes body &amp; bond with it, &amp;
makes it withstand <del>more than five</del> as many castings as you
wish. <emph>Try to moisten the <m><tl>pestled</tl> glass</m></emph> and other
<del><fr>e</fr></del> <m>sands</m> with the <m>waters of the above mentioned
salts</m>. It wants to be, like all <m>natural sand</m>, well reheated
before putting it to use. One pulverises it, because it is in lumps,
then one reheats it in a <tl><m>copper</m> kettle</tl> or similar thing,
until<del><fr>l</fr></del><comment rid="c_084r_04"/> it no longer <m>smokes</m></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

It is necessary to reheat it before using it. It is rendered better for
casting because it is reheated, but when it has been used a lot, one
ought to refresh it with new <m>sand</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>