<root>
<page>113r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f231.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p112v_1</id>

<ab>bit <del><fr>qua</fr></del> so that <del><fr>t</fr></del> you can
take it out if you need to. And take heed that it is necessary that
these <tl>points</tl> be of the most delicate <m>iron wire</m> possible
to bear the size of the animals. For, the more delicate it is, the
smaller the hole that it leaves appears. However, one needs 
different thicknesses of these, because <del><fr>il</fr></del>
<del><fr>de</fr></del> the <tl>points</tl> which are put in the body
&amp; in thicker places, like under the throat, ought to be longer &amp;
stronger than the ones of the legs &amp; thin parts, where the
<tl>needles</tl> ought to be subtle &amp; delicate, as it were like the
biggest <m>strings of <mu>spinets</mu></m>. And it is better that they
be of <m>iron wire</m>, which is firmer than <m>the one of latten</m>.
And if the end of the tail, or the end of a nail or a leg ought to be
joined to the body, do not put the <tl>point</tl> there, not to corrupt
it. But place <m>wax</m>, <ms>as much as a <m>grain of
<pa>millet</pa></m></ms>, between the body &amp; <del><fr>ce</fr></del>
<del><fr>qui</fr></del> the end of the tail, then with a bit of
flattened &amp; hot <m>iron wire</m>, touch this <m>wax</m> &amp; join
by lightly pressing. Thus having placed your animal on the
<fr>tourtelle</fr> shaped like a <mu>mandore</mu>, place all around a
circle of the same

<figure>

<id>fig_p113r_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5YkE1Vm1ZMmRoVm8</link>

</figure>

<m>earth</m>, in this way

<figure>

<id>fig_p113r_3</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5aW1sekxQWGJJY0E</link>

</figure> &amp; join everything well together in a circle, then, with a
big <tl>knife</tl>, with which you have cut your <fr>tourtelle</fr> to
the right size, pare the outside which exceeds it, &amp; place there a
piece to close it as you see in b. Then, with a <tl>small curved
instrument</tl>, mark on the inside of the circle the thickness you want
to give to the <tl>mold</tl>, which will be for a <al>common snake</al>
as thick as two <ms><bp><fr>poulces</fr></bp></ms>, in order that when you
throw in your wet sand, you will see when it is thick enough. All of
this carefully arranged, moisten well everywhere with good <m>eau-de-vie</m> with a <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> the body of the animal
which is uncovered. For this the secret <del><fr>de la plus</fr></del>
kept well hidden, because everything that is <del><fr>v</fr></del>
touched by <m>eau-de-vie</m> will undoubtedly come out very
neatly &amp; without <del>bubbles</del> any <df>small eyes or holes</df>
that we call bubbles, which usually come not at the back &amp; in the
thick sides of the <tl>mold</tl>, but on the edges. And as soon as you
have thus moistened everything with <m>eau-de-vie</m>, throw
in your wet sand without letting the <m>eau-de-vie</m> dry,
which evaporates promptly. And wet it thus.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<figure>

<id>fig_p113r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5MDEzX0RhXzJGcXc</link>

</figure>

and make sure that the <tl>point</tl> is long according to the height
you want the head, and that it be pointed on both ends. Once placed
thus, plant your <al>snake</al> on the slab of <m>earth</m>, &amp;
arrange the head first and then the rest.

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<m>Eau-de-vie</m> in three goes.

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

If after you have placed you animal on your <m>clay</m>
<fr>tourtelle</fr>, you are distracted with other occupations, rub your
animal with <m>eau-de-vie</m> &amp; under the belly so that it
does not dry &amp; attach itself to the <m>earth</m>

<figure>

<id>fig_p113r_4</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Qm8wSlJPOWxfZWM</link>

</figure>

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

If, when you pierce your animal, it renders <m>water</m> from the bottom
of the side of the belly, on the slab of <m>earth</m>, clean it well
with <m>cotton</m> for the sand that would touch it would be lumpy. If
it is on top of the animal, clean it very carefully and touch it
&amp;moisten well with <m>eau-de-vie</m>.

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p113r_1</id>

<head>Wetting sand and molding the first cast</head>

<ab>Take a <tl>bowl of <m>leaded</m> <m>earth</m></tl> of such size that
it can hold the wet sand, which will be needed <del><fr>de</fr></del> to
fill your <tl>mold</tl> in one go, which is <del><fr>mei</fr></del>
better than in two gos, because if you do not throw the second wet batch
 promptly, there is a risk that while you are preparing it, the
first one will set &amp; become solid,</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
