<root>
<page>147r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f299.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p146v_1</id>

<ab>Take heed to make a border of <m>melted wax</m>, with a <tl>hot
<m>iron</m></tl>, all around the edge of the top shell, which is towards
the tail, in order the make the vents better. And make two little
strings of the same <m>wax</m>, <del><fr>r</fr></del> connecting from
the end the belly shell to the said edge of <m>wax</m>, that is around
the shell of the spine, and make sure that <del><al>turtle</al> of</del>
the tail of the <al>turtle</al> stays between these two strings. This is
to makes the vents<comment>c_ 147r_01</comment> better. This done,
<m>oil</m> your <tl>mold</tl> and what appears of the shell. Put the
<tl>circle</tl> around &amp; cast with <m>hot water</m>, as before,
observing there what you have observed. Do the same to mold the third
part, which is the tail. And having set, <del>you</del> <del>uncover
your mold</del> remove the <tl><m>clay</m> contour</tl>, clean your
<tl>mold</tl> &amp; smooth it &amp; flatten it on all sides with a
<tl>knife</tl> like for other <tl>molds</tl>. Dip it lightly in
<m>water</m>, then try to release it. Usually one begins
<del><fr>ment</fr></del> with <del><fr>e</fr></del> <del>back</del> the
backshell, <del>it is</del> that is to say, the <tl>mold</tl> on top,
which is in two halves, and this one is easier to release. The other one
follows after, but because it is neighboring the shoulder of the
<al>turtles</al>, which are deeply ensconced, it is sometimes awkward.
Thus, when moving &amp; pulling the <tl>mold</tl> gently, take heed to
pull the one which will present itself as the easiest, for one needs to
release one after the other. The most awkward of all is the one which
molds the <del><mark>e</mark></del> <del>of</del> throat, the
underneaths of the legs &amp; the hollow shoulder pieces, which are of
such bad release that if you had not provided for it, by filling with
<m>wax</m> before molding what does not release well, it will be awkward
for you to pull your pieces out without breaking something. But should
this happen to you, there is still a remedy, provided that you keep
<del><fr>pi</fr></del> the broken pieces. For you can reassemble them
with <tl>points of <m>rather strong iron</m></tl> &amp; fill the crack
or fault that could be there with <m>melted wax</m> &amp; <tl>hot
<m>iron</m></tl>, as with others, in order that the <fr>noyau</fr> for molding
hollow is made better. Next

<rub>Go to the second leaf</rub></ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>To avoid breaking when releasing, take
heed to uncover well up until what can hold.</ab>

</div>
</root>
