<root>
<page>156r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f317.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p156r_1</id>
<head>Molding promptly and reducing a hollow to a relief</head>

<ab>You can imprint the relief of a medal in <m>colored wax</m>, &amp;
you will have a hollow, in which you can cast <fr>en noyau</fr> a relief
<add>of your sand</add>, on which you will make a hollow of <m>lead</m>
or <m>tin</m>, in which you will cast a <m>wax</m> relief. And then on
that <m>wax</m> you will make your <tl>mold</tl> in a hollow
<fr>noyau</fr>, to cast in it the relief of <m>gold</m> &amp;
<m>silver</m> or any other <m>metal</m> you like. But to hasten your
work if you are in a hurry, make the first imprint &amp; hollow in
<m>bread pith</m>, prepared as you know, which will mold very neatly.
And into that, cast <m>melted wax</m>, which will give you a beautiful
relief, on which you will make your <fr>noyau</fr>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p156r_2</id>
<head>Very light and hollow work of <m>gold</m></head>

<ab>Cast a <al>lizard</al> or any medal you like in <m>base silver</m>,
like <cn>billon</cn>. Next, <m>gild</m> it lightly. And once the first
<m>gilding</m> is done &amp; dried by fire, quicken, rub with a
<tl>scratch-brush</tl>, &amp; make another layer of light <m>gilding</m>
like the first time, &amp; do thus three or four times or more,
according to the thickness you want to give. And then, having made a
small hole in the least visible place, put your work into <m>good
aquafortis</m>, which penetrating to the <m>silver</m> through the hole
will eat it all away without damaging the <m>gold</m>, so that you will
have a <al>lizard</al> hollow to its nails, or any other work, so light
that by blowing you will agitate it. But take heed not to make the layer
of <m>amalgamated gold</m> all at once, or of hardly any thickness each
time, because that would block the small features; but proceeding
therein as said, lightly &amp; several times, <add>and cleaning
well</add>, you would do well.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
In order for the <m>aquafortis</m> to eat away better, it is necessary
to <del>cast</del> cast in <m>base silver</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p156r_3</id>
<head><tl>Chasing</tl></head>

<ab><m>Lead</m> is so fat &amp; soft that one cannot strike it boldly,
&amp; one needs to have a <bp>very light hand</bp>. The other <m>great
metals</m> are easier. With a <tl>burin</tl> called
<tl><fr>onglet</fr></tl> you make &amp; retrace the more delicate lines,
with the <tl>ordinary engraving burin</tl> the broader ones, and with
the <tl><fr>chaple</fr></tl>, you remove the big flashing, and with the
<tl>chisels</tl> you soften the harshness of the lines, you smooth, you
add relief to a line.</ab>

</div>
</root>
