<root>
><page>006v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f18.image</image>

<div>
<id>p006v_1</id>
<head>For <del><fr>ga</fr></del> <del><fr>cach</fr></del>cages</head>

<ab>You can embellish them with <tl><m>thin enamel canes</m></tl> of
various colors by covering the <m>latten or iron wire</m> with the said
<tl>thin canes</tl>. These you will break neatly to the length that you
want if you slightly notch with a <tl>cutting file</tl> at the place to
be broken, and they will not break at any other place. You can bend
<add>them</add> with a <tl><m>wood</m> model</tl> over a
<tl>chafing-dish</tl> or else by the heat of the <tl>lamp</tl>. It can
also be drawn as long as you want in a <tl>small furnace</tl> made like
a <tl>reverberatory furnace</tl> but which is pierced on both sides. And
when the large <tl>cane</tl> is red, they seize the hot end using
<tl>small pincers with a long beak</tl>, such that one prong of the beak
of the <tl>small pincers</tl> enters inside the end of the <tl>thin
cane</tl>, &amp; thus it is lengthened without becoming stopped, &amp;
the other end of the <tl>thin cane</tl> is held with the <bp>hand</bp>,
because it is not hot. When the <tl>thin cane</tl> is stretched enough,
the one who works seated, having his <tl>furnace</tl>,
the <ms>size of a <pa>carnation</pa> pot</ms>, before him,
<corr>breaks</corr> it off &amp; continues. This is for making <tl>thin
canes</tl> for capes, which are cut as already mentioned, and with a
<tl>file</tl>. <pro>Glass-button makers</pro> also avail themselves of
the said <tl>furnace</tl>.</ab>

<div>

<figure>

<id>fig_p006v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5eVFRYjVCTmczcmM</link>

</figure>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Under the door is a <tl>grill</tl> that supports the lit charcoal, &amp;
the <m>ash</m> is emptied by turning the <tl>furnace</tl> upside
down<comment>c_006v_02</comment>.</ab>

</div></div>

<div>
<id>p006v_2</id>
<head>For stamped ornaments<comment>c_006v_03</comment> used for
embellishing and inserting into or covering the edges of mirrors, the
tops of chests, or the friezes of bed valances</head>

<ab>Etch with <m>aquafortis</m> on <m>iron</m> or <m>copper</m>
whatever you have pounced and drawn there, next make it neat with a
<tl>burin</tl> or <tl>chisel</tl>. Then pour <m><fr>doulx</fr> tin</m>,
yet unused, onto <tl><m>polished marble</m></tl> &amp; flatten it,
making it quite thin, with a <tl><m>wooden</m> board</tl>. Or else pour
it on a <tl>table</tl> as is done with <m>lead</m>, or put it through a
<tl>roll-press</tl>. Next lay your <m>tin</m> plate over the etched thing,
&amp; over the <m>tin</m> plate put a <tl>piece of <m>felt</m></tl> and
strike it with a <tl>hammer</tl>. Then <m>gild</m> it in the following
manner.</ab>

</div>
</root>
