<root>
<page>150v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f306.image</image>

<div>

<id>p150v_1</id>

<head>Molding hollow</head>

<ab>This <tl><m>iron wire</m> point</tl>, which is put thus
<del><fr>bi</fr></del> through the hole, is to better hold the
<fr>noyau</fr> &amp; keep it from shifting. All of this being
<del><fr>d</fr></del> thus arranged, lay your <tl>mold</tl> on the
<tl>table</tl>, the hole at the top, as it is here marked on the side,
&amp; then adapt a <tl>circle of <m>soft clay</m></tl>
<del><fr>aultr</fr></del>, two <ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> high, around
the hole, like for other <tl>molds</tl>. And then wet your molding sand,
moderately thick, &amp; cast it through the hole until it is well
filled, up to the surface of the <tl><m>clay</m> circle</tl>. But take
heed to not cast <del><fr>r</fr></del> in through the middle of the
hole, but rather from the side, for, because the already made
<tl>mold</tl>, drinks and sucks the moisture <del>of the new</del>. The
new one that you cast in <del>which dries quickly</del>, on the edge of
the <tl>mold</tl>, being quickly dry, <del><fr>s</fr></del> would
obstruct the <tl>mold</tl> &amp; it would not finish filling. And when
you cast from the side, if you recognize that it is obstructed, you can
clear a path. Having cast in, blow on the <del><fr>f</fr></del>
<corr><del>the</del></corr> wet gate, &amp; put, a few times, the
<tl><bp>end of your finger</bp></tl> in the hole, <del><fr>po</fr></del>
or some <tl>small point</tl>, to unblock it, &amp; make the hollow
<m>wax</m> fill up. Cast in, at the end, the sand wetted a little
thickly to give strength to the <tl>mold</tl>, for <m>water</m> coming
to the surface <del><fr>s</fr></del> <add>of the <tl>mold</tl></add>,
always makes it softer. Having set, scrape off the <tl><m>clay</m>
circle</tl> &amp; the excess which is on the hole, through which you
cast the <fr>noyau</fr> &amp; nothing will be discernable. When your
<tl>mold</tl> is thus prepared, <m>lute</m> it all around with the
same sand which served for the <tl>molds</tl>. Next, reheat it in a slow
fire, at the beginning, &amp; the mouth of the gate at the bottom, in
order that the <m>wax</m> flows out <corr>gently</corr>. For if you were
to give it great heat until the <m>wax</m> came out, it would boil
inside &amp; leave some pustules &amp; lumpy things, although</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

This <tl>point</tl> is placed in the middle &amp; through the hole of
the gate, when the <tl>mold</tl> is in several pieces, like a
<al>turtle</al>, and this is done in order that the <fr>noyau</fr> does
not shake. But when the mold is only of two pieces, it is not necessary
to put <tl>points</tl> in the middle of it.

<figure>

<id>fig_p150v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5eVVJSjUwSFhpUzg</link>

</figure>

<figure>

<id>fig_p150v_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SUk5cUNtNnpqbXc</link>

</figure>

</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

Before casting the <fr>noyau</fr>, make some notches all around the hole
through which you want to cast, in order to always better secure the
<tl>mold</tl>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

Mixed <m>tallow</m> is the reason that, when emptying the <m>wax</m>,
the hole does not become obstructed. One needs <ms>half</ms>
<m>tallow</m> &amp; <ms>half</ms> <m>black wax</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

All very thick pieces come out better in hollow, because a thick mass of
mostly <m>lead</m> remains hot a long time &amp; eats the
<tl>mold</tl>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

You can, after the cast is done, mold <del>a</del> the part of the shell
of the belly where you have made the hole on the natural
one<comment>c_150v_03</comment>, and reattach it with
<m>solder</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>X</mark>Note that, after your <fr>noyau</fr> is cast, it is
better to put the <tl>mold</tl> in <m>hot water</m> to open it, in order
to remove the most <m>wax</m> that you can, always softening
<del><fr>a</fr></del> it in <m>hot water</m>. For the less <m>wax</m>
that remains in it, the better, in order that, when reboiling a lot in
the <tl>mold</tl> when you reheat it, no pustules or lumps are made in
it. And then, if there is hardly any <m>wax</m>, you will not need to
reheat it as much. When opening the <tl>mold</tl>, the cast will break.
But it can easily be repaired, even though you
cast<mark>A</mark><comment>c_150v_02</comment>

</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
