<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="107v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f220.image">




<div continues="yes" id="p107r_1" categories="casting" continued="yes">





<ab margin="top">

<tl>Molds</tl> can only be used once for
delicate things, like <pa>wormwood</pa> &amp; others, one needs to break
them, but before one needs to dip them well into <m>water</m> in which
the twice reheated things dissolve easily. Otherwise, you would not be
able <del><fr>f</fr></del> to release your work without danger of
spoiling it.</ab>

<ab><m><df>Good feather alum</df></m> is white and as lustrous
<add>as</add> <m>white <del><fr>c</fr></del> silk</m>. It is in pieces
long as a <ms><bp>finger</bp></ms>, &amp; is very breakable &amp; wooly
as <m>down</m>. The one made of <m>stone</m> is harder &amp; not so
good. <del><fr>Il</fr></del> The best of the above mentioned quality is
brought in <pl>France</pl> near <pl>Rouan</pl>. The <m>feather alum</m> for our <m>sand</m> is <tl>pestled</tl> in a <tl>mortar</tl>, and is
further ground on <tl><m>marble</m></tl>, especially since one
cannot think of passing it finely through the <tl>sieve</tl>, for it is
so fat &amp; wooly that it would not pass through it. It is this, with
its small soft <del><fr>qui</fr></del> &amp; thin filaments, which gives
binding to the <m>sand</m>, in a much more excellent fashion than
<m><fr>tondure</fr></m> in the <m>founder’s earth of the <pro>founders
of great works</pro></m>, because this <m><fr>tondure</fr></m> &amp;
<m>cloth waste</m> burns and <m>feather alum</m> resists the
fire.</ab>

<ab>To enclose the <tl>molds</tl>, when you <del><fr>em</fr></del> throw
onto the things to mold your <m>liquid sand</m>, make <del>your</del> a circle
&amp; surround with well beaten <m>fat
earth</m>.</ab>

<ab><la>Archanum omnibus fere reconditum est in re fusoria,<lb/>

<del>ut</del>v<exp>idelicet</exp><comment rid="c_107v_05"/> res exprimenda formis, sive herba sit sive
<m>animal</m><lb/>

ut <m>lucerta</m>, <del>in</del> <del>af</del> <del>inting</del><comment rid="c_107v_06"/>
inmergatur primum in <m>vini spiritum</m><lb/>

aprime rectificatum, deinde pulvere composito aspergatur<lb/>

sive illinatur (<comment rid="c_107v_07"/>si pulvis in formam pultis redactus sit, ut<lb/>

assolet).</la><comment rid="c_107v_11"/></ab>

<ab>When you want to mold hollow, it is necessary that the
core be of the same material. And if the <al>snake</al> or
the animal is curved or folded, one ought to make the core of
several pieces.</ab>

<ab><emph>Test whether <m>distilled vinegar</m></emph> is
appropriate for eating away &amp; dissolving what will be in the animal
molded hollow.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

If you know that your <m>plaster</m> is not strong enough to withstand
the fire without cracking, do not be so scrupulous an observer of the
mixture put here that sometimes you <del><fr>mecties</fr></del> would
not diminish the quantity of <m>feather alum</m>
<del><fr>l</fr></del>a<comment rid="c_107v_12"/> little bit, for it softens the
<tl>molds</tl> with its softness. Once reheated do not pulverize it, on
this occasion, as fine as said, but leave it as the
<pro>apothecaries</pro> have ground it, for it does not hinder the
neatness of the cast &amp; gives more binding. When the <del><m>sand</m></del>
<tl>mold</tl>, <del><fr>estant</fr></del> having set, retains the color of <m>brick</m>, and is reddish, it is firmer.</ab>

</div>
</root>
