<root>
<page>167v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f340.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p167r_1</id>

<ab>

The ones weighing about 27 lb. are ix inches long and the mouth is 6 in
diameter. At their breech, they are 6 <ms>lines</ms> thick, &amp; 3 for
the mouth. The ones weighing 17 lb are 8 <ms>inches</ms> long &amp; the
mouth is five. They are all covered together, all the forks, &amp; pegs,
&amp; tools which one uses, with a big canvas or big cloth so that they
do not make any noise. It is good that they sit loaded for a while.
After the <m>powder</m> has been put in, it is tamped down quite
strongly and then pressed <m>paper</m> is put in, then a cake of
<m>wax</m> well tamped-down &amp; on the <m>wax</m>, another small plate
of <m>cork</m> that that goes in only just, &amp; with force. In this
way, the <m>powder</m> remains well sealed &amp; gives much greater
force, &amp; if you wish, you can put on the small plate of <m>cork</m>
one of wood pierced in the middle, if the petard is pierced at the
breech, which one holds to be the easiest &amp; which makes a greater
breach because it cannot recoil. And for those that have a pierced
breech, one must have a good gimlet to first make the hole in order that
the peg, which is made with a gimlet-like point, may attach the petard
faster &amp; without noise. And for these, one must cover the button,
which is quite sharply filed, with <m>waxed canvas</m>, or add
<m>wax</m> to it so that it completely plugs the hole in the breech. But
because the doors are sometimes iron-clad &amp; the iron pegs cannot
pierce it, an iron fork made like pincers &amp; another iron rod made
with three claws at the end, like you see portrayed, are use. And in
this way, the petard stays in place well &amp; is quickly set. The iron
pegs must pass the petard with the entire point which is made like a
gimlet, namely by three or 4 fingers, which goes entirely into the door.
When the petards are placed, the touch-hole is filled with good
<m><fr>pulverin</fr></m><comment>c_167v_01</comment> and inserted in it
is a <m>feather quill</m> filled with <m>powder</m>, tightly pressed
&amp; moistened with <m>vinegar</m>, or, if needed, the powder is firmly
pressed with the palms of the hands &amp; having wetted it with some
<m>saliva</m>, one shapes it like a cocoon or</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
