<root>
<page>145v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f296.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p145r_2</id>

<ab>But <del>because</del> <tl><bp>fingers</bp></tl> do not press
evenly, for <del>one</del> if you press on the edges, the middle will
remain hollow. Begin, therefore, by the middle, &amp; then follow the
edges. But to make it better, put on the medal something flat &amp;
smooth, or some <tl>large square file<del>e</del></tl>, &amp; press with
this, for you will press equally, sometimes <del>after <fr>l</fr></del>
with your <tl><bp>knee</bp></tl>, other times with your
<tl><bp>foot</bp></tl>, with your shoe taken off, &amp; make the
<tl><m>bone</m></tl> be on top, thus you <del><fr>l’emprand</fr></del>
will imprint it without breaking it. If, on the first go, it is not
molded well, return to it several times. Then repair &amp; smooth on the
sides your <del><fr>d</fr></del> halves of molded <tl><m>bone</m></tl>.
<del>&amp;</del> And to cut it well, always begin coming from the
softest part to the scales. And if your medal does not come out by
itself, scratch the <tl><m>bone</m></tl> from the back, which is rugged,
and it will release. When you want to cast, secure &amp; join your two
<tl><m>bones</m></tl> with some <tl>small points of <m>wood</m></tl>
&amp;c. But to mold very neatly, there is only our sand.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p145v_1</id>

<head>Molding plants and flowers</head>

<ab>One does not need <tl><m>clay</m> slabs</tl>, because plants or
flowers are not laid on top, but as in air, without touching on any side
anything. <del>&amp;</del> Only the <del><fr>es</fr></del>
<tl>circle</tl> &amp; <tl>contour</tl> are needed, which should be
higher than for <tl>flat molds</tl>. And thus, take heed to make it
strong and thick according to the size that you want, otherwise it would
burst, the sand being inside. Secure it &amp; fortify it well by the
foot &amp; join well all the joints. Then, take your flower, well joined
&amp; <corr>securely</corr> adapted to the end <del>of
<fr>cir</fr></del> of the gate of <m>wax</m>, which should not be rough,
but rather smooth, in order that it can release well. Then, wet your
flower or plant in some <m>good eau-de-vie</m>, <del>or else
<fr>moin</fr></del> placed in a <tl>long glass</tl></ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p145v_2</id>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5b1FOQ1Z5b1J3TWc</link>

</figure>

<cont/>

</div>

<div>

<id>p145v_2</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<head>Flowers</head>

<ab><comment>c_145v_01</comment>

<mark>+</mark>

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

When you mold them, if they are not strong enough to hold themselves
upright, pass a <tl>thread</tl> through the <tl>mold</tl> to keep them
from rising up, &amp; throw the sand little by little, &amp; always blow
strongly in order that it settles everywhere, otherwise it will become
lumpy.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

Because you did not put in this a <tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl>, the
<tl>mold</tl> sometimes holds to the <tl>table</tl> where you cast it.
To undo it, hit a great blow of a <tl>hammer</tl> at the side of the
<tl>table</tl>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

It is enough to reheat your <m>luted</m> <tl>mold</tl> once for flowers
&amp; to heat it the second time if you cast with <m>tin</m> &amp;
<m>lead</m>, for with <m>gold</m> &amp; <m>silver</m>, one needs to
reheat it twice.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>bottom</margin>

Cast your <m>tin</m> very red in the <tl>mold</tl>, <sn>of
<corr>such</corr> heat that you can hold your <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl>
there without harm in the hole</sn>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
