<root>
white<page>044v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f94.image</image>

<div>

<id>p044v_1</id>

<head><m><al>Horse</al>hair</m> sieves</head>

<ab>They are made at <pl>Coustance</pl> in <pl>Normandy</pl> with
<m><al>horse</al> tail hair</m> which they clean with <m>lye</m> because
they sort them with the <tl><bp>mouth</bp></tl> &amp; separate out short
&amp; broken ones. They do not make the <tl>reed</tl> longer than the
sieve, &amp; the <tl>reed</tl> is round. They attach to both edges of
the <tl>reed</tl> the <m>hair</m>, either black or white, according to
the work they want to make. And the weft is <corr><del>is</del></corr>
done over &amp; under as for making any other fabric. And passing a
<tl>small flat stick</tl> of ii or three <ms><bp>fingers</bp> wide</ms>
between two, next they pass two <m>hairs</m> at each step of the pedal
and weave with three pedals. There are xviic <m>hairs</m> in the entire
sieve. They sell them by the <ms>dozen</ms> &amp; each <ms>dozen</ms>
xxx <ms><cn>sols</cn></ms>. They bring them to <pl>Toulouse</pl> to
transport them afterwards to <pl>Spain</pl>, and take <m>silk tammy</m>
in exchange for it .</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p044v_2</id>

<head>Excellent <m>water</m> against the pest by <pn>Monsieur de
Montorsin</pn></head>

<ab>Take some <m>theriac</m>, <m><pa>rue</pa></m> &amp;
<m><pa>dittany</pa></m>, &amp; <m>good vinegar</m>, put the whole in a
<tl><m>glass</m> bottle</tl>, leave it half-open &amp; well fixed, and
put it in a very long bath for three or 4 <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms>. Then
separate your decoction from the residue, of which decoction in time of
need you will pour some, on a <tl>flaming red tile</tl> &amp; receive
the vapor of it &amp; also perfume your clothes with it. This is a very
rare &amp; tested secret.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p044v_3</id>

<head><m>White soporific oil</m></head>

<ab>Take x or 12 <m><pa>mandrake</pa> apples</m>, put them in quarters
in <m><pa>olive</pa> oil</m>, the whole in a <del><tl>vial</tl></del>
<tl><m>glass</m> bottle</tl> which you will place in a bain marie for
two <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms> and your <m>oil</m> will turn white. If you
rub the <bp>sole of your feet</bp> with the same, you will soon feel
like sleeping.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p044v_4</id>

<head><m>Stucco</m></head>

<ab>For <m>glueing</m> <m>stone</m>, some do not use
<del><fr>poi</fr></del> <m>resin</m> &amp; <m>black pitch resin</m>
because it is too fatty, but take <m>rosin</m> &amp; <m>sulphur</m>,
<ms>as much <del>as</del> of one as the other</ms>, &amp; as much of

<m>wax</m> as the two, and mix it with <m><tl>pestled</tl> brick</m> for greater
strength. Others, <m>white chalk</m> or <m><tl>pestled</tl> &amp; pulverized
&amp; sieved white stone</m>.</ab></div>
</root>
