<root>
<page>054r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f113.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p053v_1</id>

<ab>on some of the <tl>high shelves</tl>, &amp; at that time, one knows
when they want to climb up when, on the leaf, they
<del><fr>hau</fr></del> lengthen &amp; raise the head &amp; a part of
the body. At that time one carries them to the <pa>heather</pa> branches
where they stop &amp; begin to spin their prison, which one calls
cocoon, commonly the <ms>size of a <al>pigeon</al> egg</ms>, although
one finds much larger ones because it sometimes happens that two or
three &amp; up to xi <al>worms</al> are put in a cocoon, which is hairy
&amp; downy all around <del>&amp;</del>, the hair of which is
<m>ferret-silk</m> or
<m><fr>floret</fr></m><comment>c_054r_02</comment>; &amp; from the
cocoon, which is a white, solid, continuous &amp; firm skin, <m>silk</m>
is made. The cocoon is so hard that one only cuts it with difficulty
with a <tl><bp>fingernail</bp></tl>. And nevertheless, to leave its
prison, <del><fr>elle</fr></del> the <al>worm</al> gnaws it at one end,
&amp; after <add>having</add> stayed inside living on its own sap
<del><fr>il</fr></del> for three <ms><tmp>weeks</tmp></ms>, it comes
out, diminished <ms>by half</ms>. For when it begins to spin, it is
<ms>as long as a <bp>ring finger</bp></ms> &amp; has eight feet, &amp;
coming out it <ms>shorter by half</ms> &amp; only has 4 feet. On the
other hand, it has become a <al>butterfly</al> &amp; has wings, without
flying however. And there are male &amp; female. As soon as they come
out of the cocoon, the male charges the female &amp; one puts them on a
<tl>white linen</tl>, where they make their eggs. Which female would not
be good &amp; profitable if the male was not given to her. And when the
male has detached himself from a female, one needs to throw it, for it
would not be good to give it to another. They have completed spinning
&amp; making their eggs in three <ms><tmp>weeks</tmp></ms> &amp;
<tmp>around <pn>Saint John</pn>'s Day</tmp>. And at that time one keeps
their eggs &amp; seed <ms><tmp>until Holy Week</tmp></ms>, as
<del><fr>on</fr></del> is said. Some spin among the leaves &amp; make
their cocoon there without climbing high.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

The <m>silk</m> of the cocoons where there are</ab>

</div>
</root>
