<root>
<page>025r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f55.item</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p024v_1</id>

<ab>a hundred <ms>paces</ms> away from the battery &amp; one surrounds
them with barricades or trenches. And there one goes to get
<m>powder</m> in <tl>bags</tl> or <tl>frails</tl>. And each piece has
its own <tl>frail</tl> for loading three or four times. Then, when the
cannon is placed on the platform, one puts a board that is proof of an
arquebus between two gabions. Then a <pro>gunner</pro> loads it with a
<tl>ladle</tl>, &amp; with the <tl>rammer</tl> which is at
<del><fr>len</fr></del> the other end of the <tl>ladle</tl>, two men
ram the <m>powder</m> as much as they can, in nine or ten pushes, until
they find the <m>powder</m> to be hard &amp; and well-compacted. Next,
another puts <m>hay</m> or <m>straw</m> and the <del>r</del> others
ram a little. Another puts the ball and the <m>hay</m>-bearer puts in
as much of it as before &amp; one rams a little. Some put
<tl><m>wooden</m> bungs</tl> but this runs the risk of making the piece
burst. And where one has to fire many <del>cannon</del> shots, one
would need many <tl>bungs</tl>, which would cost much to carry. Once the
cannon is loaded, xx or xxv <pro>pioneers</pro> push it forward with
bars, keeping to one side behind the gabions without taking off the
board until the cannon reaches it. Once the cannon is in front, the
<pro>gunner</pro> mounts it with the <tl>wedges</tl> which are at the
back, taking the sight on each side and then in the middle. Then another
who is nearby gives fire. Each <del><pro>gunner</pro></del> cannon needs
3 <pro>gunners</pro>: the loader, the one who aims, the one who gives
fire. Sometimes, against a camp or into a breach, one shoots cartridges,
made as you have elsewhere, or else one uses a <m>basan</m> full of
<m>flint stones</m>, <m>cart nails</m> &amp; similar.
<del><fr>P</fr></del> A <del><fr>ch</fr></del> cannon must not move
unless it has two harnesses, be they of <m>wood</m> or <m>iron</m>. And
to furnish the wheels, powder box, and other furniture of the cannon,
one needs seven <ms>quintals</ms> and a half of <m>iron</m>.
<del><fr>Pour les pre</fr></del> The best battery is done at a curtain
wall, some say, <del>for</del> that is, as if at an
<del><fr>bieve</fr></del> angle, for by doing this you shake loose
several stones.</ab>

<mark>----------------------------------------</mark>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<render>extra-wide</render>

Some put small wheels of the piece and a thick board to the end of the
carriage of the piece in order that it may be drawn more quickly and
without making a noise. Others put <m>leather</m> around the
<del>the</del> wheels &amp; also put <m>leather</m> soles or shoes on
the <al>horses'</al> hooves in order that one does not hear
them.</ab></div>
</root>
