<root>
<page>032v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f70.image</image>

<div>

<id>p032v_1</id>

<head><pro>Mat maker</pro></head>

<ab>They make two kinds of them in <pl>Toulouse</pl>, one to hang on the
<env>partition walls of rooms</env>, which they weave almost as fine as
the <m>straw</m> <corr>hats</corr> worn by <pro>villagers</pro>. And
they make them in long bands, some the <ms>width of ten
<del><fr>b</fr></del><m>straws</m></ms>, others of thirteen. And they
work on them mainly <ms><tmp>in summer</tmp></ms>. And <ms><tmp>in
winter</tmp></ms>, when they put it to use, they sew it. But beforehand,
they put it in <m>dye</m> and commonly make it in three colors, green,
red, and sometimes violet. The green one is made in <m><pa>pastel</pa>
woad dye</m> only, because green being made from yellow and blue, the
<m><pa>pastel</pa> woad</m> discharging itself onto the <m>straw</m>,
which shows its dark yellow, one obtains bright green. For the red, they
use <m>alum</m> and <m><pa>brazilwood</pa></m>. For the violet, they use
<m><pa>pastel</pa> woad</m> &amp; a little <m>copperas</m>, which
darkens the blue with its black <m>dye</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p032v_2</id>

<head><pro>Glassworker</pro></head>

<ab>They have no invention for making a perfect red in a work, so that
one needs to reheat it. However try the <m><df><pl>German</pl>
red</df></m>, which is <fr>rouge d'escaille</fr>. They make their common
red with some <m>sanguine</m>, <m>looking-glass tin</m>, <m>rock
pieces</m>, <m>litharge</m> &amp; a bit of <m>scales of iron</m>. The
said red saturates one side &amp; the other of the <m>glass</m> in order
that it has more color, if it saturated only one side it would be very
pale orange.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p032v_3</id>

<head><pro>Founder</pro></head>

<ab>They pay xx <cn>lb</cn> for a <ms>quintal</ms> of <m>rosette</m>,
which is harder to melt than <m>latten</m> because it is softer. For,
the softer the <m><add>great</add> metals</m>
<add><mark>#</mark></add> are, the <del>soft</del> harder they are
to melt. The <m>tin used to make bells</m>, which is <m>fine tin</m>
<del>is more</del> and which is brittle, is easier to melt than <m>lead,
which is soft</m>. <m>Latten, made brittle by the <m>calamine</m></m> is
melted more quickly than <m>red copper</m>. The <m>metal, which is the
substance of bells</m>, mixed with <m>tin</m>, and very brittle, is soon
melted. The more <m>silver</m> is alloyed, the sooner it melts, that is
why <m>solder</m> is made with it. In <pl>Germany</pl> they make very
light candlesticks, it is because they turn them by means of
<m>water</m>, but they are breakable. A <ms>quintal</ms> of
<del><fr>per</fr></del> <m>fine <pro>coppersmith</pro>'s rosette</m> is
sold for xxx or 40 <cn>lb</cn>. Another type used by <pro>founders</pro>
is sold for xii or xv <cn>lb</cn>. The <ms>quintal</ms> of <m>metal</m>,
six <cn>lb</cn>.<del>Put in</del></ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>#</mark>

<m>Gold</m>, <m>silver</m> <m>copper</m><lb/>

<m>latten</m> <m>iron</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
