<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="014r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f33.image">




<div id="p014r_1" categories="household and daily life">



<head>For <env>walls</env> of <m>earth</m> and rustic construction<comment rid="c_014r_01"/></head>

<ab><al>Swallows</al> have taught us this craft, making their nests out
of <m>mud</m> mixed with <m>wisps</m> &amp; <m>stalks of hay or
straw</m> to make it bond. Therefore, in places where <m>stone</m> &amp;
<m>brick</m> are lacking, one can use <m>earth</m> to make partitions
&amp; <env>walls</env>. And for this, <m>light earth</m>, which does not
form clumps when plowed, but which is as if intermixed with
<m><fr>arene</fr></m>, holds first rank, because it can be beaten &amp;
tamped down better. It is true that one needs to moisten it &amp;
<del><fr>la</fr></del> cut it into the shape of sods with a <tl><po>ditch-spade</po></tl>, and
thus place &amp; arrange it. This one lasts longer and there is not as much
construction work, and <del><fr>ne</fr></del> dryness does not make it
crack &amp; split. But, because such kinds of <m>earth</m> are not found
everywhere, those who are on <env>good &amp; fertile land</env>, after
marking out with a <tl>measuring line</tl> the width &amp; length of
their foundations, drive <del>into the ground</del> in along the edges, 
on this side &amp; that, <tl>long poles</tl>
<del>&amp;</del> or <tl>chevron beams</tl> to support <tl>boards</tl>
between which they throw the <m>earth</m>, making each
layer one <ms><bp>foot</bp></ms> thick or thereabouts, intermixing it
as if <mark>S.S.S</mark><comment rid="c_014r_05"/> with <m>branches of <pa>heather</pa></m> or
similar things, then with <tl>beaters</tl> of three
different forms they <po>tamp</po> it &amp; beat it. One is called the
<tl>mallet</tl>, which has a triangular form like A, and with this, one
first <po>tamps</po> the <m>earth</m>. Next one uses one which is made of <m>blocks of
wood</m> pointed at the tip &amp; helved to a large stick, &amp; this one
is for pressing the <m>earth</m> well at the extremities and edges of
the <env>wall</env>, which adhere to the <tl>boards</tl>, &amp; is
called.<comment rid="c_014r_02"/> The other one is called the
<tl>bat</tl>, which is for flattening &amp; beating the <m>earth</m> for
the last time, as shown in C. Then one makes another layer of
<m>earth</m> <add>&amp; <m><pa>heather</pa></m></add> and beats it as
was said, &amp; continues thus until the <env>wall</env> is complete,
which one covers with <m><pa>heather</pa></m> &amp; then with
<m>earth</m>. Some <del><fr>m</fr></del> intermix rows of <m>bricks</m>
in the said wall. They also make the
<env>wall</env> tapering, giving <del><fr>a</fr></del> width to the
foundations according to how high one wants to raise the
<env>wall</env>. Which, when old, whitens, &amp; thereby shows that it
has <m>saltpeter</m> in it. That is why, when they fall down,
<pro>gunpowder makers</pro> profit from them.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p014r_1" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5b2lVN19SU1Z6UkU">







</figure>

</div>
</root>
