<root>
<page>134r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f273.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p133v_3</id>

<ab>

avoid putting <tl>points</tl>, which should not be put except at the
raising of the head, at the thickest places of the body &amp; the simple
&amp; delicate parts in the middle of the <al>lizard</al>’s feet, the
nails of which you will enter into the <tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl>, in
order that they remain secure. When you have made the first cast &amp;
uncovered the belly of the animal; do not forget to put small thin
<del><fr>s</fr></del> <tl>slabs of <m>wax</m></tl> at the end of the
<al>lizard</al>’s legs. But, if it is a <al>small wall lizard</al>,
lightly cover with <m>wax</m> the entire bottom of the foot,
<del>and</del> and <del>this</del> the <m>wax</m>, being removed after
the second cast, leaves a cavity which fills these small fingers with
<m>metal</m>, &amp; then one repairs them. Take heed therefore to attach
well with <m>wax</m> the parts of the animal which pass one over the
other, in order that the wet sand entering between two does not take it
away. <del>And if</del> For, if this were to happen<del> <tl>mold</tl>
would corrupt</del>, the shape <del>in the first place</del> would
<del>spoil</del> corrupt &amp; your <tl>mold</tl> also, because it would
not have the thickness that <del>it</del> you think &amp; would be
pierced &amp; spoiled. And, even though to avoid this you can make the
<tl>mold</tl> thicker, however, should <del><fr>l</fr></del> this mishap
happen, you will be able to repair it in this way.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p134r_1</id>

<head>For mending a pierced <tl>mold</tl></head>

<ab>

If the molded animal comes away in some place <del>to not have</del> and
deviates from the stance that you gave it, because it was not very dead,
or because it was not well attached with the <tl><m>iron</m> points</tl>
or with melted <m>wax</m>, and it does not have the thickness that it
needs on the outside, at the middle of the swelling, or is pierced,
before removing the animal from inside, uncover what seems to you the
weakest part, or else the place that is pierced, and make small holes
all around <corr><del>all around</del></corr>, then soak the back of the
<tl>mold</tl>. And cast promptly on top of the <add>same</add> wet sand,
which will enter in these openings &amp; mold &amp; attach to the other.
But, one will need to <m>lute</m> this place well afterwards. </ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p134r_2</id>

<head>Sand of <m><la>crocum</la></m></head>

<ab>

One can use the mixture of <m><la>crocum ferri</la></m> in
<tl>molds</tl> for <m>silver</m> as well as for <m>gold</m>, for it
firms them &amp; keeps them from cracking &amp; making flashing. And I
believe that for flat things it would withstand <del><fr>bien
de</fr></del> several casts, which, however, for <m>gold</m> &amp;
<m>silver</m> is hardly practiced.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

Try, for <m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m>, <m><la>crocum</la></m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
