<root>
<page>141v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f288.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p141r_1</id>

<ab>Having therefore let your <al>crayfish</al> dry a little <env>in the
sun</env> or on its own, if it has eggs, they will shrink while drying
and will only be more beautiful. Therefore make your <tl>slab of
<m>yellow <pro>potter</pro>’s earth</m></tl>, like for other figures,
lay your <al>crayfish</al> on top, the <del><fr>s</fr></del> back
<del>on top</del> <add>on the bottom</add>, &amp; the legs, belly &amp;
eggs, which are all the most fanciful parts to mold, on the other side
and on the top. Push the back down in the <tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl>,
up to near the legs, which is about halfway. And fix the body with an
<tl><m>iron wire</m> point</tl> in the middle &amp; if it seems
necessary, another, at the end of the tail. And in order that the
<add>big</add> legs show themselves lower than the head, which is
<del><fr>enf</fr></del> half sunken, <corr>extend</corr> them &amp; from
underneath add to them a little <m>clay</m> to raise them. Hide also the
horns in the <m>clay</m>, under the big legs, to arrange them afterwards
as you like. As for small legs, extend them on the <m>clay</m>
until the joint, and the other half of the legs remain above, curved,
for the first cast. However, in order that they do not move &amp;
detach, secure them well, not only on the <m>clay</m>, but
<del><fr>att</fr></del> fix them with <m>wax</m> &amp; a <tl>little hot
<m>iron</m></tl> straight in the joints. And if you want to find the
most fanciful cast, you can attach the end of one of the legs with the
same <m>wax</m> on the body, or on one of the big legs, and aso make, if
it has eggs, the tail to be half folded on the eggs, &amp; fix it in
this form with an <tl><m>iron wire</m> point</tl>. Take special heed,
since the thing is <del><fr>s</fr></del> thus arranged, that it can be
well cleaned. Lastly, having rubbed the <al>crayfish</al> with
<m>eau-de-vie</m>, cast your sand. Having set, uncover the back of the
<al>crayfish</al>, the head &amp; the eyes &amp; its little pincers, the
big legs and the small legs all along, for one needs to uncover the most
that one can, both the long horns &amp; the tail, except if you have
folded &amp; curved it to hold the eggs. Other animals</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Secure what has detached,
<corr>like</corr> the hairy brows near the mouth, with some <m>melted
wax</m> underneath.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p141v_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5R0NIbHoyNTNQRlk</link>

</figure>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Uncover the most that you can, but take
heed that the notching that you make in the <tl>mold</tl> will release
well.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Make the <tl>mold</tl> lean on the side
that is the thickest of the animal.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>To paint it, one does the middle of the
back <del>mixed</del> with <m>vermilion</m>, mixed with a little
<m>lake</m>, and the sides &amp; the belly &amp; underneath the legs is
of a carnation made of <m>vermilion</m>, <m>white of ceruse</m>, a
little <m>yellow ochre</m>. As in this &amp; all other things, have
always the natural thing in front of you to imitate it.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Lay the horns on the big legs,
<del>&amp;</del> or make with <m>whitened latten wire</m> &amp;
<m>solder</m> them.</ab>

<ab><margin>bottom</margin>Take heed <del><fr>d</fr></del>, when
modling, to arrange the legs in such a way that they do not pass the
belly of the <al>crayfish</al>, <del><fr>Aultr</fr></del> and that,
placing them, they sit well on the belly, otherwise they <ill/>
move.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
