<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="108v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f222.image">




<div continues="yes" id="p108r_2" categories="casting">





<ab>thus one mixes it &amp; reduces it into
<del><fr>p</fr></del><comment rid="c_091v_01"/> <m>small stones</m>, purging it of its
<m>impurities</m>. Then, one puts it to cook neatly in a
<del><tl>pot</tl></del> <add><tl>earthen vessel</tl></add><comment rid="c_108v_02"/> in
the <tl><fr>fornaise</fr> of <pro>those who make <tl>pots</tl></pro></tl>, and one
leaves it there until the <tl>pots</tl> are cooked. Next, one mixes it
again with <m>sal ammoniac water</m> &amp; one grinds it very well,
and one empties the <m>muddy &amp; clean water</m> into a separate
<tl>vessel</tl>. Again, one puts the same <m>water</m> on top &amp;
one grinds, &amp; again one puts the <m>muddy water</m> with the other.
And one does thus, until it has passed everything. In this way, one
purges &amp; cleanses it, &amp; one renders it very fine &amp;
handleable. Having taken away the <m>water</m> by tilting it or with a
<tl>sponge</tl>, one takes the residue and one dries it. Then,
moistening it with the aforesaid <m>water</m>, like one does with
the other <del><m>water</m></del> <m>sand</m>, one uses it in a
<tl>frame</tl>, where, if it retracts, it is a sign that it
has not reheated enough &amp; that one needs to reheat it further. This
one is appropriate for molding all <m>metals</m>, and especially
<m>gold</m> &amp; <m>silver</m>, and the more it is used, the better it
is. One needs to set aside the one in which you cast <m>lead</m> or
<m>tin</m>, for it would sour the <m>gold</m> you would cast in it.</ab></div>
    
<div id="p108r_2" part="y">
<ab><emph><m>Feather alum</m></emph> should be reheated in a
<del><tl>cauldron</tl></del> <add><tl>crucible</tl> covered
with a <tl><m>tile</m></tl></add> in a strong <del>flame</del>
fire of <add>charcoals</add>, in order that the <m>impurity</m> which could be there
burns with the <m>feather alum</m>, which does not burn. This is done either in the
<tl><pro>goldsmith</pro>'s forge</tl>, <tl>surrounded with
<m>bricks</m></tl>, or in a <tl><fr>fourneau à vent</fr></tl> with
fusion fire, so that the <del>sand remains <tmp>long enough</tmp></del> 
<add><tl>crucible</tl> for a
<ms><tmp>quarter of an hour</tmp></ms> remains</add> red. This is done more to cleanse it
than for anything else. It becomes reddish on the surface &amp; on the
inside it remains white &amp; better dried out. <mark>#</mark><comment rid="c_112r_02"/></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle" render="tall">

<mark>#</mark><comment rid="c_112r_03"/><lb/>
After your <m>feather alum</m> is cooled,
<tl>pestle</tl> it in a <tl>mortar</tl>, then grind it on <tl><m>marble</m></tl>, and it will be rendered into very fine wooly
filaments which give bond to the <m>sand</m> without getting burned as
other things do, which is a beautiful invention. <tl>Pestle</tl> it in the
<tl>mortar</tl> by dragging the <tl>pestle</tl>, for the flying dust
could enter your <bp>throat</bp> or land on your <bp>face</bp>, which
will give you <sn>reason to scratch yourself well</sn>. Put it in the <tl>mortar</tl> a little
at a time to avoid the flying dust. It is
better</ab>

<ab margin="bottom" render="full">to grind it thus, in the <tl>mortar</tl>, dragging the
<tl>pestle</tl>, than on <tl><m>marble</m></tl>,
<del>for</del> where <del><fr>c</fr></del> it spreads, &amp; in
the <tl>mortar</tl>, it collects on all sides. Render it very fine &amp;
<sn>soft to the touch</sn>.</ab>

<ab><emph><m>Clay</m></emph> to make circles around <tl>molds</tl> should
be very fatty &amp; handleable, and serves only to make the surrounding of
the <tl>molds</tl>. Thus, one ought only to choose the quite fatty kind, and beat
very well, &amp; moisten it moderately with some <m>water</m>, &amp; keep
it in a <tl>pit</tl> or in a <tl><fr>terrine</fr></tl>, and make numerous
holes with a <tl>stick</tl> in it, which fill with <m>water</m>, in
order to keep it always fresh &amp; soft, so that it is always ready to use
when you need it.<hr/></ab>

</div>
</root>
