<root>
<page>126r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f257.item</image>

<div>

<id>p126r_1</id>

<head>Molding fruits and animals in <m>sugar</m></head>

<ab><m>Sugar</m> is fatty <add>when runny and brittle &amp; breakable
when dry</add>, and with it, one casts well round things &amp; large
muscles, but awkwardly things fine &amp; delicate. However, try <m>well
clarified sugar</m>. One needs to soak for one <ms><tmp>night</tmp></ms>
or one <ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms> the <tl><m>plaster</m> mold</tl> before
casting the <m>sugar</m>, in order that is very full of <m>water</m>
&amp; does not imbibe the <m>syrup</m>. One needs also for it to be of
easy release, for the <m>sugar</m> is sour &amp; brittle. Finally, do
not consider casting anything in <m>sugar</m> that does not release well
and that cannot be neatly molded in two halves, to open it when you will
need to. If you want to mold a bunch of <pa>grapes</pa>, one needs to
take it, like any other fruit, in its true vigor, for if it is withered,
it will <del><fr>ne</fr></del> come out that way. Take heed, therefore,
to make your <tl>molds</tl> in the natural <tmp>season</tmp> of
<del><fr>que</fr></del> all things. The <pa>grapes</pa>, that are
usually wanted cast in <m>sugar</m>, can be made artificially or with
<m>wax</m> or <m>earth</m>, or even with some <pa>grapes</pa> attached
with some melted <m>wax</m> on some <tl>slab</tl> &amp; other full
thing, so that they are very close together and when released &amp; only
make up one half. Or, if you have some of those <pa>grapes</pa> called
<pa>chauches</pa> or <pa>sauvignons</pa>, which have the <pa>grapes</pa>
very close together, encase half of them <del>on</del> in the
<tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl> and cast on the other half. And if some of the
<pa>grapes</pa> are not released, pluck them out. Note that neither in
<m>sugar</m>, nor in <m>metal</m>, can a bunch which has light &amp;
separated <pa>grapes</pa> be cast properly, because the end of the bunch
is so delicate, especially if you keep the bunch, that it could not
withstand the large <pa>grapes</pa>. Thus, you will need to cast
hollow, which you could not do if the bunch does not have close
<pa>grapes</pa> &amp; <del><tl>molds</tl></del> without having them
scattered &amp; spread apart.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

To cast <pa>pears</pa> &amp; <pa>apples</pa> in <m>sugar</m>, one ought
not make any gates, but rather, fill one half of the <tl>mold</tl> and
then join the two, and keep turning it until the <m>sugar</m> has set
and is cold. One ought to mix nothing in the <tl>mold</tl> apart from
<m>plaster</m>, reheated as you know.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>+</mark>

One needs for the <tl>mold</tl> to have soaked <ms>one <tmp>day</tmp>
and one <tmp>night</tmp></ms> in <m>cold water</m> <del>for</del>, and
to be humid, when you cast in <m>sugar</m>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

The sign that the <m>syrup</m> or the <m>sugar melted in water</m> is sufficiently
cooked to cast fruits, is when it makes threads when shaken. And
if it passes that point, it is not good, for it will always be humid. If
the <m>sugar</m> attaches to it, one needs to throw some
<m><pa>wheat</pa> starch</m> in the <tl>mold</tl>, or to rub it with an
<tl><m><pa>almond</pa></m></tl>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
