<root>
<page>168r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f341.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p167r_1</id>

<figure>

<id>fig_p168r_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5RUdzVWVNM3l6QVU</link>

</figure>

<ab>a <tl>peg</tl> which one puts into the touch-hole, &amp; then, with
a rope wrapped around the end of a <tl>stick</tl>, one gives fire &amp;
promptly retreats to take cover. The small petards of 16 or 17
<ms>lb</ms> are attached promptly with a <tl>short hooked peg</tl> made
like a <tl>wimble</tl><comment>c_168r_01</comment>, &amp; if the petard
is of a good alloy, one can give fire by <bp>hand</bp> just as one does
with petards of 27 <ms>lb</ms>, but then one only puts in three
<ms>lb</ms> of <m>powder</m>. It must certainly be a strong door if the
seventeen <ms>lb</ms> petard does not blow it up. Some use <tl>little
bells</tl> worn by <al>oxen</al> or <al>mules</al> on a
<pro>peasant</pro> door. Others load two pistol barrels &amp;, with a
<tl>gimlet</tl> &amp; a <tl>string</tl>, attach them with the muzzle
against the door. If the petards are good &amp; do not explode, they
only recoil and cannot do harm if one is next to them.</ab>

<ab>A. This is a <tl>small peg, hooked like the hinge of a door</tl>
&amp; made like a <tl><oc>gimlet</oc></tl><comment>c_080r_01</comment> on one end for quickly
attaching a small petard with ears of fifteen or xvii <ms>lb</ms> for a
common door or window.</ab>

<ab>B. This is a small petard with ears.</ab>

<ab>C. This is a <del>larg</del> common petard of 27 or 30 <ms>lb</ms>
pierced at the breech, through which a large <tl><m>iron</m> peg</tl>
passes, button-like on one end &amp; made like a
<tl><oc>gimlet</oc></tl><comment>c_080r_01</comment> at the point, for quickly attaching the petard
against a door that <del>does not have</del> <add>is not</add>
<add>covered</add> with <m>iron plates</m>.</ab>

<ab>D. These are <m>plates of wax, cork, &amp; wood</m>
for loading the petard &amp; sealing the <m>powder</m> well.</ab>

<ab>E. <del>This</del> <tl><m>Iron</m> fork made in the form of pincers
of the <ms>height of a man</ms></tl>, to quickly place the mortar
without a <tl>peg</tl>. It must be of <m><fr>doux</fr> iron</m> in order
that its branches bend easily, if need be, to fit to the height or width
of the door.</ab>

<ab>F. This is another <tl><m>iron</m> fork</tl> of the same height that
props up the <tl>fork made like pincers</tl> &amp; also supports the
petard, and with its claw at the bottom prevents the <tl>pincers</tl>
from recoiling.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
