<root>
<page>029r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f63.image</image>

<div>

<id>p029r_1</id>

<head><m>Stucco</m> for molding</head>

<ab>Take <m>tragacanth gum</m> and put it to soak until, having drunk
its <m>water</m>, it is swollen &amp; rendered like <m>jelly</m>. Then
crush it quite hard on the <tl><m>marble</m></tl> &amp; next take
<m><pa>rye</pa> flour</m>, which is better than <m><pa>wheat</pa></m>
because it is more humid and does not make the paste as brittle, and
sprinkle your <m>tragacanth gum</m> with it, &amp; continue to grind
<add>and mix in</add> thus, little by little, <del><fr>le et mesler
legi</fr></del> the very finely sieved <m>flour</m>. And knead it as if
you wanted to make <m>bread</m>, until <del>you</del> you perceive that
it has enough body &amp; is as firm as <m>bread dough</m> that one is
ready to put in the <tl>oven</tl>. This is perceivable when it can
stretch enough without breaking. And if it was not strong enough, it
would not <del><fr>sti</fr></del> release well. Thus once prepared, rub
the cavity <del><fr>au u</fr></del> with <m>oil</m>, with a
<tl>brush</tl>, in order that the <m>oil</m> penetrates everywhere to make it
release better, and press the paste inside quite hard. And if it does
not release well, mix in more <m>flour</m> until it has enough body.
With this you will mold whatever work you like, masks or garlands, which
will be dry within one <ms>day</ms>. Next, you will apply them with
<m>strong glue</m> or <m>paste glue</m>, as you like, and you will be
able to paint and decorate them with <m>gold</m> &amp; all colors. One
makes ceiling ornaments with it in <pl>Rome</pl>. One can make bed
ornaments with it. <rub>If you want that the work stays white</rub>, it
is better to mold with <m>plaster</m> instead of <m>flour</m>. It is
true that it is more brittle and firm as well, but one needs to prepare
it like this: temper it, when it is powdered <del>strong</del>, in a
good amount of <m>water</m> so that it is <add>clear</add>, &amp; grind
it several times a day for fifteen <ms>days</ms>. Then pour off the
<m>water</m> by tilting, and gather the <m>plaster</m> &amp; grind it
finely on the <tl><m>marble</m></tl>, &amp; place it in some kind of
clean <tl><m>lead</m> vessel</tl>, so that no dust &amp; dirt falls into
it, &amp; leave it <env>in the open air</env> &amp; <env><fr>au
serain</fr></env> for fifteen <ms>days</ms> with its <m>water</m>, and
it will become matte, strong, white and light, very suitable for making
a ground for burnished <m>gold</m>. And this, in powder form, you
can mix, instead of <m>flour</m>, with <m>tragacanth gum</m>, and your
work will be very beautiful. Lacking <m>plaster</m>, you can mix in well
ground <m>chalk</m> or <m>ceruse</m>, &amp; try <m>bole</m> &amp;
similar things. This <m>stucco</m> with the <m>tragacanth gum</m> has
the quality, being malleable before being dry, of fitting on either
round or flat things, as you like. It is to make an ornament at little
expense.

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<m>Flour</m> is not good in this, but <m>chalk</m> or <m>ceruse</m> is.

</ab>

</div>
</root>
