<root>
<page>144r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f293.image</image>

<div>

<id>p144r_1</id>

<head><al>Turtles</al></head>

<ab><al>Those of <env>water</env></al> are more beautiful &amp; easier
to mold <del>than those</del>, being flatter &amp; having a longer head
&amp; tail <del><fr>q</fr></del> and legs straighter &amp; better to
release than <al>those of the <pl><env><fr>garrigue</fr></env></pl></al>, which
are lean, wrinkled &amp; well ensconced in their shell, which also have
a rounder top of the shell &amp; however narrower <del><fr>v</fr></del>
on the sides than near the middle, which is the reason their
<del><fr>l</fr></del> top shell cannot be molded well in one piece, like
<al>those of the <env>water</env></al>. <del>Therefore</del> Thus, you
will mold their top shell in two pieces, the bottom ones in two or three
of four, according to the need. But, note that if you want to release
your <al>turtle</al> from the <tl>mold</tl> without burning it, it needs
to be molded it thus in several pieces. But, if you want it to be burned
<del><fr>p</fr></del> inside, you can mold the top shell in one piece.
Therefore, to start working hands-on, after you have killed it entirely
in <m>vinegar</m> &amp; <m><bp>urine</bp></m>, as said, let it dry well. And
clean it well with your <tl>cloth</tl>. Next, <del>not</del> take your
<tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl> and put it on top and smudge it a little, in order
that the bottom shell fastens to it, having, nevertheless, earlier
shaped the head with a <tl>strong point</tl>, as with other animals,
making it hold high by the means of <del>one</del> a little <tl><m>fresh
clay</m></tl>, that you will adapt from underneath. Stretch the said
head &amp; legs with your <tl>little pincers</tl>. The head arranged,
dexterously place <del><fr>d</fr></del> a <m>grain of <pa>yellow
millet</pa></m> in each eye with <tl>pincers</tl>, because as soon as
they are dead the eyes are burst and filthy. You can do this as well
with all other small animals, with the <m>grain of <pa>large
amaranth</pa></m>, the <m><pa>small one</pa></m>, and the <m>grain of
<pa>rapeseed</pa></m>, &amp; this done, you will arrange the legs,
securing them with <tl><m>iron</m> points</tl> and then, with some
<m>clay</m>, fill up all the empty space around the <al>turtle</al>,
that is to say what is between the two shells, in order that the sand
entering there does not prevent it from releasing. And because the legs
should be lower than the shell of the <del><fr>s</fr></del>
<del><fr>e</fr></del> <del>of</del> belly, make a little pit in the
<tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl> to adapt them there. Your <al>turtle</al></ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

<render>tall</render>

When they are better mortified &amp; rested two or three
<ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms>, they bend and are handled better.</ab>

<figure>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<id>fig_p144r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5emg1MXZLREtSRk0</link>

</figure>

<ab>

<man><margin>left-middle</margin>

animal eyes of my invention</man></ab>

<figure>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<id>fig_p144r_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5ZkN6Y3ZTM1pKRG8</link>

</figure>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
