<root>
<page>163v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f332.image</image>

<div>

<id>p163v_1</id>

<head><al>Crayfish</al></head>

<ab>The hairy cornicles that it has under its beak
<del><fr>coe</fr></del> tend to come out lumpy &amp; not neat because,
being burnt, it is difficult to remove them &amp; clean their
<m>ash</m>, which, staying in the <tl>mold</tl>, <del>it</del> prevents
the <m>metal</m> from running well therein; &amp; for that reason, one
makes a small gate of <m>wax</m> thread at the tips of them, both to
hold them up and to blow out the clogging <m>ash</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

Spare no <tl>pins</tl>, placing them not only in the middle of the body,
but also on the big legs, and two or three at the tail, according to the
stance that you want to <corr>give</corr> it.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p163v_2</id>

<head><m><la>Crocum</la></m></head>

<ab>That which is rusty by itself, being showered with <m>salt water</m>
or <m>vinegar</m> or <m><bp>urine</bp></m>, and then <add>very</add>
dried out <add>and reddened in fire</add>, is very red ground on
<tl><m>porphyry</m></tl> and is of the color of <m><pl>Levant</pl>
bole</m>, &amp; approaching <m>minium</m>. But that which is showered
with <m><bp>urine</bp></m> &amp; dried out acquires a deeper tincture
&amp; approaches <m>crushed <la>aes ustum</la></m> or <m>vermillion</m>.
But the first one, finely ground, acquires a bright red color, <del>in
the</del> like <m>cinnabar</m>, in <m>eau-de-vie</m>. And the ones and
the others, prepared as said, and finely ground &amp; rendered very hot,
give off a <m>red smoke</m> like a volatile spirit if, being thus hot
and fine, one throws on top <m>vinegar</m>, <m><bp>urine</bp></m>, or
<m>eau-de-vie</m>. <m><bp>Urine</bp></m> gives much tincture, and
<m>eau-de-vie</m> also.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p163v_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5anJvd0FQQ3BkRFE</link>

</figure>

</div>

<div>

<id>p163v_3</id>

<head>Repairing</head>

<ab>It is better to repair little with the <tl>burin</tl> called
<tl><fr>onglet</fr></tl>, or with that which one calls
<tl><fr>chaple</fr></tl>, or some <tl>small file</tl>. But above all,
avoid touching your work, but only the flashing or lump that will have
occurred during the cast. And while repairing, wet &amp; rub with your
<tl>small <m><al>piglet</al>-bristle</m> brushes</tl>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
