<root>
<page>164v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f334.item</image>

<div>

<id>p164v_1</id>

<head>Molds</head>

<ab>

For those <del>qui</del> in which one needs to burn something, and which
do not open before being reheated, one does not make any casts before it
is reheated. For large molds in which the gate is big and ample, it is
necessary that the gate be well notched &amp; scratched, in order that
the weight of the metal does not go with much force. They make hardly
any fins if they are pressed. But before pressing them, put between them
and the press some pieces of thick &amp; <fr>mouflé</fr> felt, which is
hardly yet crushed, for it fills the concavities &amp; keeps the mold
from breaking. The clamps should be placed before reheating or drying
it.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

When the earth, from which you make the earth slab to arrange your
animal, is too soft, the points that you put in it come out easily
&amp;come undone when you thrown in the sand &amp; thus the mold spoils
and the shape comes undone. Therefore when you recognise that your slab
is too tender &amp; soft, spread on top some hot ashes &amp; blow with
bellows.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p164v_2</id>

<head>Sable</head>

<ab>

If there is not enough good <m><fr>alum de plume</fr></m> or
<m>crocum</m>, it will easily break in the fire. But if it is mixed with
it, as it should be, it withstands it. One recognizes it as good when,
being hot after the cast, it quickly imbibes water when one quenches it
in it, &amp; breaks <del>rend</del> easily because the alum &amp; the
crocum render it spongy. Contrarily, bad sand, which is only of plaster
&amp; brick, &amp; little mixed with alum, breaks easily in the fire
&amp; hardens in water. Cast, if possible, all in one go.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p164v_3</id>

<head>Molds</head>

<ab>

Even though you cast in lead, the molds want to be well dried,
especially when they are large, and one needs to redden them on the
outside &amp; keep them in continuous heat, until they no longer smoke
from inside. Do not place them to reheat at different moments, but
continue once you have started. And do not place them to cool in the
cold, <del>with</del> for they would break, but leave them to become
lukewarm near the fire, &amp; like they are when of such a heat that you
have noticed before, when putting your finger in the gated hole. And
when the mold is large, it needs more time to reheat &amp; dry &amp; one
needs to cast hotter.</ab>

</div>
</root>
