<root>
<page>154r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f313.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p154r_1</id>
<head><m>Gold</m> not being fixed</head>

<ab><m>Gold as gilding</m> goes away once the piece is reheated &amp;
kept in high heat, especially if there is some <m>lead</m>, for
<m>lead</m> will pierce in the fire a piece with <m>gold</m>, because it
holds closely with <m>☿</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p154r_2</id>
<head>Cutting <m>lead</m></head>

<ab>Because it is fat &amp; sticks &amp; attacks the <tl>knife</tl> or
<tl>chisel</tl>, wet it &amp; you will cut it like <m>glass</m>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>

Sometimes <m>gold</m> &amp;<m>silver</m> take on, through certain smoke,
some color during the casting. But these are not at all scales &amp;
<fr>chappe</fr>, but rather this color goes aways with <m>whitening</m>
&amp; <fr><m>bullitoire</m></fr>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p154r_3</id>
<head>Sweetening <m>silver</m></head>

<ab>When <pro>goldsmiths, who are working with large works</pro> have
forged their platters, it very often happens with their sheddings that
it bursts &amp; cracks for being too soured. To avoid this, throw in,
when it is well melted, some <m>dry mortar</m>, composed of sand &amp;
<m>good lime</m> which has been worked, &amp; pulverize it &amp; throw
it in.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<pro>Goldsmiths</pro> do not work at all with
<m><cn>real</cn>silver</m>, that is not alloyed, because it is
<m>leady</m> &amp; when forging it sours.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

Some solder, for small works &amp; things which only go in the fire
once, with some <cn>old <fr>sol</fr></cn> &amp; reheated &amp; beaten
<cn>carolus</cn>. However, if the <cn><fr>sol</fr></cn> is not very
good, the <m>solder</m> eats away &amp; one needs to solder on it twice
&amp; there is too much <m>copper</m> on it. Others solder with
<ms>half</ms> <m>silver</m> &amp; <ms>half</ms> <m>fine copper</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p154r_4</id>
<head><m>Iron scales</m></head>

<ab>Once well pulverized &amp; ground on <tl><m>marble</m></tl> &amp;
mixed with the above-mentioned sand of <fr>noyau</fr>, and dried slowly
without reheating, it endures several casts of <m>lead</m> &amp;
<m>tin</m>. <m>Copper</m> &amp; <m>latten</m> come out well. But if it
is not well ground, like <m><la>crocum</la></m>, it goes to the bottom,
if the sand is not wetted thickly enough.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p154r_5</id>
<head><m>Metal filings</m></head>

<ab>They are not made by themselves, if they are not helped with some
portion of similar <m>metal</m>, melted for gathering &amp; putting them
in a <tl>bath</tl>, for it is sooner burned than melted. <m>Tin and lead
filings</m> are made with <m>tallow</m>, <m>the one of gold</m> with
<m>salpeter</m>, the <m>one of silver</m> with <m>sandever</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
