<root>
<page>127v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f260.image</image>

<div>
<id>p127v_1</id>
<head><m><pro>Founders</pro>’ earth</m></head>

<ab>It is <m><fr>terre bolbene</fr></m> mixed with <m>dung</m> or
<m>cloth waste</m>, which withstand fire, which you need to always have
provision of, to <m>lute</m> your <tl>molds</tl> which <del><fr>ont
b</fr></del> must be used to cast <m>silver</m> &amp; that you need to
reheat. Those, where one needs to burn some flower or animal, should not
be <m>luted</m>, until they have been reheated once and they have been cleaned
from <m>bones</m> &amp; <m>ashes</m> remaining inside. And having
removed the <tl>clamps</tl>, you have opened the two halves to see if
they have any cracks. For there is some <m>plaster </m>that is not so
hard in the fire, the one as much as the other. Moreover, there is some
which makes crusty the things which stay burning inside. And these are
imperfections that one needs to avoid, either <del>by</del> by bathing
well with <m>eau-de-vie</m> the animal before casting in the wet sand,
or mixing in more or less <m>brick</m>, or <m>alum</m>, or reheating the
<m>brick</m> more, or in place of the <m>brick</m>, mixing in
<m><tl>crucible</tl> bottoms</m> &amp; similar things which resist well
in the fire. Having therefore reheated your <tl>mold</tl> to burn it
inside, leave to cool well. And if it is neat &amp; not cracked, reput
the <tl>clamps</tl> &amp; <m>lute</m> it with this <m>above mentioned
<pro>founders</pro>’ earth</m> &amp; sprinkle a little <m>sifted ash</m>
&amp; let dry a little. But keep yourself from <m>luting</m> <del>that they are
not</del> until the <tl>molds</tl> are cold. Those for casting
<m>silver</m>, where there is nothing to burn inside, only need, except
when the gate &amp; vents are made, <m>luting</m> &amp; reheating once. Do not
<m>lute</m> the end of the <tl>mold</tl> where you want to make your gate,
rather leave it uncovered &amp; the exit of the vent as well. </ab>

<ab><add>If</add> <rub>the <tl>molds</tl></rub> <del>that</del> were
<del>do</del> <add>to</add> crack, it is <del>make thus</del> at the
first reheating, for at the second, they no longer crack.</ab>

<ab><rub>The smallest</rub> <tl>molds</tl> are reheated more quickly.
Take <del>the</del> therefore the first ones reheated when you cast, for
you can put several of them to reheat.</ab>

<ab>Light the charcoals, firstly in the <tl>forge</tl>, or in some other
place nearby, &amp; having placed your <tl>molds</tl> on a layer of good
embers, not burning too much, to have a slow fire at the beginning, put
there &amp; adjust a little the half-lit charcoals in the
<tl>forge</tl>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
The <m>earth that <pro>founders</pro> use to braze or solder</m>, which
is <m>sandy clay earth</m>, or else <m>clay mixed with sand</m>, after
having dried &amp; <tl>sieved</tl> &amp; then composed it, is good for
<m>luting</m> your <tl>molds</tl>, because this <m>earth</m> melts rather than
cracks. And any <m>earth</m> that melts <del>is</del> cannot be lacking
in this.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<add><tl><m>Iron wire</m></tl> to give it bond.</add></ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p127v_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5S2VzRmhYUWpfbmc</link>

</figure>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<add><m>Lute</m> thickly your <tl>molds</tl>, &amp; if they are small, you can
reheat them immediately in a good fire, especially those of
<m><la>crocum</la></m>.</add></ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
If the <m>earth</m> is good, &amp; <del><fr>l</fr></del> does not crack
while reheating, &amp; does not separate from the <tl>mold</tl>, the
<tl>molds</tl> will also not crack &amp; will not make flashing at the
casting. Reheat with slow ease in a closed fire &amp; do not expose them
hot to the air.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<m>Lute</m> rather thickly in two or three layers, especially right in the
joints, in order that the <m>silver</m> does not come out of the
<tl>mold</tl>. </ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Reheat in a <tl><fr>four de reverberation</fr></tl>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
To test if your <m>earth</m> is good, before putting it on your
<tl>mold</tl>, <m>lute</m> <add>at</add> the place of the <del>fo</del> wall of
the <tl>forge</tl> which is around the <tl><fr>tuelle</fr></tl> &amp;
barrel of the <tl>bellow</tl>, &amp; light the fire &amp; if it withstands
this without cracking, it will be good.</ab>

</div>
</root>
