<root>
<page>151r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f307.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p150v_1</id>

<ab>the <m>white wax</m> with which you have composed your <m>black
sulphured wax</m>, has such little substance, since being dry and
purified, that it leaves nothing inside, and flows very gently. As for
the <m>charcoal</m> which is mixed in, if some remains, it burns &amp;
reduces to <m>ash</m> &amp; is emptied afterwards, by blowing through
the gate. You could even open your <tl>mold</tl> after the <m>wax</m>
has melted, if there is no fanciful thing which could break, like some
reattached thing or similar. After having covered the <tl>clamps</tl>
with the <m>lute</m> from your sand &amp; having covered all of the
<tl>mold</tl>, give it on top a layer of <m>common lute</m>, &amp; then
sprinkle this with some <m><tl>pestled</tl> brick</m>, in order that you can
handle it better. Let the <m>lute</m> dry slowly, before firing it,
which melts the <m>wax</m>. The <m>wax</m> having left through the gate,
that which remains with the <m>charcoal</m> will burn. Being reheated
for the first time, <m>lute</m> it <del><fr>pou</fr></del> once more,
<del>to reheat it the second time</del> because the <m>plaster</m>, not
being good, will have readily made the <tl>mold</tl> retract, and the
joints will crack open, which might make large flashing. And for the second
time, one ought not to reheat it, if you only want to cast in
<m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m>, but rather only make sure that the
<m>lute</m> is quite dry &amp; the <tl>mold</tl> moderately hot. For
these <al>turtles</al> that have a large size &amp; enough thickness, it
is better to <del>mold <fr>ault</fr></del> cast <del>your
<m>lead</m></del> an alloy <ms>half</ms> of <m>lead</m> &amp;
<ms>half</ms> of <m>tin</m>, especially for hollow things. For, if you
only have very thin &amp; very weak things to cast, like flowers, rely
rather on the abundance of <m>lead</m> than of <m>tin</m>, which becomes
porous, once cast a little thick, &amp; readily makes some flaw around
the cast. <pn>Master Alexandre</pn> says that he has never gone wrong
with <ms>half</ms> <m>tin</m> &amp; <ms>half</ms> <m>lead</m> for things
weighty &amp; with the <ms>thickness of the <tl>back of a
knife</tl></ms>. If there is <m><la>crocum</la></m>, the joints hardly
appear &amp; consequently the flashing is very small &amp; thin. You can
repair &amp; through the hole of the belly, pull the <m>earth</m> of the
<fr>noyau</fr>, leaving it wet a long time,</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

When you have cast your <m>black wax</m> in the <del><fr>a</fr></del>
<tl>mold</tl>, &amp; when it is well cold, you need to <del>the</del>
open your <tl>mold</tl> halfway, to make the cast. And if the
figure of <m>black wax</m> breaks, there is no danger, for it
can always be reattached with a <tl>hot <m>iron</m> <del>touching</del>
point</tl>. Or else, if the pieces are not separated from the
<tl>mold</tl>, <del><fr>qu</fr></del> they meet up &amp; join like
beforehand, by joining &amp; binding well the two halves of the
<tl>mold</tl>. When the representation is large, one needs to cross
inside many <tl><m>iron wires</m></tl>, to sustain the <fr>noyau</fr>.

<figure>

<id>fig_p151r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dEhadHEzVWlxejg</link>

</figure>

</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>A</mark><comment>c_151r_01</comment>only in <m>lead</m> or
<m>tin</m>. However, one needs to redden the <tl>mold</tl> nearly as
much as if there were inside some animal to burn, in order that the
<m>wax</m> melts well &amp; leaves nothing inside &amp; flows on its
own, by keeping the <tl>mold</tl> leaning towards the gate when
reheating it. And when the <tl>mold</tl> is reheated, leave it to cool
gently, then blow inside, and draw towards yourself, while sucking, in
order that the <m>ashes of the wax</m> come out. Do this with a
<tl>bellows</tl>.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
