<root>
<page>117r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f239.image</image>

<div>
<id>p117r_1</id>
<head>A means of molding flowers and plants</head>

<ab>One needs to choose them in their full verdure &amp; vivacity, &amp;
<del><fr>les mou</fr></del> not pick them, if possible, until the time
one will want to mold them, so that they do not wilt. Or if you need to
carry them from afar, soak their stems in a <tl>bottle of
<m>water</m></tl>, or better still <m>wine</m>. Make, firstly, a
<m>wax</m> stick pointed like a big peg, of a size appropriate to what
you want to cast, as you see in the margin, marked A. Put &amp; prick at
the foot of this small peg a bit of rather thickish &amp;
strong <m>iron wire</m>. And at the point of this, you will fit your flower stem or your
plant. This done, set it aside neatly. And arrange your
<del><tl>mold</tl> of t</del> circle &amp; shape of <m>clay</m> as you
have done for the <al>snakes</al>, in the form of a <mu>mandore</mu>
<del>in such a way that</del> according to the size of your plant. Then
take the one that you have prepared to be cast, as we have taught you,
&amp; wet &amp; moisten it very carefully with <m>good
<add>eau-de-vie</add></m> with a <tl>pinceau</tl>. Then pass the
<tl>wire stem</tl> through the end of the <m>earthen</m>
<mu>mandore</mu>, in order that the <m>wax</m> <del><fr>q</fr></del>
peg, where the plant is fastened, joins to the end of the <m>earthen</m>
<mu>mandore</mu>. And arrange thus your plant in such a way lying down
that it remains in the middle of aforesaid <mu>mandore</mu>, without
touching on either side, so that <del>a</del> the sand that you will
pour in it will be of equal thickness <del>as</del> everywhere, &amp;
<corr><del>is</del></corr> exceeds everywhere by the height of two good
<ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> the top of the <del>such</del> plant. And
having secured the <tl>wire stem</tl> well, promptly pour <del>wet</del>
your wet sand, much clearer than the one for <al>snakes</al>, in the
<mu>mandore</mu>. And the sooner the better, in order that the
<m>eau-de-vie</m> does not dry. And take heed to put in a little more
<m>water of sal ammoniac among the
common</m><comment>c_117r_02</comment> than you would do for the
<al>snakes</al>. And when you will make sand especially for your
bouquets, where you would mix in a little more <m>feather alum</m>, it
will be that much better. Thus your <tl>mold</tl> will be in one piece
and it will not be necessary to unjoin it, but rather <del>leave</del>
separate it from the <m>clay</m> once it will have set, let it dry, and
then reheat it again until the plants are burnt.
<del><fr>peys</fr></del> And note that if the plant you want to cast has
a strong stalk &amp; stem, you can cast it lying down, as had been said.
But if it is some weak &amp; delicate <add>flower</add>, <del>cast</del>
plant it upright with the <tl><m>wax</m> peg</tl> because the sand will
always <del>cast</del> lift it up, it being very clear. Do not forget to
adapt two vent holes with two <tl>small sticks</tl>, starting at the
foot of the cast, which is the pointed end of the <tl><m>wax</m>
peg</tl>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
If the plants are so delicate that they rise to the top when you pour
the wet sand, one can stop and contain them with a <tl>thread</tl>
passed through the circle of the <tl>mold</tl> with a
<tl>needle</tl>.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p117r_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5WnpBbm8wN2gyTWs</link>

</figure>

<figure>

<id>fig_p117r_2</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5VURRYzlWOFByNzQ</link>

</figure>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The more delicate the fllower is, the clearer the sand must be.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p117r_3</id>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dVB5bzVUWWJuS0U</link>

<caption><tl>Mold <fr>en noyau</fr></tl>.</caption>

</figure>

</div>
</root>
