<root>
<page>052r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f109.item</image>

<div>

<id>p052r_1</id>

<head>The Work done in Algiers</head>

<ab>Have a <al>colt</al> of three of four years &amp; feed it on
<del><m>rye</m></del> <add><m>barley</m></add> &amp; <m>straw</m>
<del>pig</del> cut in the manner with which they feed horses in
<pl>Spain</pl>. Let it drink <m>water</m> from a good fountain or river.
I do not know if it would be good sometimes to let it drink the
<m>water</m> of <m>sulfur</m> springs, &amp; to sometimes give it
<m>fenugreek</m> or other hot foods, for the intention of the
<pro>worker</pro> is to use the heat of its <m>manure</m>, &amp; the
climate here is cooler than that of Algiers. Keep it in a warm place
&amp; use it &amp; it should lose none of its <m>manure</m> &amp;
<m>urine</m>, of which you will make a mass or two in order that while
one cools the other will be of a heat suitable for continuing. Also have
a large long-necked glass bottle as thick as possible, &amp; one finger
if it can be so made, &amp; of the capacity of one pitcher or
<m>earthen</m> jug. Put into it around St John a dozen &amp; a half
<m>chicken eggs</m>, that is to say, the <m>yolk</m> without the
<m>glair</m> &amp; the <m>germ</m>. See ) Others say lx <m>yolks</m>.
And <del>it will be</del> with this dozen &amp; a half of <m>egg
yolks</m> put one half ounce (others say lx <m>eggs</m> &amp; a half
pound) of <m>female silkworm eggs</m>. And after luting well the flask
(I do not know if air will be needed for the generation there). Put
&amp; bury it in the heat of the <m>manure</m> up to the neck, and leave
it there until several <al>worms</al> will be engendered. And then
remove the long-necked bottle &amp; do not bury it in the <m>manure</m>
anymore. But put it on the hot layer of the <m>manure</m> until all the
<al>worms</al> will be eaten &amp; consume one another by shriveling and
stirring, and only one remains. Once this has happened, you must entice
it at regular intervals, day &amp; night, with the assistance of two
men, who will care for it in shifts, and you will lure it with an <m>egg
yolk</m> covered in <m>gold leaf</m> or with a liquid <m>egg yolk</m>
into which the <m>gold</m> leaf has been incorporated. &amp; be careful
that it does not miss such fodder (some say one <m>egg yolk</m> per
hour, others say three, but the thing itself will demonstrate the
practice). Nourished in this way it will grow in two months or seven
weeks &amp; will become like a <al>serpent</al>, one span &amp; four
fingers long, &amp; one pound in weight. And as the wings will begin to
develop, one will need to kill it, doing so with a <m>charcoal</m> fire
in a ring around the bottle one span away from it, &amp; at that time
lute the bottle well so that it does not exhale.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
