<root>
<page>090v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f186.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p090r_3</id>

<ab>good &amp; proper for molding. For if it is coarse, pass it through a
<tl>sieve</tl>, and if it is not yet fine enough, wash it, &amp; when
the <m>water</m> will be a little rested, empty the one which is still
troubled in some separate <tl>vessel</tl>. The coarse will promptly 
fall down to the bottom of the first <tl>vessel</tl>, but the one which
will have come from the troubled <m>water</m>, placed separately, having
taken residence, will be very fine. And then, if it does not have enough
bond, grind it well dry on <tl><m>porphyry</m></tl>, &amp; you will
render it impalpable, &amp; which will have bond just like <m>chalk</m>.
Then, if it seems to need it, you will reheat it, &amp; will crush it
again &amp; mix it with <m>salts</m>, or <m>linen, <add>or</add> burned
felt</m> or <m>ashes of paper</m> &amp; similarly washed things.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p090v_1</id>
<head><m><fr>Terre fondue</fr> of <pro>potters</pro></m></head>

<ab>Grind it in a <del><tl>mortar</tl></del> <add><tl>mustard
mill</tl></add> with some <m>water</m>, &amp; and render it impalpable,
dry it &amp; next moisten it with <m>salt water</m>, which gives
strength to <del><fr>u</fr></del> all sands to withstand several
casts.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p090v_2</id>
<head><pa>Orange trees</pa></head>

<ab>In <pl>Italy</pl>, those who are in the colder regions, like
<pl>Lombardy</pl>, make <tl>square wooden cases</tl>, a little larger at
the bottom than at the top, and thereon affix <tl>buckles</tl> on the
sides for transporting them with <tl>straps</tl>, as one carries gout
sufferers, because the wheels with which one could make them roll spoil
the pathways of the <env>gardens</env>. And <ms><tmp>every two
years</tmp></ms>, they do not forget to open the sides of the
<tl>cases</tl> for paring &amp; dexterously cutting, including the soil,
the ends of the <pa>orange tree</pa>'s roots, because otherwise, as they
find the wood, they contract &amp; fold back on themselves &amp; dry at
the tips, &amp; would make the tree die. But as they are pared, it
preserves for them new space <del><fr>cos</fr></del>for expanding,
without finding resistance from the wood that inhibits them. And know
that, for this effect, it would be better to join the sides of the
<tl>cases</tl> with <tl>screws</tl> &amp; not with <tl>nails</tl>, in
order to not shake the <m>soil</m> when one opens them.</ab>

</div>
</root>
