<root>
<page>152v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f310.image</image>

<div>

<id>p152v_1</id>

<head>Repairing cast things</head>

<ab>

It happens often that what you have cast makes flashing, either through
fault in the <tl>mold</tl>, or from the cast, or from the <m>metal</m>.
The fault in the <tl>mold</tl> comes from <m>plaster</m>, which is not
hard &amp; strong and does not withstand fire (which is corrected by
mixing it with <m><la>crocum</la></m>). Usually as well, if there is an
imperfection, it is from the cast. If there is also too much <m>tin</m>,
in a moderately thick thing, it does not come out well, because
<m>tin</m> cast thickly retracts &amp; becomes porous. Also, things
molded hollow are fanciful to cast. If, therefore, some flaw should
happen, take a <tl><m>leather</m> cushionet</tl>, full of fine sand,
&amp; having placed it on the <fr>bequet</fr> of the
<tl><pro>goldsmith’s</pro> table</tl>, where one <tl>files</tl>, place
your work on it &amp; secure it with a <tl>rope</tl>, <add>which passes
under your <tl><bp>foot</bp></tl></add>. The sand in the <tl>bag</tl>
obeys &amp; arranges itself by and by, thick on one side &amp; thin on
the other. Then, forthwith, with a <tl>burin</tl>, make &amp; trace
roughly the fine lines, which were omitted or which are not apparent
enough, either with a <tl>file</tl> or a <tl><fr>chaple</fr></tl> remove
the flashing. And if there is some fault in the substance, which left some
pit or something too hollow, rescrape this with a <tl>burin</tl>, and
notch around the edge, then imprint this with some <m>wax</m>. And place
the imprint on a <tl><m>delicate plate of lead</m></tl>, &amp; mark
thus the appropriate measure of <m>lead</m> or of the alloy similar to
your substance, then place the piece of the notched thing &amp; attach
it well with some <tl><m>latten wire</m></tl>, then rub the edge with
<m>rosin</m> if it is <m>tin</m> or <m>lead</m> &amp; place all around
some small thin pieces of <m>solder</m> or <m>tin</m> or other things,
then with a <tl>hot <m>iron</m></tl> or in the fire of the
<tl>forge</tl>, <m>solder</m>, and next repair this with the above-said
tools, &amp; with the appropriate <tl>small chisels</tl>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

For <m>gold</m> &amp; small work, one needs to ciment it on a ball of
<m>lead</m>, which will be placed on the <tl>cushionet</tl> &amp; will
be held thus with the <tl>rope</tl>.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p152v_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5S3NpRV82clA2UVE</link>

</figure>

<figure>

<id>fig_p152v_2</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5cWhfVmhvbWszZlE</link>

</figure>

</div>
</root>
