<root>
<page>142v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f290.image</image>

<div>

<id>p142v_1</id>

<head>Molding <al>grasshoppers</al> and things too thin</head>

<ab>If you have a written paper to mold, which is too thin, after you
have made the first cast &amp; it has set, give a little thickness to
the reverse of your <m>paper</m> with melted <m>butter</m>, which is the
most appropriate means there is, &amp; for fortifying the wings of
either a <al>butterfly</al> or a <al>grasshopper</al>, or some delicate
part of an animal to which you need to give thickness. But take heed to
apply this melted <m>butter</m> underneath the wing or in whichever
place it cannot be seen. For giving thickness to a pansy or other
flowers, <m>butter</m> is not good, but rather <m>wheat oil</m>, which
is soon dry &amp; holds firm. <m>Wax</m> would not be appropriate here
for it is too hot once melted, &amp; it makes the thing to which it is
applied contract. But <m>butter</m> is amiable and handleable.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>If you write on <m>paper</m> or on common
<m>carton</m> &amp; that your letter is with <m>gum</m>, the humidity of
the <m>clay</m> slab or the wet sand for <fr>noyau</fr> will moisten
your letter &amp; undo it. Therefore write with <m>cinnabar</m> wettened
with <m>oil</m>, on oiled &amp; impress.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><figure>+</figure>Reheat your molds with
<m>charcoals</m>,firstly lit in the forge, in order that the fire is not
so hot &amp; does not break the molds. And do not make as much fire
where the mold is thin, like in the place where it is thick.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p142v_2</id>

<head>Molds</head>

<ab>Make some notches, with these, that enter more in the inside of the
mold than on the outside, for in this way, they have more strenght. Keep
from reheating in on go &amp; in a too ardent fire, for this makes them
<del>melt</del> break.</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Do not keep them in a humid or enclosed
place if they are not well dry, for they go moldy. So do dried
animals.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>@One ought not to reheat molds twice
when the animal can be removed without burning, like a <al>toad</al>,
which can well be molded hollow like all thick animals. However, it is
always good to redden the mold once.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p142v_3</id>

<head><m>Lute</m> for <m>luting</m> your molds</head>

<ab>I have not found one that is made more quickly than this one, nor
better. Take this lean <m>earth</m> of which the <pro>founders of
artillery</pro> &amp; <pro>bell</pro> make their <fr>trusseaulx</fr> and
molds, which is lean &amp; sandy. Wet it <del>e</del> moderately like a
very thick <m>mortar</m>. Mix in it about half <m>horse dung</m> &amp;
then have it beaten well. Next, mix in a third part of discarded
<m>cloth waste</m> or <m>cloth shavings</m>, and beat it again quite
strongly. You can reheat your mold as soon as the <m>lute</m> is
placed.</ab>

</div>
</root>
