<root>
<page>118v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f242.item</image>

<div>
<id>p118v_1</id>

<head>Casting in <tl>frames</tl></head>

<ab>The same sand that was used in the reheated <fr>noyaulx</fr>,
composed, as is said, of <m>plaster</m>, <m>brick</m> &amp; <m><fr>alum
de plume</fr></m> , is excellent for casting in <tl>frames</tl>, and I
have experienced it thus: I <tl>pestled</tl> the pieces which had come out of
<tl>molds <fr>en noyau</fr></tl> in a <tl>mortar</tl>, dragging the
<tl>pestle</tl>, because this sand is very <fr>doulx</fr>. I did not
pass it through the <tl>sieve</tl>, because the <m><fr>alum de
plume</fr></m> mixed throughout, which binds it, would not pass; but I
ground finely upon <tl><m>marble</m></tl> what seemed to me too coarse.
And having prepared it thus, I moistened it with <m>sal ammoniac
water</m>, made of <m>sal ammoniac</m>, <ms>as much as two
<pa>walnuts</pa></ms>, in a <tl>bottle of <m>common water</m></tl>, the
same size as a <tl>bottle in which one boils <m>tisane</m></tl>, or in a
<tl>good pot of <m>water</m></tl> so that you find <del><fr>d</fr></del>
the <m>water moderately salty</m>. I mixed throughout <del><m>water</m>
of</del> <ms>half a <m>glass</m> </ms> of <m>sal ammoniac</m>, <del>two
othe</del> two <del><fr>au t</fr></del> <tl><ms><m>silver</m>
spoonfuls</ms></tl> of <m><fr>eau-de-vie</fr></m>.
<del><fr>J’a</fr></del> Having thus moistened the sand in such a fashion
that it took hold well, nevertheless coming apart easily, I sprinkled my
medal with <m>pulverized charcoal</m> with a <tl>file</tl>, to rid it of
<m>oil</m>, and all other <m>grease</m>, that are necessary to avoid,
for they <del>make</del> would hinder a good release. I blew on my medal
&amp; molded it, <add>and the female part of the <tl>frame</tl> once
filled</add>, I marked &amp; made a line on the reverse <del>of
the</del> &amp; edge of the medal, &amp; on the nearby sand as well. In
order that the second <tl>frame</tl> <del><fr>s’em</fr></del> take the
imprint thereupon to denote the place for making the cast, <del>once
filled</del> <del>the female part of the <tl>frame</tl> once filled</del> I
uncovered the outline of the medal and pounced the whole side with
<m>pulverized charcoal</m>, and then filled the male part with sand.
<del>Once made</del> I separated the <tl>frame</tl> and did not hit the
corners of the <del><fr>d</fr></del> medal to make it release, because
that knocks the sand &amp; makes it <del><fr>esp</fr></del> crumble.
Rather I struck the back of the <tl>frame</tl>, retaining the obverse of
the medal on the bottom, and it molded very neatly. If it had not
released thus, I would have waited to remove it until the
<tl>frames</tl> had been dried out over fire. I lit <del>the</del> a row
of charcoals between two little <tl>trivets of <m>iron</m></tl> in the
form that you see, and put the back <del>the</del> &amp; reverse of the
<tl>frames</tl> thereupon, &amp; the imprint on top, because in this
way, they dry out gently. And if, by chance, they should crack from
being too moistened, it is on the back,which <del><fr>pr</fr></del>
takes the harshest fire, &amp; the imprint remains safe &amp;
<corr>whole</corr>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>
For the best, one needs to reheat the sand used in the <fr>noyau</fr>
before using it in the <tl>frames</tl>, until it no longer
contracts.</ab><ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin><figure>

<id>fig_p118v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Rm5qaUJCNWVFWlk</link>

</figure></ab>

<man><margin>left-top</margin>

Excellent sand</man>

<ab>Take a little of the same sand, the finest that you can, to cover
the medal with.<comment>c_118v_01</comment> <figure/></ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
For medals &amp; flat things, the true heat of <m>lead</m> &amp;
<m>tin</m> is when it is melted gently.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Note that I filled the <tl>frame</tl> before pressing it, and did not
hit it at all, but rather pressed it only with the strength of my
<tl><bp>hands</bp></tl>, because hitting it makes it go awry. Secure
your <tl>frame</tl> that it does not shift at all, &amp; if you put some
moistened sand under it, it will only hold in place more firmly.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Make the gate so that it is not too thick, so as not to overcharge the
medal, but wide enough near the medal that it embraces a third part. Do
not forget the vents.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
To dry <tl>frames</tl> is to rid them of humidity, so that they no
longer smoke, once nevertheless having been very hot.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
<df><fr>Recuire</fr></df> is to redden the <tl>frame</tl>, which is done for
<m>gold</m> and for <m>silver</m>.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
