<root>
<page>155v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f316.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p155v_1</id>
<head>Rose</head>

<ab>Because the bloomed rose is wavy &amp; has its petals disordered
&amp; turned in various ways, it does not appear beautiful if it is not
painted, &amp; also, equally, if it has weight <del><fr>ou
for</fr></del> that the stem of tin, which is brittle &amp; delicate,
would be unable to support. One molds the flower of the rose on its own
&amp;separately, making its gate large in order that it comes out
<del>b</del> better. Then one cuts this gate down closest to the stem of
the bud, on which one grafts next &amp; solders a stalk of letton wire
to which one also solders the leaves. But because <m>tin</m>, being thus
thin, is troublesome to solder, and any leaf can be melted. And also
because the cast flowers &amp; especially the rose are not beautiful
without being painted, one does not take pains to solder, but one
<del>it</del> grafts the pieces to join them &amp; one glues them with
<m>fish glue</m> that has been a little wetted &amp; thickly melted. And
in order that it imprints better, one heats the <m>tin</m> work gently
&amp; at a distance, for when cold, the <m>glue</m> would not take.
After your flower is thus repaired, you follow the joints of the added
parts with <del>esb</del> <m>modelling wax</m>, which is a white
<m>wax</m> mixed with much well-ground <m>ceruse,</m> or even better,
<m>lead white</m>, melting it &amp; applying it on your work with a
small hot point of <m>iron</m>. In this way you can repair these little
flashings that are in the middle of the rose, or the holes <del>of
the</del> that may be in any petal. Next you will paint your rose
according to nature. If you cast your rose in <m>gold</m> or
<m>silver</m>, you can join &amp; solder well. And in these same metals,
when you have something delicate to join to the flower, like a fly or
something similar, <m>fish glue</m> is remarkable for it and holds very
well, fixing it with a few small points which serve as nails. The leaves
&amp; buds can be molded in two molds that can be opened once reheated,
but not before. Next these said things are joined.</ab>

</div>
</root>
