<root>
<page>085r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f175.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p084v_4</id>

<ab>to rest on a <tl>very clean &amp; smooth table</tl>, &amp; since it
is desiccative, I knew it would dry out <del><fr>lor</fr></del>, what I
let it do in order to reduce it to powder, &amp; molding it with sand,
once broken up with my <tl><bp>fingers</bp></tl> &amp; the sharp edge of
a <tl>knife</tl>. I <m>oiled</m> my medal because <m>oil</m> cleans it
without spoiling it. <del>And</del> And having dried it &amp; cleaned it
with a <tl><m>linen</m></tl>, &amp; <tl>small bristle brushes of
<al>pork</al></tl>, I once again lightly anointed it with <m>clear
<pa>walnut</pa> oil</m>, &amp; gently passed a <tl><m>linen</m></tl>
over it, so that it does not remain too anointed, and I noted that,
by this means, it would come out better in release, because the
<m>ceruse</m>, once moistened with <m>water of glair of egg</m>, would not
attach to the <m>oil</m>. This worked very well and I molded a medal of
high relief very neatly, without making any stickiness, which a lot of
good sands, such as <m>felt</m>, <m>burnt bone</m> &amp; <m>iron
dross</m>, had failed to do on the first try. I reheated it &amp; my
<tl>mold</tl> became hard like <m>marble</m>, and I realized with this,
that sands for molding high relief should be well moistened with some
<m>water</m>, which gives them body &amp; compactness, like <m>glair of egg</m>, <m>gummed water</m>, <del><fr>ea</fr></del> <m>wine boiled
with <pa>elm root</pa></m>, &amp; and lightly <m>oil</m> the medal, it
withstands as many castings as you wish, for it is as hard as
<m>glass</m>. But even <m>soft lead</m> &amp; <m>brittle tin</m>
<del><fr>v</fr></del> want to be cast very hot.</ab>

<ab>Since then I have realized that this sand, even though it is
excellent &amp; endures many castings &amp; molds very neatly, it is
however fat and makes things porous. This, <m>soft lead</m> <del>and
the</del> does not come out so well. But try to mix it with a <m>lean
sand</m>, such as <m>pumice</m>, <m>flakes</m>, &amp; similar things, to
give them body, &amp; so that they release better. For <m>lean sands</m>
barely release well and yet they receive <m>metal</m> well.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Try to mix <m>ceruse</m> or <m>minium</m> with other sands.</ab>

<mark><margin>left-top</margin>X</mark>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<m>Oil</m> &amp; anoint with <m><pa>aspic</pa> oil</m>, which will go
away when reheating, for the <m>oil</m> makes it porous.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
One ought to moisten with <m>glair</m>, then mix it well. And once in
the <tl>frame</tl>, beat it on top with a <tl>pestle</tl>, or other
proper thing, for this makes it mold better and release better. </ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It would be good to fill the <tl>frame</tl> all at once, for the
mixture, made of several sands with <m>the one of the
<env>mine</env></m>, with which you fill the <tl>frame</tl>, corrupts
it.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p085r_1</id>
<head><m>Green varnish</m> for medals of <m>copper</m></head>

<ab>Having casted them very neatly, cover them with <m><fr>sel de
verre</fr></m> that we use for sand, &amp; moisten it, &amp; in three or
4 <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms> it will be green. Next, <m>oil</m> them &amp; keep
them under the <m>dung</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p085r_2</id>
<head><m>Glue</m></head>

<ab>The <pl>Flemish</pl> reglue their <tl><m>earthen</m> pots</tl> with
gold color, that is to say <m>minium</m>, <m>massicot</m>, &amp;
<m>varnish</m>. </ab>

</div>
</root>
