<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="059r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f123.item">




<div continues="yes" id="p058v_5" categories="painting">





<ab><m>Lake</m> &amp; <m>lead white</m> &amp; <m>ceruse</m> are easy to
work in <m>oil</m>, but every kind of <m>azure</m> is difficult. And to
make beautiful <m>azure</m>, one needs to layer it not with large
strokes of the <tl>paintbrush</tl> but with small strokes of the
point. Not only <m>ash</m> &amp;
    <m><fr>azur d’<pl>Acre</pl></fr></m><comment rid="c_059r_02"/> but mainly <m><fr>azur d’esmail</fr></m>
which one needs to choose to be very delicate, <del>for it</del>
otherwise you will not <del><fr>v</fr></del> be able to work with it
except with much work, and even then you need to allay it with
<m>turpentine</m> to give it body, and mix it with a little <m>lead
white</m>. Any <m>azure</m> wants neither to be ground nor washed for it
loses color &amp; becomes pale. But putting it powdered on your
<tl>palette</tl>, you will thin it little by little either with
<m><pa>walnut</pa> oil</m> or <m>turpentine oil</m>,
dipping a <tl>knife point</tl> in the <m>oil</m>, then
tempering it little by little on the said
<tl>palette</tl>.</ab></div>

<div id="p059r_1" categories="painting">



<head>Shadows</head>

<ab>The first shadows which are closer to light need to be clear &amp;
thoroughly softened &amp; then the last ones very dark to give relief
well. The <pl>Italians</pl> commonly make three shadows, the first one,
of light, very clear, the second one darker &amp; the third ones quite
strong, then blend these three shadows together by hatching them from
the darkest to the clearest.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle" render="tall">





The <m>varnish</m> is more beautiful on the panel when the color has
imbibed well.</ab>

    <figure size="x-small" id="fig_p059r_1" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5QWJmbC1RaG8zTGM">







</figure>

</div>

<div id="p059r_2" categories="varnish;painting">



<head><m>Azure</m></head>

<ab><m>Azure</m> is more beautiful when imbibed on the panel
<del>without</del> with <m><pa>walnut</pa> oil</m> with which it has
been first thinned, without putting in <m><pa>spike lavender</pa>
oil</m>. And if you want to know if it is dry, breathe on it and it will
not shine, thus appearing to be well-imbibed. If not, it will shine.</ab>

<ab><m><fr>Azur d’esmail</fr></m> <del>imbibed in <m>oil</m></del> tempered
in <m>oil</m>, leaves it &amp; returns to its primary nature if you mix it
in <m>water</m>.</ab>

<ab>Colors for working in miniature want to be thoroughly ground, &amp;
work them with a point of a <tl>paintbrush</tl> if you want your
work to be well-softened.</ab>

</div>
</root>
