<root>
<page>125r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f255.item.r</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p124v_3</id>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<figure>

<id>fig_p125r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5ZHJJRXJlU2RFZlk</link>

</figure>
From small rolls, you make your gates and vents without danger of
crusting &amp; removing anything from the <tl>mold</tl>, because the
<tl>wax</tl>, being taken away, leaves the empty space all made. Make
your vents coming from the head, which is in the bottom, towards the
gate. Make also your gate so that it is <del>too</del> <add>but
little</add> thick, and make within its course two or three notches, for
this breaks up the fury of the <m>metal</m> and makes it flow with ease,
without bubbling nor making too much smoke, which hinders its run. You
can divide it also in two or three branches thus

<figure>

<id>fig_p125r_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bDlqQzJZemktSFk</link>

</figure>

when it approaches the molded thing, and always make holes in the
gate.</ab>

<ab>&amp; from these conduits &amp; feeders, you can also
put there small threads of <m>wax</m>, which are joined to the body, in
order that the <m>metal</m> goes more easily from one part to another
&amp; promptly runs everywhere. And from these conduits, you lead your
gates &amp; your vents without spoiling anything.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p125r_1</id>
<head><m>Plaster</m></head>

<ab>When you <del>v</del> mold something to cast <m>wax</m> in it, you
mold in <m>plaster</m> alone, reheated after having been pulverized.
For, once reheated in <m>stone</m>, the outside is cooked &amp; the
inside stays almost raw. <m>Transparent grey plaster is not strong, but
a good one, is one, that, once wet, is white</m> &amp; sets very
quickly. However, the grey I have found to be quite firm, &amp; hard
after having set, but its takes longer to do so. One needs to know the
nature of each. <del>If you</del> You will never mold very neatly if
<corr><del><fr>ne</fr></del></corr> you do not wet, very thin &amp;
liquid, your <m>plaster</m> or your sand for <fr>noyau</fr>. Wet it
<del><tl>mortar</tl></del> immediately after it has been reheated.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>+</mark>
If you mold with <m>plaster</m> <del>crud</del> alone, reheat it
nevertheless as said. One needs to <m>oil</m> well the first
<tl>mold</tl>. And when the second one has set well, and it is ready,
soak it for a long time in <m>water</m>. And if it does not want to
release, soak it in <m>hot water</m>, for <m>cold water</m> hardens it,
and <m>hot water</m> softens it further. <m>Cold water</m> does not
penetrate it like it does with mixed plaster, because it is harder &amp;
the mixed one is more spongy. With this <m>plaster</m>, thus reheated as
powder, one can cast medals that do not fear the <env>rain</env>,
especially if they are varnished. One can find these in
<pl>Germany</pl>, on the houses. But take heed that the <m>water</m> be
very hot, &amp; if it is boiling, there is no danger. All
<tl><m>plaster</m> molds</tl>, pure or mixed, release in it.</ab></div>

<div>
<id></id>
<head>Scimitars<comment>c_125r_03</comment></head>

<man><margin>left-middle</margin>To know</man>

<ab>The <pro>workers</pro> from <pl>Damascus</pl> or from
<pl>Hungary</pl>, neighbors to the <pl>Turks</pl>, separate, in the
<env><fr>mine</fr></env>, <m>iron</m> from <m>steel</m>. And, from this
first <m>steel</m>, first melted from its <env><fr>mine</fr></env>, they
cast scimitar blades in sand <del><fr>sab</fr></del> which afterwards cut the other <m>iron</m> without any difficulty,
because any <m>melted iron</m> is harder than <m><fr>doulx</fr> iron</m>
beaten from pigs &amp; bars. Thus is the <m>steel</m> of scimitars, but
it is quite brittle. When one un-hilts <del><fr>b</fr></del> a scimitar,
one recognizes by the tang that enters the hilt that it is cast in
sand.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p125r_3</id>
<head><sn>Hearing</sn> from afar</head>

<ab>Make a small hole in the earth, &amp; place your <bp>ear</bp> fully
there, <tmp>at night or at a silent time</tmp>, &amp; you will easily
<sn>hear</sn> the noise.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p125r_4</id>
<head>Secret</head>

</div>
</root>
