<root>
<page>089v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f184.image</image>

<div>
<id>p089v_1</id>
<head><m>Sal ammoniac</m> and <m>alabaster</m></head>

<ab> <m>Sal ammoniac, well pulverized</m> <del><fr>mou</fr></del> &amp;
ground dry on <tl><m>marble</m></tl>, molds very neatly &amp; makes a
very beautiful, &amp; once mixed with <m>alabaster, pulverized</m>
similarly, ii <ms>℥</ms> per <ms>lb</ms> of
<m>alabaster</m>, makes it release well. It sufficient to moisten it in
a <env>cave</env> or <env>in the <tmp><fr>serain</fr></tmp></env> or, to
be done more quickly, in a <tl>piece of <m>paper</m></tl> between a wet
<tl>napkin</tl>. Take heed that it does not stay for too long, for it
would become so wet that it would not be good for molding in a
<tl>frame</tl>, but rather in a <fr>noyau</fr>, in which you will be
able to use it well as long as dries well at ease &amp; far from the
fire. Otherwise the heat makes it swell, &amp; push the <m>salt</m> onto
the surface, which renders it lumpy. You can <del>in</del> anoint the
medal with <m><pa>spike lavender</pa> oil</m>, molding in
<fr>noyau</fr>. It is better to put in 4 <ms>℥</ms> of
<m>sal ammoniac</m> per <ms>lb</ms>, and moisten it <env>in a damp
place</env> for two or three <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms>, &amp; so that
when you take <bp>fistfuls</bp>, it holds together, without, however,
attaching itself &amp; being pasted to your <tl><bp>hand</bp></tl>. You
will with it mold very neatly. But let it dry &amp; reheat really well,
leaving the <tl>mold</tl> inside, so that it acquires strength by
reheating, for it becomes hard as <m>stone</m>, &amp; and in this way is
more certain to release well. Otherwise if you release before having
reheated it, there would be danger of it crumbling in some place,
because of its delicateness &amp; fineness, even if the medal of high
relief. Once you have molded with it, pulverize it as before and put it
back <env>in dampness</env>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
All sand that releases well has body &amp; sticks well. <m>Ammoniac</m>
is fat and <del><fr>a va</fr></del> however, is <m><fr>areneux</fr></m>
which makes it release well. There is no better bond than <m>salts
appropriate for metals</m>, for once mixed in powder, they get moistened
together &amp; dry &amp;reheat together.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p089v_2</id>
<head><m><pro>Glassmakers'</pro> white sand from the
<env>mine</env></m>, mixed with <m>sal ammoniac</m></head>

<ab>There is found in <pl>Cominge</pl>, near the <env>town</env> of
<pl>Aurignac</pl>, a sand, white <del><fr>mai</fr></del>, like
<m>salt</m>, and lean, that <pro>glassmakers</pro> &amp;
<pro>potters</pro> use, which renders impalpable crushed on
<tl><m>porphyry</m></tl> &amp; is easy to crush. And once crushed, it
resembles <m>calcined alabaster</m>. It molds very neatly, and I have
not found any that molds as delicately as this one for low relief. It is
excellent to <tl>mold</tl> <fr>en noyau</fr> without a <tl>frame</tl>, having crushed it
impalpable with <m>gummed or pure water</m> on <tl><m>porphyry</m></tl>,
then placing it, thick as <m>mustard</m> or a little more, on the medal,
anointed lightly with <m>oil either of <pa>olive</pa>, <pa>walnut</pa>, or even
better <pa>spike lavender</pa></m>. But to do it better
<del><fr>mo</fr></del>, let it dry by itself, without fire, for one or
two <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms>. Although, if you are in a hurry, you can
heat it well, &amp; it will not crack, if it is not put on too lightly.
It is true, being thus suddenly exposed to heat all at once, it makes
some holes &amp; pustules, which it does not do when dried in the cold or
at ease, rather than being reheated. Once dry, reheat it &amp; it will
withstand several casts. </ab>

</div>
</root>
