<root>
<page>167v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f340.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p167r_1</id>

<ab>

Those of 27 lb or thereabouts are ix <ms>inches</ms> long &amp; six in
diameter at the muzzle. At the breech, they are vi <ms>lines</ms> thick,
&amp; 3 at the muzzle. The ones weighing 17 <ms>lb</ms> are 8
<ms>inches</ms> long &amp; five at the muzzle. One covers them all
together, all the <tl>forks</tl> &amp; <tl>pegs</tl> &amp;
<tl>tools</tl> which one uses, with a <tl>thick canvas</tl> or <tl>thick
cloth</tl> in order that they do not make any noise. It
<del><fr>s</fr></del> is good that they should sit loaded for some time.
After one has put the <m>powder</m> in, one tamps it down quite
thoroughly, and then one puts in <m>pressed paper</m>, then a <m>cake of
wax</m> well tamped down, &amp; on the <m>wax</m> another <m>plate of
cork</m> that goes in quite precisely &amp; with force. In this way,
the <m>powder</m> remains well sealed &amp; gives much greater violence,
&amp; if you wish, you can put on the <m>plate of cork</m> one of
<m>wood</m> pierced in the middle, if the petard is pierced at the
breech, which one holds to be the easiest &amp; which makes for greater
penetration because it cannot recoil. And for those that have a pierced
breech, one must have a good <tl>gimlet</tl> to first make the hole in
order that the <tl>peg</tl>, which is made <del>in</del> with a
<tl>gimlet</tl>-like point, may attach the petard faster &amp; without
noise. And <del>to</del> for these, one must cover the button, which is
quite evenly filed, <del><fr>p</fr></del> with <m>waxed canvas</m>, or
add <m>wax</m> to it in order that it precisely plugs the hole of the
breech. But because the doors are sometimes iron-clad &amp; the
<tl><m>iron</m> pegs</tl> cannot pierce it, one uses an <tl><m>iron</m>
fork made like pincers</tl> &amp; another <tl><m>iron</m> rod
<del><fr>q</fr></del> made with three claws at the end</tl>, as you see
depicted. And in this way, the petard holds itself well &amp; is quickly
placed. The <tl><m>iron</m> pegs</tl> must extend from the petard with
the entire point that is made like a <tl>gimlet</tl>, namely by three or
4 <ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms>, which goes entirely <del><fr>l</fr></del>
into the door. When the petards are placed, one fills the touch-hole
with good <m><fr>pulverin</fr></m><comment>c_167v_01</comment> and
<del><fr>s</fr></del> one puts in it a <m>feather quill</m> filled with
<m>powder</m> tightly pressed &amp; moistened with <m>vinegar</m>, or,
if needed, one presses the <m>powder</m> in the hollow of the hand &amp;
having wetted it with <m><bp>saliva</bp></m>, one makes from it
something like a cocoon or</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
