<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="153v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f312.image">




<div continues="yes" id="p153r_2" categories="casting">





<ab><m>flour</m>. And to flatten it, take a <tl>small stick of
<m><pa>boxwood</pa></m></tl>, very round &amp; of the same thickness
everywhere, which has, at the two ends, a little circle, more raised
than the rest, to give the necessary thickness to the <m>paste</m>. And
then, with this <tl>rolling pin</tl>, flatten it in such a way that it
is delicate &amp; thin enough. Then, apply it on the hollow
of your <tl>mold</tl> and press on it with some <tl><m>cotton</m></tl>
&amp; your figure will imprint itself in the <m>paste</m>, in relief on
one side &amp; in a hollow form on the other. This done, anoint with a
<tl>paintbrush</tl>, wetted in a little <m>melted butter</m>, the
part of the <m>paste</m> which is hollow. Then, cut the
excess <m>paste</m>, which surpasses the hollow of the
<tl>mold</tl> <del><fr>H</fr></del>. Anoint your <tl>mold</tl> also with
<m><pa>olive</pa> oil</m>, as you have done with others, place the
<tl><m>clay</m> contour</tl> &amp; cast <del><fr>s</fr></del> your
second <tl>mold</tl>. And you will have your medal as thin &amp; hollow on one
side as you will want. You can have diverse <tl>rolling pins</tl>, which will
have ends, some more raised than others, to make various thicknesses, or
use <tl><m>sheets of lead &amp; copper</m></tl> of various thicknesses
or of <tl><m><fr>carton</fr></m></tl>, cut with the <tl>rolling
pin</tl>.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p153v_1" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5czR5TF9scDhsSG8">







</figure>

<ab margin="left-middle">

If you rubbed your <m>paste</m> with <m>oil</m>, it would drink the
<m>oil</m> &amp; penetrate up to the <tl>mold</tl>, which it would
attack. But <m>butter</m> remains on the surface of the <m>paste</m>
&amp; is not imbibed at all. You should not, on these reverse sides,
temper your <m>sand</m> with <m>hot water</m>, for it would melt the
<m>butter</m>.

<figure id="fig_p153v_2" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5c3FRZnZSMnU1Njg">





</figure>

</ab></div>

<div id="p153v_1" categories="casting">



<head>Testing the goodness and strength of a <m>sand</m> to be reheated</head>

<ab>After it has set, it must be found smooth &amp; easy to cut, and not
rough. It tests better in a large &amp; fantastical <tl>mold</tl>, than
in a small one, for the large one remains <tmp>long</tmp> in the fire &amp; the
small one is soon reheated.</ab></div>

<div id="p153v_2" categories="metal process">



<head>Softening <m>gold</m></head>

<ab>Sometimes, there is <m>gold</m> so dry <del>it</del> that neither
<m>cement</m> nor <m>antimony</m> can soften it. But only
<m>verdet</m> can render it soft.</ab>

</div>
</root>
