<root>
<page>133v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f272.image</image>

<div>

<id>p133v_1</id>

<head>Bubbles and little holes which are found in the
<tl>mold</tl></head>

<ab>

This readily comes about when you cast two or three <tl>small
molds</tl>, one after the other, in the same <tl>bowl</tl>, for the last
one is cast from the bottom &amp; thickest part of the <tl>bowl</tl>,
which readily becomes porous. The lightest casts more finely &amp; more
neat, provided that one blows strongly enough when casting on the wet
&amp; cast sand in order to dissipate these small bubbles.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

When the sand is cast thickly, it readily becomes porous

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p133v_2</id>

<head>Thing that does not release</head>

<ab>

One needs to cut it to make it burn in the <tl>mold</tl>, but cut it
with <tl>chisels</tl> in one go, in order that the <tl>blood</tl> does
not fall on the <tl>mold</tl> &amp; does not create <m>filth</m>, which,
once reheated, is difficult to remove. Next, put your <tl>mold</tl> in
the <tl>oven</tl> or similar heat, in order that it dries promptly &amp;
retracts, before making a crust or <m>mold</m> on the
<tl>mold</tl>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>+</mark>

When you mold <al>small lizards</al>, and you want to uncover the part
first molded, begin to uncover the heads &amp; you will recognize its
place by the <tl>pin</tl>. Do not attempt to uncover the legs until you
have uncovered the rest of the body, in order that the stripped body, as
it moves, does not remove the legs from their place, where it is
difficult to put them back. When you remove <tl>little points</tl> which
hold the legs, fix them &amp; press them with something, in order that,
when removing the <tl>pin</tl>, they are not removed from their place,
or, in the end, you can put them back with some <m>wax</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p133v_3</id>

<head>Various animals entwined</head>

<ab>

You can entwine a <al>snake</al> <del>entwine</del> with a
<al>lizard</al>, one biting the other, or a <al>snake</al> that eats a
<al>frog</al> or a <al>wall lizard</al> <del><fr>s</fr></del> &amp;
similar things. But because these entwinings can in no way make a good
release, cut what you can &amp; leave the rest to burn. And to keep a
<al>wall lizard</al>, which is small, in the mouth of the
<al>snake</al>, which is raised &amp; needs to be supported in the air,
<del><fr>po</fr></del>, because the head of the <al>snake</al> is placed
raised, put underneath the <al>wall lizard</al> <del><fr>se</fr></del>
an elevation of <m>earth</m> suited to support it. And if you put your
<tl>mold</tl> in the <tl>oven</tl>, the animal, drying promptly, retracts
&amp; burns better afterwards. <del>if you see</del> These entwinings are
also made to cover a wound or fault in the animals, that one usually
wounds when one catches them. Also, do not forget to attach &amp; join,
with some <m>wax</m> <del><fr>s</fr></del>, finely applied with <tl>hot
<m>iron</m> wire</tl>, all the parts of the animal which pass one on top
of the other or those that you notice are not well fixed on the 
<del><m>wax</m></del> <tl><m>earthen</m> slab</tl>, in order that the wet sand
does not remove it. And it is to</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
