<root>
<page>024r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f53.image</image>

<div>

<id>p024r_1</id>

<head>Grenades</head>

<ab>Grenades should be made from the finest metal you can find, for
there is fine metal and rough metal. Fine
metal<comment>c_024r_01</comment> is that of a big bell, because one
puts in more <m>copper</m> to give it a bigger voice, &amp; for small
bells one puts more <m>tin</m> to give it a <del>bigger</del> clearer
sound. The metal of a big bell is made with <del>one</del> <add>3</add>
quintals of <m>rosette</m> &amp; twenty or xxv lb of <m>tin</m>.
<del><fr>Tan</fr></del> Each grenade must weigh four to six lb. In order
to throw them, it is necessary that they be full of powder mixed with
coarsely pestled glass. And for a quarter lb of powder, half an ounce of
glass is necessary which is put with it, in order that on the face or
places where the powder will have its effect, the wounds will be all the
worse for it. The best arquebus powder is required here. The hole needs
to be as large as the thickness of a swan's quill, &amp; there is no
need to make it threaded, it is enough to make it even. Next, you make a
pipe of well-soldered <m>fer<comment>c_024r_02</comment> blanc</m>,
which can enter into the hole &amp; enter into the middle of the grenade
&amp; which comes out of it by the width of one finger. You will fill it
with good powder, pestled in a mortar &amp; lightly mixed with good
<m>eau-de-vie</m> or strong <m>vinegar</m> <del>which seems. And
when</del>. This is done to compact the powder. And to know if it will
be slow enough to allow leisure to throw the grenade without danger, try
this powder thus bathed in another pipe. You can keep
<del><fr>d</fr></del> your loaded grenades in a very dry place, &amp; on
the contrary you shall keep your pipes filled with that bathed powder
compressed in a humid place. And nonetheless, you shall have some
already inserted into <del>the</del> grenades, so that you are always
equipped. And every 3 days you shall change them if you recognise that
they have become too dry. To throw your grenade, take it bravely
<del>&amp;</del> in one hand &amp; with the other give fire to your pipe
with <del>the</del> a match<comment>c_024r_03</comment> , &amp; throw it
quickly amidst the <del>powder</del> troops. The thickness of the
grenade<comment>c_024r_04</comment> should be twice the back edge of a
knife.<lb/>

</ab>

</div>
</root>
