<root>
<page>165r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f335.item</image>

<div>

<id>p165r_1</id>

<head>Repairing</head>

<ab>If during your cast there occurs some little hole, mend it with
<m>gummed modeling wax</m> that be black or gray.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p165r_2</id>

<head><m>Lake</m></head>

<ab>If, once it is ground, you let it dry without keeping it in
<m>water</m>, it will dry out &amp; you will have as much trouble
grinding it as before. <del><add><fr>La</fr></add></del></ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p165r_3</id>

<head>Stretching a <m>canvas</m> picture</head>

<ab>If it is crumpled &amp; creased from being rolled up, moisten it
from behind with a <tl>wet sponge</tl> &amp; you will stretch it very
evenly without spoiling it.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p165r_4</id>

<head><m>Plaster</m> for molding</head>

<ab>When it is long to set &amp; dry, it is a sign that it is too fat
&amp; moist, which is what makes it contract in fire &amp; crack,
causing flashing. That which is drawn from <env>lean soil</env> is the best.
<tl>Molds</tl> of <m>fat plaster</m> ought not to be kept for a long
time, for they act like <m>fatty earth</m>, which when drying by itself,
cracks. <add>It is best to reheat them soon after they are made, &amp;
to cast. <m>Good plaster</m> keeps a long time as
<tl>molds</tl>.</add></ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

It needs to be well <m>oiled</m>, for it is more difficult to separate
the two halves of the <tl>molds</tl> than when it is mixed.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p165r_5</id>

<head><m><al>Dragon</al>'s blood</m></head>

<ab>It can be imitated with <m>lake</m> that surpasses it in beauty if, with
this distempered in <m>oil</m>, you glaze on <m>gold</m> or
<m>silver</m>. Distempered in <m>varnish</m>, it dies.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p165r_6</id>

<head>Repairing <al>snakes</al> and <al>lizards</al></head>

<ab>You could well make some <tl>puncheons</tl> according to the form of
their scales, &amp; making some bigger &amp; some smaller, according to
the shape of the neck, the body, &amp; the tail. If there is something
broken, you can graft it on with <tl>small <del>pieces</del> points of
<m>iron or steel wire</m></tl>, &amp; <m>glue</m> with <m><al>fish</al>
glue</m>, &amp; then cover it all with gray or black <m>wax</m>. But it
is necessary to let the <m>glue</m> dry for one <ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms>
without touching it.</ab>

</div>
</root>
