<root>
<page>092r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f189.image</image>

<div>
<id>p092r_1</id>
<head><del>Sand</del>Mixture easy to melt</head>

<ab>One <del><ms>℥</ms> <fr>de</fr></del> <ms>part</ms>
<m>soft tin</m>, one <ms>part</ms> <m>fine lead</m>, one <ms>part</ms>
<m>looking glass tin</m> &amp; one <ms>part</ms> <m><fr>argent vif
arresté</fr></m><comment>c_092r_02</comment> makes an alloy &amp; a
<m>solder</m>, so easy to melt that it can easily be melted in a
<tl>dish of <m>fine tin</m></tl>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p092r_2</id>
<head>Molding a cavity on one side and in relief on the other</head>

<ab>And for this effect, one casts a medal of <m>fine tin</m>, which is
harder to melt. And since it is neat, one molds with it. And one leaves
it in one half of the <tl>frame</tl>, &amp; presses it a little so that
it holds better. And next, you will cast in your <tl>frame</tl> some
<m>solder</m> described above, or another more meltable than <m>fine
tin</m>. And thus, the second medal will melt &amp; mold itself on the
first one without spoiling it. But to make sure this is done right, mix
some <m>lamp black</m> with <m>water</m>, &amp; with a
<tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl>, give a light coat of this to the medal, which
remains in the <tl>frame</tl>, &amp; leave to dry. Thus it will not
melt.</ab>

<ab>But if you have a medal of <m>copper</m> or <m>silver</m>, you can
leave it in the cast, if you want to cast with <m>lead</m> or
<m>tin</m>. But it is necessary that it be a little hot, for the cold
would make the <m>tin</m> contract.</ab>

<ab><m>Tin</m> wants to be cast quite hot to come out neat.</ab>

<ab><rub><m>Soft tin</m></rub>, which is the best for the cast, is the
one that, once cast <tl><fr>en grille</fr></tl>, is <del>burnished
&amp;</del> shiny &amp; polished like a mirror, &amp; appears to have
been burnished. And has have holes like the one that is brittle, &amp;
that is not shiny, as if burnished.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p092r_3</id>
<head><m>Potin</m></head>

<ab><m>Potin</m>, once cast hot, runs &amp; flows like <m>tin</m>. But
the medal becomes whitish from this, and immediately pushes the
<m><fr>verd</fr></m> to the surface, which good substances do not
do.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p092r_4</id>
<head>Molding statues</head>

<ab><ms>Half</ms> <m><pro>founder</pro>’s earth, which
<pro>founders</pro> use</m>, &amp; <ms>half</ms> <m>clay earth</m>,
<del><fr>g</fr></del> renders very neatly.</ab>

</div>
</root>
