<root>
<page>080r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f165.item</image>

<div>

<id>p080r_1</id>

<head>Petard</head>

<ab>They make them of fine substance &amp; <m>fine copper</m>, which is
capable of fifty <ms>lb</ms> of <m>powder</m>, in the shape of a
<tl>reinforced firkin</tl>, and having made a hole even <del>of</del>
with the ground <env>at the foot of a wall</env>, with <tl><oc>gimlets</oc></tl><comment>c_080r_01</comment>
they set the said loaded petard in that hole, with the muzzle pointing
up, which makes a large breach.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p080r_2</id>

<head>Very hard white <m>stucco</m></head>

<ab><m>White wax</m>, <m><pl>Venice</pl> turpentine</m>,
<m>eggshell</m>, &amp; <m>ceruse</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p080r_3</id>

<head>Fountains</head>

<figure>

<id>fig_p080r_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5c3dLNVNsem9nTjQ</link>

</figure>

<ab>If you wish to make <m>water</m> rise higher than its source, make a
<tl>pipe</tl> descend as in A <del>B</del> to B in order to give it push
<del>to the <m>water</m></del>, then from B <add>to C</add> make the
<tl>pipe</tl> ascend again, which should not quite attain the height of
the source, which is represented to you by this horizontal line, then
make the <tl>pipe</tl> descend again from C to D, then raise it again,
higher than the line showing the height of the source. And do this
successively until you have reached the desired height, heeding
nonetheless that the length of the descending <tl>pipe</tl> should be
<ms>twice as long as the ascending <tl>pipe</tl></ms>. This
<tl>cornet</tl> folded back on itself also shows you a perpetual
fountain which you can fit into some rock, pulling the <m>water</m> with
which it is filled by the tip marked <corr>E</corr>, by sucking &amp;
breathing in. You can also make a watering pipe in this manner, such
that the trussed-up length is <ms>as long as</ms> its straight pipe,
&amp; nevertheless does not descend as far down.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p080r_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5N2U2RXB5UFc3TUE</link>

</figure>

<figure>

<id>fig_p080r_3</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5R2ZBNWRseEpQdnc</link>

</figure>

</div>
</root>
