<root>
<page>146r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f297.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p145v_1</id>

<ab>in order that it gets wet everywhere, if not, wet it with a
<tl>large <fr>pinceau</fr></tl> dedicated to this. Then, pass through
the end of the <tl>mold</tl> which closes the <tl>circle</tl> your bit
of <tl><m>iron wire</m></tl>, which holds the <m>wax</m> gate, and
cleaves the <tl><m>clay</m> closure</tl>, as you see, &amp;
<del>it</del> place it low, so that the plant or flower touches no
thing, &amp; can leave enough thickness for the <tl>mold</tl>, for the
wet sand always raises the plant or flower. Thus, if it is not rigid in
itself, pass with a <tl>needle</tl> some <tl>thin thread</tl>
<del><fr>po</fr></del> on the flower to keep it from rising. Or, if you
were to forget, <corr>lower</corr> the flower with some
<del><fr>b</fr></del> <tl>small stick</tl> until the cast sand begins to
<del><fr>d</fr></del> thicken. Your flower being well arranged,
<del><fr>d</fr></del> choose a <tl>bowl</tl> big enough to wet in it as
much sand as it needs to fill your <tl>mold</tl>. Put in a little <m>sal
ammoniac water</m>, then some <m><env>fountain</env> water</m>. And when
the <tl><del><fr>au en</fr> bowl </del></tl> is nearly full, put in, by
sprinkling, your sand &amp; mix &amp; dilute it well in order that it
all becomes smooth, for if it were to coalesce, it would spoil the
<tl>mold</tl>. For flowers, it does not want to be so thick, and
especially, at the beginning, you will throw, in goes, the clearest one
on the flower, &amp; when it will be half covered, blow strongly
everywhere, to make the little bubbles disappear. Next, finish filling
&amp; blow always. Make the <tl>mold</tl> lean a little towards its
widest part, and if you find the remains of thick sand, which has not
diluted well, cast it rather towards the gate than elsewhere. Finally,
you can even cast some thicker wet sand in order to make a quicker set.
I have molded thus a <pa>marigold</pa> with its leaves. The
<m><la>crocum ferri</la></m> is safer for flowers and when there is
<m><la>crocum</la></m>, <m>lute</m> with the same sand that was used and
is the most excellent of all.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-top</margin>

<render>wide</render>

The alloy, with which I cast a large branch of <pa>marigold</pa>, which
with its flower, its buds and its leaves came out neatly like its
nature, was of one <ms>lb</ms> of <m>fine tin</m>, mixed with two
<ms>ounces</ms> of <m>lead</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

If there is some flashing, repair with a <tl>pen-knife</tl>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

Uncover the molded flower by gently undoing the <tl>mold</tl> with the
<tl>point of a knife</tl>, &amp; better yet, wet it well in
<m>water</m>. Next, use <tl>small bristle brushes of <al>hog</al></tl>,
a bit of <tl><m>iron wire</m></tl>, &amp; When the <tl>mold</tl> is
reheated the first time, leave it to half cool, then gently pass through
the gate an <tl><m>iron wire</m></tl>, to make an opening for the burned
<m>ashes</m> inside. Next, blow inside with a <tl>bellows</tl>, then
turn the <tl>mold</tl> at the gate to make everything come out, &amp;
sometimes suck and draw out with the <bp>mouth</bp>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

Take heed not to attach too much the tail of the flower to the gate of
<m>wax</m>, for fear of spoiling something when you pull out the gate of
<m>wax</m>. To pull it out, one needs to dig out all around a little,
&amp; then pull it with your <tl>little pincers</tl> by the tail of
<m>iron</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
