<root>
<page>052r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f109.item</image>

<div>

<id>p052r_1</id>

<head>The work done in Algiers</head>

<ab>Take a <al>colt</al> of three of four years &amp; feed it on
<del><m>rye</m></del> <add><m>barley</m></add> &amp; <m>straw</m>
<del><fr>pig</fr></del> cut in the manner one feeds horses in
<pl>Spain</pl>, and water it with good fountain or river <m>water</m>. I
do not know if it would be good to water it occasionally with
<m>water</m> of <m>sulfurous</m> baths, &amp; to sometimes give it
<m>fenugreek</m> or other hot foods, for the intention of the
<pro>worker</pro> is <del>to it</del> to use the heat of its
<m>dung</m>, &amp; the climate here is cooler than that of Algiers. Keep
it in a warm &amp; close place &amp; so that none of its <m>dung</m>
&amp; <m>urine</m> should be lost, of which you will make a heap or two
in order that while one cools, the other will be at the appropriate heat
to continue. Also take a large glass mattras, as thick as you can, &amp;
one finger think if it can be done, &amp; of the capacity of one pitcher
or <m>earthen</m> jug. Around the feast of St John, put into it a dozen
&amp; a half <m>chicken eggs</m>, that is to say, the <m>yolk</m>
without the <m>glair</m> &amp; the (<m>germ</m>) see). Others say lx
<m>yolks</m>. And <del>it will be</del> with this dozen &amp; a half
<m>egg yolks</m> put in half an ounce (others say for lx <m>eggs</m>
half a lb) of <m>female silkworm seeds</m>. And after having thoroughly
luted the mattras (I do not know if there needs to be air for the
generation), put it &amp; bury it in the heat of the <m>dung</m> up to
the neck, and leave it there until several <del><fr>f<ill/></fr></del>
<al>worms</al> are engendered. And then remove the mattras &amp; do not
bury it in the <m>dung</m> any longer, but only keep it placed on the
hot layer of the <m>dung</m> until all the <al>worms</al> will have
eaten &amp; consumed one another, bustling &amp; stirring, and only one
remains. When this is the case you need to feed it at regular intervals,
day &amp; night, with the aid of two men, who by intervals will take
care of it, and you will feed it with an <m>egg yolk</m> covered with a
<m>gold leaf</m>, or with a liquid <m>egg yolk</m> with the <m>gold</m>
leaf incorporated; &amp; take good care that it does not want for such
food (some say one <m>egg yolk</m> per hour, others three, but the thing
itself will demonstrate the practice). Nourished in this way it will
achieve its growth in two months or seven weeks &amp; will become like a
<al>snake</al>, one <fr>empan</fr> &amp; four fingers long, &amp; one lb
in weight, and as the wings begin to arise on it, one will need to make
it die, doing so with a <m>charcoal</m> fire in a ring around the bottle
one <fr>empan</fr> distant from it, then stopper &amp; lute the bottle
well in order that it does not exhale.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
