<root>
<page>045r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f95.image</image>

<div>

<id>p045r_1</id>

<head>Loading an arquebus with a hail shot </head>

<figure>

<id>fig_p045r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bkhmQklfNHJoRnc</link>

</figure>

<ab>One needs to make a <m>wooden</m> pipe as<ms> long as the width of 4
or 5 <bp>fingers</bp></ms>, which should be hollowed precisely according
to the mouth of your barrel, of the form represented in <del>D</del> A.
Then, having cut <m>strong paper, <del>of the</del> as of large printed
books</m>, in the form of D, as <ms>wide as you want to make your
cartridge<comment>c_045r_01</comment> long</ms>, wrap the <m>paper</m>
around the <tl>baton</tl> B &amp; at the end, where the point F will be,
fold all around the said <m>paper</m>, &amp; your cartridge will be
formed. But, in order to make the bottom more uniform, put it into
<tl>pipe</tl> A, then put in the <tl>baton</tl> B and, through the other
end of the <tl>pipe</tl>, which is marked G, put the <tl>baton</tl> C
&amp;beat so as to tamp &amp; press the folded tip of your cartridge,
then take it out, &amp; load it. Put three or 4
<fr>drageons</fr><comment>c_045r_02</comment> or
tears<comment>c_045r_03</comment> into it. Then, with a
<tl>cutting-punch</tl>, marked E, which should be of the same caliber as
your arquebus or pistol, punch round pieces on <m>cardboard</m> or
<m>felt</m> or <m>waxed cloth</m>, and put this round piece into your
cartridge, and push it onto the <fr>drageons</fr> with the
<tl>baton</tl> B. Next, more <fr>drageons</fr>, 3 or 4, then a round
piece. And do thus until the cartridge is full, then put it into your
arquebus. If you want your hail shot to scatter sooner, make the round
pieces out of <m>paper</m>. If you want it to reach farther without
scattering, make the piece out of <m>cardboard</m>. If you want even
farther, make the round piece out of <m>waxed cloth</m>, or else of
<m>leather</m> or <m>felt</m>, &amp; a piece of <m>waxed cloth</m> on
the top. And if you make the cartridge itself of <m>waxed cloth</m> or
<m>waxed paper</m>, it will reach one hundred <ms>paces</ms> &amp; will
make for great piercing, &amp; the hail shot, barely scattering, will
make an opening. But if you make your cartridge with <m>waxed cloth</m>
or a material stronger than <m>paper</m>, you ought not to make it so
long from the square coming to the point as in D, because it is enough
that it makes two turns. <mark>#</mark> In this manner, the hail
shot barely scatters &amp; makes for great piercing against a door, body
of a cuirass<comment>c_045r_04</comment>, and others.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<sup><mark>#</mark></sup> as <del>D</del> H

</ab>

</div>
</root>
