<root>
<page>015r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f35.image</image>

<div>
<id>p015r_1</id>
<head><m>Damasked cloth</m></head>

<ab>You can damask a <m>cloth</m> with two different colors and imitate
embroidery without adding anything else to it, in this way. Once it is
<m>dyed</m> yellow, pounce onto it such a pattern as will please you.
Then you will baste some <m>string</m> or a thicker <m>cord</m> onto the
pouncing and thrust it into a <m>dye</m> of <m><pa>guesde woad</pa></m>
or <m><pa>pastel woad</pa></m> &amp; it will become green, except that
which is beneath the <m>string</m>, which will remain yellow because the
<m>green dye</m> will not have penetrated there. And you can do thus
with other colors, and instead of <m>cord</m> or <m>string</m>, add some
pieces of <m>paltry cloth</m>, cut into moresque shapes, on top of the
first color. In that manner, you will have cheap embroidery.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p015r_2</id>
<head>Foundry casting</head>

<ab>One casts candlesticks and small works in a <tl>frame</tl> with
sand. And after having imprinted the work, one sprinkles it with
<m>flour</m> in order to make the <del><fr>e metal</fr></del>
<m>copper</m> or <m>latten</m> run better. When the sand has been used
for a <ms>month</ms>, it is necessary to take some new, because the one
that was used, having been reheated <del>in fire</del>
<mark>+</mark>, dries out &amp; loses its ability to bond. However,
it is used to mix among the new, for it makes the work not so porous.
One casts large works such as artillery, bells &amp; similar things in
<m>earth</m>, &amp; <m>copper</m> cast in <m>earth</m> makes less of a
<fr>chappe</fr>, and is whiter than the one cast in sand. The
<m>earth</m> is <m>sandy clay</m> mixed with <m><al>horse</al> dung</m>
&amp; <m>cloth waste</m>. That which <del>is</del> has been used for
founding, which is black, cooked &amp; as if burnt, is used to cast,
<del><fr>gecte</fr></del> mixed with <m>artificial sand</m>, &amp; is
very good. <mark>/</mark> <add>To soften &amp; make the <m>copper</m> run, throw in,
once it is melted, a little <m>lead</m>, which does not form an alloy
but is found on the surface of the cast.</add></ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<mark>+</mark> by the heat of molten <m>metal</m></ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p015r_3</id>
<head>Casting <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m></head>

<ab>It is necessary that the sand be from something very dry &amp; arid
&amp; reheated well in the <tl>frame</tl>, because, if it were humid,
like <m><pro>founder</pro>'s sand</m>, the <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m>
would spatter, &amp; cause damage. It is also necessary for the
<m>earth</m> to drink the <m>metal</m>, for cast <m>gold</m> or
<m>silver</m> <del>is</del> becomes very spongy. That is why it must be
beaten again, otherwise it is brittle, as one sees in spoon
handles.</ab>

</div>
</root>
