<root>
<page>132v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f270.item.r=</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p132r_2</id>

<ab>cool by itself. When it begins to redden, it is soon red everywhere.
But make sure, through the gate, that it is red at the bottom &amp; that
nothing appears black.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p132v_1</id>
<head><m>Common sand from the <env><fr>mine</fr></env></m></head>

<ab>In a <tl>frame</tl>, if one casts hot, it becomes porous, therefore
one only needs to dry it out.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
I have tried to make it so the <tl>molds</tl> where it is mixed do not crack
during reheating, &amp; thus do not make flashing.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is better made with <m>distilled vinegar</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p132v_2</id>
<head><m><la>Crocum ferri</la></m></head>

<ab>Having <del><fr>d</fr></del> passed it through <m>vinegar</m> &amp;
reddened it in the fire, I had it finely ground on <tl>porphyry</tl>,
until no roughness was recognisable on the <tl><bp>nail</bp></tl>. Then,
I wet it with <m>very good vinegar</m>, &amp; <del><fr>a</fr></del>
<corr>’</corr> left it two or three <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms>, stirring
it <tmp><ms>several times each day</ms></tmp>. Finally I boiled it,
&amp; reddened <del>in</del> the <tl>pot</tl> &amp;
<m><la>crocum</la></m> all together in the <tl><fr>four à
vent</fr></tl>. It came back in a mass full of small bubbles, but that
can be pulverized very finely between the <tl><bp>fingers</bp></tl>. I
put some in the sand, <del><fr>a</fr></del> <ms>half</ms> as much as
<m><fr>alum de plume</fr></m>. I wet the sand quite thinly &amp; molded
out of it a <al>very small lizard</al>, which molded very neatly &amp;
delicately &amp; very finely. The <m><la>crocum ferri</la></m> did not
render the <tl>mold</tl> harder, but it firmed it. And when your
<tl>mold</tl> is <fr>douls</fr> &amp; fat, when scraping it with a
<tl><bp>nail</bp></tl>, it is a sign that the <m><la>crocum</la></m> is
good, very fine &amp; well prepared. The quantity cannot spoil the
<tl>mold</tl>, because it is a friend to <m>gold</m>. And I believe that
<m>silver</m> would come out well. And that the <tl>mold</tl>, through
this means, does not crack. <rub>Make it from <m>filings of
needles</m></rub>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
One can put some amongst the <tl>molds</tl>, where you want to cast
<m>silver</m>, for it firms the <tl>molds</tl>, and you will find it so,
by scraping a little harder than the other where there is none. It molds
very neatly.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
This one is appropriate for all <tl>molds</tl>, &amp; keeps them from
breaking &amp; bursting in the fire. And for flat medals, it withstands
several casts. The one of <m>steel fillings &amp; needles</m> is redder
&amp; better.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p132v_3</id>
<head><m>Gilding</m> animals cast in <m>silver</m></head>

<ab>You can <m>gild </m>them with <m>amalgam</m>, without spoiling any
of the features, if they are made of <m>silver</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
