<root>
<page>042r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f89.image</image>

<div>
<id>p042r_1</id>
<head><pro>Founder</pro></head>

<ab>The <tl>mold of <m>earth</m></tl> is reheated until sometimes it
becomes red hot, for otherwise the <m>metal</m> would spatter &amp;
would not do anything good. And similarly, the <fr>noyau</fr> on the
inside should be very reheated, &amp; mixed with <m>charcoal
powder</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p042r_2</id>
<head><m>Wax</m> for seal and imprint</head>

<ab>For the large <m>wax</m> seals, one needs to have <m>tepid water</m>
always ready &amp; <del><fr>apre</fr></del> to keep your <m>wax</m> in
it. But before, it should have been kneaded between your <bp>hands</bp>
to render it very even, for otherwise the <m>water</m> that would get in
between would prevent it from coming together. Next, you will imprint
whatever you want and put three or four pieces of <m>paper</m> on, &amp;
with a <tl>stick</tl> <del>you</del> even &amp; round like a
<tl>pestle</tl>, you will roll it as if you wanted to polish it, and it
will attach itself to the <m>paper</m>, which will help you lift it off
the <tl>mold</tl>. Thus you will imprint better than if you dripped it
molten. You can carve the figures &amp; gild them, silver them, &amp;
paint them with <m>colors in varnish</m>, &amp; transfer them onto a
base of <m>glass</m> painted with <m>colors in turpentine &amp;
mastic</m>. And if you want to apply these plates by inlaying, do it
with <m>gum ammoniac </m> mixed with <m>vinegar</m>, and you will have
good <m>glue</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p042r_3</id>
<head>For casting in <m>plaster</m></head>

<ab>Melt some <m>wax</m>, &amp; with a large <tl>brush</tl>, coat the
relief of which you want to have the cavity, as if you wanted to paint
it. And a light crust <del>upon which <fr>qu</fr></del> will be formed,
upon which you will cast <del>you</del> <m>plaster</m>, to give it body
and strength. Next, in the <m>wax</m> cavity, you will also cast your
<m>plaster</m> in order to have your relief, &amp; it will come out very
easily, thanks to the <m>wax</m>. This is done more often for large
pieces in high relief than for others.</ab>

</div>
</root>
