<root>
<page>028v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f62.image</image>

<div>

<id>p028v_1</id>

<head><pro>Pewterers</pro></head>

<ab>They deem the best <m>tin</m> is the one that comes in
 <fr>saulmons</fr>,<comment>c_028v_04</comment> which has not been remelted since it came from the
<env>mine</env>, because the masters remelt it <del>a</del> in
<tl><fr>grilles</fr></tl>, weighing two or three <ms>lb</ms>, to easily
cut it up and sell it by the piece. And in this they often mix in
leftovers from <m>plates</m>, <m>solder</m> &amp; <m>common tin</m>.
And to recognise the best one, it is the most lustrous, which looks
burnished, because it is the softest. Sometimes in their
<fr>saulmons</fr> they find pieces of <m>iron</m>, stones, &amp; similar
things mixed in, to cheat on the weight. The <m>tin from
<pl>England</pl></m> is so hard that the <pro>miners</pro> put in
<m>lead</m> to soften it. The one that comes by way of <pl>Germany</pl>
is softer. Usually, the <pro>sworn master pewterers</pro>, from
<env><fr>bonnes villes</fr></env><comment>c_028v_02</comment>, add six <ms>lb</ms> of <m>fine
lead</m> <del>on</del> or eight on a <ms>quintal</ms> of <m>fine
tin</m>. The <pro>others, who work in the <env>countryside</env></pro>,
put fifteen or 20 or as much as they can, and to cover up the blackness
of the <m>lead</m> <del>they</del> and its softness, they put in
<m>looking-glass tin</m>, 4 <ms>lb</ms> per <ms>quintal</ms>,
<mark>+</mark>, <del><fr>po</fr></del> which whitens &amp; hardens,
and <del>a little</del> six or eight <ms>lb</ms> of <m>rosette</m> on a
quintal to render the plate <sn>sonorous</sn>. </ab>

<ab>

To mold platters &amp; dishes, they make them out of <m><fr>pierre
<del><fr>porte</fr></del> morte</fr></m>, that is from
<m><fr>grais</fr></m>, &amp; they shape &amp;polish <del>around</del>
them on the <tl>wheel</tl>. They melt their <m>tin</m> in an
<del><fr>dest</fr></del> <tl><m>iron</m> posnet</tl> on a
<m>charcoal</m> fire, and with an <tl><m>iron</m> spoon</tl> that holds
<del>almost</del> a sufficient quantity for a platter, they cast
<del><fr>leu</fr></del> in their <tl>cold molds</tl>, which they keep
joined &amp; tight between their <bp>knees</bp>. And soon after, they
open the <tl>molds</tl> so that they do not heat up, &amp; having taken
out the cast which is on the female side, &amp; which breaks easily.
Then, with a <tl>cloth</tl> which soaks in <m>water</m>, which they
always have beside them, they rub the middle of the back of the dish
&amp; around the edge, so that it comes out better, and they rub the
female mold.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>+</mark>

When the <m>tin is fine</m>, one adds less <m>glass-looking tin</m>,
namely 4 <ms>lb</ms> per <ms>quintal</ms>, but if the <m>tin is low
quality</m>, that is to say allied with a lot of <m>lead</m>, one puts
at least five or six <ms>lb</ms> of <m>looking-glass tin</m> to it.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

If there is not a lot of <m>looking-glass tin</m>, one puts about two or
three <ms>lb</ms> per <ms>quintal</ms>. One puts eight <ms>lb</ms> of
<m>rosette</m>. But if there is a lot of <m>looking-glass tin</m>
<del>one</del>, like 4 or 5 <ms>lb</ms>, one only puts six of
<m>rosette</m>. And commonly, per <ms>quintal</ms> of <m>tin</m>, one
adds x <ms>lb</ms> of both.

</ab>

<ab><rub>Go to the fifth leaf.</rub></ab>

</div>
</root>
