<root>
<page>133r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f271.image</image>

<div>

<id>p133r_1</id>

<head><m>Hard wax</m> for imprinting seals</head>

<ab>It is made from <m>white wax</m>, which is harder than the other,
&amp; one mixes in <m>very finely ground ceruse or lead white</m> until
it becomes as hard as you fancy <del><fr>u</fr></del>, adding to it a
<ms>drop</ms> of <m>turpentine</m> to bind it. Next, mix in whatever
color you want. That is the <m>wax</m> <pro>goldsmiths</pro> use for
modeling.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p133r_2</id>

<head>Feet of <al>small<del><fr>s</fr></del> lizards</al> for
<m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m></head>

<ab>Because the feet of these, which are very small, are very delicate,
as you molded the top and <del><fr>d</fr></del> uncovered the belly
&amp; the bottom of the feet, cover them lightly with <m>wax </m>&amp;
then cast the second <tl>mold</tl>. And the <m>wax</m> being removed, it
leaves a <del><fr>g</fr></del> little gate for the aforesaid feet. And
should the bottom of these come of in one piece, you can repair it. And
the scales from the top of the toes will come out well.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

At the end of the nails <corr>of</corr> <al>large lizards</al>, place
<del>make</del> on each one a little circle of <m>wax</m>, to make the
gate thus :</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p133r_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5V2JZcWtNeEJmYWs</link>

</figure>

</div>

<div>

<id>p133r_3</id>

<head>Marks from the <tl>points of <m>iron</m> wire</tl> which are found
on the head of the animal</head>

<ab><del><fr>L</fr></del> With the <tl>points</tl>, one has previously
set the stance, especially that of the head. But the head being pierced,
there remains around the hole some moisture and a little exudation,
which hinders the sand from covering the <tl>point</tl> &amp; there
always remains some little opening <del><fr>g</fr></del>. But to avoid
this, you can plant <add>in the slab of the<ill/><comment>c_133r_01</comment></add> an
<tl><m>iron</m> point</tl>, <del><fr>arro</fr></del> cleaned &amp;
rounded at the top end &amp; on this end place there a little <m>hard
wax</m> or <del><fr>du</fr></del> a little <m>mastic</m> or
<m>cement</m>, and by means of this <tl>hot <m>iron</m>
wire</tl>, hold in place the throat of the animal, which can be removed
when you come to uncover the belly &amp; the throat to make the second
cast.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p133r_4</id>

<head><tl>Clamps</tl> and broken <tl>mold</tl></head>

<ab>When you have made the first reheating &amp; removed the
<tl>clamps</tl>, and you have <del>the</del> opened your <tl>mold</tl>
to clean it by blowing, with <m>quicksilver</m>, which is used only in
enclosed <tl>molds</tl>, close the <tl>mold</tl> again &amp; put the
<tl>clamps</tl> on again, but not in the first place where they were.
<m>Lute</m> again &amp; dry again. But if it is for a cast with
<m>silver</m> or <m>gold</m>, <m>lute</m> with the remainder of the sand
that was used, for it is the safest. If your <tl>mold</tl>, while
reheating, is broken, you can adjust it with some <tl>clamps</tl> &amp;
<m>lute</m>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<mark>X</mark>

</ab>

</div>
</root>
