<root>
<page>045r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f95.image</image>

<div>

<id>p045r_1</id>

<head>Loading an arquebus with a <m>hail shot</m> </head>

<figure>

<id>fig_p045r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bkhmQklfNHJoRnc</link>

</figure>

<ab>It is necessary to make a <m>wooden</m> pipe 4 or 5 fingers wide
that is perfectly hollow, according to the mouth of your barrel, of the
form represented in A. Then, having cut some <m>paper</m>, which has to
be as strong as that of large printed books, in the form indicated in D
and as wide as you want your cartridge<comment>c_045r_01</comment> to be
long, wrap the <m>paper</m> around the baton B and at the top, where the
pointed tip F will be around the aforementioned <m>paper</m>, and the
cartridge will be formed. But, in order to make the bottom more uniform,
put it into pipe A, then introduce baton B and, in the other end of the
pipe, which is marked G, insert baton C and pack so as to compact and
press the folded tip of your cartridge, then take it out, and load it,
put three or four <fr>drageons</fr><comment>c_045r_02</comment> or
tears<comment>c_045r_03</comment>. Then, with a punch, marked E, of the
same caliber of your arquebus or pistol, punch round pieces on
<m>cardboard</m> or <m>felt</m> or <m>waxed cloth</m>, and put this
round piece into your cartridge, and push it until the <fr>drageons</fr>
with the baton B, the more <fr>drageons</fr>, 3 or 4, then a round
piece. And continue like that until the cartridge is full, then put it
into the arquebus. If you want your hail shot to scatter earlier, make
round pieces out of <m>paper</m>. If you want it to reach further
without scattering, make the piece out of <m>cardboard</m>. If you want
it to reach even further, make the round piece out of <m>waxed
cloth</m>, or either of <m>leather</m> or <m>felt</m>, and a piece of
<m>waxed cloth</m> on the top. And if you make the cartridge in part
with <m>waxed cloth</m> or <m>waxed paper</m>, it will reach one hundred
paces and will make a big piercing, and the <m>pellet</m>, barely
scattering, will produce a big opening. But if you make your cartridge
with <m>waxed cloth</m> or a material stronger than <m>paper</m>, one
ought not to make it so long in the square coming to a point like in D,
because it is enough that it wraps around twice. In this manner, the
<m>hail shot</m> barely scatters and makes a big piercing in a door,
body of a cuirass<comment>c_045r_04</comment>, or other.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<x><figure>#</figure></x> co<exp>mm</exp>e <del>D</del>H

</ab>

</div>
</root>
