<root>
<page>162v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f330.item</image>

<div>

<id>p162v_1</id>

<head><pa>Peach tree</pa></head>

<ab>Because they sprout &amp; flower among the first, &amp; thus are
caught by the <del><fr>ch</fr></del> <env><tmp>frost</tmp></env>, one
extracts them <ms><tmp>during winter</tmp></ms> in order
<del><ms><tmp>the winter</tmp></ms></del> that the <env>cold</env> slows
them, and that blossoming later, the flowers come to profit.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p162v_2</id>

<head><pa>Olive trees</pa></head>

<ab>In <pl>Spain</pl>, one extracts them <ms><tmp>during
winter</tmp></ms> &amp; <ms><tmp>in summer</tmp></ms> one plants them
well with <m>earth</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p162v_3</id>

<head><m>Bittern</m> foot</head>

<ab>To mold it, it is better to spread the toes &amp; nails out well, on
something flat, &amp; leave it thusly to dry a few days, because, in
drying, the scales appear coarser &amp; the nerves &amp; tendons become
more apparent, and thusly the molded foot will be more artistic.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p162v_4</id>

<head>Molds of things that do not release</head>

<ab>Animals that do not release can only be molded in two molds, which
should not be opened until after they are well reheated &amp; the
enclosed animal is well burned. Animals that have bones or scales, which
do not reduce into powder, but rather remain as calcined lumps, will
never leave through the gate, whatever blowing that one does, or
whatever quicksilver that one puts there, or a feather quill molded to
use as a gate. This is why one molds in two halves, in order that, the
mold being opened after having been reheated, the burned thing can be
cleaned out well. But take heed to let it cool well, in order that, when
removing the clamps, being hot, and when it is most frangible, something
does not breaks while it is hot. The crust &amp; ashes that it leaves
&amp; which adhere to the mold, are removed better once cold. Note also
that on the bottom side of the mold, when you reheat, the animal which
boils leaves some filth. And, on this occasion, one always marks the
mold where the back of the animal is, in order that, when reheating, it
is above &amp; on top &amp; that through this means it is neater.</ab>

</div>
</root>
