<root>
<page>129r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f263.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p129r_1</id>

<head>Painting <m>metal</m> herbs</head>

<ab>If you are in a hurry it would be better to mix your color with a
not-too-thick <m>gum</m> <del>or</del> because <m>oil</m> takes a
<tmp>long time</tmp> to dry, and it runs if it is transparently layered,
as the herbs require. And if you still want it <add>done</add> promptly,
mix your color with <m>glair</m> beaten with <m>peelings of the <pa>fig tree</pa></m>, 
and your work will soon be dry. But layer it
transparently.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129r_2</id>

<head>For <pa>wormseed</pa></head>

<ab> The pallid white of this herb is made from <m>green verditer</m>,
<m>white lead</m> or <m>ceruse</m>, a bit of <m>massicot</m>, <m>stil de
grain yellow</m>, and <m><fr>cendré d'azur</fr></m>. Mix &amp; compose
your color according to a natural branch that you will have. </ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129r_3</id>

<head><al>Viper color</al></head>

<ab>

It is the most beautiful <al>snake</al> that can be molded, because it
has very beautiful scales, &amp; hard &amp; transparent. Its true color
is made with good <m>verdigris</m>, well ground with some <m>good
vinegar</m>, if it is of <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m>. And if it is in some
place darker, fumigate this first color with<m> sulphur</m>, as you
know. And if one needs to lighten and whiten, like under the throat, rub
with <tl><m>coarse linen</m></tl>. <add>The male, ejects from its
nature<comment>c_129r_01</comment>, which is at the bottom, when it is
firmly pressed, a little mass like <ms>half an arquebus ball</ms>,
made in the genitals and full of very venomous spurs.</add></ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>+</mark> Put a bit of <m><fr>metalline</fr></m> in your
<m>tin</m> &amp; your <al>lizard</al> will resemble <m>silver</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p129r_4</id>

<head>Molded <pa>roses</pa></head>

<ab>

They are awkward to mold because the petals are very fine &amp; weak
&amp; doubled. But, to <del><fr>obl</fr></del> avoid this, one needs to
anoint them with <m>wheat oil</m>, which is very dessicative. And having
quickly dried, it firms &amp; stiffens the leaves to be able to separate
them &amp; withstand the wet sand. The same is done with <al>flies</al>,
with <pa>pansies</pa>, &amp; similar delicate things, with flowers from
the <pa>caper plant</pa>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
