<root>
<page>117v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f240.image</image>

<div>
<id>p117v_1</id>
<head>For making the <m>ashes</m> of flowers and plants leave
<tl>molds</tl></head>

<ab>Some <del>mix</del> put <m>quicksilver</m> inside it. But, if it is
a little work, or fine &amp; delicate foliage, that only has
<del>p</del> a slender exit, they make two errors: the first, that
<m>quicksilver</m> by its heaviness can break <del>f</del> some delicate
feature inside when shaken, the other, that some grains will always
linger inside that will make <m>metals</m> sour &amp; hinder the
perfection of the cast. It is true that if it is to empty the
<tl>mold</tl> of some animal which is thickish &amp; which has big conduits
&amp; passages by which the <m>quicksilver</m> can easily exit, like a
<al>bird</al> or a <al>serpent</al>, one can indeed put in it some
<m>quicksilver</m> <del><fr>pou</fr></del> to break by shaking the
<m>calcined bones of the animal</m>, because the aforesaid <m>☿</m> will
come out &amp; not remain at all.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
The <pa>asparagus</pa> stalk is so hard that most often it remains as
<m>charcoal</m>. Because of this, dry it out beforehand, or wet it with
<m>oil of sulfur &amp; turpentine</m>, or cast separately the little
branches &amp; <m>solder</m> them onto a thick stalk drawn through the
<tl>wire drawing plate</tl>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
If the burnt thing has left some <m>filth</m> or <m>ash</m>, let it cool
a little, &amp; with an <tl><m>iron wire</m> wrapped in
<m>cotton</m></tl> that can bend according to the cavities that you have
to search out, clean &amp; blow out this defect, or with a <tl>soft
brush</tl> or a <tl>clipped <fr>pinceau</fr></tl>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p117v_2</id>
<head><pa>Daisies</pa></head>

<ab>They can be cast well in <m>gold</m>. But if you want to
<m>enamel</m> them, you have to make them by hand &amp; <m>enamel</m>
them &amp; then attach them. Otherwise, the leaves would be so pressed
together that the <m>enamel</m> would muddle together there. </ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p117v_3</id>
<head>Sand that was used</head>

<ab>Do not cast it. But because it is mixed with <m><fr>alum de plume</fr></m>,
you can use it in the mixture of other things &amp; it can serve in
place of <m>brick</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p117v_4</id>
<head>Molding <fr>en noyau</fr> figures of <m>wax</m> or medals of
<m>lead</m></head>

<ab>Rub them with <m>oil</m> with a <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl>, but let
it be so lightly that your medal is almost rubbed dry &amp; that it
hardly appears to have been anointed. Next, <del><fr>destr</fr></del> rub
it with <m>eau-de-vie</m> and heat the <m>water</m> with which you will
wet your aforementioned sand, with <m>plaster</m>, <m>brick</m> &amp;
<m>alum</m>, in order that being <del><fr>chau</fr></del> like lukewarm
when you cast it, the <m>oil</m> will not refuse it, as it does with
<m>cold water</m>, &amp; <add>do not forget when moistening your sand to
always mix in it a little <m>sal ammoniac</m></add>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Medals mold in such a way very neatly.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p117v_5</id>
<head><m>Blood of <al>snakes</al></m></head>

<ab>If you need to cut some <al>snake</al> inside the <tl>mold</tl> to
burn <corr>it</corr>, cut <corr>it</corr> far from the entrance of the
<tl>mold</tl> in order that no <m>blood</m> remains, for it would
make a crust that afterwards would not be taken away by the same
<m>quicksilver</m> &amp; would remove the imprints from your
<tl>mold</tl>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
