<root>
<page>004r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f13.image</image>

<div>

<id>p004r_1</id>

<head><m>Varnish of spike lavender oil</m></head>

<ab>One needs to heat <m>lavender spike oil</m> and as it begins to
simmer, put in <m>powdered sandarac gum</m> so that it soon melts. And
over a <m>charcoal</m> fire stir continuously until the <m>sandarac</m>
is well melted, which you will know by taking a little of the said
<m>varnish</m> on a <tl>plate</tl>. And if it is fatty when you handle
it with a <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl>, it is ready. And for one <ms>lb</ms>
of <m>lavender spike oil</m>, you will put five <ms>ounces</ms> of
<m>pulverized sandarac</m>, although some only put in four
<ms>ounces</ms>, but this is not so good nor so fatty. This one is
promptly dry. <pro>Framemakers</pro>, to avoid the trouble of polishing
their <m>ebony</m>, varnish it with this, as do <pro>guitarmakers</pro>.
This is not as appropriate for panels as that of <m>fine turpentine</m>,
though it is good for the moldings of panels. One did not used to
varnish the landscape of a panel when <m>linseed varnish</m> was in use,
because it would have yellowed the landscape. But with that of
<m>turpentine</m>, one varnishes everything. You can put in
<m>pulverized mastic</m> extracted in tears or otherwise, and it will be
more dessicative in place of <m>sandarac</m>.</ab>

<ab>If you want to varnish on <m>plaster</m> or a wall, first put on
your very hot <m><fr>colle de retaille</fr></m>, because if cold it
would not penetrate the wall, &amp; when you would put your
<m>varnish</m> on, it would come off.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<m>Varnish of spike lavender oil</m> is not as appropriate for colors as
that of <m>turpentine</m>, for <m>spike lavender oil</m> <del>makes them
die</del> <add>eats away at</add> the colors since it is too
penetrating.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p004r_2</id>

<head>For removing <m>varnish</m> from an old panel that has yellowed &amp;
varnish it anew</head>

<ab>Take <m>white soap</m> &amp; <m><tl>sieved</tl> ashes</m>, &amp;
soak both in <m>water</m>. And with a <tl>sponge</tl>, take the said
<m>ashes</m> &amp; <m>soap</m> &amp; rub the panel with them. And as you
see that the old <m>varnish</m> is removed, throw a
<tl><ms>bucket</ms></tl> of <m>water</m> against the panel to clean it.
Next put it for <ms><tmp>a quarter of an hour</tmp></ms> <env>in the
sun</env> to make it dry and to revive the colors. Next, once the panel
dries, you can apply your <m>turpentine varnish</m>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

Make sure the colors do not come off.</ab>

</div>
</root>
