<root>
<page>159r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f323.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p159r_1</id>
<head><m>Wax</m> portraits</head>

<ab>

If they are painted with colors on the <m>wax</m> &amp; if the
<m>wax</m> is not tinted &amp; mixed with color within, the color lifts
off &amp; is undone if you mold them <fr>en noyau</fr>, but the portrait
is not spoiled. One needs to <m>oil</m> them lightly, bathing in
<m>eau-de-vie</m> &amp; wetting with <m>hot water</m>. If they are
varnished, one needs to mold them two or three times to lift off the
<m>varnish</m>, which sticks to the <tl>mold</tl>. After it is removed,
you will be able to mold neat. If they are on <m>wood</m>, one needs to
saturate the <m>wood</m> with <m>very hot melted wax</m>, for otherwise the
<tl>mold</tl> would be attached to it. <m>Lead white</m> is much better
for mixing with <m>white wax</m> than <m>ceruse</m>, for <m>lead
white</m> is firmer &amp; whiter.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p159r_2</id>
<head><tl>Chiseling</tl></head>

<ab>

If the <tl>small chisel</tl> has passed through some part of a portrait,
one needs to repair &amp; retrace it all. Otherwise it would look like a
joined piece.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p159r_3</id>
<head>

<m><al>Fish</al> glue</m></head>

<ab>

Beat it very finely &amp; thinly on a well-cleaned <tl>anvil</tl>, &amp;
next wet it with <m>eau-de-vie</m> over <del><fr>ch</fr></del> <m>hot
ashes</m> &amp; a low fire, &amp; it will be quickly melted; &amp; if it
is not strong &amp; thick enough, add <m>eau-de-vie</m>. And take heed
<del>them</del> not to put it to melt in a <tl>fatty vessel</tl>, but in
a new one, if you can. It is melted on the fire &amp;is also dried
quickly on the fire, but it may be warmed from a distance once on the
work. It holds strongly. With it one joins flowers &amp; delicate things
of <m>gold</m>, of <m>silver</m>, of <m>tin</m>, &amp; other materials
which are in danger of spoiling if <m>soldered</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p159r_4</id>
<head><m>Tin</m> and <m>lead</m></head>

<ab>

They are beaten very thin <del>without itself</del>. And the <m>tin</m>
does not sour &amp; crack if the <m>lead</m> is done well,
<del><fr>Ma</fr></del> but it is even more fatty, but one reheats it
under <m>hot ash</m>. And it is necessary to beat them with several
leaves together.</ab>

</div>
</root>
