<root>
<page>095r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f195.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p094r_1</id>

<ab>The <pro>furbisher</pro> buys his blades by the <ms>dozen</ms> which
are not fully drawn by the tang because he does this himself to adjust
them well to the <del><fr>l</fr></del> pommel &amp; guards.</ab>

<ab><pl>Spanish</pl> ones are deemed better for being of <m>better steel
&amp;iron</m> but they are not as <tl>well-forged</tl> as swords from
<pl>Vienne</pl> in <del><fr>pro</fr></del> <pl>Dauphiné</pl>. The
<pl>Spanish</pl> ones are not as well ground coming from the
<tl>forge</tl> because they grind them with the
<tl><bp>foot</bp></tl><comment>c_095r_05</comment> &amp; this is what
makes them wavy.</ab>

<ab>Blades from <pl>Vienne</pl> commonly cost xviii or 19
<ms><cn>lb</cn> a dozen</ms>.</ab>

<ab>The first thing the <pro>furbisher</pro> does when he gets his new
blades is to draw out their tang, which he does himself, or has done by
<pro>locksmiths</pro> or <pro>farriers</pro>, giving him some
<cn>liard</cn><comment>c_095r_06</comment> for his charcoal. Next, they
pass it over a <tl>grindstone</tl> to make it
cut<comment>c_095r_07</comment>, then lay it down on the
<tl><fr>chameau</fr></tl>, and <add>with</add> some <m>pulverized
emery</m>, fine &amp; soft as <m>flour</m>, &amp; mixed with <m>oil</m>
to make it hold, they furbish the sword with the <tl>stick</tl> used to
remove the traces of the <tl>grindstone</tl> and then <del>the</del>
clean <del><fr>po</fr></del> the sword <add>well</add> with the
<m>emery</m>, and give it a <ms>drop</ms> or two of <m>oil</m> which
they spread with the <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl> to give it luster. Having
put the <m>oil</m>, they furnish the sword again on the
<tl><fr>chameau</fr></tl> with the
<tl><m><df><fr>felin</fr></df></m></tl> which is a
<tl><m>thunderstone</m></tl> mounted in the middle of a stick like the
<tl><fr>fustée</fr></tl>, and this stick is called the <df><fr>baton à
<m>felinder</m></fr></df>. Next, having passed it on the
<tl><m><fr>felin</fr></m></tl>, they furbish it with <m>chalk</m> &amp;
the <m>oil</m> which is on the sword. Next, they wipe it &amp; go over
it again, &amp; furbish with <m>dry chalk</m>. And at the end, when they
are ready mounted, one gives them the edge with the
<tl><fr>gratteau</fr></tl><comment>c_095r_08</comment>.
<del><fr>Ai</fr></del></ab>

<ab>Once furbished, one mounts it on the guards which one presents to
know if they are quite suitable. And taking hold of a blade such that
the whole ricasso is held in the <tl><bp>hand</bp></tl>, one conjectures
that it will be just as heavy once mounted.</ab>

<ab>One puts the blade in a <tl>vice</tl> between two pieces of
<m>wood</m>, then with a <tl>file</tl> they enlarge the opening of the
guard<comment>c_095r_09</comment> if it is necessary. Then to rivet it,
one places on the tang<comment>c_095r_10</comment> <del>a piece of</del>
&amp; the pommel a piece of <m>wood</m> &amp; with a <tl>hammer</tl>,
one beats on it to align &amp; secure the pommel well. Then with the
<tl>hammer</tl>, one works the tang when the pommel is well secured
&amp; does not wobble. The <m>wood</m> is put there so as not to spoil
the pommel. Next, one fits the tang with a <tl>file</tl> or
<tl>chisel</tl>. And some make <del>the <fr>b</fr></del> the tang in a
square diamond-shape<comment>c_095r_11</comment> but it is not as good
as the round one, for when faceted, the tang breaks.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
