<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="057r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f119.image">




<div continues="yes" id="p056v_1" categories="painting;varnish">





<ab>

<m>Lake</m> takes long to dry in <m>oil</m> and for that reason one must
grind some <m>glass</m> with it. But one needs to choose <m><fr>cristallin</fr></m>
because it is cleaner. And because it would be too difficult to grind by
itself, one must redden it on the fire, then when entirely red throw it
into <m>cold water</m>, &amp; it will crumble &amp; pulverize
easily for grinding it afterward. Being well ground <del>it</del> with a lot of
<m>water</m>, it resembles ground <m>lead white</m>, but for all this it has
no body. I think it would be good for casting.</ab>

<ab hand="handd">

<comment rid="c_057r_02"/><m>Lead white</m> is made with <m>plate lead</m>, beaten thin &amp; put
under the <env><tl><m>dung</m> heap</tl></env>.</ab>

<ab hand="handd">

<m>White varnish of <m>turpentine</m> or of <m><pa>spike lavender</pa>
oil</m> and <m>turpentine</m></m> is colored with <m>pulverized
<fr>terra emerita</fr></m>, making it boil together. It gives a gold
color on <m>silver</m> and more beautiful if it is burnished. It is dry
in a <tmp>quarter of an hour</tmp>. <pa><m>Aloe</m></pa> would make brighter
color still, but it takes long to dry &amp; the other is dry in <tmp>a quarter
of an hour</tmp>, <tmp>in winter</tmp> as well as
<tmp>summer</tmp>.</ab>

<ab hand="handd">

Good <m>lake</m> moistened with <m>saliva</m> is promptly rendered dark.
That from <pl>Florence</pl> is too gummed.</ab>

<ab hand="handd">

If you make a layer of <m><pro>printers</pro>' ink</m> on <m>velvet</m>
and there apply <m>gold leaf</m> and then stretch the <m>velvet</m>, it
will appear grainy as if there were <m>gold powder</m> disseminated on
it.</ab>

<ab>

<comment rid="c_057r_01"/><m>Vermilion</m> ground by itself is wan and pale, but ground after
<m>lake</m>, it is more beautiful.</ab>

<ab>For ridding <tl><m>marbles</m></tl> of grease, one grinds
<m>common ashes</m> on it, which is good afterward to make the first
imprimatura of a panel that is prepared in <m>oil</m> in order to seal
the cracks &amp; chinks of the <m>wood</m>. It has more body than
<m>chalk</m> &amp; it has <del><m>chalk</m></del> a certain fattiness.
One mixes it with the said <m>chalk</m> or <del><fr>ra</fr></del>
with the colors collected from the <tl>vessel</tl> where one cleans the
<tl>paintbrush</tl>. It is desiccative and spares the color.
<del>On</del> Once this first imprimatura is made on the <m>wood</m>, one
scrapes with a <tl>knife</tl> to even it. Next, one makes there a second imprimatura
of <m>ceruse</m> or of the <add>meanest</add> colors mixed together. In
a painting in <m>oil</m> <add>on <m>canvas</m></add>, one applies only
one imprimatura, and the same <m>ashes</m> can be used there. Also, after one
has ground a color, one grinds some <m>pith of coarse bread</m> on it to
rid the <tl><m>marble</m></tl> of grease.</ab>

</div>
</root>
