<root>
<page>108v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f222.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p108r_2</id>

<ab>thus one mixes it &amp; reducing it into
<del><fr>p</fr></del><m><add>b</add> small stones</m>, purging it of its
impurities. Then one puts it to cook neatly in a
<del><tl><fr>pot</fr></tl></del> <add><tl>earthen vessel</tl></add> in
the <tl>furnace of <pro>those who make <tl>pots</tl></pro></tl>, and one
leaves it there until the <tl>pots</tl> are cooked. Next, one mixes it
again with <m>essence of sal ammoniac</m> &amp; one grinds it very well,
and one empties the <m>muddy &amp; clean water</m> in a separate
<tl>vessel</tl>. Again, one puts the same <m>essence</m> on top &amp;
one grinds &amp; again one puts the <m>muddy water</m> with the other.
And one does thus, until it has passed everything. In this way, one
purges &amp; cleanses it, &amp; one renders it very fine &amp;
handleable. Having taken away the <m>water</m>, by tilting it or with a
<tl>sponge</tl>, one takes the residue and one dries it. Then,
moistening it with the aforementioned <m>water</m>, like one does with
the other <del><m><fr>eau</fr></m></del> sand, one uses it in a
<tl>frame</tl>, where, if it retracts, it is a sign that it
has not reheated enough &amp; that one needs to reheat it further. This
one is appropriate for molding all <m>metals</m>, and especially
<m>gold</m> &amp; <m>silver</m>, and the more it is used the better it
is. One needs to set aside the one in which you cast <m>lead</m> or
<m>tin</m>, for it would sour the <m>gold</m> you would cast.</ab>

<ab><rub><m><fr>Alum de plume</fr></m></rub> should be reheated in a
<del><tl><fr>chaulderon</fr></tl></del> <add><tl>crucible</tl> covered
with a <tl><m>tile</m></tl></add> in a strong <del><fr>flamme</fr></del>
<add>charcoal</add> fire, in order that the impurities which could be there
is burned with that which does not burn. This is done either in the
<tl><pro>goldsmith</pro>’s forge</tl>, <tl>surrounded with
<m>bricks</m></tl>, or in a <tl><fr>fourneau à vent</fr></tl> with
<fr>foeu de fusion</fr>, so that the <del><fr>sable demeure <tmp>asses
long temps</tmp></fr></del> <add><tl>crucible</tl> remains red for a
<ms><tmp>quarter hour</tmp></ms></add>. This is done more to cleanse it
than for anything else. It becomes reddish on the surface &amp; on the
inside it remains white &amp; better dried out <mark>#</mark></ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<mark>#</mark> After your <m><fr>alum de plume</fr></m> is cooled,
pestle it in a <tl>mortar</tl>, then grind it on the
<tl><m>marble</m></tl>, and it will be rendered in very fine wooly
filaments, which gives binding to the sand, without getting burned as
other things do, which is a fine invention. Pestle it in the
<tl>mortar</tl>, by dragging the <tl>pestle</tl>, for the flying dust
could enter your <bp>throat</bp> or land on your <bp>face</bp>, which
will give you reason <sn>to scratch yourself well</sn>. Put a little
every time in the <tl>mortar</tl>, to avoid the flying dust. It is
better to grind it thus, in the <tl>mortar</tl>, dragging the
<tl>pestle</tl>, than on the <tl><m>marble</m></tl>,
<del><fr>car</fr></del> where <del><fr>c</fr></del> it spreads &amp; in
the <tl>mortar</tl>, it collects on all sides. Render it very fine &amp;
<sn>soft to the touch</sn>.</ab>

<ab><rub><m>Clay</m></rub>,to make circles around <tl>molds</tl>, should
be very fat &amp; handleable, and serves only to make the surrounding of
the <tl>molds</tl>. Thus, one needs only choose it well fat, and beat
very well &amp; moisten it moderately with some <m>water</m> &amp; keep
it in a <tl>pit</tl> or in a <tl><fr>terrine</fr></tl> and make numerous
holes with a <tl>stick</tl> in it, which fill with <m>water</m>, in
order to keep always fresh &amp; soft, so that it is always ready to use
when needed.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
