<root>
<page>105r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f215.image</image>

<div>

<id>p105r_1</id>

<head><al>Turtles</al></head>

<ab>Males have the shell overturned at the end near the tail, and have
the underbelly shell notched all its length from the tail to the
<del><fr>que</fr></del> head. And the females have neither the
overturned shell near the tail nor the notches.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p105r_2</id>

<head>Drying colors</head>

<ab><m>Soot black</m> &amp; others would not dry in <m>oil</m> if one
did not put <m>verdigris</m> with it.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p105r_3</id>

<head><pro>Painter</pro></head>

<ab>Colors laid down twice are thicker in and of themselves, if they
are not managed. Otherwise, one paints on <m>wood</m>; otherwise on
<m>canvas</m>; otherwise on walls.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p105r_4</id>

<head>Gardening</head>

<ab>For shield grafting, one needs to take the new output
that the tree that you want to graft made <tmp>in that year</tmp>, &amp;
there cut a branch on which you see that, next to
<del><fr>raci</fr></del> the sprouting of leaves there are little
buttons that one calls <fr>oeillets</fr>, which are the beginnings of
sprouts. One needs to nimbly, with a <tl>very sharp pen-knife</tl>, cut
in the shape of a shield a little bit of the skin <del>with</del> which
contains an <fr>oeillet</fr> or sprout with the leaf, thus marked B.
<del>But</del> <del><fr>plustot</fr></del> Then carefully make on the
tender wood <del><fr>s</fr></del> which is full of sap, on which you
want to graft, two lines thus <del><fr>de</fr></del> cut <figure/>, then
make in the middle a cleft thus

<figure>

<id>fig_p105r_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5T1FZYTdOT1U4Qzg</link>

</figure>

. Next, separate with the point of the <tl>pen-knife</tl> the bark &amp;
open it from the cleft in the middle, and having neatly lodged your
shield so that nothing comes out but the sprout, bind it well &amp; wrap
it entirely with a <tl><m>slip of <pa>linen</pa></m></tl> or <tl><m>very
soft thread</m></tl>, so that there is nothing uncovered but the leaf,
which in three or 4 <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms> will give you an indication
whether the shield should take, accordingly it will be green. Leave your
graft seven or eight <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms> thus, then unbind it &amp;
join it well to the bark, especially at the sprout, &amp; then rebind
all gently but not as strongly as before; &amp; if there is any output
or growth, leave it space to go out; &amp; do thus three or 4
times.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p105r_1</id>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5UWpzdGVweGVvQTg</link>

</figure>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
