<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="083v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f172.item">




<div id="p083v_1" categories="casting">

<head>A way for molding excellently with <m>water</m></head>

<ab>

Dissolve in <env>humid place</env> some <m>sandiver</m>, and then
place this <m>water</m> on what you want to mold, having encircled it,
and place it to coagulate on the hot <m>ashes</m>. Do the same with
<m>vitriol</m> &amp; <m>copperas</m>, which, once well calcined, reduce
in <m>water</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p083v_2" categories="casting">

<head>

Molding in relief on one part and hollow on the other</head>

<ab>

It is necessary to cast two pieces of <m>copper</m>, <m>latten</m> or
similar <m>metal</m>, very neatly, and then when you have molded the
hollow form in the <m>sand</m>, leave the figure of <m>metal</m> that you
<corr><del>s</del></corr> have molded in the <tl>frame</tl>, without moving it
from its place. And cast, &amp; if there is not enough thickness press a
little &amp; push the figure down in the <tl>frame</tl>.</ab>

<ab>

It is good to mold always the faces not on the side of the cast, but
with the head on the bottom, because the force of the substance is at
the entry of the medal, &amp; there, where the force is, the
<m>filth</m> &amp; <m>grime</m> accumulate. And, in this way, if you
were mold the face toward the cast, some <m>grime</m> could be found
there, &amp; it is better that is found on the clothing, which is easier
to repair.</ab>

<ab>

<m>Vinegar</m> is better for moistening than <m>wine</m>. It is
necessary that the <tl>frame</tl> be quite smooth and even, otherwise
<del>and that the cast be</del>, as you press on one side, the other one
lifts.</ab>

<ab>

This is why the <tl>press</tl> is better, for it tightens evenly, &amp;
more than your <tl><bp>hands</bp></tl>, and makes

the <m>coarse sand</m>, which is humid, communicate its humidity to the
<m>soft &amp; fine sand</m>, which is sprinkled &amp; pounced dry
on the medal.</ab>

<ab>

When you mold, always leave your medal in <del>one of</del>
<add>the</add><comment rid="c_083v_02"/> <tl>frames</tl>, <del>is</del> <add>without stirring
it</add> because, if your hollow form is not molded very neatly, you can put
it back in the right place by means of <tl>pegs</tl>, which will prevent
it from shifting. But, at first, pounce your medal with very
fine <m><pa>willow</pa> charcoal</m>, &amp; <del><fr>se</fr></del> next
clean it, for this degreases it, &amp; makes it easier to release afterward.</ab>

<ab>Do not knock it when molding because this will shake loose the
<tl>frame</tl> &amp; the <m>sand</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p083v_3" categories="tool;metal process" margin="left-middle">

<head margin="left-middle"><tl>Bellows</tl></head>

<ab margin="left-middle">To melt with <tl>bellows</tl>, &amp; hasten your melt,
&amp; also cast hotter <del><fr>po</fr></del>, do not place your
<tl>bellows</tl> at the bottom near the foot of the <tl>furnace</tl>,
for fear that some <m>charcoal</m> might <del>you</del> enter it, put
them almost under the <tl>grate</tl>. It is good that your
<tl><fr>four à vent</fr></tl> be in an <env>aerated place</env> so that the
<env>wind</env> might make it heat better, &amp; that it be well dry,
&amp; reheat. One ought to plug the doors of the <tl>furnace</tl>
&amp; that there is only the entry of the <tl>blast-pipe</tl> of the
<tl>bellows</tl>. And by the end, you need to give it force,
as at the beginning you will blow gently.</ab>

</div>
</root>
