<root>
<page>149v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f304.image</image>

<div>

<id>p149v_1</id>

<head>Molding vases in several pieces</head>

<ab><pro>Goldsmiths</pro> who work in grand works and plate get whatever
wooden forms they please turned on a lathe. And then, with some
<m>wax</m>, they model on top masks, festoons, and whatever they please.
And they mold next, in three, in four, or several pieces.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p149v_2</id>

<head><m>Gold</m> solder</head>

<ab>They take on a <m>gold</m> <fr>denier</fr> a <fr>grain</fr> of the
fine <m><fr>aloé</fr></m>, like old <cn><fr>douzains</fr></cn> are.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p149v_3</id>

<head>Molding a <al>fly</al></head>

<ab>Large <al>flies</al> can be molded &amp; <del>g</del> made by
casting. But one needs <del>par d</del> to grease underneath their wings
with <m>wheat oil</m>, which dries quickly and fortifies them &amp;
gives them a little thickness. The same is done to <al>butterflies</al>,
<al>cicadas</al>, <al>grasshoppers</al>, &amp; similar things. But to
cast them more easily, one applies them on some leaf or bouquet. The
others are made by hand with a very thin <m>silver</m> blade. <add>One
ought not to keep them once dead, because they dry out and their legs
break.</add></ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>

<m>Wheat oil</m> is put underneath delicate things to render them more
rigid &amp; firm &amp; to make them hold their natural position. Because
being weak &amp; delicate, the wet sand, weighting down their tops,
would change their form.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p149v_4</id>

<head><al>Bat</al></head>

<ab>They have very thin wings, &amp; if they are large &amp; dry and
their wings extended, one would need a very large mold &amp; it would
not be certain that the <m>metal</m> would run sufficiently. Thus, when
you want to mold them, choose the medium-sized ones &amp; make the pose
<del>qu</del> so that they have their wings half folded. Because in this
way they will come out better, but support the side of the wings with
<m>wax</m>, as you know, to feed the cast well.</ab>

</div>
</root>
