<root>
<page>106r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f217.image</image>

<div>
<id>p106r_1</id>
<head>For casting</head>

<ab><m>Asphaltum <del>is</del>, which is found in <pl>Germany</pl></m>,
is the most excellent sand one can find for molding in a <tl>frame</tl>,
because it is appropriate for <m>silver</m> &amp; for <m>gold</m>, &amp;
the more you use it and the older it is, the better it is. One molds in
it very thinly &amp; finely.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p106r_2</id>
<head><add>Making <m>gold</m> run</add> for casting</head>

<ab>Because <m>gold</m> cools down very quickly, one ought to give it a
mix when <del>melted <fr>q</fr></del> it is well melted which maintains
the heat. <m>Sublimate</m> softens it nicely. But, because it goes up in
smoke, it does not continue to help. Therefore mix this composition when
you want to cast: <m>sal ammoniac</m>, the best <m><fr>verdet</fr></m>
that you can find, a little <m>borax</m> &amp; <m>saltpeter</m>
<del><add><fr>qui li</fr></add></del>. And this, by keeping it warm, it
will come out neatly. <add><m>Saltpeter</m> clarifies it &amp;
<del><fr>p</fr></del> heats it. But the most important thing in this
mixture is the <m><fr>verdet</fr></m>, which has to be good. This
mixture softens the <m>gold</m> <del><fr>qui</fr></del> so much that it
becomes treatable like <m>lead</m>, even <m>fine gold</m>.</add></ab>

<ab>For sand for molding flowers &amp; leaves &amp; delicate things, mix
in <m>well-ground raw plaster</m>, <m>brick</m> &amp; <m><fr>alum de
plume</fr></m>.</ab>

<ab>To moisten sands, <m>eau-de-vie</m> is excellent, for it
grinds the sand finely &amp; evaporates <del><fr>que</fr></del> when one
reheats the <tl>frames</tl>.</ab>

<ab><m>Sal ammoniac water</m> is very good, is excellent for moistening
sands, but for lots of <m>water</m> one only needs a little <m>sal
ammoniac</m>.</ab>

<ab>A loop<comment>c_106r_02</comment> of <m>iron</m>, for lack of <m><la>crocum ferri</la></m>, is
<del><fr>exce</fr></del> good for <m>gold</m>.</ab>

<ab>The <al>snakes</al> or <al>lizards</al> you want to mold should not
be kept for a <tmp>long time</tmp>, for if they are alive, they get
thin, and if they are <del>dry <fr>il</fr></del> dead, they wither.</ab>

<ab><m>Plaster of <pl>Paris</pl></m> is as firm as <m>stone</m> &amp;
very good. When you will want to choose some for your sand, take it raw,
the hardest possible &amp; which does not make any powder. The
transparent one and the one that thus makes powder retracts,
<del><fr>Ce</fr></del> which is not good for this work. A sign of the
one that is close to perfection is that it is hard &amp; made of
lustrous grains nearing the shape of <m>sugar</m>. Finally, to mix some
into the sand to cast <m>gold</m>, it is necessary that it endures the
fire twice, &amp; is reheated twice.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<mark>+</mark> When <m>gold</m> is very fine, it is so dry that it
can hardly endure a <tl>hammer</tl>, but this mixture softens it like
<m>lead</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
