<root>
<page>068v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f142.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p068r_3</id>

<ab>and immediately you will be able to crumble it between your
<tl><bp>fingers</bp></tl> and to easily pestle it in a <tl><m>metal</m>
mortar</tl>, or better yet, in an <tl><m>iron</m> one</tl>. Next, it
will be easy to grind it, not <del>only</del> on <m>common
<tl>marble</tl></m> <add>that would corrode</add>, but on
<tl><m>porphyry</m></tl>, and it is necessary that it be finely ground
with <add><m>water</m></add> so that when putting it on your
<tl><bp>fingernail</bp></tl>, you find it soft without any asperity like
the colors that the <pro>painters</pro> grind for <m>oil</m>. You can
use <del><fr>au lii</fr></del> this one, once dry, in a <tl>frame</tl> instead
of sand, without moistening it with anything nor reheating it. If you do
not like it, fumigate the cavity with <m>sulfur</m> smoke or <del><fr>de
p</fr></del> with the tip of the flame of a <tl><m>wax candle</m></tl>
that barely makes smoke, and it will make a very neat &amp; shiny &amp;
polished work, in <m><add>pure</add> lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m>. I would
say the same for <m>finely pulverized tripoly</m> that does not want to
be <del>not</del> reheated or moistened. <m>Burnt linen</m> gives less
trouble than others, because it does not need to be reheated, nor
moistened, &amp; molds <add>and releases</add> very neatly <del>&amp;
very</del>, subtlety <del>&amp; releases well</del> neat, like the
previous ones &amp; withstands several castings. First you ought to burn
it with a flame, then leave it to rest &amp; to be consumed with its
fire until it is completely dead, then finely grind it on
<tl><m>marble</m></tl> or on a <tl><m>paper</m></tl>. <del>But because a
lot</del> And if you reheat it in a <tl>crucible</tl>, red hot due to
the fire, to render all of it fine &amp; impalpable, I believe it will
be even better. But because a lot of <m>linen</m> is reduced to very
little when burned, if you want to save some, you can sprinkle only the
medal that you want to mold &amp; cover it, and fill the <tl>frame</tl> with <m><tl>pestled</tl> slate</m>, which molds also very neatly, but
note that the first cast is always the most beautiful &amp; the neatest.
If you cast at your convenience <m>soft tin</m> that seems to be
burnished in little wheels that <pro>pewterers</pro> sell, comes out
very neatly &amp; approaching the color of <m>silver</m>, without mixing
in anything else, it is true that one ought to cast it rather hot, &amp;
so that the molded object should be four <ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> away
from the cast. In order to know its heat, first melt it well, <add>so
hot</add> <del>with such a <ms>degree of heat</ms></del> that it
promptly burns a <tl><m>paper</m></tl> or <tl><m>straw</m></tl> placed
inside, by simmering. Then remove it from the fire &amp; leave it to
rest a little &amp; cast the <m>tin</m> mixed

</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
