<root>
<page>139v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f284.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p139r_1</id>

<ab> either of earth or <m>blades of copper</m>, or <m>iron</m>, or
<m>wood</m> covered with <m>white iron</m>, to bury more easily these
aforementioned molds between the thin sheets of <m>copper</m>, and the
stirrup or screw of <m>iron</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p139v_1</id>
<head>Cast of <m>wax</m> to represent an animal that one has not
got</head>

<ab>Take some <m>white wax</m> which is more appropriate for this work
than anything else, because it is firmer &amp; does not leave as much
filth, as much as you need to mold the animal that you propose, &amp; no
more, and half as much charcoal, pestled &amp; finely passed through a
linen or a sleeve. The charcoal gives color and body to the wax, which
would otherwise be transparent &amp; the features would not be seen as
well. Therefore, put your <m>wax</m> to melt in the fire or charcoal.
And as it is well melted &amp; liquid, have, for a bowl with handles
full of melted wax, as much <m>sulphur</m> <del>la</del> as a large
walnut. Pulverize it, melt it over a slow fire &amp; when it is melted,
do not leave it on the fire because it will become too hard, but take it
away, &amp; always agitate it with a little stick &amp; let it finish
its bubbling &amp; as it is liquid as water, throw it in the <m>wax</m>
that you have removed from the fire. And mix &amp; always stir the one
&amp; the other, in order that they mix well. Next, mix in, always
stirring &amp; in several goes, the above said pulverized charcoal
<corr><del>in several goes</del></corr>. And as it will be well
incorporated, take heed if your wax has passed its high heat, which you
will recognize when it no longer smokes, when, pulling at the edges, it
makes large tracts <del><add>se</add></del> <del>re</del>,&amp;
unmoving, &amp; close <del>de</del> one to another. For, if you were to
cast too hot, you could not separate your wax from the mold, &amp; it
would set in the cast. When it is in this good state, stir it with a
little stick, in order that the pulverized charcoal is everywhere &amp;
not placed at the bottom. And in this way, cast in your mold, little by
little, &amp; not in one go, because the wax, by its unctuousness, does
not flow<cont/></ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
This black sulphured <m>wax</m> is for modelling round figures that are
not for releasing, and that one needs to burn in the mold <fr>à
noyau</fr> before opening it, <del>po</del> like those which have arms
&amp; legs out front or entwined. And then this wax, by means of
sulphur, melts with very little heat, and exits without leaving any
filth. If, by chance, the pestled charcoal remains there as ash, by
opening the mold &amp; blowing inside, it stays neat.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
@To make snakes with wax, or another thing to fix on a candle, one needs
to cast with modelling wax, in all colors.</ab>

</div>
</root>
