<root>
<page>050v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f106.image</image>

<div>

<id>p050v_1</id>

<head><al>Small birds</al></head>

<ab><al><fr>Benarris</fr></al> sing <tmp>at night</tmp> if they are left
<env>in <fr>serain</fr></env>, but they are better for fattening for
fine tables than for singing. <al>Chaffinches</al> are prone to becoming
blind, &amp; their eyes become swollen at the <tmp>beginning of
August</tmp>. <al>Goldfinches</al> like <pa>lettuce</pa> seeds very
much, &amp; often one catches them in <env>gardens</env> on seeded
<pa>lettuces</pa> with two <tl>lime-twigs</tl>. But because such regular
fare would be too expensive for them, they are ordinarily fed with
<pa>hemp</pa> seed. The <al><fr>passe solitaire</fr></al><comment>c_050v_01</comment> is purged
with a <m><al>spider</al></m>, which one needs to give to it
<ms><tmp>once a week</tmp></ms> in order that no
<fr>gaillardisse</fr> comes to it. The <al>calandra</al> is purged with <m>dry
mortar</m>, composed of <m>lime</m> &amp; sand to keep it from
<fr>gaillardise</fr> &amp; fattening too much. <al>Young small
birds</al> are purged with the same <m>dry mortar</m>, by putting some
pieces in their <tl>cages</tl>. The <al>cuckoo</al> lays in the nest of
<al><fr>benarris</fr></al> otherwise called <al><fr>verdaule</fr></al>.
This <al>bird</al> is very simple. I have heretofore given leave to two,
which <tmp>after several days</tmp> returned to their cage. For feeding
young <al>goldfinches</al>, one needs to <tl>pestle</tl>
<m><pa>almonds</pa></m> with <del><m>pith</m></del> a very little amount
of <m><add>bread pith</add></m> and <m>l<pa>ettuce</pa> seed</m> or
<m><pa>hemp</pa> seed</m>. If it is for <al>linnet</al>, some
<m><pa>rapeseed</pa></m>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p050v_2</id>

<head>Curried <m>steel</m> and <tl>files</tl></head>

<ab>The <m>steel</m> that <pro>blacksmiths</pro> &amp; <pro><m>iron</m>
workers</pro> commonly use is not refined like that from
<pl>Germany</pl> or <pl>Biscay</pl>, which is reduced in hardness
<del><fr>p</fr></del> in a bath of a <m>molten iron</m>, but
<del>only</del> among the <m>iron bars</m> which are transported in flat
ingots from the <env>forges of <pl>Foix</pl></env> &amp; elsewhere,
there is a harder &amp; whiter &amp; finer kind than the other, as it
comes from the <env>mine</env>. And the <pro>workers</pro> choose it
&amp; use it like the other <m>steel</m>. And because it comes from
<m>common iron</m>, they call it <m>strong iron</m>. But it is not as
excellent as <m>purified steel</m> like that from <pl>Germany</pl> &amp;
<pl>Biscaye</pl>, which is sold in <ms>small beads</ms>. Some curry
<m>steel</m>, giving it a heating, then temper it <del>&amp;
<m>water</m></del> in a large quantity of <m>water</m>, then forge it.
&amp; <m>fine steel</m>, which is brittle, breaks, and crumbles, &amp;
<m>iron</m> allows itself to be stretched. Thus they separate <m>the
finest steel</m> <del>&amp;</del>, which with another heating they
reduce to a mass. The <pl>Germans</pl> make their <tl>files</tl> from
<m>strong iron</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>One applies <m>steel</m> to tools
<del><fr>dess</fr></del> not on both sides, but underneath the part
where one sharpens &amp; whets them. &amp; in this part, they must be of
<m>very <fr>doulx</fr> iron</m>.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><pl>Levantines</pl> refine our
<m>steel</m> because their country does not provide them with any. And
they reheat it in a <tl>pot</tl> with <m>bitumen</m>, &amp;c.</ab></div>
</root>
