<root>
<page>122r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f249.item.r=</image>

<div>

<id>p122r_1</id>

<head>Arranging various animals</head>

<ab>When you discover some <al>lizards</al>, writhing while biting each
other <del>&amp;</del>, which is the most difficult thing to mold,
because of the number of feet &amp; because of the tip of their tails
which are very fine, <del><fr>Il</fr></del> take heed that should
<del><fr>trou</fr></del> some part be uncovered, that remains as if
suspended in mid air, to steady it, in order that the second cast, which
you will do on top for the second half, will not vary. And to steady it
over the void, take a little <m>wax</m>, &amp; rub it &amp; lay it on a
<tl>table</tl>, shaped like a <tl>thick needle</tl>, then cut that which
you will need, &amp; with the <tl>tip of a hot <m>iron wire</m></tl>
join it where it will be necessary. Steady also on the <del><tl>frame</tl></del> <add><tl>mold</tl></add> all that will
have detached from it (when you uncover the half of the belly) with
some <m>wax</m>, taken lightly with the <tl>point of a pen-knife</tl>,
&amp; joined &amp; melted with the <tl><m>iron wire</m></tl>. And when
you will make your cast, one ought only to bring the wax to there &amp;
the edge of the <m>wax</m> joined to the animal, &amp; which, while
melting, will continue the casting up to the animal, without spoiling
anything, which is a secret.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p122r_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5TVo3Y3lKWjA0dXM</link>

</figure>

<ab>One can arrange <al>snakes</al> bound together in embraces of love,
but that is only when they are small.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p122r_2</id>

<head>Flower in the mouth of the <al>snake</al></head>

<ab>If you want to put in the mouth of the <al>snake</al> some flower
<del><fr>q</fr></del> or some branch of a plant which contains the
<md>antidote</md> against its bite, take a little branch, as best
arranged as you can find, &amp; pose its stem into its mouth. Then put
two little pieces of <m>wax</m> around the stem of the plant. And with
the <tl>end of a <m><del>iron</del> wire</m>, that is hot</tl>, melt the
<m>wax</m> a little, &amp; with the other <tl><bp>hand</bp></tl>, close
the jaws of the animal. And then you can cut the head to make it burn
with the flower. If the plant <del><fr>s</fr></del> is strong enough, it
will hold up by itself, and should it be weak like <pa>wormwood</pa>
leaf, which droops, the dampness of the sand will lift it up, &amp; make
it swim &amp; hold up without putting anything there, although you could
pass underneath it some <tl>thread</tl>, going through with a
<tl>needle</tl>.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p122r_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5ZDJlZ0g5OXNKeDQ</link>

</figure>

<del>

<figure>

<id>fig_p122r_3</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5UDgyYnNSZnlndjg</link>

</figure>

</del>

<del>

<figure>

<id>fig_p122r_4</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5elo4VzJZRUppOWc</link>

</figure>

</del>

</div>
</root>
