<root>
<page>037v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f80.image</image>

<div>

<id>p037v_1</id>

<head><pro>Gardener</pro></head>

<ab>

For sowing <pa>melons</pa> well, one needs it to be the <tmp>end of a
moon cycle</tmp> for otherwise they would bud too many leaves &amp;
not bear enough fruit. Make small <del><fr>e</fr></del> holes, <ms>two
<bp>fingers</bp> by two <bp>fingers</bp></ms>, with a <tl>pickaxe</tl>
&amp; put in each two or three <m>seeds</m>. Next, take <m>very fine
earth</m> &amp; fill the depressions lightly with it. Next, spread over
all to the <ms>thickness of a <bp>thumb</bp></ms> <oc>havets</oc>, that
is to say <pa>wheat</pa> <del><fr>fl</fr></del> chaff, in order that the
coming rain does not beat the earth &amp; prevent their birth.
<add><oc>Havets</oc> attract <al>field mice</al> who eat the seeds. And
for avoiding this, one must moisten them with <del><fr>s</fr></del> a
<m>decoction of <pa>wormwood</pa></m>.</add>

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p037v_2</id>

<head><pro>Glassworker</pro></head>

<ab>

Some do not saturate the <m>glass</m> with <m><fr>gris
d'escaille</fr></m> for working as primer, but trace on the <m>clean
glass</m> with <m>noir à huile</m>. But it is very necessary that the
<m>wood</m> be rid of <m>grease</m>, because if it has even a bit of
<m>grease</m>, the color will not take on it at all. And further, if the
<pro>glassworker</pro> who is working has a <sn>stench</sn> from his
<bp>nose</bp> or his <bp>mouth</bp> <del><fr>la</fr></del>, &amp; he
<bp>breathes</bp> on the <m>glass</m>, the color will not take on it.
Those who discovered the invention of working in small works of supple
<m>enamels</m> use only <m><fr>esmail d'azur</fr></m>, which is blue,
&amp; <m><fr>esmail colombin</fr></m>, which is the color of purple,
which they make supple with <m>rock pieces</m> or <m>leaded glass</m>.
As for the yellow, they make it from <m>silver</m>, the red from
<m>sanguine</m>, as is said elsewhere, the black &amp; gray &amp;
shadows with the <m><fr>noir d'escaille</fr></m>, either strong or weak,
the carnation with the <m>light sanguine</m>. The green is made first
from yellow, then on top they coat <m><fr>esmail d'azur</fr></m>, either
strong or weak, according to whether they want to make it bright or
dark.

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p037v_3</id>

<head><m>Yellow Amber</m></head>

<ab>

It is cut with a <tl>file</tl>, then one passes a certain <m>pulverized
salt</m> across the surface, which an <pl>Englishman</pl> called
<df><fr>desramonet</fr></df>. But I believe that this was <m>pulverized
pumice stone</m>, for it had the harshness of <m>arène</m>. And with a
taut <tl>cord</tl>, he polished his <m>amber</m>, then passed
<tl><m>tripoli from <pl>Bretagne</pl></m></tl> on it with the
<tl><bp>finger</bp></tl>; others used a piece of <tl><m>leather</m></tl>
or a <tl>cane</tl>. <m>Amber</m> loses its color if an unhealthy person
wears it, &amp; becomes whitish. But to restore it, it needs to be
soaked for one <ms><tmp>night</tmp></ms> in <m><bp>urine</bp></m>, then boiled a
little in it.

</ab>

</div>
</root>
