<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="127v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f260.image">



<div></div>

<div id="p127v_1" categories="casting">

<head><m><pro>Founders</pro>’ earth</m></head>

<ab>It is <m><fr>terre bolvene</fr></m> mixed with <m>dung</m> or
<m>cloth waste</m>, which withstands fire, which you need to always have
provision of to <m><tl>lute</tl></m> your <tl>molds</tl> that <del>have
<fr>b</fr></del> are meant to serve for casting <m>silver</m> &amp; that one needs to
reheat. Those where one needs to burn some flower or animal should not
be <m><tl>luted</tl></m> until they have been reheated once, and they have been cleaned
of <m>bones</m> &amp; <m>ashes</m> remaining inside, and, having removed 
the <tl>clamps</tl>, you have opened the two halves to see if
they are cracked. For there is <m>plaster </m>that is not so
hard in the fire, one as the other. Moreover, there is some
which makes crusty the things which stay burning inside. And these are
imperfections that one needs to avoid, either <del>by</del> by bathing
well with <m>eau-de-vie</m> the animal before casting in the <m>tempered sand</m>,
or mixing in more or less <m>brick</m> or <m>alum</m>, or reheating the
<m>brick</m> more, or in place of the <m>brick</m>, mixing in
<m><tl><oc>crucible</oc></tl> bottoms</m> &amp; similar things which resist well
in the fire. Having therefore reheated your <tl>mold</tl> to burn it
inside, leave to cool well. And if it is neat &amp; not cracked, put
the <tl>clamps</tl> back &amp; <m><tl>lute</tl></m> it with this <m>aforesaid
<pro>founders</pro>’ earth</m> &amp; sprinkle a little <m>sifted ash</m>
&amp; let dry a little. But keep yourself from <m>luting</m> <del>that they are
not</del> until the <tl>molds</tl> are cold. Those for casting
<m>silver</m>, where there is nothing to burn inside, only need, except
when the gate &amp; vents are made, <m>luting</m> &amp; reheating once. Do not
<m><tl>lute</tl></m> the end of the <tl>mold</tl> where you want to make your gate,
but leave it uncovered &amp; the exit of the vent as well. </ab>

<ab><add>If</add> <emph>the <tl>molds</tl></emph> <del>that</del> were
<del><fr>do</fr></del> <add>to</add> crack, it <add>is</add> <del>made thus</del> at the
first reheating, for at the second, they no longer crack.</ab>

<ab><emph>The smallest</emph> <tl>molds</tl> are reheated more quickly.
Take <del>them</del> therefore, the first reheated ones when you cast, for
you can put several of them to reheat.</ab>

<ab>Light the charcoals first, in the <tl>forge</tl> or in some other
place nearby, &amp; having placed your <tl>molds</tl> on a layer of good
embers, not burning too much, to have a slow fire at the beginning, put
there &amp; adjust a little the half-lit charcoals in the
<tl>forge</tl>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

The <m>earth that <pro>locksmiths</pro> use to braze or solder</m>, which
is <m>sandy clay earth</m>, or else <m>clay</m> mixed with <m>sand</m>, after
having dried &amp; <tl>sieved</tl> &amp; then composed it, is good for
<m>luting</m> your <tl>molds</tl> because this <m>earth</m> melts rather than
cracks. And any <m>earth</m> that melts <del>is</del> cannot be lacking
in this.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<add><tl><m>Iron wire</m></tl> to<lb/>
give it bond.</add></ab>

<figure id="fig_p127v_1" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5S2VzRmhYUWpfbmc">
</figure>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<add><m><tl>Lute</tl></m> thickly your <tl>molds</tl>, &amp; if they are small, you can
reheat them immediately in a good fire, especially those of
<m><la>crocum</la></m>.</add></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

If the <m>earth</m> is good, &amp; <del><fr>l</fr></del> does not crack
while reheating, &amp; does not separate from the <tl>mold</tl>, the
<tl>molds</tl> will also not crack &amp; will not make flashing at the
casting. Reheat with slow ease in a closed fire, &amp; do not expose them
hot<comment rid="c_127v_02"/> to the air.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<m><tl>Lute</tl></m> rather thickly in two or three layers, especially right in the
joints, in order that the <m>silver</m> does not come out of the
<tl>mold</tl>. </ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

Reheat in a <tl>reverberatory furnace</tl>.
<hr/></ab>


<ab margin="left-middle">

To test if your <m>earth</m> is good, before putting it on your
<tl>mold</tl>, <m><tl>lute</tl></m> <add>at</add> the place of the <del><fr>fo</fr></del> wall of
the <tl>forge</tl> which is around the <tl>blast-pipe</tl> &amp;
barrel of the <tl>bellows</tl>, &amp; light the fire, &amp; if it withstands
this without cracking, it will be good.</ab>

</div>
</root>
