<root>
<page>071v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f148.image</image>

<div>

<id>p071v_1</id>

<head><m>Varnish</m></head>

<ab>To a <ms>half lb</ms> of <m><pa>spike lavender</pa> oil</m>, put in
4 <ms>℥</ms> of <m>sandarac</m> &amp; <m>mastic,
pulverized subtly</m> . And first, boil your <m>oil</m> in a
<tl>pot</tl> on a <tl>chafing dish</tl>, and then mix in little <add>by
little</add> the aforesaid <m>gums</m>, stirring continually with a
<tl>small stick split and quartered at the tip</tl>, &amp; when you do
not collect <m>gum</m> with the tip, that is to say that it is totally
melted &amp; that your <m>varnish</m> is done. And to render it clearer,
put into the concoction a little lump of <m>camphor</m>. It is true that
with this it is not dry so soon. Heed well that the <m><pa>spike
lavender</pa> oil</m> will be good, clear &amp; not fatty, otherwise
your <m>varnish</m> will be worth nothing. You can test it
<del><fr>d</fr></del> by soaking some <m>paper</m> in it &amp; heating
it. If the <m>oil</m>, which will evaporate, leaves the <m>paper</m>
clean, without <del>being</del> a yellow mark, it is good, if not, it is
fatty.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p071v_2</id>

<head><al>Sheep</al> fat</head>

<ab>In a certain region of <pl>England</pl>, the <al>sheep</al> that
graze there have very yellow fat and are nevertheless just as good as
others.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p071v_3</id>

<head><al>Spider</al></head>

<ab>In <pl>Ireland</pl>, one finds none there, &amp; if one touches them
with <tl><m>wood</m></tl> that is there, they die. This is why some of
the <pro>rich</pro> from <pl>England</pl> make their ceilings from this
<m>wood</m>, &amp; by this method, they never have cobwebs
&amp; spiderwebs.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p071v_4</id>

<head>Sand</head>

<ab>The <m><fr>cimolée</fr></m> is very good for casting in
<m>copper</m>, but one ought not take <m>the one from
<pro>cutlers</pro></m>, because it is only <m>sludge</m>, but rather the
one of those who <del><fr>moulent</fr></del> mold large shears.</ab>

<ab><m>Pierres de filieres</m>, which <pro>knife grinders</pro> use for
whetting, mold very neatly, once scraped, for <m>lead</m>. It is
commonly <m>slate</m>-colored. One frequently brings them to
<pl>Toulouse</pl> from around <pl>Carcassonne</pl> .</ab>

</div>
</root>
