<root>
<page>110v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f226.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p110r_3</id>

<ab>When it has eaten something, by tormenting it, it will render it.
And if, after having eaten something, it is thus pressed
<tl><bp>underfoot</bp></tl>, this pains it a lot &amp; hurts it. If it
is wounded, it will not eat willingly.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p110v_1</id>
<head><tl>Molds</tl></head>

<ab>There is nothing better for opening them up than to anoint them with
<m><pa>olive</pa> oil</m>, &amp; nothing else. And next, when you
want to unjoin them, soak them in <m>cold water</m>, which is the
secret. <del><fr>L</fr></del><add>E</add> And you will see that the
<m>oil</m> although it seems to be imbued, will detach itself, like
grease. <tl>Molds</tl> become stronger in <m>cold water</m>. And <m>hot
water</m> would dissolve them awkwardly, although once reheated, they
are more handleable &amp; easier to dissolve in the
<m>water</m>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p110v_2</id>

<head><m><pa>Wheat</pa> oil</m></head>

<ab>Is made on a <tl>blade of <m>iron</m> reddened in the fire</tl>. And
the <m>oil</m> drips off, which is appropriate for anointing the hair of
a <al>butterfly</al> or similar thing, for this <m>oil</m> is instantly
dry &amp; makes the remainder dry out. It is necessary that the hair or
down of any animal that you want to mold be flat, for it were upright it
would elevate the sand &amp; become porous.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><mark>#</mark> If you want to mold
something delicate, like a <pa>pansy</pa>, some, to give it a little
thickness, more than what is natural, rub it with <m>butter</m>. But it
is best to anoint it with <m><pa>wheat</pa> oil</m> for it has no body
&amp; does not obstruct the small lineaments as much, and makes the
flower firm.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p110v_3</id>

<head>Cast of <m>lead</m> and <m>tin</m></head>

<ab>Because <m>tin</m> wants to be cast very thinly, if your medal,
plant or other thing for molding is <del><fr>espe</fr></del> thin &amp;
fine, do it so that there is more <m>tin</m>, much more than
<m>lead</m>, namely less than the <ms>fourth part <m>lead</m> for three
parts <m>tin</m></ms>. And still, one puts <m>lead</m> only to form an
alloy. On the contrary, if you want to mold something strong &amp;
thick, put a lot more <m>lead</m> in than <m>tin</m>. And in one &amp;
the other you can put a little <m>looking-glass tin</m>, but only a
little, with a little <m>resin</m>, when you want to cast. <add>Since
then, when molding with <m>fine and new lead</m>, I put into one
<ms>lb</ms> two <ms>ounces</ms> of <m>fine tin</m>. And when molding
with <m>fine tin</m>, I put in two <ms>ounces</ms> of <m>fine lead</m>
for one <ms>pound</ms>. I made plants &amp; <al>snakes</al> just like
nature.</add></ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin><del><fr>S<ill/></fr></del></ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>

I cast <m>tin</m> almost red, and <m>lead</m> the same, which however
had not remained in the fire for too long, for it becomes brittle and
calcines.</ab>

</div>
</root>
