<root>
<page>003v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f12.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p003r_3</id>

<ab>instead of <m>fine turpentine</m>. And you can put into two
<ms>lbs</ms> of <del>tou</del><m>common turpentine</m> one <ms>lb</ms>
of <m>fine turpentine oil</m> &amp; do as with the other one. This one
will cost you no more than five or six <cn><fr>sols</fr></cn> per
<ms>lb</ms> &amp; is sold for 40 <cn><fr>sols</fr></cn> per
<ms>lb</ms>.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p003v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5ZUY4SkZBblA5MjA</link>

</figure>

<ab>This <tl>vessel</tl> is used to make large quantities of
<m>turpentine oil</m>, that is to say a <ms><ms>bucket</ms> an
<tmp>hour</tmp></ms>, and no matter which <m>turpentine it may be,
whether fine or crude</m>. One needs to give, as you know, a little
fire at the beginning. And always keep <m>cold water</m> in the cooler
on the top. The <ms>lb</ms> is sold at xii <cn><fr>sols</fr></cn>, &amp;
at the bottom of the <tl>vessel</tl> remains the <m>colophony</m>, known
as <m><la>pix graeca</la></m>. In this <tl>vessel</tl>, <m>eau-de-vie</m> is also made well and there is no need to distill it again. You
do not need a <tl>oven</tl> for this <tl><m>copper</m> vessel</tl>, but
only <m>charcoal</m> around it if it has a flat bottom, but if it is
round, you will place it on a <tl>trivet</tl>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
@ It is better to heat the <m>varnish</m> a little bit, rather than to
put it out <env>in the sun</env>, because this makes the panel
warp.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
@ Some say it is not good to distil in this <tl><m>copper</m>
vessel</tl> because it is made green. However, when <m>tinned</m>, it is
good.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p003v_1</id>
<head>For varnishing</head>

<ab><m>Turpentine varnish</m> does not need any <m>glue</m> because it
is fat and viscous and it is not absorbed in the <m>wood</m> like that
of <m>spike lavender</m> and <m>sandarac</m>. Also, that of <m>spike
lavender</m> does not require any <m>glue</m> on <m>iron</m> &amp;
similar materials that do not absorb, but on <m>wood</m> and on colors
which <del>have</del> <add>do not have</add> <m>gum</m> or <m><fr>colle
de destrempe</fr></m>, it is necessary to lay one coat of the said
<m><fr>colle de retailles</fr></m> &amp; to let it dry &amp; to
varnish.</ab>

</div>
</root>
