<root>
<page>064v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f134.image</image>

<div>

<id>p064v_1</id>

<head>Apprenticeship of the <pro>painter</pro></head>

<ab>First, one gives him an <m>egg</m> to do in which one has him make
half a face, then a whole one with the ears, next the neck, then the
parts of the body separately, next joined, then one figure, then two
&amp; three, finally a history, teaching him how to hold the
<m>charcoal</m> by the end, &amp; also the <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl>.
Once he knows how to draw, one teaches him how to layer colors.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p064v_2</id>

<head>One also presents him with these strokes &amp; lines</head>

<ab><del><fr>C</fr></del> <add>T</add>he figure of the <m>egg</m> is the
main pattern for faces <add>and for bent bodies</add>, as the cross is
the model for a straight &amp; whole figure<comment>c_064v_01</comment>.
Without these strokes you will never do well.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p064v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NmZDTmZwc1Jqb2M</link>

</figure>

</div>

<div>

<id>p064v_3</id>

<head>Softening</head>

<ab>To soften well, one ought not to layer the colors thickly, but
rather layer them twice, except for <m><fr>azur d’esmail</fr></m>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

All colors that have no body in <m>oil</m> have none in
<m>distemper</m>, <del>and</del> but in <m>distemper</m> they sink to
the bottom. <m>Distemper</m> colors want to be greasy, which is
recognized when they gel on the <tl>palette</tl> once distempered in
<m>oil</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p064v_4</id>

<head>Straight lines</head>

<ab>You can use the <tl>ruler</tl>, but do not lay it flat on the panel,
but as if lifted off, &amp; resting on the edges of the panel. Otherwise
you would smudge everything, &amp; also you would not see the stroke
well.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p064v_5</id>

<head><m>Distemper</m></head>

<ab><m>Distemper</m> colors need to be <add>kept</add> darker
<del><fr>pr</fr></del> while you temper them, <add>because they whiten
while drying</add>. But <m>oil</m> colors remain the same in color.</ab>

</div>
</root>
