<root>
<page>151v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f308.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p150v_1</id>

<ab>however, do not remove it until you have completely repaired the
<al>turtle</al>, for you will use this <m>earth</m> as <m>cement</m>, if
you need to embed something or repair with the <tl>small chisel</tl>. If
there is some flashing at the joints of the <tl>mold</tl>, you will remove
it, either with the <tl>burin</tl>, called a
<df><tl><fr>chaple</fr></tl></df>, or a <tl>very sharp pen-knife</tl>,
or with a <tl>small file</tl>, &amp; then with the <tl>small
chisel</tl>, always having the natural thing, to do this better, in
front of you. You can curl on a <tl>file</tl> the point of a <tl>small
chisel</tl>, which is not quenched, to make something lumpy. For these
<del>two</del> <al>turtles</al> &amp; other hollow things, that
presuppose being large enough, cast your alloy of <ms>half</ms>
<m>lead</m> &amp; <ms>half</ms> <m>fine tin</m>. There is more work in
molding a <al>turtle</al> than for twelve <tl>molds</tl> of flowers. If
there is some <m><la>crocum</la></m> in your sand, there will not be
flashing &amp; if, by some chance, there is some on the sides, it will be
thinner than <m>paper</m>, as long as your <tl>mold</tl> is tightened
well with a <tl>press</tl>. And to make the scales of <al>turtles</al>
or other animals, you can make some <tl>little small chisels</tl>, in
the fashion of a <tl>round cutting-punch</tl>, others in the fashion of a
<tl>gouge</tl>, or the scale of a <al>snake</al> &amp; <al>lizard</al>,
and others on a <tl>file</tl> to make the curly &amp; lumpy bits. The
<al>turtles</al>, which are not molded hollow, do not have as much work,
for they are molded in two pieces to repair them, with <tl>small
chisels</tl>, <tl>small cutting-punches</tl>, <tl>small gouges</tl>
&amp; <tl>small serrated chisels</tl>.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p151v_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bk1US2QxRTVwa2s</link>

</figure>

</div>

<div>

<id>p151v_1</id>

<head><m><pa>Wheat</pa> oil</m></head>

<ab>One needs to make it between two quite <tl>sparkling hot <m>iron
plates</m></tl>, especially the lower one, which will be sloping, on
which you will put some <m><pa>wheat</pa></m>, quite even &amp; uniform.
And then you will place the other, all red, on top, &amp; you will press
it until you see the <m>black oil</m> drip well. Reiterate that until
you have enough of it. This <m>oil</m> dries immediately. It gives gold
color to <m>silvered</m> &amp; burnished things, augments the color of
<m>gilded</m> things, serves as a <m>varnish</m> on <m>iron</m> for
etching on it afterwards, for <m>varnishing</m> sword guards tawny. And could
also serve <pro>makers of <m>gilded leather</m></pro> well.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>One needs to use it when it is newly
made. And for things to be molded, it must not be as thick as for
coloring.

</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>It is not for anointing hairy animals,
for it is too strong &amp; rigid, but it is good to give form to the
legs of a small animal, like a <al>fly</al> &amp; suchlike. It is also
excellent for coloring <m>white false stones</m>.</ab></div>
</root>
