<root>
<page>062v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f130.item</image>

<div>

<id>p062v_1</id>

<head>Drawing</head>

<ab>To become an <pro>artist</pro>, one needs to draw by
<tl><bp>eye</bp></tl>, without <tl>compass</tl> or <tl>ruler</tl>.
<pro>Masters</pro> do not allow <pro>apprentices</pro> to do this.</ab>

<ab>When the priming has been <tmp>long</tmp> done, it becomes greasy.
One needs to rub it with <m>ash</m> &amp; <m>water</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p062v_2</id>

<head>Perspective</head>

<ab>To know the point, one needs to lay down a <tl>ruler</tl> over the
lines, &amp; at the intersection of these the point will
be<comment>c_062v_01</comment>. Some make a hole at the end of their
<tl>rulers</tl> to fix the point by that hole &amp; move the
<tl>ruler</tl> about. Others lay down a <tl>ruler</tl> across the panel,
then on this laid-down <tl>ruler</tl> they set the <tl>tip of another
ruler</tl>, which, attached to the former by means of a <tl>screw</tl>,
moves about &amp; reaches as far as necessary without losing the point.
The <tl>ruler</tl> and <tl>compass</tl> without the <tl>judgement of the
<bp>eye</bp></tl> cause errors. Perspective is very difficult.

<figure>

<id>fig_p062v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5ZkRNOG9hZmpMT2M</link>

</figure></ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

To paint perspective in <m>oil</m>, you ought not to use a
<tl>ruler</tl>, for you would smudge everything. But when layering your
colors you need to keep to <del>the</del> &amp; follow the lines of your
first drawing.</ab>

<ab>Also, to make <tl><m>plumb</m> lines</tl>, which go from the top
<del>to make</del> <del><fr>vif</fr></del> to the bottom of the panel,
you need to have a <tl><m>thread</m></tl> with some piece of <m>lead</m>
attached to one end &amp; a little <tl>hook</tl> to the other for
hanging the said <tl><m>thread</m></tl> from the top of the panel.

<figure>

<id>fig_p062v_2</id>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5X0hKa0FueWdjMFk</link>

</figure>

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p062v_3</id>

<head>Panel</head>

<ab>To draw &amp; to layer the colors, especially in <m>oil</m>, it is necessary that you
hold your panel as upright as you can on the <tl>easel</tl>, for if
it is slanted there is a danger that some dust &amp; dirt might stick on
it. Keep clean &amp; without dust the place where you paint.</ab>

</div>
</root>
