<root>
<page>155r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f315.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p155r_1</id>
<head>Molding a <pa>rose</pa></head>

<ab>Because the little branches <add>of the <pa>rose bush</pa></add>
which are <del><fr>aupart</fr></del> around the flower are sometimes
very spread out &amp; would make too large a <tl>mold</tl>, one makes
<add>and molds</add> them separately, and the <pa>rose</pa> &amp; some
buds separately. And then one joins them with <m>solder</m>, the little
branches &amp; leaves of the <pa>rose bush</pa> to the stem of the
<pa>rose</pa>, on which one intentionally leaves the little tips of the
small branches. Put your leaf or <pa>rose</pa> as low as you can in the
<tl>mold</tl> because the <m>sand</m> always raises it up. You
<del><fr>en</fr></del> can also mold several petals together, once
arranged one on top of the other, separating them with <tl>threads</tl>,
as is said. And regarding the <pa>rose</pa>, you can give a thin layer
of <m>melted butter</m> on the back of the petal, <del>of</del> <add>on
the first petals on the outside, not those on the inside</add>
<del><fr>be</fr></del>, to fortify it &amp; give it the strength to
withstand, <add>in order that the wet sand does not spread out &amp;
expand more than it should.</add> You <del>them</del> can also mold well
the leaves of <pa>rose bushes</pa>, <pa>strawberry plants</pa>, &amp;
similar things, that are flat &amp; can be flattened without spoiling
them, with two gates; to open your <tl>mold</tl> when it is reheated
&amp;clean the <m>ashes</m> from it, <del>All</del>, and make vents
&amp; several gates. And this is the easiest way, but the other can also
be done. And with a <m>wax</m> sprue applied &amp; joined from petal to
petal, you can make casts. You can even make a <m>wax</m> sprue from
<add>the back of</add> the first petal <del>until</del>, which will join
to the gate. All of this facilitates the cast. <del><fr>Aulcu</fr></del>
The principal thing is to let your reheated <tl>molds</tl> cool down
well, rather than cleaning them &amp; blowing inside them to make the
<m>wax</m> come out, because when the <tl>mold</tl> is hot, the ash
holds to it as if attached. But when it is cold, it wanders and leaves
with air or when one blows one's <bp>breath</bp> through the small
opening. </ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p155r_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5b3lFZ18wbGducEk</link>

</figure>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
You can give quite a little thickness at the ends of the stalks that
support the leaves, anointing them lightly underneath with <m>melted
butter</m>, because the leaves are large &amp; weighty, and the stalk of
<m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m> would not have enough strength.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
I would be of the opinion to mold the <pa>rose </pa>on its own with a
little of its stem close to its bud, &amp; then to join it to a longer
one of <m>tinned latten</m>, because the bloomed <pa>rose</pa> has great
volume &amp; weight.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>bottom</margin>
Wet the <pa>rose</pa> with <m>eau-de-vie</m> before putting it in the
<tl>circle of <m>clay</m></tl>. Do not forget to <m>oil</m> the gate
with <m>wax</m>. And when you will have cast your wet sand, blow
thoroughly, until it begins to take hold. The <pa>rose</pa> came out
well. But because the sand is found mixed among the petals, make your
work soak in <m>water</m> for a long time in order that shaking it in
the <m>water</m>, the <m>earth</m> is gone from it.</ab>

</div>
</root>
