<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="122r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f249.item.r=">




<div id="p122r_1" categories="casting">



<head>Arranging various animals</head>

<ab>When you uncover some <al>female lizards</al> entwined while biting each
other, <del>&amp;</del> which is the most difficult thing to mold
because of the number of feet &amp; because of the tip of their tails,
which are very fine, <del>One</del> take heed that if some part should
<del><fr>trou</fr></del> be uncovered that remains as if
suspended in mid air to steady it, in order that the second cast, which
you will do on top for the second half, will not vary. And to steady it
over the void, take a little <m>wax</m> &amp; rub<comment rid="c_122r_02"/> it, 
&amp; lengthen it on a <tl>table</tl> into the form of a <tl>thick needle</tl>, 
then cut that which you will need, &amp; with the <tl>tip of a hot <m>iron wire</m></tl>, 
join it where it will be necessary. Steady also on the <del><tl>frame</tl></del> <add><tl>mold</tl></add> all that will
have detached from it (when you uncover the half of the belly) with
some <m>wax</m>, taken lightly with the <tl>point of a penknife</tl>,
&amp; joined &amp; melted with the <tl><m>iron wire</m></tl>. And when
you make your gate, you ought only to bring the wax to the place &amp;
to the edge of the <m>wax</m> which, being joined to the animal &amp;
melting, will continue the gate up to the animal without spoiling
anything, which is a secret.</ab>

<figure size="small" id="fig_p122r_2" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5TVo3Y3lKWjA0dXM">
</figure>

<ab>One arranges <al>snakes</al> bound together in embraces of love,
but that is when they are small.</ab>

    <figure size="small" id="fig_p122r_1" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5ZDJlZ0g5OXNKeDQ">
    </figure>
    
    <figure size="small" id="fig_p122r_3" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5UDgyYnNSZnlndjg">
    </figure>
    
    <figure size="small" id="fig_p122r_4" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5elo4VzJZRUppOWc">
    </figure>
    
</div>



<div id="p122r_2" categories="casting">

<head>Flower in the mouth of the <al>snake</al></head>

<ab>If you want to put in the mouth of the <al>snake</al> some flower
<del><fr>q</fr></del> or some branch of a plant which contains the
<md>antidote</md> against its bite, take a little branch, as best
arranged as you can find, &amp; pose its stem into its mouth. Then put
two little pieces of <m>wax</m> around the stem of the plant. And with
the <tl>end of a <m><del>iron</del> wire</m> that is hot</tl>, melt the
<m>wax</m> a little, &amp; with the other <tl><bp>hand</bp></tl>, close
the jaws of the animal. And then you can cut the head to make it burn
with the flower. If the plant <del><fr>s</fr></del> is strong enough, it
will hold up by itself, and should it be weak like <pa>wormwood</pa>
leaf, which droops, the humidity of the <m>sand</m> will lift it up, &amp; make
it swim &amp; hold up without putting anything there, although you could
pass underneath it some <tl>thread</tl>, going through with a
<tl>needle</tl>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
