<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="068r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f141.image">




<div id="p068r_1" categories="decorative">

<head>Fanciful tables</head>

<ab>You can make various grooved compartments &amp; in these, put
<al>fishes</al> painted from nature &amp; with colors on <m>simple
<fr>carton</fr></m>, &amp; if you please, on <m>silvered &amp;
<tl>burnished</tl> paper</m> which will represent the scales. And next,
cover this with <m>very clear lantern horn</m>. You can apply the same
to other works.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p068r_2" categories="cultivation">

<head>Planting trees</head>

<ab> One needs to plant them in <del><env>dry place</env></del>
<env>dry weather</env>, &amp; gather plenty of <m>earth</m> at the
foot all around, like a mound, in order that the <env>rains</env> do not fill
the holes &amp; drown the trees.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p068r_3" categories="casting" continued="yes">

<head>Casting</head>

<ab>I have tried four kinds of <m>sand</m> for <m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m>:
<m>chalk</m>, <m><tl>pestled</tl> glass</m>, <m>tripoli</m> &amp; <m>burnt
linen</m>, all 4 excellent. But as for the <m>chalk</m>, it needs to
be of the softest kind you can find, like <m>the <pl>Champagne</pl> one
that <pro>painters</pro> use</m>. It releases very neatly, does not want
to be moistened with <m><fr>magistra</fr></m> or anything else, but needs to be
completely dry, in its natural state, finely
pulverized. The first cast is always the
neatest; however, it will well withstand two or three. But there is only
the first one that you need to take heed of, when you want to remake
your <tl>frame mold</tl> to take new <m>powdered chalk</m> that has not
yet been put to use, for the one previously used in the <tl>frame</tl> has
dried out &amp; does not have as much hold &amp; bond like the fresh one.
<m><tl>Pestled</tl> glass</m> can be made from <m>common glass sand</m>, however,
<m><fr>cristallin</fr></m> is more excellent, for common glass contains
<del><m>glass</m></del> <m>salt of saltwort</m> only, but
<m><fr>cristallin</fr></m> contains both <m>salt of tartar</m> &amp;
<m>saltwort</m> all together, which both help fusion, the <m>glass</m>
once calcined &amp; reduced as if to its prime substance. In order to
calcine it perfectly, throw your pieces of <m>glass</m>, whichever it be,
among the largest possible lit <m>charcoals</m> that you can, if you are
lacking another amenity <del><fr>t</fr></del>of<comment rid="c_068r_04"/> violent fire<del><fr>t</fr></del>.
And when it is well red, throw it into
<m>water</m></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<m>Putty</m> is considered excellent for these two <m>metals</m>.</ab>



</div>
</root>
