<root>
<page>154r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f313.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p154r_1</id>
<head><m>Gold</m> not being fixed</head>

<ab><m>Gold</m> as gilding goes away once the piece is reheated &amp;
kept in high heat, especially if there is some lead, for lead will
pierce in the fire a piece with gold, because it holds closely with
<m><figure>☿</figure></m>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p154r_2</id>
<head>Cutting <m>lead</m></head>

<ab>Because it is fat &amp; grips &amp; attacks the knife or chisel, wet
it &amp; you will cut it like glass.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>

Sometimes <m>gold</m> &amp;<m>silver</m> take on, through certain smoke,
some color during the casting. But these are not at all scales &amp;
<fr>chappe</fr>, but rather this color goes aways with whitening &amp;
<fr>bullitoire</fr>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p154r_3</id>
<head>Sweetening <m>silver</m></head>

<ab>When <pro>goldsmiths</pro>, who are working with large works have
forged their platters, it very often happens with their sheddings that
it bursts &amp; breaks for being too soured. To avoid this, throw in,
when it is well melted, some dry mortar, composed of sand &amp; good
lime which has been worked, &amp; pulverize it &amp; throw it in.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<pro>Goldsmiths</pro> do not work at all with
<m><cn>real</cn></m><m>silver</m>, that is not alloyed, because it is
leady &amp; when forging it sours.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

Some solder, for small works &amp; things which only go in the fire
once, with some old <cn><fr>sol</fr></cn> &amp; reheated &amp; beaten
<cn>carolus</cn>. However, if the sol is not very good, the solder eats
away &amp; one needs to solder on it twice &amp; there is too much
copper on it. Others solder with half silver &amp; half fine
copper.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p154r_4</id>
<head><m>Iron</m> scales</head>

<ab>Once well pulverized &amp; ground on marble &amp; mixed with the
above-mentioned sand of <fr>noyau</fr>, and dried slowly without
reheating, it endures several casts of lead &amp; tin. Copper &amp;
latten come out well. But if it is not well ground, like crocum, it goes
to the bottom, if the sand is not wetted thickly enough.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p154r_5</id>
<head><m>Metal filings</m></head>

<ab>They are not made by themselves, if they are not helped with some
portion of similar metal, melted for gathering &amp; putting them in a
bath, for it is sooner burned than melted. Tin and lead filings are made
with tallow, the one of gold with salpeter, the one of silver with
sandever.</ab>

</div>
</root>
