<root>
<page>102v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f210.image</image>

<div>

<id>p102v_1</id>

<head>Painting on <m>crystal</m> or <m>glass</m></head>

<ab>They paint in <m>oil</m> without lines, except for the faces where
they trace the nose &amp; the mouth with black in small work, then they
make strokes &amp; and highlights in white, next they coat all with
carnation. And as for the ground, they make it with <m>azur
d’<pl>Acre</pl></m> for more beauty, or with <m>lake for a quickly-done
red</m>, or with <m><al>dragon</al>'s blood</m> for the most beauty. But
one needs to layer it little by little so that it appears even &amp; of
one color, &amp; thus for other colors. Next they put underneath it a
<m>foil backing for <m>topaz</m>, or one of <m>gold</m> or
<m>silver</m></m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p102v_2</id>

<head>Infusion of <m><pa>anthos</pa></m> or
<m><pa>rosemary</pa></m><comment>c_102v_05</comment></head>

<ab><tmp>In the <ms>month</ms> of August</tmp>, the flower is better
cooked &amp; more suitable for making <m>oil</m>. Take of it whatever
quantity you like and put it into a <tl>bottle</tl>
<add>subsequently</add> well stoppered, &amp; leave to wilt in there
<env>in the shade</env> for a <ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms>. Then put in it
the <m>first substance of wine</m><comment>c_102v_06</comment> &amp;
leave it to rest three or four <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms>; and next express the
whole into another <tl>vessel</tl> &amp; into this very same
<tl>substance of <m>wine</m></tl><comment>c_102v_07</comment>, put in
seven or eight <ms>infusions</ms> of new flowers. Next, leave the last
<ms>infusion</ms> <env>in the sun</env> <ms><tmp>for a month</tmp></ms>.
Next, distil it through an <tl>alembic</tl>. <del>Ne</del>, And take ii
<ms>ounces</ms> of this <m>water</m> in two or three
<tl><ms>spoonfuls</ms></tl> of <m>white wine</m>; but this is for the
<pro>elderly</pro>. <pn>Paul the Third</pn> used it.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p102v_3</id>

<head>Cast</head>

<ab><m>Tin</m> comes out better being thin &amp; fine, rather than
thick, because being thick &amp; in great heat, it retracts. Therefore,
if you want to mold a thick piece in <m>tin</m>, mold it only on one
side, &amp; with a cavity on one side, if it is possible, in that way
you will have it more neat, and then you will be able to <m>solder</m>
two halves together. But if you have to mold it thick, make it in the
form &amp; mold a lot of feeders around the figure, in this
way.

<figure>

<id>fig_p102v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SjZwV0ZHdW93ZEk</link>

</figure>

</ab>

</div>
</root>
