<root>
<page>146v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f298.image</image>

<div>

<id>p146v_1</id>

<head>Molding <al>turtles</al></head>

<ab>This is the continuation of the second preceding leaf. When you have
well uncovered the part of the belly of the <al>turtle</al>, the
underneath of the throat &amp; legs, &amp; having cleaned it all well,
do not forget to neatly uncover this cavity that these animals have in
their shell, between the neck &amp; the shoulders. <al>Those of the
<env>water</env></al> do not have ones as deep as <al>those of the
<pl><env><fr>garrigue</fr></env></pl></al>, which are leaner. And among
these, there are some that have ones more ensconced than others. Do not
forget, therefore, to uncover well all of this to best represent its
nature. But if there is some cavity which twists too much inside, and
cannot be seen, does not release, put in some small pieces of <m>wax</m>
&amp; with <tl>points of hot, <m>thick iron wire</m></tl>, stretch &amp;
adapt the said <m>wax</m>. Then, <del><fr>bouch</fr></del> stuff with
<m>soft clay</m> the entrance of all its cavities. Put the
<tl><m>clay</m> circle</tl> around your <tl>mold</tl>, made already of
two pieces, which contains the back of the <al>turtle</al>. And to mold
its belly, one needs to divide in three, as you see. That is to say, you
will put a <tl><fr>entre deulx</fr> of <m>clay</m></tl> on top of the
throat &amp; another on the edge of the shell of the tail,
<mark>#</mark>. And having <m>oiled</m> <del>and</del> the shell of
the belly &amp; having rubbed it with <m>eau-de-vie</m>, cast your sand
a little thick &amp; wet with <m>hot water</m> as before. Having set,
remove these <tl><fr>entredeulx</fr> of <m>clay</m></tl>, then uncover
well the front &amp; back legs, that is to say the part underneath &amp;
the tail &amp; the throat &amp; remove the <m>cay</m> from the cavities
<del><fr>qu</fr></del>, all in one piece if you can, for this will show
you if this cavity will release well. And if the pulled out <m>clay</m>,
brings with it the <m>wax</m> that you put there, reput it in the places
that can not release, as is said. And if some part is taken away or let
go, attach &amp; rejoin it to the <tl>mold</tl> with some <m>wax</m>
&amp; the <tl>point of hot <m>iron</m></tl>. Do not forget to put some
<del><fr>po</fr></del> <m>melted wax</m> at the end of the nails of the
<al>turtles</al>, to make the gate. Your molded <add>and uncovered</add>
belly shell, your <tl>mold</tl> can be seen thus.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p146v_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bUk2c1E3LWtOTDA</link>

</figure>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

in such a way that only the entire belly shell be uncovered, to mold it
alone.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p146v_2</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5WGEzek5peHJ6VDA</link>

</figure>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
