<root>
<page>135v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f276.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p135v_1</id>
<head>Casting in <m>☼</m></head>

<ab>Take a <tl>crucible</tl> with a capacity suitable for what you want
to put in it, coarsely pestle a little <m>borax</m> &amp; put it at the
bottom, then the <m>☼</m> on top. Arrange on the
<m>charcoals</m> of the <tl>forge</tl> the <tl>crucible</tl> in such a
way that the wind of the <tl>bellows</tl> blows on it from underneath
and not at the side, for this cools it &amp; does not heat it enough.
Make sure also that it is distanced three <ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> from
the wall of the <tl>forge</tl>, in order that it can be surrounded with
<m>charcoal</m>. Let the said <tl>crucible</tl> reheat, until it is well
red. Then, make your <pro>boy</pro> blow on it with long and strong
pushes, for in this way it heats <del>well</del> better. And
nevertheless <del>blow by</del> when the <m>gold</m> is melted, blow on
top with a <tl>little bellows</tl>, for the <m>gold</m> will become
brittle &amp; take on a <fr>chappe</fr>. And as long as it makes a
swirling smoke, as you blow thus, it means that is not <fr>doulx</fr>
enough for the cast. Uncover therefore the <tl>crucible</tl> &amp;
without moving <del><fr>ch</fr></del> it from its place and without
interrupting the blowing, make it lean towards you in order to see well
inside. Throw in it the <ms>size of a <pa>bean</pa></ms> of <m>borax</m>
&amp; blow inside in jolts with the <tl>little bellows</tl>. But if
there is <m>charcoal</m> inside, blow a little stronger to make it go
out. And if the <m>gold</m> smokes &amp; swirls, put some more
<m>borax</m> in and <del>note</del> blow on top, making sure that, if it
is still brittle &amp; not softened enough, it does not cover itself
when you blow, as if it had cooled. But if it does not make this sign,
it is <fr>douls</fr> enough. @At that point blow very strongly in order
to heat it well, and as you think it is hot enough, throw in on top, in
the <tl>crucible</tl>, the<m> <def><m><fr>couleur</fr></m></def><comment>c_135r_01</comment>
composed, as said beforehand here, of <m>verdet</m>, <m>saltpeter</m>,
<m>sal ammoniac</m> &amp; <m>borax</m></m>, <add>a little</add>. And
<del>let rest</del> blow always with the <tl>small bellows</tl>, and the
<m>gold</m> will become shiny like</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
If you cast in <m>gold</m> some important piece, <m>lute</m> your
<tl>mold</tl> with the same sand where <del>there is</del> there is some
<m><la>crocum</la></m>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
If you want to cast some large work in <m>gold</m>, or which is
important, make at the foot of the <tl>forge</tl>, or at one end of it a
<add><tl><fr>four à vent</fr></tl></add>, where you can hold your
<tl>mold</tl> in the completely <del><fr>n</fr></del> red sand. </ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
One can cast two or three <ms>lb</ms> of <m>gold</m>.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
