<root>
<page>165v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f336.image</image>

<div>
<id>p165v_1</id>
<head>Stance of animals</head>

<ab>Not only with <tl><m>iron</m> points</tl>, but with <m>melted
wax</m>, animals are secured on the <tl><m>earthen</m> slab</tl>.
<add>Wash them first in <m>clear water</m>, once killed in the mixture of
<m>vinegar</m> &amp; <m><bp>urine</bp></m>, &amp; with a <tl>sponge</tl>
purge their mouth, eyes and head of the <m>slaver</m> which comes out,
for the sand would never set well there and would become
lumpy.</add></ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
If you want to make them keep their mouths open, put in a little bit of
<tl><mu>spinet</mu> string</tl>, which will not take up space.

</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p165v_2</id>
<head>Keeping animals</head>

<ab>Having molded them once, if you want to keep them for molding again,
put them back into the mixture of <m><bp>urine</bp></m>, <m>vinegar</m>
&amp; <m>eau-de-vie</m> where you killed the others, and they will keep
for a long time without decaying. If you have a <md>cut on your hand,
take care that this mixture does not touch it</md>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p165v_3</id>
<head><tl>Molds</tl></head>

<ab>Once molded, do not keep them for a long time, but rather use them
<del><fr>u</fr></del> as soon as you can, because when kept a long time,
they are subject to corrupting.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

When they are reheated, the thing comes out better.

</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p165v_4</id>
<head><m>Lute</m></head>

<ab>When reheating, you can use <m>common lute</m>. But when you want to
cast, strip it from the <tl>mold</tl> &amp; promptly, with a
<tl>brush</tl>, layer the <m>lute of plaster that has been used for
<tl>molds</tl></m>, for it will be dry when it is placed, &amp; cast.
One needs to mainly put this <m>lute</m> on the joints.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p165v_5</id>
<head><m>Silver</m></head>

<ab><ms>When it quivers</ms>, once melted, it is a sign that it is well
hot &amp; because usually it is <m>leady</m>, it is good to throw in it
some <m>lime mortar</m>, for this attracts &amp; gathers the
<m>lead</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p165v_6</id>
<head><al>Fly</al> wings</head>

<ab>In order that they come out better, put from the gate to the edges
of these some <m>veins of wax</m>. Make sure also that under the belly
there is enough <m>wax</m>, for this is what makes the gate.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p165v_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5UmhqY1RkWFRhYzg</link>

</figure>

</div>

<div>
<id>p165v_7</id>
<head>Joining some <al>fly</al> wings, or similar</head>

<ab>They are joined with <m><al>fish</al> glue</m> mixed with
<m>eau-de-vie</m> over slow fire, heating also the work. Then this is
covered with <m>modelling wax</m>, which is grey.</ab>

</div>
</root>
