<root>
<page>147v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f300.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p147v_1</id>

<head><figure>+</figure>Casting with <m>copper</m> alloyed with
<m><figure>☾</figure></m>, which is like very low <m>solder</m> and
ard<x>...</x>es and <m>old K</m> and some Re out of xii</head>

<ab>I have cast the cleanest I have ever seen, making very small figures
as thin as paper. I have cast extremely hot in the very red mold, and
have put into the melted mixture the two compositions which makes
<m>silver</m> runny, and have done as if I wanted to throw with <m>pure
silver</m>. This <m>league</m> is white when it boils, as with every
other alloy which contains even just a small bit of <m>silver</m>. To
cast something very delicate, use this.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p147v_2</id>

<head><m>Lute</m></head>

<ab>There is no better than the one <del>that has</del> which you have
molded, namely pieces from your molds. But one needs to choose those
better reheated.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p147v_3</id>

<head>Crucible</head>

<ab>Beware that it should be three fingers away from the mouth of the
bellows and that the aforesaid bellows is positioned underneath the
bottom of the crucible, otherwise it will cool it down.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p147v_4</id>

<head><m>Latten</m> casting</head>

<ab>I have taken the one you find in <m>latten</m> skillets, which have
been beaten and forged quite thinly. Having well-heated it, I threw in
two or three grains, like beads of <m>sal ammonicac</m>. This will
clarify it like a mirror, having turned very white from all the heating,
I threw in it some crushed raw and pure <m>calamine</m>. The I casted it
in its very red mold. Il cast cleanly and thin like <m>paper</m>, and
hollow on the back. Because it has become crusty I cooked it again,
which to means to say, I reddened it, and left it to cool, then put it
in <m>bleach</m>, made partly with raw <m>tartar</m> and half of common
<m>salt</m>. Having boiled it well, I brushed it in clear <m>water</m>,
because the first time it was</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>Do not let it cool down when melting. It
always makes into filaments, as you would find with melted <m>glass</m>,
because of the <m>calamine</m>. Usually, the soft <m>letten</m> of
skillets, becomes red from casting, even when it has been in the fire
for a longtime, because the <m>calamine</m> evaporates. But the brittle
<m>letten</m> of candleholders becomes yellow, as well as the
<m>filings</m> made of needles.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
