<root>
<page>034v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f74.image</image>

<div>

<id>p034v_1</id>

<head>For melting or transmuting a <tl>jewel</tl> put inside a
<tl>box</tl></head>

<figure>

<id>fig_p034v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5VTA5cWtrWktEajQ</link>

</figure>

<ab>

Take a <tl>box of <m>boxwood</m> banded with rings</tl>, as you see,
into which will easily fit another <tl>small box</tl>, like that which
you see marked B, and make sure that it does not touch the bottom of the
large one marked A, but that there is some distance. That which enters
the <tl>large box</tl> must be smooth, but the rim must be made with
rings so that, being joined, it appears as if they are one and the same
<tl>box</tl>. You must also have a round <tl><m>leather</m> cover of the
same length as the <tl>box</tl></tl>, as you see marked C, which will
fit <del>let</del> <add>easily</add> &amp; surround the aforesaid
<tl>boxes</tl> thus placed one within the other. But before you do your
trick, you must put at the bottom of the <tl>larger box</tl> <m>powdered
gold or silver</m>, or <m>mercury</m> amalgamated with <m>silver</m>,
and then place the <tl>little box</tl> marked B on top. Next, holding
the <tl>box</tl> with your <bp>index finger</bp> on top, you present
<add>it</add>, and seeing only the bottom of the <tl>smaller
<add>box</add></tl> marked B, one places a <tl>jewel</tl> or something
similar in it. This being done, placing the <tl>box</tl> on the
<tl>table</tl>, you cover it with the <tl><m>leather</m> box</tl>, and
making the requisite gestures, you will remove the <tl><m>leather</m>
box</tl>, &amp; without showing the inside, will put it on the
<tl>table</tl> &amp; let it be recognized that the <tl>jewel</tl> is
<del>in the</del> placed in the bottom of the <tl>small box</tl> marked
B. Then you will gently place the <tl><m>leather</m> box</tl> back,
&amp; after saying
<la>inhonorificabilitidinita<del>d</del>tudinibus</la>, you will take
the top of the <tl><m>leather</m> box</tl> with two <bp>fingers</bp>,
and <del>with the</del> clasping it more firmly than usual, at the same
time you <del><fr>d</fr></del> will lift <del><fr>pe</fr></del> the
<tl>smaller box</tl> that is inside &amp; which contains the
<tl>jewel</tl>, &amp; you will gently put both on the <tl>table</tl>,
then you will pour the powder or amalgam that is at the bottom of the
<tl>large box</tl>, then replace the <tl><m>leather</m> box</tl> with
the box inside it, as it was at the start. Then, removing the
<tl><m>leather</m> box</tl> without removing the smaller one, you will
show the <tl>jewel</tl> at the bottom which has returned to its previous
state, holding your <bp>index finger</bp> on the rim of the <tl>box</tl>
so that it does not slip.</ab>

</div>
</root>
