<root>
<page>158v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f322.image</image>

<div>

<id>p158v_1</id>

<head>Colors for green leaves</head>

<ab>One usually paints them in <m>oil</m>, because <m>distemper</m>
colors have no hold. For <pa>marigold flowers</pa>, <m>lightly ground
minium</m> for some, &amp; for others which are more yellowish, a bit of
<m>massicot</m> with it. For green, the <m>verdigris</m> has depth &amp;
is too dark. If it is a yellowish green, you can mix with the
<m>verdigris</m> a little <m>yellow ochre</m> &amp; <m>stil de grain
yellow</m>. If the green is dark, put with it <m>charcoal of <pa>peach
tree</pa> pits</m>, which makes a <del>v</del> greenish black, in the
same way that black of <m><al>ox</al> foot bone</m> looks bluish. And
thus, by judgement &amp; discretion, put the color on the <m>natural
flower or leaf</m> to see whether it comes close. But layer it
transparently so as not to cover the lines of the work.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p158v_2</id>

<head>Large <tl>molds</tl></head>

<ab>Because of the great weight of the <m>metal</m>, they want to be put
in a <tl>press</tl> in order that they do not open.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p158v_3</id>

<head><m><tl>Candle</tl> smoke</m></head>

<ab>It makes it come out neater, &amp; even if it is <add>a little</add>
thick, it does not hold to any place because it has no body. I have thus
fumigated my <fr><tl>moules</tl> de noyau</fr> for <m>tin</m> &amp;
<m>lead</m>, and have cast in the cold <tl>mold</tl> well dried
beforehand, and it came out very neat. It is true that <m>lead</m> mixed
with half of <m>tin</m> was very hot, because the medal was thick.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p158v_4</id>

<head>Gate</head>

<ab><del>Even though</del> <add>If</add> the medal is very thick, for
this reason do not give it as thick of a gate. It suffices for the gate
to have <ms>half of its thickness</ms>. But if it <corr>is</corr> thin,
give it a gate of its thickness. Do not forget to make vents in the gate
where typically the material becomes porous.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

Never forget to <m>oil</m> the <m>wax</m> gate when you mold plants
or flowers, otherwise it breaks &amp; cannot be taken out.

</ab>

</div>
</root>
