<root>
<page>112v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f230.image</image>

<div>
<cont/>

<id>p112r_4</id>

<ab>to cast, make him take through the mouth some good <m>eau-de-vie</m> or else mix a bit with the <m>vinegar</m>. And soon it will
be dead, without any lesion which deforms it. For large animals, for
whom one would need a lot of <m>eau-de-vie</m>, one uses
<m>vinegar</m> and <del><fr>er</fr></del> <m><bp>urine</bp></m>. But for small
ones, only <m>eau-de-vie</m>, which is done sooner. <lb/>

When your animal is dead, take it out &amp; clean it carefully of its
old skin, if it sheds, or of the filth, or of the <al>lice</al>, like
<al>lizards</al> have, and then apply thus.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

now put enough in a <tl>glass</tl>, &amp; soak there &amp; keep there
continually the head of the animal, or the whole of it, if it is not
big.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

Take head, before it dies,to keep the eyes open, <del><fr>es</fr></del>
by blocking the eyelids with a little of <m>wax</m> or something
else.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p112v_1</id>

<head><del><fr>Mouler</fr></del> Making the arrangement and disposition
of the animal</head>

<ab>Having made provision of <m><df>fat earth</df></m> called
<m>clay</m>, that should be grey, because that commonly the best, or
another which has good binding &amp; will should well prepared &amp;
beaten, such that it is handleable without attaching to the
<tl><bp>hands</bp></tl> nor the work, make a <fr>lazagne</fr> or like a
<fr>torteau</fr> of this <m>earth</m> equally flattened with a <tl>round
stick, which <pro>pastry-makers</pro></tl> use, which should be a little
thicker than a <ms><bp>thumb</bp></ms>. And on this
<fr>tourtelle</fr>, arrange your animal, <del><fr>aya</fr></del>
imitating in that its nature, &amp; <del><fr>fa</fr></del> the fashion in
which it is commonly shaped. And firstly, with a good <tl>needle</tl>,
pierce it from underneath, in the middle of the throat, &amp; up to
<del><fr>u <ill/></fr></del> the top bone of the head. Retract the
<tl>needle</tl>, &amp; in its place &amp; its hole, put the <tl>point of
an <m>iron wire</m></tl>, of such a length that it suffices to hold the
head of the animal as <del><fr>q</fr></del> high as it must be, &amp; if
the skin gets in to the inside <del>&amp;</del> when you put in the
<tl>point</tl>, pull it out with <del><fr>a</fr></del>
<del><tl>point</tl></del> the edge of your <tl>small pincers</tl>, &amp;
arrange it as it was. Push the other end of the <tl>point</tl> in the
<fr>tourtelle</fr> of <m>clay</m>. Thus, the head will be held high,
which will have better grace &amp;once fixed; next, arrange the gesture
of the body, &amp; the feet, &amp; the entanglement as you think will
look best. And so that it is secure &amp; does not move at all when you
throw in the sand, <del><fr>mects</fr></del> secure the legs
<del><fr>&amp; le corp</fr></del> with little <tl>points of <m>iron
wire</m></tl>, having already made the first hole with a very sharp
<tl>needle</tl>. Do the same on the body parts that you deem necessary,
<del><fr>plantant</fr></del> making sure that the <tl>points</tl>
passing through the animal are fixed in the <fr>tourtelle</fr> of earth,
and not so far in front that they jut out beyond the body of the animal
by a</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

Take a <tl>fine needle of <m>steel</m></tl>, &amp; which is the sharpest
possible, in order that, making with it the first hole to place the <tl>points
of <m>iron</m></tl>, it passes without forcing anything, &amp; by its
harshness, does not push in or pull out the skin. Next, put in a thickish
<tl>point of <m>iron</m></tl> in thick places, &amp; thin ones in thin
places. But head as a secret to not plant, in the first go, the
<tl>point</tl> passed through the animal in the slab of <m>earth</m>,
<del><fr>pour</fr></del> but having planted it, take it out of the
<m>earth</m> &amp; not out of the animal, &amp; <del><fr>fais
ains</fr></del> next, fix it. This is done because by fixing it the
first time, it pushes in the skin of the <al>snake</al> and by taking
the point out, it replaces the skin in its original state.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

When you put the <tl>points</tl> again you have already used, clean them
well of <m>rust</m>, so that they do not take away some skin.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>bottom</margin>

The main layout of your arrangement is to <del><fr>di</fr></del> place
the head raised &amp; looking sideways. For this effect, pierce the head
on a <tl>solid plank or table</tl> <del>&amp; <ill/></del>, making the
<tl>point</tl> pass through the bottom of the throat,
<del><fr>s’arrestan</fr></del> entering into the top of the head

<figure>

<id>fig_p112v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5c3dzVlNzcUd6MnM</link>

</figure>

</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
