<root>
<page>142v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f290.image</image>

<div>

<id>p142v_1</id>

<head>Molding <al>grasshoppers</al> and things too thin</head>

<ab>If you have a <m>written paper</m> to mold, which is too thin, after
you have made the first cast &amp; it has set, give a little thickness
to the reverse of your <m>paper</m> with <m>melted butter</m>, which is
the most appropriate means there is, &amp; for fortifying the wings of
either a <al>butterfly</al> or a <al>grasshopper</al>, or some delicate
part of an animal to which you need to give thickness. But take heed to
apply this <m>melted butter</m> underneath the wing or in whichever
place it cannot be seen. For giving thickness to a <pa>pansy</pa> or
other flowers, <m>butter</m> is not good, but rather <m><pa>wheat</pa>
oil</m>, which is soon dry &amp; holds firm. <m>Wax</m> would not be
appropriate here for it is too hot once melted, &amp; it makes the thing
to which it is applied contract. But <m>butter</m> is amiable and
handleable.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>If you write on <m>paper</m> or on
<m>common <fr>carton</fr></m> <comment>c_142v_05</comment>&amp; that your
<m>letter</m> is with <m>gum</m>, the humidity of the <tl><m>clay</m>
slab</tl> or the wet sand for <fr>noyau</fr> will moisten your
<m>letter</m> <corr>&amp;</corr> undo it. Therefore write with
<m>cinnabar</m> wettened with <m>oil</m>, on <m>oiled paper</m>
&amp;<comment>c_142v_05</comment>impress.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><mark>+</mark>Reheat your
<tl>molds</tl> with <m>charcoals</m>,firstly lit in the <tl>forge</tl>,
in order that the fire is not so hot &amp; does not break the
<tl>molds</tl>. And do not make as much fire where the <tl>mold</tl> is
thin, like in the place where it is thick.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p142v_2</id>

<head><tl>Molds</tl></head>

<ab>Make some notches, with these, that enter more in the inside of the
<tl>mold</tl> than on the outside, for in this way, they have more
strength. Keep from reheating in one go &amp; in a too ardent fire, for
this makes them <del>melt</del> break.</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Do not keep them in a <env>humid or
enclosed place</env> if they are not well dry, for they go moldy. So do
dried animals.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>@One ought not to reheat <tl>molds</tl>
twice when the animal can be removed without burning, like a
<al>toad</al>, which can well be molded hollow like all thick animals.
However, it is always good to redden the <tl>mold</tl> once.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p142v_3</id>

<head><m>Lute</m> for <m>luting</m> your <tl>molds</tl></head>

<ab>I have not found one that is made more quickly than this one, nor
better. Take this <m>lean earth of which the <pro>founders of artillery
&amp; bells</pro> make their <tl><fr>trusseaulx</fr></tl> and
<tl>molds</tl></m>, which is lean &amp; sandy. Wet it
<del><fr>e</fr></del> moderately like a very thick <m>mortar</m>. Mix in
it about <ms>half</ms> <m><al>horse</al> dung</m> &amp; then have it
beaten well. Next, mix in a <ms>third part</ms> of <m>discarded cloth
waste</m> or <m>cloth shavings</m>, and beat it again quite strongly.
You can reheat your <tl>mold</tl> as soon as the <m>lute</m> is
placed.</ab>

</div>
</root>
