<root>
<page>099r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f203.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p098v_5</id>

<ab><m>Earth</m>, or sand, moistened or ground with <m>water</m>, wants
to be reheated more than sand.</ab>

<ab><m>Latten from a candlestick</m> is not pure, for one mixes in it
<m>iron filings</m> &amp; <m>potin</m>.</ab>

<ab><m>Latten</m> wants to be cast hotter than <m>copper</m>, <la>quod
non credo</la>.</ab>

<ab>To cast carefully, one ought not to take <m>metals already
alloyed</m>, but take them pure &amp; mix them.</ab>

<ab><m>Iron</m> hardly agrees with being cast in a mixture of
<m>copper</m> or <m>latten</m>.</ab>

<ab>It is better all with a sand, either in a <tl>frame</tl> or
<fr>noyau</fr> at once, rather than several mixed.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>

One ought to reheat for one or two <ms><tmp>hours</tmp></ms> <del><fr>et
p</fr></del>, in <add><del>that</del>a</add> <m>charcoal</m> fire which
lights by itself, a <tl>crucible</tl> with the substance inside, and
then blow &amp; cover the <tl>crucible</tl> with large <m>charcoals</m>
&amp; the mouth of the <tl>furnace</tl> with <tl><m>bricks</m></tl>, and
let it consume two or three feedings of <m>charcoal</m>, which
<del><fr>se</fr></del> fill the <tl>furnace</tl> above the
<tl>crucible</tl>. In the end feed and stoke the fire, &amp; when the
flame is very white &amp; that the substance will be in a liquid
<fr>bain</fr> like <m>water</m> &amp; casting off pale blue flames,
cast. The secret is to cast <add>very</add> hot &amp; in one go.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p099r_2</id>
<head><m>Lean white sand</m></head>

<ab>Without bond renders well proper for casting, &amp; having body, if
you grind it very finely on <tl><m>porphyry</m></tl> or calcine it,
reddening it several times in the fire, &amp; spread it in
<m>vinegar</m> or finely grind it with <m>water</m>, as you know. It
also molds very neatly in <fr>noyau</fr>, as I have experimented. But do
not moisten it with <m>salt water</m> if you want to promptly reheat it,
for <m>salt</m> boils on the fire &amp; makes pustules, being pressed by
the fire. I believe that the <fr>noyau</fr>, gently reheated, would not
do this. I molded very neatly in <fr>noyau</fr> the <m>substance of
skillets</m>. <m>White sand</m> <sn>smells like <m>sulphur</m></sn> when
reheated, and I believe it would melt. And since the substance has been
cast in it, it acquires in the <tl>mold</tl>
<del><fr>co<exp>mm</exp>e</fr></del> a luster as if it were
<m>leaded</m> or vitrified. I believe that <pro>glassmakers</pro> could
use it.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>

One needs very little of <m>sal ammoniac</m> dissolved in
<m>water</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p099r_3</id>
<head>Bell handles</head>

<ab>

They can be put back on, without remaking the bell, which one ought to
put back in the pit, &amp; and mold it there. But should you
<m>solder</m> a <del><fr>ref</fr></del> cracked bell, it is considered
impossible to give it its first voice.</ab>

</div>
</root>
