<root>
<page>137v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f280.image</image>

<div>
<id>p137v_1</id>
<head>Tempering sand for <tl>molds</tl> of flat medals</head>

<ab>Flat medals, of <m>wax</m> or <m>metal</m>, are <m>oiled</m> very
lightly &amp; then are touched with a <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> of
<m>eau-de-vie</m>. And in order that the <tl>mold</tl>, wet with
<m>water</m>, takes without refusing the <m>oiled</m> thing, one heats
the <m>water</m> well for wetting the sand, for with <m>cold water</m>
it would refuse. Medals are <m>oiled</m> because they are not malleable
&amp; thus could break the <tl>mold</tl>. And animals, which are
malleable, do not want to be <m>oiled</m>. <m>Hot water</m> should be
<ms><sn>of such heat that you cannot hold your <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl>
there, without feeling strong heat</sn></ms>. Wet your sand thicker for
flat medals &amp; solids than for <al>lizards</al> &amp; fine things.
Your sand, having set, clean &amp; scrape your <tl>mold</tl> on one side
&amp; the other &amp; make a notch at the foot &amp; the border of the
medal on the side of the gate, in order that you can take it away
better. Lower also <add>the <tl>mold</tl>, scraping</add> the surround
of the medal, in order that, from all sides, you can take it away
without it corrupting the <tl>mold</tl>. Next, make your scorings around
<del>of the</del> the first cast <tl>mold</tl> <del><fr>mes</fr></del>,
in order that the second cast joins with it without varying, &amp;
<corr>especially</corr> make a notch at the bottom of the <tl>mold</tl>
where the head of the molded thing is. Make some also at the sides of
the gate. This done, dip the reverse of the first <tl>mold</tl> in
<m>water</m>, <m>oil</m> it, &amp; thus it will not be imbibed. Rub
the reverse of the medal with <m>eau-de-vie</m> &amp; secondly cast,
wetting in <m>hot water</m>. If you have molded a medal <fr>en
noyau</fr>, having made the first cast &amp; this one having set,
outline, with the <tl>point of a knife</tl>, the surround of the medal,
in order that it is raised on the cast &amp; and not buried in it. Then
having made the second cast, &amp; having opened your <tl>mold</tl>,
<del>have</del> take away the medal, in one go, with <del>one</del> two
<tl>knife points</tl> <del><fr>q</fr></del>, and that one takes it from
the side of the gate &amp; the other from the side of the head, which is
opposite.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Take care not to <m>oil</m> your medal too much, for if the <m>oil</m>
seeps out, it diverts the sand from becoming smooth &amp; amassing &amp;
makes it wavy &amp; lumpy. One should only touch the middle of the medal
<del>of the <fr>p</fr></del> with the <tl>point of an <m>oiled</m>
<fr>pinceau</fr></tl>, &amp; then spread the <m>oil</m> everywhere.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>

Make especially sure that the gate be the widest you can
<del><fr>p</fr></del> towards the medal &amp; embraces it well, that the
entrance of the gate is ample, always narrowing towards the medal. Do
not forget also to notch the entrance of the gate.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
