<root>
<page>103r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f211.item</image>

<div>

<id>p103r_1</id>

<head>Against burns, excellent</head>

<ab>Heat <m><pa>linseed</pa> oil</m> on a gentle fire, without letting
it boil &amp; simmer, but once it is hot put in a <ms>quarter</ms> as
much of the <m>newest wax</m> you can. Once melted, let it cool, &amp;
once they begin to curdle, stir continuously with a <tl><m>new
wooden</m> spatula</tl> <del><fr>t</fr></del> for as long as it takes
you to say <del>one</del> 9 <ms>pater nosters</ms>, and as you say them,
wash this composition with <m>holy water</m>, stirring all the while.
Having said the first <add>9</add> <ms>pater nosters</ms>, pour out the
<m>first water</m> &amp; put in new one, &amp; wash &amp; stir the
composition <ms><tmp>for the time it takes you to say 8 pater
nosters</tmp></ms>, and the 3rd time for as long as 7, &amp; and thus
you will consecutively <del>until</del> add <m>new water</m>, doing the
same as above, until the last &amp; single <ms>pater noster</ms> of
nine. Then you shall have a soft &amp; <m>white ointment</m>, with which
you shall anoint the burn <ms><tmp>for the space of 9 days</tmp></ms>.
But do not apply it any longer than this, for it would cause
<del><fr>a</fr></del> your <bp>flesh</bp> to grow excessively. You
<del>b</del> shall bandage yourself <ms><tmp>twice a day</tmp></ms>,
&amp; each time you shall wash your <bp>face</bp> with <m>water</m>
&amp; <m>wine</m> mixed together, a little tepid, not rubbing, but as if
pressing with <tl>wet linen cloth</tl>, and you shall wipe it similarly
<del><fr>aff</fr></del> with a <tl>fine linen cloth</tl>. &amp; next put
the <m>ointment</m>, over which you can put <m><pa>ivy</pa> leaves</m>.
This causes <bp>hair</bp> to regrow &amp; leaves no scar. A
<pro>gunpowder maker</pro> who had almost completely burnt himself
<del><fr>m’a</fr></del> &amp; showed no sign of the burn, taught me
this.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p103r_2</id>

<head>Against <al>dogs</al>’ mange.</head>

<ab>The <pl>English</pl>, who caress their d<al>ogs</al> a lot for
taking care of their livestock, have <pro>grooms</pro> for them, who
<del>not</del> particularly hold this office. And melting <m>pitch</m>
in <m>water</m> &amp; leaving it to soak, they rub the <al>dogs</al>
with that <m>water</m>, or else with <m>water of sublimate</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
