<root>
<page>120r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f245.image</image>

<div>
<id>p120r_1</id>
<head>Medals stamped from the <m>wax</m></head>

<ab>You can mold in <m>wax</m>, mixed with a bit of <m>resin</m> so it
will be harder &amp; firmer, the relief of whatever you please, either
an animal or a medal, &amp; then, from it, make a hollow of
<m>latten</m> or <m>copper</m>. Or <del>hit it</del> <add>mold it</add>
in relief <add>and hammer it</add> in a <tl>sheet of tin</tl>,
<del><fr>Et pu</fr></del> and then fill with <m>lead</m> &amp; heat it.
Try <m>sheets of gemstone foils</m> molded in hollow for <al>lizards</al>
&amp;c.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p120r_2</id>
<head>Sand for casting in <m>gold</m></head>

<ab>Take <m>common sand</m> of <m>alum</m>, of <m>plaster</m> &amp;
<m>brick</m>, according to the composition as said above. Add to it some
more <m><fr>alum de plume</fr></m>. And mix in not the whole of a <ms>third
part</ms> of <m><la>crocum ferri</la></m>. However its quantity cannot
be harmful, for it is that which receives the <m>gold</m>, &amp; thanks
to which it comes out very neatly. But it is good that your
<m><la>crocum</la></m> will have been previously in the
<tl><pro>glassmaker's</pro> furnace</tl>, <ms>three <del>or four</del>
<tmp>days</tmp> and <del>three <tmp>days</tmp></del> and three
<tmp>nights</tmp></ms>, in a <tl>flat box</tl>, where it will be not
very thick, so that it will reheat better.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
You could cast well <m>gold</m> in <m>common sand of
<pro>goldsmiths</pro></m>, should you throw therein some substance that makes it
run. Before the invention of <m><la>crocum</la></m>, one would cast
flowers in <m>silver</m>, but not at all in <m>gold</m>. It has not been
forty <ms><tmp>years</tmp></ms> that one knows this in
<pl>Germany</pl>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<m>Sublimate</m> is commonly employed by <pro>goldsmiths</pro> for
<m>gold</m>. Some add <m>sulphur</m>, but they &amp; others are wrong,
for <m>sulphur</m> sours, even as it heats. And the <m>sublimate</m> is
agitated, boils and bubbles. It is very good to clean <m>gold</m>
because by its exhalations, it draws everything out as it goes up in
smoke. But to warm <m>gold</m>, &amp; conserve its heat, there is only
the color, which is <m>verdet</m>, <m>sal ammoniac</m>,
<m>saltpeter</m>, &amp; <m>borax</m>. This makes it run &amp; you can
throw in a <m>branch of <pa>wormseed</pa></m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p120r_3</id>
<head><del>Il</del><add><al>Nightingale</al></add></head>

<ab>One needs for the <tl>cage</tl>, made like those for <al>larks</al>
in <env>barns</env> &amp; lined with <tl><m>green fabric</m></tl>, to be
made with a <tl>drawer</tl> underneath, to refresh its fresh earth
<tmp>everyday</tmp>, for it takes much delight in this, &amp; mix in it
some <al>ants</al>. You can carry an <env>ant-hill</env> with its earth
in a <tl>barrel full of earth</tl>, &amp; keep them there &amp; they
will lay their eggs there, in order to always have some at hand when you
want them, should you take pleasure in feeding <al>nightingales</al>.
When you caught it, it is fat &amp; full, &amp;, thus, to keep it in
its strength, one needs to, for the <tmp>first day</tmp>,
<del><fr>luy</fr></del> take <add>it</add> in their
<tl><bp>hand</bp></tl> &amp; open its beak &amp; put in its beak with a
<tl>small pointed stick</tl> some <m><al>mutton</al> heart</m> or other
<m>delicate flesh</m>, chopped up not too finely, in order to fill its
belly &amp; keep it from diminishing &amp; growing leaner, until it
has gotten over its fancy. <del>The <tmp>next day</tmp> you will give
him</del> And you will feed it in this way three or four <ms>times a
<tmp>day</tmp></ms>, &amp; will also make it drink. The <tmp>next
morning</tmp>, you will give it in his <tl>cage</tl> some <m>well-minced
flesh with the yolk of a hard-boiled egg</m>, and change it two or three
<ms>times a <tmp>day</tmp></ms>, for it will not eat it if it is
hardened &amp; if it is not fresh. And if it goes <ms>half a
<tmp>day</tmp></ms> without eating, one needs to feed it as before &amp;
do so until it</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
