<root>
<page>082v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f170.item</image>

<div>

<id>p082v_1</id>

<head><pro>Clockmakers</pro></head>

<ab><tmp>In the past</tmp>, they tempered their springs by dipping them
into <m>molten lead</m>. But <tmp>today</tmp> they temper their springs
straight, &amp; bend them once tempered, which is a
<del><fr>pa</fr></del> beautiful secret.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p082v_2</id>

<head>Casting <m>lead</m> in <m>lead</m></head>

<ab>There are some who make their cavities with thick <m>lead</m>, then
cast <m>lead</m> in them.<lb/>

<m>Lead</m> when not cast hot enough, is white, &amp; blacker when cast
well hot.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

One can make a <tl><m>lead</m> mold</tl>. &amp; to cast in it, fumigate
it with <m><tl>candle</tl> soot</m>. But it is never that neat.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

Never does <m>Lead</m> come so neat as <m>tin</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p082v_3</id>

<head>Sand</head>

<ab>If it is too fat, one ought to reheat it and sieve it again.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p082v_4</id>

<head>Method of casting in <m>bronze</m></head>

<ab><m>Latten of <fr>potin</fr></m> <del><fr>cor</fr></del>, which is
the most brittle, molds more neatly, according to the opinion of many
people, than <m>fine latten of skillets</m>, just like all <m>fine
latten</m> molds neater than <m>red copper</m>. If you want to cast
something fine &amp; thin, the entire secret is to cast as hot as
possible so that the substance boils. You will recognize that it is hot
enough when it smokes a lot and while stirring it throws sparks. To heat
well, place your <tl>crucible</tl> as low as possible &amp; at the very
bottom of the <tl>forge</tl>, so that the <tl>bellows</tl>
<del><fr>fra</fr></del> beat on the middle of the <tl>crucible</tl>, for
in this way it is better than on the <tl>grill</tl> on which one usually
puts the <tl>crucible</tl>, under which the <tl>bellows</tl> beat. It is
true that the <tl>crucible</tl> risks more danger breaking, but you can
<m>lute</m> it as you know <pro>founders</pro> do. And also, one ought
to maintain the <m>charcoal</m> between the <tl>bellows</tl> &amp; the
<tl>crucible</tl>. Also take heed to cast all at once &amp; not in
increments &amp; drop by drop, which would stop &amp; plug up the
conduit of the substance. And if you were to make in the cast an
trough to feed the medal, it would be even better. And in order
that the substance heats well at the bottom, stir it, once melted, with
a <tl><m>wood</m> stick</tl>, for <m>iron</m> only makes it brittle.
Turn.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

Some put <m>wool stuffing</m> in order to heat it &amp; make it
run.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

Put under your <tl>crucible</tl> a thick <tl><m>iron</m>
slab</tl>, which will redden &amp; will maintain the heat
under your <tl>crucible</tl>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

The <m>copper</m> substance is found to be good for casting, when once
broken it makes the grain long &amp; not short, for it demonstrates that
it is soft. It is <ms>half</ms> <m>fine latten</m> &amp; <ms>half</ms>
<m>red copper</m>. This long grain is called long stalk.</ab>

</div>
</root>
