<root>
<page>0121r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f248.item</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p120v_4</id>

<ab>a sign that it has some humidity, &amp; if the flower also had some
aquosity, it would rot. It also ought not to be <del>too</del> coarse,
for with its heaviness it would weigh down the flower &amp; make it lose
its form. Having thus chosen it as is needed, take a <tl>box</tl>, in
which you first make a mound of the said sand, on which you will set the
stalk of your flower <del>so that</del> laid down so that the flower
touches neither the bottom nor the sides of the <tl>box</tl>, but
remains in the air. Then weigh down the stalk with more <del>on</del>
sand in order that it remains firm &amp; fixed. Finally take some of the
same sand &amp; with two <tl><bp>fingers</bp></tl> pulverize &amp; cast
it delicately on the flower, <del>e</del> imitating in that the flow of
an <ms><tl>hourglass</tl></ms>. And when the flower is as if
<del>half</del> covered, strike your <bp><tl>fist</tl></bp> on the table
where the <tl>box</tl> is set in order that the sand drops &amp; enters
everywhere. Finally cover it all over and lay thus there other flowers,
in order, one over the other, as many as your <tl>box</tl> can contain.
That being thus arranged, expose it for <ms><tmp>several
days</tmp></ms>to <env>hot sun</env>. And while the flower dries, the
sand, which ever accompanies it &amp; holds it, does not allow that in
contracting, it shrivels &amp; closes in on itself, rather it is
necessary that it dries in the same state as when you put it there. Now
take heed that you choose for that effect <pa>cornflowers</pa>,
<pa>marigolds</pa>, the <pa>yellow meadow flowers</pa> called
<la><pa>ranunculus</pa></la> or <la><pa>pa<corr>l</corr>ta
lupina</pa></la>, <pa>amaranth</pa> &amp; suchlike, and <pa>broom</pa>,
and others that your experience will teach you.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

The sand with which <pro>goldsmiths</pro> buff <m>enamels</m> or the
white one that <pro>glassmakers</pro> use &amp; any lean sand that does
not hold together, pass it through a <tl><m>horsehair</m> sieve</tl> for
it ought not be so thin. Next, dry it well in the <env>sun</env> for
<ms><tmp>several days</tmp></ms> to remove all humidity from it, and
ventilate it like <m>grain</m> so that the dust goes away. Once it is
rid of that dust, &amp; well dried, use it as you know.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<pa>Pansies</pa> are kept thus.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p121r_1</id>

<head>For keeping fruits all <tmp>year</tmp></head>

<ab>One needs to pick them in <env><fr>serain</fr> &amp;
<del><fr>s</fr></del> quite dry weather</env> &amp; by the stem without
<del>en</del> <sn>touching</sn> the fruit with your <bp>hand</bp>, and
put <corr>them</corr> in <tl><m>glass</m> bottles</tl> that have a wide
opening, like tall <tl><m>glass</m> boxes</tl> for putting preserves.
Fortify them with <m>straw</m> or something else, so that they may not
break, and seal them well with <m>wax</m> so that they may not breathe.
And if they had a <m>glass</m> lid well-sealed with <m>wax</m>, they
would be all the better. Put them in a <tl>case</tl> in your
<env>well</env>, or in your <env>cellar</env> in a <tl>vat, or in a
corner of earth full of <m>water</m></tl>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-bottom</margin>

For the place where the <bp>hand</bp> will <sn>touch</sn>, it will rot,
and it is even good not to <bp>breathe</bp> on them. You can also put in
<m>leaves from <pa>vine</pa></m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
