<root>
<page>159v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f324.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p159v_1</id>
<head>Cleaning files</head>

<ab>Sometimes they are fattened &amp; by means of the <m>grease</m>, the
<m>lead</m>, which is fatty in itself, or other <m>filings</m>, attach
to it. And you will be able to clean them either with <m>hot
charcoal</m> or a <tl>wire brush made of <m>wires of
latten.</m></tl></ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p159v_2</id>
<head><pa>Carnation</pa></head>

<ab>It is molded like the <pa>rose</pa>, <pa>marigold</pa>, &amp; all
other flowers, thus as is said, namely, whole-mold flowers, &amp; all
the leaves, if you want, in two halves, joining them by <m>solder</m>
for a more assured way, even if you could mold them together in a closed
<tl>mold</tl>. I cast one that came out very well. But it is necessary
that the the sand be very thin &amp; blown thoroughly.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p159v_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5LXNkdWdBLXZ1RVk</link>

</figure>

</div>
<div>
<id>p159v_3</id>
<head><tl>Molds</tl></head>

<ab>Make the two sides so that they are, <del>es</del> if it is
possible, one as thick<del>ness</del> as the other, in order that they
can be quite evenly reheated. When you mold some animal that should be
burned <del>you</del>, like <al>crayfish</al>, you cannot open it to
clean it &amp; make the cast so that it is not reheated. And when they
are reheated one time, keep them scarcely at all without casting, for
they are rendered musty &amp; moist, &amp; the <tl>mold</tl> is undone
&amp; loses its strength.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>

The part where the back of the animal is, is usually thicker.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p159v_4</id>
<head><m>Plaster</m> alone</head>

<ab>Reheated <m>stone plaster</m> <del>fears</del> is undone in
<m>water</m>, but that which is <del>reheated &amp;</del> first
pulverized and then reheated does not fear it. But if it is good it
hardens in it, like <m>the one of <pl>Paris</pl> &amp;
<pl>Spain</pl></m>, which is hard with <m>stone</m>, as is that which
grows in <env>lean &amp; dry earth</env> and which seems like <m>white
salt</m>. <pl>Germans</pl> make statues for their <env>fountains</env>
with it, which are not spoiled, especially once varnished, but it is
hardened in <m>water</m>. When it is alone &amp; not mixed, it takes
hold more quickly than otherwise. One needs to <m>oil</m> very lightly
your molds that are of <m>metal</m> or <m>stone</m>, otherwise it will
not release. And however you <m>oil</m>, one needs to wet it with <m>hot
water</m>. And when it will have taken hold &amp; is well cooled, one
needs to wet it sometimes in <m>cold water</m>, but if it refuses to
open, in <m>hot water</m> &amp; sometimes in <m>boiling water</m>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

Sometimes one even needs to make the <tl>mold</tl> boil in <m>hot
water</m>, as when you have molded some <m>wax</m> that you fear would
not be easily released from it.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>

<m>Cold water</m> makes <m>oil</m> withdraw to the surface of the
<m>plaster</m> that has sucked it in, &amp; thus it released.</ab>

</div>
</root>
