<root>
<page>123v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f252.item.r=</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p123r_1</id>

<ab>Your <m>lute</m> once dry, put, <ms><tmp>in the early
morning</tmp></ms>, your <tl>crucible</tl> in a <tl><fr>four à
vent</fr></tl>, &amp; at the beginning, give slow fire, as much for
reheating your <tl>crucible</tl> than for gently letting the fury of the
<m>saltpeter</m> pass. Then, invigorate little by little &amp; with
judgment the fire. And <del>y</del> leave in the fire’s full vigor, your
substances, for 12 <ms><tmp>hours</tmp></ms>, or a <env><tmp>natural
day</tmp></env>. Make each time a good quantity of this substance, to
not repeat it often, because the <md>fumes, which are dangerous, could
hurt you</md>. And before working at it, take in the
<ms><tmp>morning</tmp></ms> <m>good buttered toast</m>, and hold the
said <m>butter</m>, or <m><pa>zedoary</pa></m>, or <m>gold coins</m>, in
your <bp>mouth</bp>, and <del><fr>ada</fr></del> cover your
<bp>face</bp> with a <tl>cloth</tl> from the <bp>eyes</bp> down. From
this mass, the crust will serve you <del>make run</del> <add>to
clear</add> <del>the great works of</del> the <m>silver</m> <add>from
the <m>metallic</m> mass</add> <del>like <al>snakes</al> &amp; similar
things</del> <add>when it starts to melt.</add> <del>But</del> <add>And
then</add>, the grain that will be at the bottom of the
<tl>crucible</tl> should be put aside for <del>principally delicate
flowers and herbs</del> <add>putting a little in the <m>melted
silver</m> when you want to cast it</add>, <del>However is it necessary
to always put a little of this grain in the <m>silver</m> when <del>you
want to cast</del> it is well melted and when you are ready to
cast</del>. Thus, do as you make fine <m>tin</m> on <m>copper</m>,
&amp; for <m>looking-glass tin</m> on <m>lead</m> and on <m>tin</m>.
And, just as <m>looking-glass tin</m> sours <m>lead</m> and <m>tin</m>
too much, if you put it in too great a quantity, likewise, the grain
composed of the above-mentioned substances would sour your <m>silver</m>
if <del>l</del> you were to put in too much, <add>and obscure it</add>.
This above-mentioned composition will suffice you for a long time, when
it has been <ms><tmp>for a whole day</tmp></ms> on a <del>gentle</del>
gentle fire at the beginning &amp; invigorated degree by degree until
the end. Then, having given it one load of charcoal, let it consume it
by itself, &amp; let your <tl>crucible</tl> cool. Next, break it. You
will find two hard slabs &amp; <fr>tourtelles</fr> in the
<tl>crucible</tl>. The upper one is like petrified <del>Once</del>,
composed of <m>salts sublimated</m> &amp; mixed together. The lower one
is <m>metallic</m>, composed of <m>fillings</m>, <m><la>aes
ustum</la></m> &amp; <m>antimony</m>, having the grain very small.
Pulverize the upper <fr>tourtelle</fr>, made from <m>salts</m>, &amp;
put some to clear &amp; clean the <m>silver</m>, and the <m>metallic
grain</m> can be used to put in the <m>melted metal</m>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Charcoal fire</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Or else, after you have had your drugs pestled by a <pro>peasant</pro>. And
having put them in your <tl>crucible</tl>, &amp; the latter <m>luted</m> &amp;
dry as said &amp; placed into the <tl>furnace</tl>, have the fire
managed by a <pro><env>shop</env> boy</pro>, familiar with charcoal.
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
One sells well to <pro>silversmiths</pro> this <m>metallic</m> mass to
soften their <m>solder</m>, because when melting, <m>latten</m> exhales.
And with a little of this substance, they <m>solder</m> over the other
<m>solder</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
