<root>
<page>020v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f46.image</image>

<div>

<id>p020v_1</id>

<head>For whitening the <bp>face</bp></head>

<ab>Pestle <m><pa>puffball</pa></m> in <m>cistern water</m>, &amp; no
other, &amp; wash with this <m>whitened water</m>. This is considered
quite exquisit. And I believe that making it from <m><pa>wheat</pa>
starch</m> &amp; to use it would be even better.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p020v_2</id>

<head>Against winds, colic, &amp;c.</head>

<ab><m>Sap squeezed or water <del><ill/></del> distilled from
<pa>orange</pa> peel</m> is excellent against the windy colic.
<m>Candied peel</m>, too, is excellent for the winds of the
<bp>belly</bp>. And to make a trial of it, having poured <m>foaming
wine</m> in a <tl><m>glass</m></tl>, squeeze <m><pa>orange</pa>
juice</m> on the <m>wine foam</m>, which proceeds only from vapor &amp;
wind, and you will see that the foam will immediately disappear. Also,
if you squeeze <m>juice</m> against a <tl>candle</tl> it will burn all
the brighter.

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p020v_3</id>

<head><pa>Skirret</pa> root</head>

<ab>They want to be planted <env>in a very humid place where with such
<oc>puys rodier</oc> or fountain one can water it often</env>, for by
this means they are tender. Otherwise they make a hard heart inside,
which takes from it all its goodness.

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p020v_4</id>

<head>Against burn</head>

<ab>Pestle an <m><pa>onion</pa></m> with <m>verjuice</m> &amp; leave it
to soak like this, then apply it.

Or else, apply <m>black soap</m> on the burn. Experimented.

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p020v_5</id>

<head>Common saying</head>

<ab>Bell tower of <pl>Rodez</pl>, <env>church</env> of <pl>Albi</pl>,
bells of <pl>Mende</pl>. However, one holds the <corr>bell</corr> of
<pl>Toulouse</pl> named Cardaillac as one of the most beautiful in
<pl>France</pl>, all the more since it weighs two hundred and fifty
<ms><fr>quintals</fr></ms>.

</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p020v_6</id>

<head>A form of regimen</head>

<ab><tmp>Every morning</tmp>, take two or three <m>eggs</m> laid one or
two <tmp>days</tmp> ago. Heat them <del>until</del> &amp; do not cook
them. Take the <m>yolks</m> well dusted with <m>sugar</m>. And next
drink one <ms><bp>finger</bp></ms> of <m>wine</m>. And apart from being
nourishing, it makes a good <bp>stomach</bp>.

</ab>

</div>
</root>
