<root>
<page>118r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f241.image</image>

<div>
<id>p118r_1</id>
<head><al>Snails</al></head>

<ab>Those which are found in the <env>sea</env> &amp; similarly those in
which certain <al>small crabs</al> dwell are very beautiful for
<env>grottos</env>, if they are stripped of the first crust of their
shell with <m>aquafortis</m>, for they truly appear to be made of
<m>mother-of-pearl</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p118r_2</id>
<head>For removing flashing and barbs from things molded <fr>en
noyau</fr></head>

<ab>If your <tl>molds</tl> are of <m>good plaster</m> which withstands
well the fire <del>&amp;</del>, they will not crack at all, especially
if, with <tl>presses</tl>, they are squeezed well between two
<tl>boards</tl> or in a <tl>vessel filled with <m>ashes</m> or
sand</tl>, &amp; in this way they will make no flashing. But if they do
make some, you can remove it with a <tl>burin</tl> that one calls
<tl><df><fr>chaple</fr></df></tl>, which has a tip like a small
<tl>chisel</tl>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p118r_3</id>
<head>For <env>grottos</env></head>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The <m>old <pa>vine</pa> stocks</m></ab>

<ab><m>Stones made from water</m> called <m><df>stuf</df></m>;
<m>charcoal</m>; the <m>compound of tin &amp; fine latten</m>; <m>paper
pestled</m> &amp; mixed with <m><tl>pestled</tl> glass</m>; <m>cork</m>;
<m>heated parchment</m>; <m>white coral</m> are appropriate for making
<env>grottos</env>. But <m>fantastical pieces of wood</m> which are
found in the <env>forests</env> &amp; <m><pa>mushrooms</pa></m> and
<m><pa><fr>potirons</fr></pa> of trees</m>, once dry, are better than
any other because they are light. One mixes in small pieces of
<m>looking-glass tin</m> which has a shiny luster. One finely pestles in
a different kind of <m>marcasite</m> which one washes to cleanse them of
<m>earth</m>, &amp;one sprinkles the work with it, which is very
beautiful. If there is no fountain in the <env>grotto</env>, one
<m>glues</m> all <del><fr>al</fr></del> of this with <m><fr>colle
forte</fr></m>, <del>which</del> and it is soon done. <add>Take
specimens of all kinds of <m>mines</m>. The <m>sulfurous marcasites</m>,
which do not have a grain but are even like <m>looking-glass tin</m>,
are very beautiful.</add></ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<m><fr>Rosette</fr></m> is found sometimes mixed with certain brittle
lumps which are pulverized under the <tl>hammer</tl>, which are very
beautiful pulverized on <env>grottos</env>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p118r_4</id>
<head><m>Looking-glass tin</m></head>

<ab>It whitens &amp; renders <m>firm fine tin</m> if <del><fr>en
on</fr></del> one puts <del>in</del> in one <ms>ounce</ms> of it, that
is to say, i <ms>℥</ms> of <m>looking-glass tin</m> in
one <ms>lb</ms> of fine <m>tin</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p118r_5</id>
<head><m>Sal ammoniac</m></head>

<ab><del>It</del><m>Sal ammoniac water</m> is very natural for casting
in <m>gold</m> &amp; in <m>silver</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
