<root>
<page>091r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f187.image</image>

<div>

<id>p091r_1</id>

<head>Grafting</head>

<ab>Every tree that has coarser marrow, <add>the graft</add> is awkward
to <del><fr>estre</fr></del> cut <add>well</add>, because there is a
danger of wounding the marrow, &amp; if it is wounded at the point of
juncture, it takes uneasily, like from the <pa>vine</pa>, from all
<pa>peaches</pa> &amp; <pa>apricots</pa>.</ab>

<ab><pa>Apricot trees</pa> have a very thin bark, &amp; thus one needs
to graft them onto young trees which do not yet have thick bark, like on
shoots of <pa>prune trees</pa> &amp; <pa>almond trees</pa>.</ab>

<ab>The grafts scarcely <del><ill/></del> take if the cut of the tree is
dampened. One needs then to graft in <env><fr>serain</fr> &amp; mild
weather, &amp; not too cold &amp; windy</env>.</ab>

<ab>Old wood that one leaves to graft is necessary if one grafts on a
tree that is already made &amp; of good size, because being such, it
tightens the graft more, &amp; if it is from young wood, it is so
compressed that it cannot profit. But old wood resists the compression
of old wood <del>than the young</del> better, because it is harder than
the young. But if the graft is all of old wood, it will never hold
beautifully, but turns fragile &amp; short &amp; slow to
grow.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p091r_2</id>

<head>Molding with <tl><m><al>cuttlefish</al> bone</m></tl></head>

<ab>Guard against keeping them <env>in a damp place</env>, for they are
well prone to getting moist. If your medal is small, cut the <m>bone</m>
in two then even it out with a <tl>knife</tl>. And on a <tl>hooked
<m>rooftile</m></tl>, well dry &amp;well smooth &amp; covered with
<m>pulverized <pa>willow</pa> charcoal</m>, rub &amp; smooth the two
half <tl><m>bones</m></tl>. Thus they imbibe this <m><pa>willow</pa>
charcoal</m>, which makes them release, &amp; guard against removing
anything. Then on a <tl>counter bone</tl>, that is to say a lump of
<m>brick</m>, smoothed to the size of your <tl><m>bone</m></tl>, place
your medal, &amp; then on this one, place the <tl><m>bone</m></tl>,
&amp; press well with some other piece of the same size above. And for
the second time, mold it, but before, <fr>ponce</fr> on top with
<m><pa>willow</pa> charcoal</m> &amp; blow gently, then press as before,
and it will come out neatly. If it is for a spoon handle, one needs two
whole <tl><m>bones</m></tl>. All cast work is brittle &amp; subject to
breaking, because the <m>metal</m> expands when cast, &amp; retracts
&amp; condenses when <tl>hammered</tl>. That is why, one ought to
retrace the cast thing with a <tl>chisel</tl>, &amp; in this way the
<m>metal</m> retracts, and let it thus <fr>escrouir</fr>. If the piece
for molding is of high relief, first trace the <tl>mold</tl> &amp; the
cavity with a <tl>pen-knife</tl>, to make way for the medal &amp; then
mold. And if the medal has two sides</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>Before casting, heat the
<tl><m>bones</m></tl> in order to make them lose only the coldness &amp;
dampness.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>When the <m>lead</m> gets too hot, it
calcines.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
