






Stamped medals from wax

You can mold in wax, mixed with a bit of rosin so it
will be harder &amp; firmer, the relief of whatever you please, either
an animal or a medal, &amp; then, from it, make a hollow form of
latten or copper. Or, hit it mold it
in relief and hammer it in a sheet of tin,
Et pu and then fill with lead &amp; heat it.
Try sheets of gemstone foils molded in a hollow form for lizards,
&amp;c.





Sand for casting in gold

Take common sand of alum, of plaster &amp;
brick, according to the composition said above. Add to it some
more feather alum. And mix in not quite the third
part of crocum ferri. However, its quantity cannot
be harmful, for it is that which receives the gold &amp; thanks
to which it comes out very neatly. But it were good that your
crocum had previously been in the
glassmaker’s fornaise, three or four
days and three days and three
nights, in a flat box where it should not be very thick, so that it reheats better.



You could cast gold well in common sand of
goldsmiths, should you throw therein some substance that makes it
run. Before the invention of crocum, one would cast
flowers in silver but not at all in gold. It has not been
forty years that one knows this in
Germany.



Sublimate is commonly employed by goldsmiths for
gold. Some add sulfur, but they &amp; others are wrong,
for sulfur sours, even as it heats. And the sublimate is
agitated, boils, and bubbles. It is very good to clean gold
because by its exhalations, it draws everything out as it goes up in
smoke. But to warm gold &amp; conserve its heat, there is only
the couleur, which is verdet, sal ammoniac,
saltpeter &amp; borax. This makes it run, &amp; you can
throw in a branch of wormseed.





IlNightingale

One needs for the cage, made like those for larks
like a barn &amp; lined with green fabric, to be
made with a drawer underneath, to refresh its fresh earth
everyday, for it takes much delight in this, &amp; mix in it
some ants. You can carry an anthill with its earth
in a barrel full of earth, &amp; keep them there &amp; they
will lay their eggs there, in order to always have some at hand when you
want them, should you take pleasure in feeding nightingales.
When you have taken it, it is fat &amp; full, &amp; thus, to keep it in
its strength, one needs to, for the first day,
take uyit in the
hand &amp; open its beak &amp; put in its beak with a
small pointed stick some mutton heart or other
delicate flesh, chopped up not too finely, in order to fill its
belly &amp; keep it from diminishing &amp; growing leaner, until it
has gotten over its fancy. The next day you will give
him And you will feed it in this way three or four times a
day &amp; will also make it drink. The next
morning, you will give it in its cage some well-minced
flesh with the yolk of a hard-boiled egg, and change it two or three
times a day, for it will not eat it if it is
hardened &amp; if it is not fresh. And if it goes half a
day without eating, one needs to feed it as before &amp;
do so until it





