<root>
<page>059r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f123.item</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p058v_5</id>

<ab><m>Lake</m> &amp; <m>lead white</m> &amp; <m>ceruse</m> are easy to
work in <m>oil</m>, but every kind of <m>azure</m> is difficult. And to
make beautiful <m>azure</m>, one needs to layer it not with large
strokes of the <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> but with small strokes of the
point. Not only <m>ash <sup>from <pl>Acre</pl></sup></m> &amp;
<m><fr>azur d’Acre</fr></m> but mainly <m><fr>azur d’esmail</fr></m>
which one needs to choose to be very delicate, <del>for it</del>
otherwise you will not <del><fr>v</fr></del> be able to work with it
except with great work, and even then you need to thin it with
<m>turpentine</m> to give it body, and mix it with a little <m>lead
white</m>. Any <m>azure</m> does not want to be ground or washed for it
loses color &amp; becomes wan. But putting it powdered on your
<tl>palette</tl>, you will thin it little by little either with
<m><pa>walnut</pa> oil</m> or <m>turpentine oil</m>,
<corr>dipping</corr> a <tl>knife point</tl> in <m>oil</m>, then
<corr>tempering</corr> it little by little on the said
<tl>palette</tl>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p059r_1</id>

<head>Shadows</head>

<ab>The first shadows which are closer to light need to be clear &amp;
thoroughly softened &amp; then the last ones very dark to accentuate
well. The <pl>Italians</pl> usually make three shadows, the first one,
of light, very clear, the second one darker &amp; the third ones quite
strong, then blend these three shadows together by hatching them from
the darkest to the clearest.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<render>tall</render>

The <m>varnish</m> is more beautiful on the panel when the color has
imbibed well.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p059r_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5QWJmbC1RaG8zTGM</link>

</figure>

</div>

<div>

<id>p059r_2</id>

<head><m>Azure</m></head>

<ab><m>Azure</m> is more beautiful when imbibed on the panel
<del>without</del> with <m><pa>walnut</pa> oil</m> with which it has
been first thinned, without putting in <m><pa>spike lavender</pa>
oil</m>. And if you want to know if it is dry, breathe on it and it will
not shine, thus appearing to be well-imbibed. If not it will shine</ab>

<ab><m>Azur d'esmail </m> <del>imbibed in <m>oil</m></del> distempered
in <m>oil</m>, leaves it &amp; returns to its first nature if you dip it
in <m>water</m>.</ab>

<ab>Colors for working in miniature want to be thoroughly ground, &amp;
work them with a point of a <tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl> if you want your
work to be well-softened.</ab>

</div>
</root>
