<root>
<page>082r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f169.image</image>

<div>
<id>p082r_1</id>
<head> Heat of <m>copper</m></head>

<ab>It is hot enough when you see it neat &amp; even on top, without
<m>filth</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p082r_2</id>
<head><tl>Frame</tl></head>

<ab><m>Iron</m> &amp; <m>copper</m> make it porous if the <m>metal</m>
touches it, &amp; the <m>wood</m> warps. Thus, make a mold of
<m>wood</m>, &amp; have <tl>frames</tl> of <m>bricks</m> made inside this mold of
whatever thickness that you want.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p082r_3</id>
<head><m>Glair of eggs</m></head>

<ab><m>Glair of eggs</m> gives strength to sand to make several
casts.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p082r_4</id>
<head><pro>Clockmakers</pro></head>

<ab>To divide the teeth of their cogwheels proportionately, they do not
use a <tl>compass</tl>, for there is none so fine that it can
<tl>compass</tl> <ms>distances as small as those of the small
cogwheels</ms>. But they make a <fr>platteforme</fr> (as they call it)
of <m>latten</m> <del><fr>fais</fr></del> divided into several circles,
&amp; each circle is divided into <ms>equal distances</ms> marked by a
point, and each circle has a certain number of them, for example one 30,
another 36, another 40, &amp;c. Then, on the pierced center of the
<fr>platteforme</fr>, they set the small cogwheel there, and on the
center of the cogwheel a flat line or alidade which is moved to the
circle with the number that you want to mark on your cogwheel. Then they
draw a line on the cogwheel with a <tl>prick</tl>, then move the alidade
to the following point, &amp; continue to mark thus. And to mark the
points on the circles of their <fr>platteforme</fr>, they divide the
circle into three &amp; then divide this <ms>third part into as many
distances as is necessary with regard to the total division of the
circle</ms>, &amp; make in this manner their division &amp; distribution
of the teeth as fine as they please.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p082r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5MG1jZS1LOUE2QWs</link>

</figure>

</div>
</root>
