<root>
<page>148r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f301.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p147v_4</id>

<ab>not come out as clear as I wanted. I reheated it again, let it cool,
put it into the <m>bleach</m> again, and brushed <x>it</x>. It came out
very clear. In this way, you will do <x>the same</x> for <m>copper</m>
and <m>silver</m>. And if you want to give...</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p148r_1</id>

<head>Beautiful color for <m>latten</m></head>

<ab>Having cleaned it well, as is said, &amp; wire-brushed it well, make
it boil in water &amp; <m>turmeric root</m> or <m><fr>terra
merita</fr></m>, and it will become very beautiful.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p148r_2</id>

<head><m><fr>Whitening</fr></m></head>

<ab>If it is for <m>silver</m>, do not pestle your <m>tartar</m> with
<m>iron</m>, but with the handle of a hammer, for if you touch &amp; dip
<m>iron</m> in your whitening, the <m>silver</m> would become red like
<m>copper</m> &amp; you would need to reheat it &amp; put it again in
<m>whitening</m>. Mix nothing with your <m>tartar</m> that should not
enter the <m>whitening</m>, for this corrupts it. Do not let it spill
out of its first boil, for in this is all its strength. The
<m>whitening</m> is made with one part pulverized <m>tartar</m> &amp; a
half of common <m>salt</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p148r_3</id>

<head>Moulding the foot of the bittern, or of the eagle, or of other
birds for the foot of saltcellars or vases</head>

<ab>One usually molds the foot &amp; the leg up to the joint. And for
this effect, one molds it in five pieces: the leg in two pieces, the top
of the foot in two, and the bottom in one piece.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>in three pieces</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p148r_4</id>

<head><m>Crocum ferri</m></head>

<ab>To make this quickly, redden the <m>filings</m> in an <m>iron</m>
case, stirring it often. Then sprinkle it with good <m>vinegar</m> &amp;
let it evaporate &amp; without removing it from atop the fire,
<del>rou</del> let it redden &amp; inflame. Once cooled, pulverise it on
the <m>marble</m> &amp; return it to the fire, sprinkle with
<m>vinegar</m>, and then inflame. Thus it will quickly be colored &amp;
made fine.</ab>

</div>
</root>
