<root>
<page>114v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f234.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p114r_1</id>

<figure>

<id>fig_p114v_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dmlRQm1lTjc4aXc</link>

</figure>

<ab>This thus prepared, place your <del><fr>de</fr></del> first
half-<tl>mold</tl> on the <fr>tourtelle</fr> of <del><m>earth</m></del>
<m>clay</m>, &amp; put the circle also around, &amp; make the mark for
the thickness similar to the first. Then, with another rather thickish
<tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl>, moisten well everywhere the uncovered half
<del>&amp; belly</del> of your animal
<del><fr>Et</fr></del> <add>with <m>eau-de-vie</m></add>,
without leaving anything, if it is possible, which is not moistened, for
this is the secret, which makes it come out neat. And next, as promptly
as possible, before the <m>eau-de-vie</m>
<del><fr>ne</fr></del> evaporates, wet your sand, and throw it, in
shakes, and while blowing, &amp; moving the <tl>mold</tl>, as you did
for the first one, making sure that the <del><fr>premier q</fr></del>
first thing you pour on the animal should be a little clearer than the
next one, so that it moistens everywhere &amp;retrace the more delicate
parts. So, leave it for a <ms><tmp>quarter hour</tmp></ms> to set, then
remove the circle &amp; the <m>clay</m> <fr>tourtelle</fr>. And, with a
<tl>knife</tl>, arrange your two <tl>molds</tl> uniformly together in a
long shape of a <mu>mandore</mu>, as mentioned, because of the cast.
Then dip a little the whole <tl>mold</tl> evenly, at the level of the
joints, in <m>water</m>, for this is another secret to unjoin them,
otherwise you will break everything. Separate them nimbly, therefore, by
this means, and next, extract gently &amp; with patience and immediacy
the half of the animal remaining in one of the <tl>molds</tl>,
<del>for</del> pulling it sometimes from one side &amp; sometimes from
the other, to avoid breaking any of it, or also spoiling something from
your <tl>mold</tl>. <del><fr>Et</fr></del> The latter being empty,
<del><fr>retire</fr></del> rejoints the two halves so that no dust
enters it, &amp; put them aside until you want to reheat them, make a
cast &amp; vents, &amp; place <tl>clamps</tl>. As for the animal, so
that it does not dry &amp; that you might be able to mold it four of
five times, put in in <m>water</m>. And I think that it would keep even
better in <m>eau-de-vie</m>. However, the best would be to mold
in the same <tmp>day</tmp> the 4 or 5 <tl>molds</tl> that you can do,
because these infected animals themselves are <sn>stinky</sn> in one
<ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms>. Having left your <tl>molds</tl> one or two
<del><fr>es</fr></del> <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms> to dry, for they stay
damp for a good <ms><tmp>month</tmp></ms>, make the vents on one
half.<figure>

<id>fig_p114v_3</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dkk3MW10YzNIbDg</link>

</figure></ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<mark>+</mark> Note that when you have made your second
<add>cast</add>, if you leave your <tl>mold</tl>, for one
<ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms> or a <ms><tmp>night</tmp></ms>, without opening
it, you would need to then dip it in <m>hot water</m>, or else reheat it
before opening it, as for <al>crabs</al>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

If after both halves of the noyau have made a strong &amp; hard set, you
would not dip your <tl>mold</tl> in <m>water</m>, it would not unjoin at
all. But as you dip the reverse of the <tl>mold</tl> in <m>water</m>,
the imbibed <m>oil</m> collects at the top &amp; at the level of the
joints &amp; and makes it separate.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

However, take heed your second <tl>mold</tl> be of good thickness &amp;
that it is hard enough because if it is lacking in this, after having
dipped it in <m>water</m>, &amp; you want to open it, there is a risk
that it breaks. Take heed therefore to avoid this, and wanting to open
it, dip all of it in <m>water</m>, <add>and rub it everywhere</add>,
where it will harden if it has set well.Then, take your two
<tl>molds</tl>, joined with a <tl>rough <m>linen</m> cloth</tl>, in in
order to have a better grip, and separate them with strength as if you
wanted to quarter a loaf of <m>bread</m>. But if happens to break, join
it &amp; on the reverse, strenghten the joints with <tl>clamps</tl>.

<figure>

<id>fig_p114v_4</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NmZxVUxKTmhYSXM</link>

</figure>

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>bottom</margin>

Next, you can repair the faults with small <tl>chisels</tl>.

<cont/>

</ab>

</div>
</root>
