<root>
<page>144v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f294.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p144r_1</id>

<ab>having been thus arranged &amp; well cleaned with
<tl>brushes</tl>, place <del>the</del> the <tl>circle of
<m>clay</m></tl> around the <tl>slab</tl>. Then, with a <tl>band of
<m>clay</m></tl> placed on the middle of <del><fr>e</fr></del> the
<del>the</del> back of the <al>turtle</al>, as you see, &amp; at the
widest place, divide your <tl>mold</tl>. Subsequently, <m>oil</m> with
your <m><fr>pinceau</fr></m>, dedicated for this, the half of the shell
you want to mold. Wet in <m>hot water</m>, <sn>so that without burning
yourself, you can hold your <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl> in it without
burning yourself</sn>, your sand, a little <del><fr>p</fr></del> thick.
And <del><fr>f</fr></del> before throwing it, rub the shell with
<m>eau-de-vie</m>. And next, cast your sand &amp; let it set and note
that all things that have shells, or that are hard, or are not
malleable, like <al>snakes</al> &amp; <al>lizards</al>, want to be
<m>oiled</m> to release. Things that are malleable do not need this.
<m>Hot water</m> makes the wet sand <del>in <m>water</m></del> set
better on <m>oil</m>, which otherwise would be refused. Your half of the
<al>turtle</al>, having thus <del><fr>desp</fr></del> been molded,
separate it with its <tl>half mold</tl>, from the <tl><m>clay</m>
slab</tl>, that you will set aside to return it to when it is necessary.
Next, clean your <tl>half mold</tl> &amp; smooth it &amp; flatten, like
the others. But because it happens that because <del><fr>u</fr></del> of
the <m>clay</m> <fr>entredeux</fr>, the <tl>half mold</tl> will consist
of more than half of the <al>turtle</al>, cut &amp; pair down smoothly
the excess, &amp; clean everything well with <tl>brushes</tl>. Then,
make on the top edge of the <tl>mold</tl>, on the side that is cut &amp;
halfway, two notches, like for other <tl>molds</tl> and return your
<al>turtle</al> to its <tl>slab</tl>, as it was &amp; secure its two
legs, which are not molded, with <tl><m>iron wire</m> points</tl>. And
stuff all around what is empty, up until the edge of the top shell with
<m>clay</m>. Next, place the <tl>circle</tl> around and put a
<m>clay</m> <fr>entredeulx</fr> on the first <tl>mold</tl>, a little
above the notches. And having <m>oiled</m> the <del><fr>d</fr></del>
first <tl>half mold</tl> &amp; its notches and the shell of the
<al>turtle</al>, &amp; having also showered it with <m>eau-de-vie</m>,
heat your <m>water</m>, wet you sand with a little <m>water of sal
ammoniac</m> &amp; the said <m>hot water</m>, &amp; cast. Having set,
adapt the sides of these two <tl>molds</tl> smoothly &amp; on each side
secure their joint, which only recognize each other a little, with two
<tl>clamps</tl>, in order that when uncovering afterwards the underneath
of the <al>turtle</al>, they are not undone. Next, uncover the side of
the belly &amp; of the throat, in the way that you uncover a
<al>crayfish</al>, which is the most difficult to mold of the little
beasts, which are molded in two halves.</ab>

<figure>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<id>fig_p144v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5ZGhySWFITlRSaG8</link>

</figure>

<figure>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<id>fig_p144v_2</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SlhGM2FYLUUteXc</link>

</figure>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

You can mold the <al>turtle</al> with one piece for each side, but one
would need to burn it. And afterwards, to make the hollow, the reheated
<tl>mold</tl> cannot be <m>oiled</m> because it drinks the
<m>oil</m>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>+</mark>

If there is some <m><la>crocum</la></m> in the sand, the joints of the
<tl>molds</tl> will almost not recognize each other. </ab>

<ab>

<man><margin>bottom</margin>

Turn to the second leaf.</man></ab>

</div>
</root>
