<root>
<page>136v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f278.image</image>

<div>

<id>p136v_1</id>

<head>For casting with <m>latten</m></head>

<ab>The <m>latten</m> from skillets, where one makes the mush for
<pro>little children</pro>, which is <fr>doulx</fr>, is appropriate for
the cast. Some say that <m><pl>German</pl> tokens</m> <del>are</del>
contain a lot of <m>calamine</m>. However, as they are thin, the
<m>calamine</m> ex<add>h</add>ales out when melting them, as it does in
all <del><fr>meta</fr></del> remelted latten, which through melting
again returns red. However, <m>fresh calamine</m> &amp; on its own, put
again on melted <m>latten</m>, makes it run &amp; cast neatly, because
the one that is in the remelted <del><fr>de</fr></del> <m>latten</m> is
half corrupted in its natural state, &amp; makes it become porous &amp;
blusters because it is disposed to exhaling. Therefore use
<m>calamine</m> alone, on its own, very recent, on the melted
<m>latten</m>. Take heed to cast very hot &amp; that your <tl>mold</tl>
be red like for <m>gold</m>, <m>silver</m>, <m>copper</m> &amp;
<m>metal</m>. If you cast with recent <m>calamine</m>, <md>keep yourself
away from the <m>smoke</m>, for it is pernicious</md>. I wanted to use
<m><pl>German</pl> tokens</m> to cast medals &amp; took thirty &amp; xii
<m>nails of <fr>rosette</fr></m>, like for chairs, which are of
<m><fr>doulx</fr> latten</m>. This substance, containing a lot of
<m>calamine</m>, like all <m>strong yellow latten</m>, strongly smoked,
which is what prevents <m>latten</m> from running<add> and makes it
porous</add>. Make many vents &amp; cast very hot, that your
<m>latten</m> is white like <m>water</m> or <m>melted silver</m> &amp;
similar to a very polished <m>steel</m> mirror. The second fusion comes
out better, because there is exhaled <m>calamine</m> and does not make
as much <m>smoke</m>. If it is in a <tl>frame</tl> which does not break
&amp; withstands <del><fr>a</fr></del>, the second cast comes out neat,
because it is imbued with <m>calamine smoke</m>, which embraces &amp;
receives the second one. <m>Sal ammoniac</m> alone, put in
<m>latten</m>, renders it neat &amp; shiny. <m><fr>Huile
tingente</fr></m> even more so. It does not need any sand other than the
previous in <fr>noyau</fr> &amp; that the <tl>mold</tl> be red like for
<m>gold</m>. Make many vents. And if you cast <m>yellowed latten</m>
with the <m>prepared tutty</m>, you will not have any <m>bad smoke</m>.
</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

This <m>metal</m> is very fanciful to cast, because of the <m>calamine
smoke</m>, and one ought not leave it <del><fr>pass</fr></del> rest even
a little bit outside the fire, like some do with <m>silver</m>, for it
is immediately cold when it feels <env>the air</env> and <env>the
wind</env>. It always leaves some type of tail, like <m>glass</m>, when
you cast it. <pro>Casters</pro> do not usually take that <m>very yellow
latten</m>, because of the <m>calamine</m> passed through the fire. But
when wanting to cast <m>red copper</m>, they yellow it either with
<m>fresh calamine</m>, or with <m>prepared tutty</m>. Wanting to cast,
one purifies it well of <m>charcoal</m>, with a <tl>stalk of
<m>copper</m> or <m>iron</m></tl>, and one covers it with a
<tl><m>cloth</m>, soaked in <m><al>pig</al> fat</m>, mixed with
<add><m>saltpeter</m></add> or <m>sal ammoniac</m></tl> to keep it from
the <env>wind</env> &amp; from cooling. </ab>

</div>
</root>
