<root>
<page>155r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f315.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p155r_1</id>
<head>Molding a rose</head>

<ab>Because the little branches of the rose bush which are
<del>aupart</del> around the flower are sometimes very spread out &amp;
would make too large a mold, one makes <add>and molds</add> them
separately, and the rose &amp; some buds separately. And then one joins
them with solder, the little branches &amp; leaves of the rose bush to
the stem of the rose, on which one intentionally leaves the little tips
of the small branches. Put your leaf or rose as low as you can in the
mold because the <m>sand</m> always raises it up. You <del>en</del> can
also mold several petals together, once arranged one on top of the
other, separating them with threads, as is said. And regarding the rose,
you can give a thin layer of <m>melted butter</m> on the back of the
petal, <del>of</del> <add>on the first petals on the outside, not those
on the inside</add> <del>be</del>, to fortify it &amp; give it the
strength to withstand, <add>in order that the wet sand does not spread
out &amp; expand more than it should.</add> You <del>them</del> can also
mold well the leaves of rose bushes, strawberry plants, &amp; similar
things, that are flat &amp; can be flattened without spoiling them, with
two gates; to open your mold when it is reheated &amp;clean the ashes
from it, <del>All</del>, and make vents &amp; several gates. And this is
the easiest way, but the other can also be done. And with a <m>wax</m>
sprue applied &amp; joined from petal to petal, you can make casts. You
can even make a <m>wax</m> sprue from <add>the back of</add> the first
petal <del>until</del>, which will join to the cast. All of this
facilitates the cast. <del>Aulcu</del> The principal thing is to let
your reheated molds cool down well, rather than cleaning them &amp;
blowing inside them to make the wax come out, because when the mold is
hot, the ash holds to it as if attached. But when it is cold, it wanders
and leaves with air or when one blows one's breath through the small
opening. </ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p155r_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5b3lFZ18wbGducEk</link>

</figure>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
You can give quite a little thickness at the ends of the stalks that
support the leaves, greasing them lightly underneath with <m>melted
butter</m>, because the leaves are large &amp; weighty, and the stalk of
<m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m> would not have enough strength.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
I would be of the opinion to mold the rose on its own with a little of
its stem close to its bud, &amp; then to join it to a longer one of
tinned <m>letton</m>, because the bloomed rose has great volume &amp;
weight.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>bottom</margin>
Wet the rose with <m>eau-de-vie</m> before putting it in the circle of
clay. Do not forget to oil the gate with <m>wax</m>. And when you will
have cast your <m>wet sand</m>, blow thoroughly, until it begins to take
hold. The rose came out well. But because the <m>sand</m> is found mixed
among the petals, make your work soak in water for a long time in order
that shaking it in the water, the earth is gone from it.</ab>

</div>
</root>
