<root>
<page>143v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f292.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p143r_3</id>

<ab>one leg up to the other, in order that the spread out extremities
come to join one with the other by means of the said gates,
which you will start in the round parts, empty of <m>wax</m>, that you
have put at the end of the feet to attract the <m>metal</m>. Thus, the
gate being made by <m>wax</m>, you are in no danger of encrusting
something from the molded animal. And it is more expedient to make
thus the gate of <m>wax</m>, to cast the second mold on top, than to
wait to do them after the <tl>mold</tl> is
reheated<del><fr>q</fr></del>, for at that point, it is necessary, if
possible, that everything be ready. One needs to heat well &amp; even
redden the <tl>molds</tl>, where they are gates of <m>wax</m>, in order
that it melts well &amp; leaves nothing inside.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p143v_1</id>

<head>Carcanets made <fr>à jour</fr></head>

<ab>They are molded like <al>crayfish</al> in <fr>noyau</fr>, first with
one side being raised up with <m>clay</m> which is hollow, &amp; then
one uncovers them from the other side &amp; one makes the second
casting. They can also be cast well in <tl>frames</tl>, provided
that they are released easily. If they are not, one models them in
<m>wax</m>, or else one fills the cavities that were not able to release
with <m>wax</m> or <m>clay</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p143v_2</id>

<head><m>Iron filings</m></head>

<ab>Because usually <m>filings</m> are mixed with <m>nastiness</m>, it
is good to redden them in fire to burn the <m>impurities</m>, and then
wash them in <m>clear water</m>. In this way, the dirt will go to the
top of the <m>water</m>, that you throw out, &amp; the <m>good
filings</m> will go to the bottom.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p143v_3</id>

<head><pa>Carnations</pa></head>

<ab>Because the ones that are cast are usually massive, <del>or
<fr>bi</fr></del> they are weighty &amp; for this reason, one makes them
with <m>leaves &amp; blades of silver</m>.</ab></div>
</root>
