<root>
<page>005v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f16.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p005r_2</id>

<ab>string &amp; will reflect a <bp>nipple</bp> as large as a plate, and
<pro>women</pro> can see the <bp>secret places</bp> that they do not
want to show to <pro>surgeons</pro>. It casts the representation out of
itself, and if you <sn>touch</sn> <del><fr>le lieu</fr></del> the eye of
the representation with your <bp>finger</bp>, another <bp>finger</bp>
will come against yours.</ab>

<ab>You will make a light <tmp>at night</tmp> for someone quite far
away, if you place the <tl>concave mirror</tl> behind a <tl>candle</tl>
placed on the <tl><env>window</env></tl>. You can read and write quite
far from the <tl>candle</tl> if you place it behind the <tl>candle</tl>
&amp; place <add>&amp; turn</add> the concavity towards you. If you put
the <tl>mirror</tl> <ms>at the end of a <tl>table</tl></ms> &amp; a
<tl>candle</tl> on it, it will represent two lights on the
<tl>table</tl> for you. To see what is happening on a <env>street</env>,
shutter the <env>window</env>, and the more you can shut there the
better. Make a hole at the lower pane, as wide as your <ms><bp>little
finger</bp></ms>, perfectly round, from one side to the other. Then
place a <tl>sheet of <m>paper</m></tl> on the <tl><env>window</env></tl>
&amp; let the <ms>middle of the <tl>sheet</tl></ms> be over the hole.
Pierce the <tl>sheet</tl> in the same place as the hole &amp; the same
size. After, aim the concave face of the <tl>mirror</tl> towards the
hole, &amp; it will represent for you anyone passing by in the
<env>street</env> on the <tl>sheet of <m>paper</m></tl>. Similarly with
the <env>pierced door of a closed room</env>. You can make wavy ones
&amp; triangular ones, in the fashion described by <pn>Ptolemy</pn> &amp;
<pn>Archimedes</pn>. The concave one also sets fire to <m>straw</m>,
lights a <tl><m>candle</m></tl> from afar, using the <env>sun</env>. By
reverberating fire too, it heats.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p005v_1</id>
<head>For bronzing in yellow and white</head>

<ab>Take <m>looking-glass tin</m> and melt it. On <ms>half a lb</ms> of
this, put <ms>half an ounce</ms> of <m>quicksilver</m>, and remove it
all at once from the fire &amp; grind it, and it will be like
<m>ash</m>. <del>Grind</del> Wash it quite well in <m>clean water</m>.
After, grind it on <tl><m>marble</m></tl> &amp; soak it with <m>water of
<del><fr>ret</fr></del> <fr>colle de retailles</fr></m>. After, apply to
your <m>wooden</m> candlesticks &amp; any other work you like,
&amp; burnish with the <tl>tooth</tl>. You can grind <m>pin filings</m>
and apply them with the said <m>glue</m>. </ab>

</div>
</root>
