<root>
<page>080v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f166.image</image>

<div>
<id>p080v_1</id>
<head><pro>Founders of small works <add>@ of
<m>tin</m></add></pro></head>

<ab>They usually cast with <m>solder</m>, even the things that should
not come out empty, for the latter require <m>fine &amp; soft tin</m>,
which however would not release, &amp; would not come out empty if it
was mixed or had some <m>looking glass tin</m> <del>mix</del>
<add>in</add> it, just like they put in a little of it in <m>soft
tin</m>. They engrave their works on <m>stones of which are made the
sharpening stones or files of <pro>barbers</pro></m>, which are found in
<env>great flakes towards the mountains</env>, &amp; resemble
<m>slate</m>. They are three colors of them: reddish, which is not as
perfect as the others because it does not last as long in the fire
<del>&amp; as</del>,one <del><fr>dard</fr></del> of the color of dark
<m>slate</m>, the other whitish. When they have some relief, first they
imprint it on <tl><m><fr>carton</fr></m></tl>, as thick as one
<ms><bp>finger</bp></ms>, <add>to serve as a pattern</add>, then with a
little <tl>compass</tl> &amp; little matching <m>iron fittings</m>, they
engrave their figures, having first flattened their <m>stones</m> &amp;
worn down one against the other, they make their <del><fr>p</fr></del>
molds of three or four pieces, to make a circle or a square which joins
perfectly, because the <m>stones</m> render themselves even. Before
casting, they rub the mold with <m>tallow</m>, which has quickly
absorbed it because it is hot. Then, taking <m>fine powder of
quicklime</m> in a <tl><m>linen</m></tl>, they rub the mold while
beating with the <tl><m>linen</m></tl> on top, then blow a little on top
to prevent it from becoming porous. The main thing is to make vents, if
the work is a little large. They make them in this manner, as you see
represented here. They pierce a hole in some place on the medal that is
least visible. And then with a <tl>borer</tl> they pierce the mold on
the side of the medal.

<figure>

<id>fig_p080v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5VktqeFlScTAyczQ</link>

</figure>

And if they want their work to stay pierced in any place, they drive in
<tl>a piece of <m>cork</m></tl> at this place in the <tl>mold</tl>. And
the <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m> will not attach to it. </ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Make sure the <tl>pegs</tl> of your <tl>frame</tl> enter easily so
that <del>opening</del> <tl>frame</tl> will easily open without shifting anything;
and that your <tl>frames</tl> fit well together; &amp; the <tl>table
is quite flat</tl>. </ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Try to etch with <m>distilled vinegar</m>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>
Try <m>calcined <al>oyster</al> shells</m>. They are said to be
excellent for molding.</ab>

</div>
</root>
