<root>
<page>135r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f275.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p135r_1</id>
<head>Colors for <m>gold</m> or mixture</head>

<ab>

<m>Verdigris</m> &amp; <m>sal ammoniac</m>, as much of one as the other,
&amp; as big as a bean of <m>saltpeter</m>. For if you put a quantity,
it would make it all boil so much that it would boil over. Saltpeter is
only put in to make it boil, in order that one recognizes when the
substance has boiled enough. This color, put on sour melted gold,
renders it <fr>doulx</fr> immediately.</ab>

<man><margin>left-top</margin>Softening <m>gold</m></man>

</div>

<div>
<id>p135r_2</id>
<head>Gate</head>

<ab>

It is necessary that it be longish with regard to the thing that you
molded. And for big molds, at the very least, it is necessary that it
have four of five fingers of length. You can make it wide up until the
middle &amp; then divide it in three points in this way. And as much as
the molded thing is small, it is also necessary that your points be
small. And in the middle of the gate &amp; of its points, make there
some openings in order to prevent the fury of the metal &amp; make it
run gently. One also needs to <del>c</del> conjoin the folded parts of
the animal with little notched lines, <del>a</del>especially the end of
the tail or other delicate part, in order that the metal flows
everywhere &amp; carries itself from <del>e l</del> one part to the
other.</ab>

<ab>

Do not forget to make a gate of wax for the legs of sand lizards &amp;
delicate things like this.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

When you have molded an animal in the first part of the mold, do not let
this part dry before you have taken away the said animal, for the mold,
in drying, contracts and would also make the animal contract. Keep it
therefore in some moist &amp; humid place until you have done it.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p135r_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5U3BqOGxwTHNPeVk</link>

</figure>

</div>

<div>
<id>p135r_3</id>
<head><m>Vine leaf</m> and small <m>frog</m></head>

<ab>

Take <m>vine leaves</m> to mold, as they are in growth, likewise with
all plants &amp; flowers or a young vine growing again after having been
cut, or when they rebud in autumn, because the new leaves are more lumpy
&amp; have more apparent lineation. On the contrary old leaves are
smooth on the inside &amp; pierced in several places. Therefore place
your leaf bottom down on the clay slab, and secure it with small points,
nevertheless leaving it its natural curve. And make a notch in the clay
to hide the stem at the first gate, which, once made &amp; dry, you will
take away the stem from the leaf &amp; clean with it well with small
bristle brushes &amp; fix it with a small mount of clay. Next, make
several gates around the leaf with wax as you know &amp; <del>gec</del>
make the gate thin &amp; with several lines &amp; lumpy.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>

The vine <m>leaf</m> is painted with green made of <m>stil de grain
yellow</m> &amp; <m><fr>verd de terre</fr></m>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>

You can cast on the leaf a spider or frog &amp; whatever you like.</ab>

</div>
</root>
