<root>
<page>058r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f121.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p057v_2</id>

<ab>One needs to make at least three layers of flesh color to accomplish
faces in <m>oil</m>. And at the beginning, one puts the black and umber
where it is appropriate. Next, the <corr>heightening</corr> with <m>lead
white</m> must not be put on the black. Flesh colors and <gap/> with
<m>ceruse</m> going in will yellow in five or six <tmp>months</tmp>, but
<m>lead white</m> does not change.</ab>

<ab><m><pl>Florence</pl> lake</m> is better than the kind from
<pl>Flanders</pl> for in <pl>Florence</pl> the best dyes are made. To
make a beautiful flesh color, the reddest &amp; liveliest <m>lake</m> is
the best, for the kind that contains <m>purpurine</m> &amp;
violet, by admixture of too much <m>alum</m>, makes flesh color like
that of one who is very cold. That is why ladies, wanting to color their
<bp>cheeks</bp>, ground <m><pl>Florence</pl> lake</m> very finely, then
fill a little <tl><m><pa>cotton</pa></m></tl> with it, which they next
wrap in a little <tl><m>fabric of <pl>Cambray</pl></m></tl> which is
clear. And thus they pounce the <m>lake</m> on their <bp>cheeks</bp>
&amp; then, with another clean <tl><m><pa>cotton</pa></m></tl>, they
soften it.</ab>

<ab><m><fr>Cristallin</fr></m> having been ground with <m>water</m>
appears to <del>be</del> have body, but with <m>oil</m> it does not have
any. It is ground with <m>lake</m> &amp; with <m>asphaltum</m>, which
would not dry for a <tmp>very long time</tmp> without this.</ab>

<ab><m><pa>Spike lavender</pa> oil</m> is commonly put with <m>lead
white</m>, <del><fr>d</fr></del> not entirely pure but mixed with a
little <m><pa>walnut</pa> oil</m>. The said <m><pa>spike lavender</pa>
oil</m> would not be good for <m>lake</m> &amp; colors that do not have
body <add>for it would make them crack</add>, but with those that have
body &amp; are somewhat greasy, it is quite appropriate.</ab>

<ab><m>Verdigris</m> and <m>orpiment</m> must first be ground with
<m><bp>urine</bp></m> rather than thinning them with <m>oil</m>. Thus they are
beautiful &amp; do not die.</ab>

</div>
</root>
