<root>
<page>052r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f109.item</image>

<div>

<id>p052r_1</id>

<head>The work done in <pl>Algiers</pl></head>

<ab>Take a <al>colt</al> of three or 4 years &amp; feed it on
<del><m>rye</m></del> <add><m>barley</m></add> &amp; <m>straw</m>
<del><fr>pig</fr></del> cut in the manner one feeds <al>horses</al> in
<pl>Spain</pl>, and water it with <m>good fountain or river
<m>water</m></m>. I do not know if it would be good to water it
occasionally with <m>water of sulfurous baths</m>, &amp; to sometimes
give it <m><pa>fenugreek</pa></m> or other hot foods, for the intention
of the <pro>worker</pro> is <del>to it</del> to use the heat of its
<m>dung</m>, &amp; the climate here is cooler than that of
<pl>Algiers</pl>. Keep it in a <env>warm &amp; close place</env> &amp;
so that none of its <m>dung</m> &amp; <m><bp>urine</bp></m> should be lost, of
which you will make a heap or two in order that while one cools, the
other will be at the appropriate heat to continue. Also take a<tl> large
<m>glass</m> mattras</tl>, as thick as you can, &amp; one
<ms><bp>finger</bp></ms> thick if it can be done, &amp; of the
<ms>capacity of one <tl>pitcher</tl> or <tl><m>earthen</m>
jug</tl></ms>. <tmp>Around the feast of <pn>St John</pn></tmp>, put into
it a dozen &amp; a half <m>chicken eggs</m>, that is to say, the
<m>yolk</m> without the <m>glair</m> &amp; the <m>germ</m> (see). Others
say lx <m>yolks</m>. And <del>it will be</del> with this dozen &amp; a
half <m>egg yolks</m> put in <ms>half an ounce</ms> (others say for lx
<m>eggs</m> <ms>half a lb</ms>) of <m><al><add>female</add> silkworm
seeds</al></m>. And after having <m>luted</m> the
<tl>mattras</tl> well (I do not know if there needs to be air for the
generation), put it &amp; bury it in the heat of the <m>dung</m> up to
the neck, and leave it there until several <del><fr>f<ill/></fr></del>
<al>worms</al> are engendered. And then remove the <tl>mattras</tl>
&amp; do not bury it in the <m>dung</m> any longer, but only keep it
placed on the hot<comment>c_052r_01</comment> layer of the <m>dung</m>
until all the <al>worms</al> will have eaten &amp; consumed one
<del><fr>d</fr></del> another, bustling &amp; stirring, and only one
remains. When this is the case you need to feed it <tmp>at regular
intervals, day &amp; night</tmp>, with the aid of two men, who by
intervals will take care of it, and you will feed it with an <m>egg
yolk</m> covered with a <m>gold leaf</m>, or with a liquid <m>egg
yolk</m> with the <m>gold leaf</m> incorporated; &amp; take good care
that it does not want for such food (some say one <m>egg yolk</m> per
<tmp>hour</tmp>, others three, but the thing itself will demonstrate the
practice). Nourished in this way it will achieve its growth in two
<tmp>months</tmp> or seven <tmp>weeks</tmp> &amp; will become like a
<al>snake</al>, one <ms><fr>empan</fr></ms> &amp; 4
<ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> long, &amp; one <ms>lb</ms> in weight, and as
the wings begin to arise on it, one will need to make it die, doing so
with a <m>charcoal</m> fire in a ring around the <tl>bottle</tl> one
<ms><fr>empan</fr></ms> distant from it, and then stopper &amp;
<m>lute</m> the <tl>bottle</tl> well in order that it does not
exhale.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
