<root>
<page>157v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f320.image</image>

<div>

<id>p157v_1</id>

<head><m>Ash</m> in the <tl>molds</tl></head>

<ab>One needs to let the <tl>mold</tl> cool before blowing to make the
<m>ashes</m> go out. For when the <tl>mold</tl> is hot, they adhere
against it &amp; once cold, they separate from it more easily, &amp; go
out from it by blowing with air <fr>en vapeur</fr>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p157v_2</id>

<head>Molding a <al>bird</al></head>

<ab>One needs to give it its shape. And to do this, place it on its side
on a <tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl>, and hide &amp; sink within it half the
aforesaid <al>bird</al>, <add>in order</add> that it only shows one leg
&amp; one foot, then you will anoint it with <m>butter</m> to make it
hold the feathers down, finally <del>of<m>oil</m></del>
<m>eau-de-vie</m>. And then cast. And having made this take, clean &amp;
uncover whatever needs it. Next, mold the other side in the same way. But
because the feet, being of <m>bone</m> that is difficult to burn, &amp;
are not able to be cleaned with either by <m>quicksilver</m>
<del>If</del> or by any other means, if the <tl>mold</tl> would not
open, uncover the bottom of the feet &amp; the toe or the little finger
of the claw, &amp; mold as a separate piece. Reheat &amp; open your
<tl>mold</tl> &amp; clean the <m>bones</m>. The feet usually remain too
weak to support the mass of a <al>solid bird</al>. And for this reason
one applies an <tl><m>iron thread</m></tl> in the <tl>mold</tl> of the
feet, which passes into the body before casting, thus they are
reinforced. Some mold the wings in a <tl>frame</tl>. Others mold the
head &amp;the said wings separately <fr>en noyau</fr>, then join &amp;
repair them, to first rough out a form that will be rigid &amp;
withstand the wet sand.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

They are skinned &amp; filled with <tl><m>cotton cloth</m></tl>. &amp;
even better, one needs to dress them in the fashion that <pro>curriers</pro>
do, in order that they do not lose a <m>feather</m>, weight it. The
dressing is <m>alum</m> &amp; <m>paste of flour</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p157v_3</id>

<head>For making <fr>h</fr><exp>…</exp> wine
<fr>f</fr><exp>…</exp><fr>rs</fr></head>

<ab>Take<comment>c_157v_02</comment> a <tl>sock from the <bp>right
<del><fr>d</fr></del> foot</bp> that has been worn</tl> and make
<del>drink at</del> it soak in <m>water</m>, and of the <m>water</m>
that comes out, make that same person or someone else drink it, and you
will see marvels.</ab>

</div>
</root>
