<root>
<page>098v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f202.image</image>

<div>
<id>p098v_1</id>
<head>Small <al>dogs</al></head>

<ab>Small <al>dogs</al> who should be shaggy are known by this, that
they have a larger muzzle than others.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p098v_2</id>
<head>Salted <pa>artichokes</pa></head>

<ab>One puts them whole &amp; not too ripe in a <tl>firkin</tl> that one
fills with <m>brine</m>. Then one serves them <ms><tmp>all
year</tmp></ms>, among salads, raw with <m>oil</m> &amp; <m>vinegar</m>,
for being thus prepared, they take long to cook. But take heed to test
your <m>brine</m> with an <m>egg</m> for if it is good &amp; and strong
enough, the <m>egg</m> will float on top. If not, it is not strong
enough and would not preserve the <m>fruits</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p098v_3</id>
<head>Trees</head>

<ab>Which bear fruits quickly are aged and scarcely last.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p098v_4</id>
<head><al>Birds</al></head>

<ab>Which have been fed by the <tl>rod</tl> do not whistle among the
company of others if they are not in a separate cage. For teaching them
well to whistle, one needs to take them from the nest before they can
see &amp; cover them with <m>down</m> or a <m>hare skin</m>. Thus,
having not seen their father and known his voice, they learn the whistle
that one teaches them better.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p098v_5</id>
<head><fr>Fonte</fr></head>

<ab>The <m><fr>potée</fr></m> is made of <m>burnt earth</m> which was
used in the <fr>fonte</fr>, this is <m>earth <fr>bourre bolvene</fr></m>
in which one has melted it. One grinds it on a big
<tl><m>stone</m></tl>, &amp; with this one one makes the
<del><fr>chappe</fr> of</del> first coat of the <fr>chappe</fr> of
bells, where there are letters &amp; works, &amp; <del><fr>le</fr></del>
only needs to be reheated in the flame of a <m>straw</m>, and mold very
neatly.</ab>

<ab>The <m>earth</m> which molds in <fr>noyau</fr> is subject to making
it porous, if you do not rub well with a <tl>brush</tl> or your
<tl><bp>finger</bp></tl> on the molded piece, which should be well
<m>oiled</m>. And do it coat by coat, &amp; not all at once.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
