<root>
<page>072r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f149.item</image>

<div>

<id>p072r_1</id>

<head><pro>Printers</pro>’ letters</head>

<ab>Those who make them, mix into the <m>lead</m> some
<del><m>nails</m></del> <m>nailheads</m> &amp; <m>old
<al>horse</al>shoes</m>, &amp; <m>antimony</m> which makes it all melt.
This composition is strong for printing, &amp; holds steadfast. It runs
and is good for casting in <m>lead</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p072r_2</id>

<head>Casting in <m>copper</m> </head>

<ab>It is necessary that the <tl>frame</tl> be quite smooth &amp; that
it fits well also on the <tl>board</tl> where it sits, so that it holds
firm &amp; does not shift when one molds. It is necessary that the sand
be clean &amp; well chosen and well reheated, &amp; pulverised very
finely on the <tl><m>marble</m></tl>, for the one that you want to put
first on the medal, and when molding you press strongly. Guard against
<m>oiling</m> your medal, for this would make it porous. Reheat slowly
and reheat well, &amp; let cool. Moisten your sand with <m>wine boiled
with <pa>elm</pa> root</m>, and cast <m>latten</m> which comes out well,
namely from the <m>substance of the <fr>trebuschets</fr></m> and similar
thin things. Make your cast broad &amp; even if it is barely thick, it
will not be worse off, but it will enter well in the <tl>mold</tl>. Cast
from the foot of the medal, in order that the face, further away from the
heat, comes out better &amp; sweetened from the violent heat. And if
your <tl>frame</tl> does not have vents, make some
<del><fr>qu</fr></del> in the sand, which come, from the corners of the
piece, to render themselves into the cast. Cast very hot, something that
you will know, when you cast a little leftover substance in the one
which has already been melted, &amp; if it melts quickly, this is a sign
it is <del><fr>fo</fr></del> well hot. At that time, invigorate the heat
of your <tl>furnace</tl> with <tl>bellows</tl> of the right size,
keeping the mouth of the <tl>furnace</tl> well covered with some large
<del><m>copper</m></del> <tl><m>tile</m></tl> or other similar thing,
which should be very red before you cast. When you want to cast, take
your well red <tl><fr>mollettes</fr></tl> &amp; the <tl>crooked
<m>iron</m></tl> as well, to clean the <m>charcoals</m> which are in
your substance. Having cast, rub your work with a <tl><m>latten</m>
wirebrush</tl>. The <m>grindings from sharpening large scissors &amp;
large knives</m> is very good for <m>copper</m>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

One believes it to be a great secret to add in it
<m><pa>persicaire</pa></m>, which renders them soft as <m>lead</m>.Try
to extract <m>salts</m> from it.</ab></div>
</root>
