<root>
<page>033v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f72.image</image>

<div>

<id>p033v_1</id>

<head>For making it seem <del>that</del> to someone that he has a <tl>piece
of <m>silver</m></tl> on his <bp>forehead</bp></head>

<ab>Take a <tl>token</tl> or <tl>piece of <m>silver</m></tl> and wet it
and make it hold against your <bp>forehead</bp>. Then say to the
<pro>bystander</pro> that if you put it thus on his <bp>forehead</bp>,
he will not be able to make it fall without lifting his <bp>hands</bp>
to it, no matter how he shakes his <bp>head</bp>. And making it seem as
if you are placing it on his <bp>forehead</bp>, retain it in your
<bp>hand</bp> &amp; wet your <bp>thumb</bp> with your
<m><bp>saliva</bp></m> then press it quite strongly on his
<bp>forehead</bp>. And thinking he has the piece on his
<bp>forehead</bp> due to the <sn>coolness</sn> of the
<m><bp>saliva</bp></m>, he will shake his <bp>ears</bp> &amp; will get
nowhere.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p033v_2</id>

<head>For making <m><bp>blood</bp></m> or <m>wine</m> issue from
someone's <bp>forehead</bp> or from a <env>wall</env></head>

<figure>

<id>fig_p033v_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5MXk2RzNQdF9aeDg</link>

</figure>

<ab>Take an <tl><oc>ambu</oc></tl> or <tl>funnel of <m>white
iron</m></tl> which is double-walled in the body <del><fr>d</fr></del>
but not in the spout. Make a small hole at the top edge &amp;
<del><fr>au</fr></del> another slightly bigger on the inner wall that
will be a little above the spout, just as you can see in the adjacent
example. Then when you want to use it, <corr>put</corr> in <m>wine</m>
or <m>liquid rosette of Brazilwood</m> or <m><pa>black cherry</pa>
juice</m>, and blocking the hole of the spout <del>the</del> with your
<bp>little finger</bp>, make sure that the <tl>funnel</tl> is well
filled in order that the <m>wine</m> can enter <del>there</del> between the
double walls through the hole at the side, &amp; if it does not enter
well, making it seem as if you are <sn>tasting</sn> the <m>wine</m>,
suck &amp; draw in a little <m>air</m>, drinking where the little hole
is. Next, make one of the close <pro>bystanders</pro> drink the rest of
the <m>wine</m> or cast it aside or let it flow through the tip, but
before, you must have pressed your <bp>thumb</bp> well over the hole on
the top edge, because in this way, by the compression of <m>air</m>, the
<m>wine</m> will be retained between the double walls. Then with a
<tl>bodkin rounded at the tip &amp; that goes into its handle</tl>, you
make it seem as if you pierce the <bp>forehead</bp> of someone who holds
a <tl><m>glass</m></tl> in his <bp>hand</bp>, and while you pierce, you
cover what you are doing with the <tl><oc>funnel</oc></tl> that you hold
close to <mark>#</mark></ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>#</mark>

his <bp>forehead</bp>. Then removing your <bp>thumb</bp> from over the
hole on the top edge, the <m>air</m>, being free, will make the
<m>wine</m> issue from between the double walls through the hole marked
B, &amp; fall through the tip marked C into the <tl><m>glass</m></tl>.
But you must make the <pro>fellow</pro> bend his <bp>head</bp> enough in
order to do it well.</ab>

</div>
</root>
