<root>
<page>155v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f316.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p155v_1</id>
<head><pa>Rose</pa></head>

<ab>Because the bloomed flower is wavy &amp; has its petals disordered
&amp; turned in various fashions, it does not appear beautiful if it is not
painted, &amp; also, equally, if it has weight <del><fr>ou
for</fr></del> that the stem of <m>tin</m>, which is brittle &amp;
delicate, would be unable to support. One molds the flower of the
<pa>rose</pa> on its own &amp;separately, making its gate largeish in order
that it comes out <del><fr>b</fr></del> better. Then one cuts this gate
down closest to the stem of the bud, on which one grafts next &amp;
<m>solders</m> a <tl>stalk of <m>latten wire</m></tl> to which one also
<m>solders</m> the leaves. But because <m>tin</m>, being thus thin, is
troublesome to <m>solder</m>, and any leaf can be melted. And also
because the cast flowers &amp; especially the <pa>rose</pa> are not
beautiful without being painted, one does not take pains to
<m>solder</m>, but one <del>it</del> grafts the pieces to join them
&amp; one <m>glues</m> them with <m><al>fish</al> glue</m> that has been
a little wetted &amp; thickly melted. And in order that it imprints
better, one heats the <m>tin</m> work gently &amp; at a distance, for
when cold, the <m>glue</m> would not take. After your flower is thus
repaired, you follow the joints of the added parts with <m>modelling
wax</m> <del><fr>esb</fr></del>, which is a <m>white wax</m> mixed with
much <m><add>well-ground</add> ceruse</m>, or even better, <m>lead
white</m>, melting it &amp; applying it on your work with a <tl>small
hot point of <m>iron</m></tl>. In this way you can repair these little
flashings that are in the middle of the <pa>rose</pa>, or the holes
<del>of the</del> that may be in any petal. Next, you will paint your
<pa>rose</pa> according to nature. If you cast your <pa>rose</pa> in
<m>gold</m> or <m>silver</m>, you can join &amp; <m>solder</m> well. And
in these same <m>metals</m>, when you have something delicate to join to
the flower, like a <al>fly</al> or something similar, <m><al>fish</al>
glue</m> is remarkable for it &amp; holds very well, fixing it with a
few <tl>small points</tl> which serve as <tl>nails</tl>. The leaves
&amp; buds can be molded in two <tl>molds</tl> that can be opened once
reheated, but not before. Next, these said things are joined.</ab>

</div>
</root>
