<root>
<page>048v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f102.image</image>

<div>
<id>p048v_1</id>
<head><m>Extraction of regulus</m></head>

<ab>Take one <ms>lb</ms> of <m>antimony</m>, <ms>half a lb</ms> <m>black
soap</m>, and <ms>half a lb</ms> of <m>tartar from
<pl>Montpellier</pl></m>. Once the whole is pulverized, one needs to
boil in a <tl>varnished earthenware pot</tl> on a big fire while
stirring the whole often with a <tl>pick of <m>wood</m> or
<m>iron</m></tl>, &amp; the said <m>soap</m> will be consumed and burn
off and the rest will stay more or less red, and it will be necessary
that it is reduced by <ms>a third</ms>. Then one needs to throw it on a
<tl>tile</tl> and it will turn blackish. One will need to melt this four
or five times and pour it on the <tl>flat tile</tl> and then you will
have the <m>regulus</m> drawn from <m>antimony</m>.</ab>

<ab>Others pulverize the <m>antimony</m> &amp; mix it with
<m>saltpeter</m> &amp;<m>pulverized tartar</m>, <ms>as much of one as of
the other</ms>, &amp;, having heated a <tl>pot</tl> or <tl>crucible</tl>
red hot, they put a little of it at a time, &amp; <del><fr>se</fr></del>
turn their <bp>back</bp> for fear of the smoke, and continue thus until
everything is put in, and strengthen the fire until everything is
thoroughly melted &amp; melt it again several times.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p048v_2</id>
<head><m>Lead</m>, <m>tin</m></head>

<ab>They become brittle having been put back to melt often or for a long
time, and they thicken and burn, in such a way that even when one melts
a <fr>saulmon</fr>,<comment>c_028v_04</comment> the <m>tin</m> thickens at the bottom if, while
casting, one does not stir it often. It is best for casting to melt a
little <m>lead</m> <del>&amp; the</del> or <m>tin</m> &amp;
<del>stir</del> to renew at each melting. The <m>antimony</m> renders
them breakable. The <m>looking glass tin</m> whitens them.
<del>One</del> <pro>Pewterers</pro> put in <del>on the <m>fine
tin</m></del> one <ms>lb</ms> of <m>looking glass tin</m> per one
<ms>quintal</ms> of <m>fine tin</m> &amp; two <ms>lb</ms> &amp; a half
or three <ms>lb</ms> of <m>red &amp; soft copper of cauldrons</m>, which
is better than <m>latten.</m> There is <m>fine &amp; soft tin</m> &amp;
<m>brittle tin</m>. The brittle one is cast in <tl><fr>grille</fr></tl>
by the <pro>pewterers</pro> to sell it better. <del><fr>O</fr></del>
They come out better &amp; more neatly in <tl><m>stone</m> molds</tl>
than in a <tl><m>copper</m> mold</tl>, because <m>copper</m> is fat
&amp; sticks unless one heats the <tl>mold</tl> well or one casts large
works. Three <ms>quarters</ms> of <m>lead</m> per one <ms>lb</ms> of
<m><fr>doux</fr> tin</m>, makes a very liquid line &amp; proper for
casting, which has a shine like a mirror. <m>Sandever</m> lightens them.
All things that thoroughly lighten <m>metals</m> &amp; remove their
thickness &amp; dense nature &amp; render them <del>like</del> liquid
like <m>water</m>, render them proper for casting, for it is the
thickness that prevents them from running. <m><fr>doux</fr> tin</m> is
more even <del><fr>com</fr></del> than the <m>brittle one</m>, which is
whiter and seems to be burnished like a mirror.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
To alloy well <m>tin</m> &amp; <m>lead</m>, one needs to melt one by
itself, and then mix in the other, small pieces at a time, and throw it
often on the <tl><m>marble</m></tl> or the <tl><m>square tile</m></tl>.
And when you will see it become quite even <del>like</del> &amp; shiny
as if it were burnished, it is good. For sometimes it becomes spotted
due to too much <m>lead</m> &amp; sometimes due to too much <m>tin</m>.
There is some <m>tin</m> which takes more <m>lead</m> than another.
<m>Common tin</m> is the one that is mixed with <m>lead</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
