<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="117r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f239.image">




<div id="p117r_1" categories="casting">

<head>A means of molding flowers and plants</head>

<ab>One needs to choose them in their full verdure &amp; vivacity, &amp;
<del>them <fr>mou</fr></del> not pick them, if possible, until the time
one will want to mold them, so that they do not wilt. Or, if you need to
carry them from afar, soak their stems in a <tl>bottle <add>of
<m>water</m></add></tl> or, better still, <m>wine</m>. Make, first, a
<m>wax</m> stick pointed like a large peg, of a size appropriate to what
you want to cast, as you see in the margin, marked A. Put &amp; prick at
the foot of this small peg a bit of rather thickish &amp;
strong <m>iron wire</m>. And at the point of this, you will fit your flower stem or your
plant. This done, set it aside neatly. And arrange your
<del><tl>mold</tl> of <fr>t</fr></del> circle &amp; shape of <m>clay</m>, as you
have done for the <al>snakes</al>, in the form of a <mu>mandore</mu>
<del>in such a way that</del> according to the size of your plant. Then,
take the one that you have prepared to be cast, as we have taught you,
&amp; wet &amp; moisten it very carefully with <m>good
<add>eau-de-vie</add></m> with a <tl>paintbrush</tl>. Then pass the
<tl><m>iron</m> stem</tl> through the end of the <m>earthen</m>
<mu>mandore</mu>, in order that the <m>wax</m> <del><fr>q</fr></del>
peg, where the plant is fastened, joins to the end of the <m>earthen</m>
<mu>mandore</mu>. And arrange thus your plant in such a way lying down
that it remains in the middle of the said <mu>mandore</mu>, without
touching on either side, so that <del>a</del><comment rid="c_033r_01"/> the <m>sand</m> that you will
pour in it will be of equal thickness <del>as</del> everywhere &amp;
<add>exceed</add> <corr><del>is</del></corr> everywhere by the height of two good
<ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> the top of the <del>such</del> plant. And
having secured the <tl><m>iron</m> stem</tl> well, promptly pour <del>wetted</del>
your <m>wetted sand</m>, much thinner than the one for <al>snakes</al>, in the
<mu>mandore</mu>. And the sooner the better, in order that the
<m>eau-de-vie</m> does not dry. And take heed to put in a little more
<m>sal ammoniac water among the
common</m><comment rid="c_117r_02"/> than you would do for the
<al>snakes</al>. And when you will make <m>sand</m> especially for your
bouquets, where you would mix in a little more <m>feather alum</m>, it
can only be better. Thus, your <tl>mold</tl> will be in one piece
and it will not be necessary to unjoin it, but rather <del>leave</del>
separate it from the <m>clay</m> once it will have set, let it dry, and
then reheat it again until the plants are burnt.
<del>Then</del> And note that if the plant you want to cast has
a strong stalk &amp; stem, you can cast it lying down, as had been said.
But if it is some weak &amp; delicate <add>flower</add>, <del>cast</del>
plant it upright with the <tl><m>wax</m> peg</tl> because the <m>sand</m> will
always <del>cast</del> lift it up, it being very thin. Do not forget to
adapt two vent holes with two <tl>small sticks</tl>, starting at the
foot of the cast, which is the pointed end of the <tl><m>wax</m>
peg</tl>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

If the plants are so delicate that they rise to the top when you pour
the <m>tempered sand</m>, one can fix and contain them with a <tl>thread</tl>
passed through the circle of the <tl>mold</tl> with a
<tl>needle</tl>.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p117r_1" size="small" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5WnpBbm8wN2gyTWs">
</figure>

<figure id="fig_p117r_2" size="small" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5VURRYzlWOFByNzQ">
</figure>

<ab margin="left-middle">

The more delicate the flower is, the thinner the <m>sand</m> must be.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p117r_3" size="small" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dVB5bzVUWWJuS0U">
<caption><tl>Mold <fr>en noyau</fr></tl></caption>

</figure>

</div>
</root>
