<root>
<page>138r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f281.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p137v_1</id>

<ab>If you want to cast <m>gold</m>, <m>silver</m>, <m>copper</m> or
<m>latten</m>, it is necessary that they be perfectly red, &amp;
inflammed on the inside when you cast, &amp; perfectly reheated two
times, if there is something inside to be burnt &amp; cleaned.</ab>

<ab>The <tl>molds</tl> of animals that one burns must be heated in
such a way that the animal burns. But if it has <m>thick bones</m>, it is
troublesome to pull out &amp; <m>☿</m> often breaks
some fine things by its weightiness. One does not put
<m>☿</m>in <tl>molds</tl> that can open. This readily
happens with flowers, the <tl>mold</tl> of these does not open because
they are made all in one go.</ab>

<ab>When you want to reheat your <tl>molds</tl>, put the <tl>clamps</tl>
on the joints, in order that, when reheating, they do not bend,
contract, or break. This is done after the gate is made.</ab>

<ab>The <m>scrapings of the mold</m> can still be used, using them in
place of <m>brick</m>, after having reheated them, &amp; also the
<m>pieces of the molds that have been used</m>. One <m>lutes</m> with it
also important things, like works of <m>gold</m> or <m>silver</m>. One
also reheats it, &amp; prepares it with <del><fr>se</fr></del> <m>water
of sal ammoniac</m>, as <m>spat from <pl>Germany</pl></m>, &amp; it is
excellent sand for <tl>frames</tl> for all <m>metals</m>.</ab>

<ab>The <tl>molds</tl> of things where one needs to burn them inside, do
<del><fr>souf</fr></del> not open until the things which are inside are
burnt, like with <tl>molds</tl> of <al>crayfish</al>, <al>crabs</al>,
<al>stag beetles</al>, portraits &amp; pieces of <m>sulphured
black wax</m>, which do not release well.</ab>

<ab>One ought not to mold on <m>brick</m> or <m>wood</m> because they
<del><fr>l’ea</fr></del> drink &amp; attract <m>water</m> too soon, and
do not allow the sand to set. It would never be better than on a
<tl><m>fresh clay</m> slab</tl>. Yet, I have experienced that <m>grey
earth</m> dries the <tl>mold</tl> too soon. <m>The yellow</m> is
better.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
For medals, and flat things, it is necessary that the sand be thick
enough, wet, because it sets quickly. And when the sand is thus thick,
one can hit and shake the <tl>table</tl> where the <tl>mold</tl> is
placed, to make it run everywhere. But when the sand is thin, like for
flowers and plants, one ought not to hit, nor when there is something
attached with <m>wax</m> or another thing that is subject to coming off,
like <al>crayfish</al> legs or similar things. And if the sand is, by
chance, too thick, you <corr>promptly</corr> put in it some
<corr><del>pour</del></corr> <m>water</m>. Having put the sand in
<m>water</m>, <del>it</del> examine that it is thick at the bottom &amp;
thin on top. The thinnest is cast at the beginning and then becomes
porous &amp; the thickest at the end in order to fortify the
<tl>mold</tl>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
