<root>
<page>111r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f227.image</image>

<div>
<id>p111r_1</id>
<head>Reheating <tl>molds</tl></head>

<ab>The <tl>frames</tl> readily dry out &amp; do not reheat. For
reheating is actually <del>for the second time</del> to redden &amp;
inflame the <tl>molds</tl> in the fire, and drying out is to let the
<tl>molds</tl> dry themselves, or to make their dampness evaporate by
placing them in front of a flaming fire or a charcoal one.
<tl><fr>Noyau</fr> molds</tl> readily reheat &amp; <tl>frame molds</tl>
dry out.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p111r_2</id>
<head><m><m>Latten</m> smoke</m></head>

<ab>

It is good to reheat in it the <tl>molds for casting <m>latten</m></tl>,
for this <del><fr>g</fr></del><add>c</add> <m>yellow filth</m>, which
appears nevertheless to refill the <tl>molds</tl>, casts very neatly,
being of the same nature.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p111r_3</id>
<head>For <m>red copper</m></head>

<ab>When it is melted, it is good to throw in a little <m>fine tin</m>,
for this makes it run.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p111r_4</id>
<head><m>Clay earth</m></head>

<ab>This one, moistened &amp; well beaten &amp; kneaded as you know, is
necessary for you to make the contour for containing your
<tl>molds</tl>. But take heed that it not be too soft, but rather as if
half dry, that <del><fr>i</fr></del><add>e</add>l<add>le</add> it does
<sn>not attach to your <tl><bp>hands</bp></tl></sn>, because otherwise
it would attach to your work. Always keep it <env>in a damp place</env>,
and make holes in it, and fill them with <m>water</m>, to keep it
fresh.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The gray one is best, which does not crack at all.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is more appropriate than a <tl>blade of <m>lead</m></tl>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<figure>

<id>fig_p111r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5X085N09VejNheTQ</link>

</figure>

</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p111r_5</id>
<head><m>Iron wire</m></head>

<ab>You need to have enough provisions of different thicknesses,
according to the <tl>molds</tl> that you want to make, some <ms>thick
like cord, some <ill/></ms> &amp; some <ms>thin <del><fr>p</fr></del>,
like the thick strings of a <mu>spinet</mu>, for small works</ms>. You
make, once <del><fr>de</fr></del> reheated, <tl>clamps</tl> from it to close the
<tl>molds</tl> &amp; the points, like needles of different lengths,
according to your need, to pierce the animal to be molded &amp; keep it
subjected. <tl>Needles</tl> would not be good for this because it is
necessary that their points be empty &amp; of the same thickness
throughout, except at the point. And then, one must make them as long as
you have need of. <m>Iron wire is firmer</m> than <m>that of
latten</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
