<root>
<page>130v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f266.item</image>

<div>
<id>p130v_1</id>
<head>Molding a <al>crab</al></head>

<ab>It is a secret and a masterpiece to mold it well, because one needs
to proceed differently than with other animals, because its shell is
very difficult to <del>mold</del> burn &amp; in this case, one
<del><fr>le</fr></del> needs to sometimes reheat the <tl>mold</tl> three
or four times. And with all of this, it leaves a hard crust, grey like
<m>ash</m>. But because it does not mold in one piece &amp; one cast,
like plants, but rather in two casts like <al>snakes</al> that release
well, one removes this crust, <add>not with <m>quicksilver</m>, which
<man><margin>left-middle</margin>would do nothing</man></add>, after it
has been opened, with the very fine point of a <tl>pen-knife</tl> with
dexterity, as with the little crusts of the second cast, which enter in
the nooks that the sand or the molded animal made. But,
<del><fr>la</fr></del> because it has curved legs, here is the cunning
way &amp; secret for releasing it. Therefore, as you have molded it on
one side, which is on the back, in the same fashion as others, uncover its
belly, &amp; all its curved legs. Make your second cast in the same fashion
as others, but, as it will have set, keep from opening the <tl>mold</tl>
until you have first reheated it well. Otherwise, because of its curved
legs, you would break everything. In this lies the dexterity. If you
recognize, after having reheated &amp; opened it, that the crust is not
burned enough, reheat until it does.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is painted like a <al>crayfish</al>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<del>Know that</del> <add>For</add> opening the <tl>mold</tl>, there is
no need to soak it, for once reheated, it will open by itself.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p130v_2</id>
<head><al>Stag beetle</al></head>

<ab>It is as difficult to burn as a <al>crab</al>, therefore do for it
as you did for the <al>crab</al>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p130v_3</id>
<head>For molding thin</head>

<ab>After you have molded in <fr>noyau</fr> <del><fr>la</fr></del>
<del><fr>e figur</fr></del> the first <tl>mold</tl>, let it dry well
before taking away the figure of <m>wax</m>, <del>in order</del> in order
that the <tl>mold</tl> does not corrupt. Next, make a small lasagna of
<m>paste</m> of such thickness that you would like, and having anointed
with <m>butter</m> <del>your</del> the hollow of your first hollow
<tl>mold</tl>, adapt the <m>paste</m> to it and then make your second
<tl>mold</tl> on top. If you were to anoint with <m>oil</m>, it would be
absorbed &amp; would not be as appropriate as <m>butter</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
