<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="153r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f311.image">




<div id="p153r_1" categories="casting">



<head>Molding hollow for seals or other things</head>

<ab>First, model your figure in <m>wax</m> on a piece of
<tl><m>glass</m> or smooth <m>slate</m></tl>. Next, mold it with our
aforementioned <m>sand</m>, <del><fr>l’</fr></del> having first anointed lightly
with <m>oil</m>, as you know, &amp; then rubbed with <m>eau-de-vie</m>,
<del>having</del> and tempering your <m>sand</m> with <m>hot water</m>. Having
the hollow form, cast it in <m>alloyed lead</m>, in the same form as  other figures that you make very neatly. However, if it did not come
out at all neatly, repair it. And then, <del>cast some</del> <add>mold
with some</add> <m>wax</m> on the relief of <m>lead</m>, &amp; you will
have a very neat hollow form in the <m>wax</m>, which comes out very neatly
on the <m>lead</m>. Next, in the hollow form of <m>wax</m>, cast your <m>tempered sand</m>, which will make for you a relief, on which you will cast your
hollow form in <m>silver</m> or another <m>metal</m> for seals. But, note
that you should not make your hollow form with <m>melted wax</m>, but rather,
only heated in <m>warm water</m>, or, even better, in <m>warm
<bp>urine</bp></m>. Or else, if you have a relief of <m>gold</m> or
<m>silver</m>, or other <m>metal</m>, very <del><fr>faço</fr></del> neat
&amp; repaired, imprint on top your hollow form of <m>wax</m>, &amp; then in
the latter, cast your <m>sand</m>, which will come out in relief, on which you will next cast your hollow form for seals or other works. You could even
cast a hollow form on the principal<comment rid="c_137r_03"/> of <m><fr>metal</fr></m><comment rid="c_016v_05"/> relief, &amp;
even with <m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m>, which will not melt the
principal<comment rid="c_153r_03"/> if it is lightly anointed with <m>crushed chalk</m> with a <tl>paintbrush</tl>, or <m>smoked</m> with <m><tl>candle</tl> smoke</m> or with
<m>dried glair of egg</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">When you have imprinted your seal of
<m>wax</m>, mold <fr>en noyau</fr> this piece of <m>wax</m>, which is
hollow, like your seal, &amp; your <fr>noyau</fr> will render it molded,
similar to <del><fr>u</fr></del> the imprint &amp; the seal.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

It is necessary that your <m>wax</m> be mixed with some color which
hardly has body, in order that you see the imprint better. <m>Lamp
smoke</m> or <m>soot black</m> is good for this. <m>White wax</m>, for
this effect, is <del><fr>exc</fr></del> better.</ab></div>

<div id="p153r_2" categories="casting" continued="yes">



<head>Giving the thickness that you wish to a medal</head>

<ab>Having cast your first <tl>mold</tl>, mix <ill/><comment rid="c_153r_02"/>
<m><la>crocum</la></m> or <m>well-ground iron scales</m> to firm it up.
And having set, &amp; rendered your hollow form very neat, take some
paste of fine</ab>



</div>
</root>
