<root>
<page>168r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f341.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p167r_1</id>

<figure>

<id>fig_p168r_1</id>

<margin>left-top</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5RUdzVWVNM3l6QVU</link>

</figure>

<ab>peg that one puts into the touch-hole, &amp; hen, with a rope
wrapped around the end of a stick, one gives fire &amp; promptly
retreats to take cover. The small petards of 16 or 17 lb are attached
quickly, with a short, hooked peg made like a
wimble<comment>c_168r_01</comment>, &amp; if the petard is of a good
alloy, one can give fire by hand as one does with petards of 27 lb., but
then one only puts three lb of powder. It must be a strong door if the
seventeen lb petards does not blow it up. Some people use little bells
worn by oxen or mules on a peasant door. Others load two pistol barrels
&amp; attach them with a gimlet &amp; a string with the muzzle against
the door. If the petards are good &amp; do not explode, they only recoil
and cannot harm if one is next to them.</ab>

<ab>A is a small peg, hooked like the pintle of a door and made like a
gimlet on one end for quickly attaching a small petard with ears of
fifteen or xvii lb. for a common door or window.</ab>

<ab>B is a small petard with ears.</ab>

<ab>C is a common petard of 27 or 30 lb. pierced at the breech, through
which a large <m>iron</m> peg passes, button-like on one end &amp; made
like a gimlet at the point for quickly attaching the petard against a
door that will not be covered with <m>iron</m> plates.</ab>

<ab>D These are small plates of <m>wax</m>, <m>cork</m> and <m>wood</m>
for loading the petard and sealing the powder well.</ab>

<ab>E <m>iron</m> fork made in the form of pincers as tall as a man, to
promptly set the mortar without a peg. It must be of <fr>doux</fr>
<m>iron</m> in order that the branches bend easily, if need be, to fit
to the height or width of the door.</ab>

<ab>F This is another <m>iron</m> fork of the same height that supports
the fork made like pincers and also sustains the petard, and with its
low claw prevents the pincers from recoiling.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
