<root>
<page>126v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f258.image</image>

<div>

<id>p126v_1</id>

<head><m><la>Crocum ferri</la></m></head>

<ab>It is best made rather with <m>iron rust</m> than with
<m>filings</m>. For if the <m>vinegar</m> <add>is good</add>, you will
see it boil with large bubbles <del>as if it</del> on the <m>rust</m>,
as it it were on the fire, on the <m>fillings</m>, it does not boil
unless it is put on the fire or <m>hot ashes</m>. However, when the
<m>fillings</m> are passed through <m>vinegar</m> &amp; you have made it
evaporate &amp; heat up &amp; it is very red, if you do this again for a
second time, the <m>vinegar</m> will have much more strength, &amp; the
<m><la>crocum</la></m> will only be finer for it &amp; redder. Those who
use it to cast in <m>gold</m> <del><fr>ven</fr></del> buy the
<ms>ounce</ms> for forty or fifty <ms><cn>sols</cn></ms>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

It does not harden the <tl>molds</tl>, and, in scraping, one cannot tell
that they are harder from it. But it makes the <tl>mold</tl> less dense,
and it drinks in and attracts the <m>gold</m> better.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p126v_2</id>

<head><m>Plaster</m></head>

<ab>You can mold with it as large a piece as you please. But if you take
your <tl>molds</tl> from large works &amp; pieces of <m>wood</m>, it
will not release well, unless you <del>boil</del> make your <m>wood</m>
imbibe <m>very hot wax</m>. For the <m>wood</m> absorbs &amp; drinks
&amp; in this way attracts the <m>plaster</m>. You can assume the same
thing for any other large piece of work. But the cure is to
<del><fr>l’ab</fr></del> saturate <del><fr>l’ouvra</fr></del> with <m>very
hot wax</m> the work on which you want to cast your <m>plaster</m>. For,
by this means, it will not drink it up &amp; will release very
neatly.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

If the <m>plaster</m> shrinks, it will always make flashing. Find some hard
ones and <del>it</del> put your <tl>molds</tl> well in the <tl>press</tl> before
casting.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>It is not good when it
shrinks.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p126v_3</id>

<head>Plants difficult to burn in the <fr>noyau</fr></head>

<ab>Any plant which has a hard stem &amp; like <m>wood</m> is very
difficult to burn in the <fr>noyau</fr>, such as <pa>asparagus</pa>,
<pa>thyme</pa>, &amp; similar things, because they stay as <m>coal</m>
in the small conduits, &amp; if they do not reduce well into
<m>ashes</m>, it is not possible to empty them from the <tl>mold</tl>.
Some reheat them, to this effect, two or <del><fr>d</fr></del> three
times. Others, putting several plants together in the <tl>mold</tl>,
pass through <del>threads</del> the plants &amp; <add>the</add>
<del><fr>es <tl>moules</tl></fr></del> <tl>circle of <m>earth</m></tl>,
which is to receive the wet sand,<del><fr>plusi</fr></del></ab>

<ab><margin>left-bottom</margin>

This does proceed from plants that have a stem with lines, because
<pa>rosemary</pa> burns well, but it is in the nature of certain
plants.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
