<root>
<page>140r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f285.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p139v_1</id>

<ab> like other things, &amp; on this occasion, you can cast in two or
three times until your <tl>mold</tl> is full. As for the <tl>mold which
is of <m>white plaster</m></tl>, pulverized &amp; reheated as for
previous sands, you should have made it <tmp>a long time ago</tmp>, for
it serves several times. But before you use it, soak it for <tmp>a good
<ms>hour</ms></tmp> in <ms>cold water</ms> &amp; for <tmp>at least
<ms>as long</ms></tmp> in <ms><m>water <add>so</add> hot</m>, that, at
the beginning, you cannot hold your <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl> in it</ms>.
And <del><fr>q</fr></del> take heed that it does not imbibe
<del><fr>b</fr></del> more,<del>thus</del> but rather that it shows
itself to be very wet everywhere, without the water being imbibed in it.
And, removing it from the <m>hot water</m>, closed, cast your <m>wax</m>
in such a state of heat as has been said. And readily, neither the first
nor second cast come out until the <tl>mold</tl> is imbibed. Let it cool
before opening it, in order that the cast thing does not break. You will
recognize that the cast is good when the <m>wax</m> spilled out onto the
outside of the <tl>mold</tl> is thin and smooth. Remember to make many
gates all along the <tl>mold</tl>, in order that the <m>wax</m> may thus run
better.</ab>

<ab>Make the first

<figure>

<id>fig_p140r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NFdsdU4tVFgxOTg</link>

</figure> gate twice as large as for other <tl>molds</tl>. And if, in
the first cast, your work becomes porous and does not come out neat,
<del><ill/></del>, it is all the same, for it is necessary that you
realise that the three of four first ones are not readily good. In the
first one, you recognize if there are some flashings, which keep from
releasing well and you remove them if they do not remove
<add>themselves</add> at the second or third first cast. And the more
you cast, the neater you will make it, and your <tl>mold</tl> will serve
you for more than a hundred times, if it is well overseen. But it is
good to soak it one <ms><tmp>night</tmp></ms> or one
<ms><tmp>day</tmp></ms> before casting in it, in order that it be well
imbibed. The same must be done for fruits of <m>sugar</m>. This
<m><m>wax</m></m> is very <fr>doulce</fr> &amp; amiable &amp; pliant as
<m>copper</m>, and if it is strong because of the <m>sulphur</m>, which
renders it melted, far before the other, that you can thus prove on a
<tl>hot <m>slate</m></tl>. And the <m>sulfur</m> that you will have put
in it, will be found, the second time that you melt it, cracked at the
bottom. Having thus passed through the <m>wax</m>, it does not inflame
from a <tl>candle</tl>. And on this occasion, <del><fr>que</fr></del> I
think it will cast very neatly for medals. One uses the same <m>wax</m>
in place of <m>varnish</m> to etch <ill/></ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
When your animal is cast, cut with a <tl>hot penknife</tl> the flashing
&amp; superfluous things. And if you want to refold it &amp; twist it
around on some <tl>stick</tl> or <tl>taper</tl>, put it to soften
<del>on</del> in <m>hot water</m>, and hold it while twisting it
around.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Cut down the protuberance of the gates, in order that they are smooth
&amp; that the <m>wax</m> has more of the <m>silver</m> to run, in one
go, without turning around in the folds of the <al>snake</al>.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
