<root>
<page>156v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f318.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p156v_1</id>
<head>Molding a <al>fly</al></head>

<ab>Take the <al>largest <del><fr>vo</fr></del> flies</al> that go into
<env>pantries</env>, which are not hairy, if it is possible. If they
are, anoint lightly their down &amp; capricious hair with
<m><pa>olive</pa> oil</m> to lay it down. Also take them and use them as
soon as you can after they are dead, because if you were to leave them
to dry a lot, their <del><fr>e</fr></del> legs would break when you
would want to spread them out. One needs also, to make them come out
better, to place them on something like a leaf, or similar thing, to
help the casting of their little legs, which are so frangible that by
themselves, they would not come out well in the cast. They can be
planted on a <pa>sage</pa> leaf, or similar thing. They are cast well in
<m>silver</m> &amp; <m>gold</m>, but one usually makes the legs &amp;
wings separately &amp; one reattaches them. I have molded one on a
<del><fr>e</fr></del> <del><pa>sage</pa> leaf</del> bouquet of
<pa>sage</pa>, which had seven or eight leaves. And to make its stance
<del><fr>att</fr></del>, I fixed its legs <del><fr>au</fr></del> on the
widest leaf with a little <m>wax, melted</m> &amp; reattached with a
<tl>hot <m>iron wire</m> point</tl>. And in order that the wings come
out better, I anointed the underside of these with <m>melted butter</m>
with a <tl>little <fr>pinceau</fr></tl>. And with the same <tl>hot
<m>iron wire</m> point</tl>, I anointed the legs &amp; feet with
<m><pa>wheat</pa> oil</m>. And to lay down &amp; couch the
<add>downy</add> hair that it had, I anointed it also
<del><fr>u</fr></del> with a little <m><pa>olive</pa> oil</m>.</ab>

<ab>I did not leave the <m><pa>wheat</pa> oil</m> to dry a lot, because
it is thick &amp; has body, &amp; the <m>eau-de-vie</m> does not take at
all.</ab>

<ab>For unction, <del><fr>a</fr></del> <m>tallow</m> is too harsh,
<m><al>pork</al> fat</m> is too soft, and <m>butter</m> is the most
excellent because it is soon dry &amp; curdles &amp; melted quickly
&amp; firmer. Take heed that the legs &amp; feet are well seated on the
leaf &amp; not outside it, for what would exceed would not come out
well, especially in <m>silver</m>, because this <del>would exceed
the</del>, <add>so fine</add>, would be of no help in the casting. And,
in truth, the feet which had been laid on the leaf came out well, but
those which straddled from leaf to leaf &amp; remained in the void, did
not come out in <m>tin</m>. The rest of the <al>fly</al> came out well,
and especially the bouquet of <pa>sage</pa>, which is very beautiful
molded.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
One could even cast it in <m>gold</m> &amp; <m>silver</m>, without the
feet &amp; without applying it on a flower, by making the gate under the
belly &amp; reattaching with <m>solder</m> the feet, &amp; if needs be
the wings with the same <m>metal</m>, &amp; it could be <m>enamelled</m>
by fortifying the wings a little &amp; the feet, as said.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
If your <pa>sage</pa> or branch has something to repair, do as said
below. And then paint, according to its nature.

<figure>

<id>fig_p156v_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5VjFPeWlJc05CbDQ</link>

</figure></ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Once cast in <m>gold</m>, one <m>enamels</m> the wings with <m>window
glass from <pl>Lorraine</pl></m>, which is <fr>verdesin</fr> and
transparent.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
One needs to make the gate for the <al>fly</al> from the bottom <del>in
order</del> with <m>melted wax</m>, adapted with the <tl><m>iron</m>
point</tl>, as you know, to which the <al>fly</al> attaches itself,
&amp; then the <m>wax</m>, while melting, serves as a gate for the
<al>fly</al>.

</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>+</mark>
If some flaw happens to the wings of your <al>fly</al>, beat some
<m>tin</m> very thin, or <del>&amp;</del> some <m>gold</m> or
<m>silver</m>, if you have cast it in it, &amp; <del>with</del> trim
with some <tl>scissors</tl> what one needs to reattach there, &amp;
next, apply it with your <tl>small pincers</tl> &amp; <m>glue</m> it
with <m><al>fish</al> glue</m>, prepared as put below. And before, heat
lightly your work, in order that its coldness does not refuse the
<m>glue</m>, which will be soon dry, heating it from afar. Next, cover
lightly the joints of the reattached thing with some <df><m>modelling
wax</m></df>, which is <m>white wax</m> mixed with a lot of
<m>ceruse</m> or <m>lead white</m>, melting it well with a <tl>hot
<m>iron</m> point</tl>. You will also cut some small bits of
<m><mu>spinet</mu> strings</m> &amp; <m>glue</m> with the said
<m>glue</m>, &amp; once dry, that is to say the feet, repair with this.
You will thicken them with the same <m>melted wax</m>, to render them
equal.</ab>

</div>
</root>
