<root>
<page>166r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f337.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p166r_1</id>
<head>For the <env>workshop</env></head>

<ab>

If something is omitted: the <pro>harvester</pro> is not reproached for
leaving some ears of <pa>wheat</pa>. If any <pro>artisans</pro> complain
that one discovers their craft secrets, and if the
<corr>goddesses</corr><comment>c_166r_02</comment> of <pl>Eleusis</pl>
complain, as they did to <pn>N</pn><comment>c_166r_03</comment>. the
<pn>Pythagorean</pn>, that one has divulged their mysteries, excuse
yourself based on the words of the ancient <pl>Hebrews</pl> quoted by
<pn>Josephus</pn><comment>c_166r_04</comment>.</ab>

<ab>

As the <al>hen</al> carefully searches the garbage thrown out of a
<env>house</env> for a crumb or a grain that she divides among her
<al>chicks</al>, thus one distributes to <pro>orphans</pro> that which
has been researched among the arts considered vile &amp; abject.</ab>

<ab>

Tablet of <pn>Cebes</pn>, idle, but the
<env>workshop</env><comment>c_166r_05</comment> represents all things
active. </ab>

<ab>

If the jealous disapprove that these things are picked up &amp; taken
from others, reply that since <la>Nullum est jam dictum quod non dictum
aut factum sit prius</la><comment>c_166r_06</comment> &amp; that one
knows that all arts were invented <tmp>in the space of a thousand
years</tmp>, so that you do not think that you are able to invent
anything new but rather rediscover anew the books of <pn>Numa</pn>,
buried <del>par</del> &amp; long unknown &amp; forgotten, in order to
publish them for those who do not know them; so that as the
<tmp>preceding day</tmp> is teacher for the <tmp>subsequent day</tmp>,
thus you needed to learn from those who proceeded you in order to teach
to those who come after. The <pl>Latins</pl> took from the
<pl>Greeks</pl>, as <pn>Cicero</pn> from <pn>Plato</pn> &amp;
<pn>Virgil</pn> from <pn>Homer</pn>. <pn>Aulus
Gellius</pn><comment>c_166r_07</comment>, <pn>Valerius Maximus</pn> only
made a collection from various <pro>authors</pro> who had already
written. <pn>Livy</pn> made his xxiii book from the 2nd or 3rd of
<pn>Polybius</pn>. <pn>Serapis</pn> was deemed the <pro>inventor</pro>
of agriculture among the <pl>Egyptians</pl> , &amp; however so was
<pn>Ceres</pn> among the <pl>Sicilians</pl>. <pn>Pythagoras</pn> &amp;
others from <pl>Tyana</pl> learned by their travels the disciplines
which they claimed to have invented in their country, &amp;c. Will one
not say the <pro>weaver</pro> has made a cloth or precious stuff, even
though he did not dye &amp; twist, wind &amp; prepare the bobbins and
balls of thread? Will one say the <pro>mason</pro> has not made a
<env>house</env>, but only piled up ready-made stones?
<la><pn>Apollo</pn> a <pn>Chirone</pn> <pro>medicari</pro> didicit
&amp; tamen deus medicinae habitus</la><comment>c_166r_08</comment>.
<la><pn>Homerus</pn> <pn>Orphei</pn> poema imitatus est, nam cum
<pn>Orpheus</pn> sic prius exorsus esset: Iram cane,
<del><la>deam</la></del> dea, <pn>Cereris</pn> frugiferentis, ita reddit
<pn>Homerus</pn>: Iram cane, dea, <pn>Pelidae</pn> <pn>Achillis</pn>.
In <pn>Justino martire</pn>, circa
princip<exp>ium</exp>.</la><comment>c_166r_09</comment></ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
