<root>
<page>020r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f45.image</image>

<div>

<id>p020r_1</id>

<head>@For making <m><oc>millas</oc></m></head>

<ab>It is necessary to have <m><pa>millet</pa></m> pilled to remove the
<m>husks</m> and then you will clean it well. Next one needs to
grind it again quite finely and pass it through a <tl>hair sieve</tl>
quite finely. This done, it is necessary to mix the <m>flour</m> with
<m>melted fresh butter</m> and some <m>milk</m>, and that there be
<ms>as much of one as the other</ms>, in such a manner that it is very light in color,
like the <m>dough to make fritters</m>. And you will put in <m>egg
yolks</m> according to the quantity of <m>flour</m>, so that it amounts
to two <m>egg <corr>yolks</corr></m> for each <m><oc>millas</oc></m>.
Then you will put in some <m><pa>saffron</pa></m>, if you like, to give
them a little color.</ab>

<ab>Next, you need to have your <tl>molds</tl>, and it is
necessary that they be <m>earthenware</m>, in the fashion of the crown of
a catholic hat, but it is necessary that they be open at both ends. And
then, having made a good fire, you will clean the place in the
<tl><env>hearth</env></tl> where you want to put your
<m><oc>millas</oc></m>, and then you will take your <tl>molds</tl> and
grease them quite heavily in order that the <m>dough</m> does not stick when
cooked. Having done that, you will put your said <tl>molds</tl> on the
well-cleaned place in the <tl><env>hearth</env></tl> and will put a
little <m>flour</m> at the bottom and fill them with the aforementioned
<m>dough</m>. Next you will cover the said <tl>molds</tl> with
<tl>lids</tl> which will be made like the <tl>molds</tl>, but it is
necessary that they be larger and not be open at the top. Then having
done that, you will put a little <m>hay</m> on the said <tl>lids</tl>
and plenty of <tl>embers</tl>, and make a good charcoal fire all around.
That done, you will uncover one of them soon thereafter and see when it
is cooked. It should be hard.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p020r_2</id>

<head>@<pro>Glassworker</pro></head>

<ab><m>Glass from <pl>Lorraine</pl></m> is smoother &amp; more even than
<m>plate glass</m> and it is sturdier &amp; more durable. But commonly
it is stained by veins, in straight lines as if tanned, which happens
because the <pro>glassmakers</pro>, having made it, put it when totally
hot on <m><pa>straw</pa></m>, which stains it in this way. However, this
is removed with <m>varnish</m> &amp; <m>salt</m> &amp; other
<m>drugs</m> that the <pro>glassworkers</pro> put on. <m>Glass from <pl>Lorraine</pl></m> is sold by the <ms>bundle</ms><comment>c_020r_04</comment> &amp; each
<ms><df>bundle</df></ms> is composed of three <ms>tablets</ms>.
The <ms>bundle</ms> costs usually x <cn><fr>sous</fr></cn>.
<m>Plate glass</m> <del>sold in</del> is made in <pl>France</pl>, it is
whiter &amp; clearer, but alternately it is not so durable as that from
<pl>Lorraine</pl>. It is also commonly blown &amp; in that case, it is
better to make little diamonds rather than large square pieces in the
shape of a frame, because they are not able to seat themselves very
evenly.</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

<m>Plate glass</m> is sold by <ms><fr>paniers</fr></ms>. Every
<ms><df><fr>panier</fr></df></ms> contains 24 <ms>plates</ms> that are
commonly sold at x or twelve <cn>lb</cn>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
