<root>
<page>162v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f330.item</image>

<div>

<id>p162v_1</id>

<head><pa>Peach tree</pa></head>

<ab>Because they sprout &amp; flower among the first, &amp; thus are
caught by the <del><fr>ch</fr></del> <env><tmp>frost</tmp></env>, one
extracts them <ms><tmp>during winter</tmp></ms> in order that
<del><ms><tmp>the winter</tmp></ms></del> the <env>cold</env> slows
them, and that blossoming later, the flowers come to profit.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p162v_2</id>

<head><pa>Olive trees</pa></head>

<ab>In <pl>Spain</pl>, one extracts them <ms><tmp>during
winter</tmp></ms> &amp; <ms><tmp>in summer</tmp></ms> one plants them
well with <m>earth</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p162v_3</id>

<head><al>Bittern</al> foot</head>

<ab>To mold it, it is better to spread the toes &amp; nails out well, on
something flat, &amp; leave it thus to dry a few
<ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms>, because, in drying, the scales appear coarser
&amp; the nerves &amp; tendons become more apparent, and thus the
molded foot will be more artistic.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p162v_4</id>

<head><tl>Molds</tl> of things that do not release</head>

<ab>Animals that do not release can only be molded in two
<tl>molds</tl>, which should not be opened until after they are well
reheated &amp; the enclosed animal is well burned. Animals that have
bones or scales, which do not reduce into powder, but rather remain as
calcined lumps, will never leave through the gate, whatever blowing that
one does, or whatever <m>quicksilver</m> that one puts there, or a
<tl><m>feather</m> quill</tl> molded to use as a gate. This is why one
molds in two halves, in order that, the <tl>mold</tl> being opened after
having been reheated, the burned thing can be cleaned out well. But take
heed to let it cool well, in order that, when removing the
<tl>clamps</tl>, being hot, and when it is most frangible, something
does not break. The <m>crust</m> &amp; <m>ashes</m> that it leaves &amp;
which adhere to the <tl>mold</tl> while it is hot are removed better
once cold. Note also that on the bottom side of the <tl>mold</tl>, when
you reheat, the animal which boils leaves some <m>filth</m>. And, on
this occasion, one always marks the <tl>mold</tl> where the back of the
animal is, in order that, when reheating, it is above &amp; on top &amp;
that through this means it is neater.</ab>

</div>
</root>
