<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="003r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f11.image">




<div id="p003r_1" categories="stones">

<head><m>Counterfeit coral</m><comment rid="c_003r_02"/></head>

    <ab>
        &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
        &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
        <mark>+</mark>
    </ab>

<ab>One needs to first make the branches of <m>wood</m> or take a
bizarre <m>thorn branch</m>, then melt a <ms>lb</ms> of the most
beautiful <m>clear pitch resin</m> and put in one <ms>ounce</ms> of
<m>subtly ground vermilion</m> with <m><pa>walnut</pa> oil</m>, and if
you add in a little <m><pl>Venice</pl> <fr>laque platte</fr></m>, the
color will be more vivid, and stir everything in the <m>resin</m> melted
over a <m>charcoal</m> fire and not of flame, for fear that it catches fire. 
Next dip in your branches while turning, &amp; if any filaments
should remain on it, turn the branch over the heat of the
<m>charcoal</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top" render="tall">

<df><m>Colophony</m></df> is nothing other than recooked <m>resin</m>. To do
it well, take a <tl><m>leaded</m> pot</tl> &amp; melt the <m>resin</m>,
&amp; boil it over the <tl>brazier</tl> a good <ms><tmp>hour</tmp></ms>,
&amp; until it appears not to be thick, but clear &amp; liquid like
<m>water</m>, &amp; easily runs &amp; flows from the tip of a
<tl>stick</tl> with which you grind it, &amp; test it. Then pour it
through a <tl><m>coarse canvas</m></tl> or a <tl><m>very light tammy
cloth</m></tl>, such that when pouring it falls into the
strongest <m>vinegar</m> that you can find, for the <m>vinegar</m> gives
it strength &amp; prevents it from being so fragile. Reiterate this two
or three times &amp; it will be beautiful &amp; well purified. For
counterfeiting your <m>coral</m>, you can mix a <ms>quarter part</ms> of
<m>mastic</m> into your <m>purified resin</m> to render it more firm
and more beautiful, &amp; if you were to take a single tear of
<m>mastic</m>, it would be all the better, but it would be too long.

</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">

<m>Sulfur</m> &amp; <m>vermilion</m> makes the same effect.</ab>

<ab margin="top">

The <m>coral</m> made of <m>gules red enamel</m> endures the
<tl>file</tl> and polishing.</ab>

<ab margin="right-top">

It is made like <m>cement</m> that is stronger mixed with <m><tl>pestled</tl>
<del>than of</del> glass</m> rather than with <m>brick</m>. Thus, here one
mixes well <tl>pestled</tl> <m>gules red enamel</m>, which
is red in body, with the <m>vermilion</m>. Thus with all colors of
<m>enamels</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p003r_2" categories="varnish">

<head><m>Varnish</m> for panels</head>

<ab>Take a <ms>lb</ms> of <m><pl>Venice</pl> turpentine</m> &amp; heat
it in a <tl>pot</tl> until it simmers, and put in half a <ms>lb</ms> of
the <m>turpentine oil</m> of the whitest you can find, and stir it
together well on a <m>charcoal</m> fire and take it off immediately. And
<del><fr>elle</fr></del> it is done. But if it seems too thick to you,
add in a little more <m>oil</m>. Similarly if it is too clear, you can
thicken it by putting in a little <m>turpentine</m>. Thus you will give it
whatever body you want. It could be made well without fire, but, when
heated, it is more desiccative. It is appropriate for panel paintings
and other painted things without corrupting the colors or yellowing. And
it dries both <env>in the shade</env> and <env>in the sun</env>, and
<tmp>overnight</tmp>, and <tmp>during the winter</tmp> as well as
<tmp>in the summer</tmp>. It is commonly sold 15 <cn>sous</cn> a
<ms>lb</ms>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom" render="tall">




A little more <m>turpentine</m> than <m>turpentine oil</m> is needed in
order to give body to the <m>varnish</m>, which needs to be applied with
the <tl><bp>finger</bp></tl> in order to spread it thinner and less thick,
for when it is thick, it turns yellow and sticks. One does not
<m>varnish</m> to make paintings shine, for it just takes the light out
of them.</ab>

</div>



<div id="p003r_3" categories="varnish" continued="yes">

<head><m>Thick varnish</m> for planks</head>

<ab>There is a <m>varnish</m> that takes a long time to dry &amp;
drips more than two <tmp>months</tmp> after it has been applied to the
planks. But this one does not drip like that of <tmp>times
past</tmp>, which was made of <m>linseed oil</m>, <m>garlic</m> boiled in it
to extinguish it &amp; rid it of grease, 
&amp; with <m>wheat</m>. And this one yellowed &amp;
rendered greenish the blue color of paintings. This one is made like the
other one except that one puts <m>coarse common turpentine</m></ab>

</div>


<div id="p003r_2" part="y">
        
<ab margin="left-middle" render="wide">    
But it is used to heighten colors which have soaked in and to keep them
from dust. <m>Mastic varnish</m> does not resist <env>rain</env>,
whereas that of <m>oil</m> and <m>rosin</m> does.</ab>  
</div>
    
</root>
