<root>
<page>087v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f180.image</image>

<div>
<id>p087v_1</id>
<head><m>Sand</m>, <m>slate</m>, and <m>burned earth</m></head>

<ab><m>Very burnt sand</m> loses its bond. <m>Slate</m> is reheated &amp; molds
neatly. Next, it is true that it often becomes porous, like <m>burned
earth</m> also does, like <m>fat sand</m> also does.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-top</margin>
I find that one ought not to knock on <m>very finely ground sands</m>, for it
shakes them loose, &amp; <del>make</del> prevents them from releasing
neatly. But one ought to press hard and moisten them sufficiently.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p087v_2</id>
<head><m><fr>Magistra</fr></m></head>

<ab><pro>Founders</pro> take the <m>roots of a young <pa>elm</pa></m>
when it is in sap, &amp; boil it in <m>wine</m>, or better yet
<m>vinegar</m>, and keep it <tmp>all year long</tmp> in a
<tl>barrel</tl>.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p087v_3</id>
<head><m>Sand of the <env>mine</env> of <pl>Thoulouse</pl></m></head>

<ab> <m>Casting sand coming from the <env>mine</env></m>, once passed through a
<tl>double sieve</tl>, next put in with <m>melted resin</m>, burns &amp;
inflames &amp; becomes all red &amp; inflamed like <m>iron</m>. Once
cold it is completely black and can be ground very finely on
<tl><m>porphyry</m></tl>. Thus having prepared it &amp; rendered it
without asperity on the <tl><bp>fingernail</bp></tl>, I moistened it
with <m>beaten glair of egg</m> &amp; beat it well, until it was not pasty
but rather powdery. I found it of very good release, &amp; molded with
it in <m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m> very neatly, but it wants to be well
reheated &amp; at ease.</ab>

<ab>Others beat it well in a <tl>mortar</tl>, in small amounts at a
time, &amp; thus it is <po>pressed together</po> and rendered very fine. Then
they reheat it moderately, only to dry it. Next, they grind it dry on
<tl><m>porphyry</m></tl>. And thus it becomes as if impalpable, and not
too dried out, <del>it</del> and it retains the body &amp; the bond of the
<m>earth</m> to which it is kin, and is better than when it is so
burnt. Once moistened with <m>glair of egg passed through a
<tl>sponge</tl></m>, it releases <del>very neatly <fr>M</fr></del> very
neatly in low relief, but not for figures in high relief. Therefore,
since then I have experimented <del><fr>lexper</fr></del> with
moistening it only with very strong <m>vinegar</m>. It released a
figure which I could not release previously. And I believe that,
moistening the finest in a fashion as with <m>glair</m> &amp; the
coarsest, for filling, with gushes of <m>salt water</m> or
<m>wine</m>, that they do not join so well. But as they are of one
nature &amp; are moistened the same, they embrace each other, &amp; hold
together one with the other.</ab>

<ab>
<emph>To mold well</emph>, after having prepared your <m>sands</m>, mold <tmp>in
a day</tmp>. Slowly reheat them <tmp>the next day</tmp>, then cast them
on another.

</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
One ought to choose the one which is <del>as</del> in clods
&amp; lumps, well <env>deep in the earth</env>, for usually the one that
is found higher up is too much a kin of the <m>earth</m>, and the lower is a kin of the <m>rock</m>.<comment>c_087v_01</comment></ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
I have molded it from <m>pure lead</m> cast very <del>neatly</del>hot, &amp; I had as an example the very neat principal,<comment>c_137r_03</comment> but the
<m>vinegar</m> hardly gives it any bond, &amp; thus it sustained only
one cast. </ab>

</div>
</root>
