<root>
<page>128v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f262.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p128r_1</id>

<ab>

You will see that it will torment it &amp; heat it very well and soon
render it very liquid &amp; ready to cast and be clarified, as it should
be. When it is in this state &amp; that it is very white and polished,
shining like <m>quicksilver</m>, prepare yourself to cast. And to this
effect, have some <m>lean delicate sand</m>, in a
<tl><fr>terrine</fr></tl> or another <tl>vessel</tl>, that you would
like to help yourself to. Make a pit in your sand, then, with your
<tl>pincers</tl>, take your <tl>well reddened mold</tl> &amp; place it
in this pit of sand. Cover immediately the opening of your <tl>mold
</tl>in order that no <m>ash </m>&amp; dust enters inside, &amp; then
enclose it with sand up to end of the gate &amp; the vents. This done,
uncover your <tl>mold </tl>&amp; throw on top of your <tl>well melted
silver</tl>, the <ms>size of a <pa>pea</pa></ms>, or thereabouts, some
of this metallic <fr>grain</fr>, which will immediately spread through
all your <m>silver</m> &amp; make it boil &amp; turn. Cast as soon as
you have put in this substance, for it is this that is the secret to
making the <m>silver </m>run, since its crust heats it &amp; clarifies
it. You can cast <m>silver finer than the alloy from the <pl>capital
</pl>and like the <cn>realle</cn></m>, but you must add this
<fr>grain</fr> in.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

With all of this, do not let yourself forget to put, before all things,
a little <m>borax </m>in the <m>melted silver</m>, for even though
<pro>goldsmiths</pro> do not put any in, however it is good, and I have
seen it practised well. Next, one puts in the crust of the substance at
two different times &amp; then the metallic thing. Then make sure that
it be placed at the end of your <tl>forge</tl>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

If you want to blow the <m>ash</m>that is around your <tl>mold</tl> when
you hold it between the <tl>pincers</tl>, hold it with the opening at
the bottom, &amp; blow.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

When <m>silver</m> is well melted you can uncover it and blow with the
<tl>small bellows</tl>, not continually like with <m>gold</m>, but only
to cast out the <m>charcoals</m> in order to put in the substances that
make it run.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p128v_1</id>

<head>Whitening of cast <m>silver</m></head>

<ab>

Because one commonly casts in <m>base silver</m>, &amp; especially the
<pl>Germans</pl>, and that such an alloy readily makes <fr>chappe</fr>
or crust, <del>which is contrary to</del> <del>our</del> some
<pro>goldsmiths</pro> <del>from <pl>France</pl></del> are usually quick
to whiten their works, especially rough ones, because they only
use <m>common <fr>bullitoyre</fr></m>, which is <m>tartar</m> &amp;
<m>common salt</m>, <ms>nearly as much of one as the other</ms>. But I
have seen an excellent <pl>German</pl> working thus. Having, in my
presence, cast a <al>little lizard</al> with an <m>alloy of
<cn>teston</cn></m>, he made a greyish <del><fr>noi</fr></del> crust.
And to clean it from it, he boiled it in the above mentioned
<m><fr>bullitoyre</fr></m> of <m>tartar</m> &amp; <add>pulverized</add>
<m>common salt</m> <del>and</del> mixed with <m>common water</m>, in the
fire of his <tl>forge</tl>. Once taken out, he <tl>brushed</tl> it. And
because it was not as clean of this crust as he fancied, he burned some
<m>tartar</m> <add>in some <tl><m>paper</m></tl></add> until it was
black &amp; no longer smoked. Then, he wet the aforesaid <m>tartar</m>
<del><fr>d</fr></del> with the <m>water of <fr>bullitoyre</fr></m> ,
composed of <m>salt</m> &amp; <m>tartar</m>, &amp; covered all his
<al>lizard</al> with it. Then he put it between the live <del>of</del>
charcoals of his <tl>forge</tl> &amp; blew a little. When the
<al>lizard</al> was red, he took it out, let it cool, then reheated it
in the <m><fr>bullitoyre</fr></m>. Next, he <tl>brushed</tl> it in
<m>clear water</m>. </ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>+</mark>

Note that the <m><fr>bullitoyre</fr></m> for <m>silver</m> is never good
in a <tl>crucible</tl> because the water, taking the form of the
<del><fr>f</fr></del> <m>tartar</m>, evaporates. But the <tl>vessel</tl>
for boiling, being of <m>copper</m>, is excellent for the whitening of
<m>silver</m> &amp; for the mixture which colors <m>gold</m>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

He heeded to not let his <m>water of tartar</m> boil so much that it
poured out on top, because then its strength goes away. Therefore, when
this first fury of boiling comes, remove it from the fire &amp; put it
back. He held as a secret this <m>burned tartar</m> put on top for
<m>base silver</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
