<root>
<page>067v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f140.image</image>

<div>
<id>p067v_1</id>
<head><tl>Files</tl></head>

<ab>If they are not <fr>trempées à pacquet</fr>, that is, in the fashion
described, with <m>soot</m>, <m>salt</m>, &amp; <m>vinegar</m>, they
will not be good. The <del>square</del> large <tl>square files</tl> used
by <pro>locksmiths</pro> for their rough work are only made of
<m><fr>doulx</fr> iron</m>, But the <tl>soft files</tl> must be made of
<m>steel</m>. <pro>Founders</pro> whose work is to repair <m>latten</m>
&amp; <m>copper</m> must have their <tl>files</tl> <del><fr>d</fr></del>
coarse otherwise they would fill up with the <m>copper</m> which would
make them smooth &amp; soon render them useless. <m>Latten</m>, which is
more brittle, welcomes softer <tl>files</tl> than <m>copper</m>
does.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p067v_2</id>
<head><m>Bones of the foot of <al>oxen</al> for sand</m></head>

<ab>Once having been burned well twice &amp; pulverized, they mold very
neatly in sand &amp; need not be reheated, but simply heated with the
flame of <m>straw</m>. But if you mold them in a <fr>noyau</fr>, give it
its first layer, simple &amp; very thin, with a
<tl><fr>pinceau</fr></tl>, &amp; leave to dry at ease. Next, fortify the
following layers with <m>wadding</m> mixed with the said tempered
<m>sand of bone</m>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
It is the neatest sand that can be found for <m>copper</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p067v_3</id>
<head><m><fr>Huiles d'essence</fr></m></head>

<ab><m><add><pa>Walnut</pa></add> oil</m> mixed with as much of
<m>turpentine</m> &amp; distilled by an <tl>alembic</tl> renders an
essence whiter than <m>common water</m>. But this has no body &amp; does
not give a bond for colors that are immediately imbibed, and then leaves
the color without stickiness and faded. These, imbibed in this way,
would not let you work or soften, no more than in <m>distemper</m>. But
you rectify this fault, by giving it a little body with
<m>turpentine</m>, not at all so thick as for varnish. And thus you can
work with <m><fr>azur d’esmail</fr></m> &amp; will make a perfect
<m>lead white</m>. <m>Turpentine varnish</m> made with this <m>oil</m>
is dry in one <ms><tmp>hour</tmp></ms>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
