<root>
<page>045r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f95.image</image>

<div>

<id>p045r_1</id>

<head>Loading an arquebus with a <m>hail shot</m> </head>

<figure>

<id>fig_p045r_1</id>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bkhmQklfNHJoRnc</link>

</figure>

<ab>One needs to make a <m>wooden</m> pipe as long as the width of 4 or
5 fingers, which should be hollowed precisely according to the mouth of
your barrel, of the form represented in <del>D</del> A. Then, having cut
strong <m>paper</m>, <del>of the</del> as of large printed books, in the
form of D, as wide as you want to make your
cartridge<comment>c_045r_01</comment> long, wrap the <m>paper</m> around
the baton B &amp; at the end, where the point F will be, fold it all
around the said <m>paper</m>, &amp; your cartridge will be formed. But,
in order to make the bottom more uniform, put it into pipe A, then put
in the baton B and, through the other end of the pipe, which is marked
G, put the baton C &amp;beat so as to tamp &amp; press the folded tip of
your cartridge, then take it out, &amp; load it. Put three or four
<fr>drageons</fr><comment>c_045r_02</comment> or
tears<comment>c_045r_03</comment> into it. Then, with a cutting-punch,
marked E, which should be of the same caliber as your arquebus or
pistol, punch round pieces on <m>cardboard</m> or <m>felt</m> or
<m>waxed cloth</m>, and put this round piece into your cartridge, and
push it onto the <fr>drageons</fr> with the baton B. Next, more
<fr>drageons</fr>, 3 or 4, then a round piece. And do thus until the
cartridge is full, then put it into your arquebus. If you want your hail
shot to scatter sooner, make the round pieces out of <m>paper</m>. If
you want it to reach farther without scattering, make the piece out of
<m>cardboard</m>. If you want even farther, make the round piece out of
<m>waxed cloth</m>, or else of <m>leather</m> or <m>felt</m>, &amp; a
piece of <m>waxed cloth</m> on the top. And if you make the cartridge
itself of <m>waxed cloth</m> or <m>waxed paper</m>, it will reach one
hundred paces &amp; will make for great piercing, &amp; the hail shot,
barely scattering, will make an opening. But if you make your cartridge
with <m>waxed cloth</m> or a material stronger than <m>paper</m>, you
ought not to make it so long from the square coming to the point as in
D, because it is enough that it makes two turns. <figure>#</figure>In
this manner, the <m>hail shot</m> barely scatters &amp; makes for great
piercing against a door, body of a cuirass<comment>c_045r_04</comment>,
and others.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<x><figure>#</figure></x> as <del>D</del> H

</ab>

</div>
</root>
