<root>
<page>023v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f52.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p023r_1</id>

<figure>

<id>fig_p023v_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Tm4ySC1wcUx6Yzg</link>

</figure>

<ab><m>powder</m>. When the sausage is full, dip it <del>well in</del>
lightly, to wet the <m>canvas</m> &amp; not the <m>powder</m>, in two
<ms>parts</ms> of <m>vinegar</m> &amp; <del>of</del> one of
<m>eau-de-vie</m>. Next, let the said <m>canvas</m> dry well, and then
one needs to join to the said sausage a long <tl>string</tl> or
<tl>cord</tl> which should be <ms>two times longer than the
sausage</ms>, &amp; one ought not to tighten it to the sausage but only
to bind it to it at both ends &amp; to sew it on the sausage in a few
places in the middle. Next one needs to anoint the entire sausage with
<m>very good turpentine</m>, and at whichever end of it you wish to join
to the touch-hole of the petard for giving fire, you can sew
<del>a</del> or tightly attach a <m>large strip of canvas</m> one
<fr><ms>empan</ms></fr> wide which should also be well soaked in
<m>turpentine</m>, &amp; this strip must be split in the middle in order
to wrap &amp; tie it around the petard, and one needs to attach it in
such a way that <del>the touch-hole should be close to <del><fr>u
m</fr></del>the</del> the tip of the sausage, which should be open,
should be joined to the touch-hole of the petard. Then one needs to put
a lot of tightly-pressed <m>powder</m> onto the touch-hole of the
petard. And next, the one outside the ditch needs to pull the
<tl>thread</tl> &amp; <tl>cord</tl> that is joined to the sausage until
it is moderately extended, but not so much that it is detached. And if
there was <m>water</m> in the ditch, one would need to support the
sausage with forks. Then, the one who holds the end of the sausage will
be able to give fire, having gotten himself to safety, &amp; the others
also.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p023v_1</id>

<ab>Petards that one wants to place on doors or <m>iron</m> grates are
sufficient if they weigh 40 or 50 <ms>lb</ms>. Moreover, as for its
charge, ball, &amp; fashion of proceeding, one needs to do all as is
already said above, concerning the one of 3 <ms>quintals</ms>. One man
can carry it.</ab>

<ab>The ball needs to be be round on one side &amp; flat on the other
like <del>a half ball</del> a <ms>half</ms> of a cut ball. It is also
necessary that the cross is held to the ball and that it, when the ball
is founded if you make it from <m>metal</m>, is bound up with the middle
of the cross.</ab>

</div>
</root>
