<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="024r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f53.image">




<div id="p024r_1" categories="arms and armor">



<head><wp>Grenades</wp></head>

<ab><wp>Grenades</wp> must be made from the <m>finest <fr>metal</fr><comment rid="c_016v_05"/> one can find</m>, for
there is <m>fine <fr>metal</fr></m> and <m>crude <fr>metal</fr></m>. <m>Fine
<fr>metal</fr></m> is that of a large bell, because one
puts in more <m>copper</m> to give it a bigger voice, &amp; for small
bells one puts more <m>tin</m> to give it a <del>bigger</del> clearer
sound. The <m><fr>metal</fr> of a large bell</m> is made <del>one</del><comment rid="c_024r_05"/> with
<add>3</add> <ms>quintal</ms><add>s</add> of <m>rosette</m> &amp; twenty or xxv
<ms>lb</ms> of <m>tin</m>. <del><fr>Tan</fr></del> Each <wp>grenade</wp> must
weigh four to six <ms>lb</ms>. And in order to throw them, it is necessary
that they be full of <m>powder</m> mixed with <m>coarsely <tl>pestled</tl>
glass</m>. And for a quarter <ms>lb</ms> of <m>powder</m>, one needs
half an <ms>ounce</ms> of <m>glass</m> which is put with it, in order
that on the face or places where the <m>powder</m> will have its effect,
the <md><bp>wounds</bp></md> will be all the worse for it. The <m>best <wp>arquebus</wp>
powder</m> is required here. The hole needs to be as large as <ms>the
thickness of a <al>swan</al>’s quill</ms>, &amp; you need not bother to
make it threaded, but it is enough to make it even. Next, you make a
<add>well-soldered</add> pipe of <m><fr>fer blanc</fr></m>,<comment rid="c_024r_02"/> 
which can enter into the hole &amp; enter into the middle of
the <wp>grenade</wp> &amp; which comes out of it <ms>by the width of one
<bp>finger</bp></ms>. You will fill it with <m>good powder</m>, <tl>pestled</tl>
in a <tl>mortar</tl> &amp; lightly mixed with <m>good eau-de-vie</m> or
<m>strong vinegar</m> <del>which seems. And when</del> This is done to
temper the <m>powder</m>. And to know if it will be slow enough to allow
leisure to throw the <wp>grenade</wp> without danger, try this <m>powder</m> thus
bathed in another pipe. You can keep <del><fr>d</fr></del> your loaded
<wp>grenades</wp> in a <env>very dry place</env>, &amp; on the contrary you shall
keep your pipes filled with that bathed and well-compressed
<m>powder</m> in a <env>humid place</env>. And nonetheless, you shall
have some already inserted into <del>the</del> <add>some</add> <wp>grenades</wp>,
to be always provisioned. And <tmp>every three days</tmp> you shall
change them if you recognize that they have become too dry. To throw
your <wp>grenade</wp>, take it bravely <del>&amp;</del> in one <bp>hand</bp>
&amp; with the other give fire to your pipe with <del>the</del> a
match,<comment rid="c_024r_03"/> &amp; throw it promptly amidst the
<del>powder</del> troops. The thickness of the
<wp>grenade</wp><comment rid="c_024r_04"/> should be <ms>twice the back edge of
a knife</ms>.</ab>

</div>
</root>
