<root>
<page>131r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f267.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p131r_1</id>
<head><m>Plants</m> that are awkward to burn in the <tl>mold</tl></head>

<ab>Mold them with two or three gates, which once reheated will open
&amp; it will be easier for you to take away the <m>charcoal</m> from
inside.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Try</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p131r_2</id>
<head>Letters and molded <m>paper</m></head>

<ab>Write with well gummed <m>ink</m> or with any color which has body
&amp; which does not erase once moistened with <m>eau-de-vie</m>.
Then, place your <m>paper</m> on a <tl><m>clay</m> slab</tl> &amp;
moisten it with <m>eau-de-vie</m> and cast on one side &amp; the
other.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p131r_3</id>
<head>For adorning <env>beds</env>, <env>mirrors</env>, and
suchlike</head>

<ab>Rough out some design in half relief on a <tl>quite flat
<m>slate</m></tl> to adapt it to either round or flat things. And having
cast it in <m>mixed tin</m>, quite thin, you can <m>gild</m> it with
<m>gold leaf</m>, &amp; adapt it to whatever you want, and fill the
<del><fr>vui</fr></del> bottom of the relief with small <m>rubies</m>,
<m>orpiment</m>, &amp; little grains of diverse colors.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p131r_4</id>
<head>For teaching a <al>dog</al> well</head>

<ab>It is necessary to keep it tied up &amp; when it does what you
command it, to make it love you, give it some <m>cheese</m> that has
been held under your <bp>armpit</bp>. Which must be a bad drug both for
the master, if he is red-haired, and for the <pro>apprentice</pro>
too.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p131r_5</id>
<head>Molded <m>waxes</m></head>

<ab>Figures of <m>wax</m> composed of <m>ceruse</m> &amp; <m>lead
white</m> are not for burning &amp; melting in a <tl>mold</tl> where you
want to cast <m>gold</m> &amp; <m>silver</m>, for this would sour it.
And then, if you think about taking away these <m>waxes</m> composed of
things coming from the <m>metals</m> reheated in the <tl>mold</tl>, you
will be wrong, because, the asperity of the fire, making them boil
<del><fr>ir</fr></del>, the <m>wax</m> goes away &amp; the composition
of the <m>ceruse</m> or other metallic color, attacks the <tl>mold</tl>.
And for this reason, if you want to rough out something</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>

<mark>+</mark><lb/>

<la>Nota</la><lb/>

<m>White wax</m> is more delicate than the other &amp; it does not leave
any <m>filth</m> when you want to make <fr>noyau</fr> and mold
hollow.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
