<root>
<page>135r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f275.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p135r_1</id>
<head><m><fr>Couleur</fr></m><comment>c_135r_01</comment> for <m>gold</m> or mixture</head>

<ab>

<m>Verdigris</m> &amp; <m>sal ammoniac</m>, <ms>as much of one as the
other</ms>, &amp; <ms>as much as a <pa>bean</pa></ms> of
<m>saltpeter</m>. For if you put a quantity, it would make it all boil
so much that it would boil over. <m>Saltpeter</m> is only put in to make
it boil, in order that one recognizes when the substance has boiled
enough. This <m><fr>couleur</fr></m>, put on <m>sour melted gold</m>,
renders it <fr>doulx</fr> immediately.</ab>

<man><margin>left-middle</margin>Softening <m>gold</m></man>

</div>

<div>
<id>p135r_2</id>
<head>Gate</head>

<ab>

It is necessary that it be longish with regard to the thing that you
molded. And for <tl>big molds</tl>, at the very least, it is necessary
that it have four of five <ms><bp>fingers</bp></ms> of length. You can
make it wide up until the middle &amp; then divide it in three points in
this way. And as much as the molded thing is small, it is also necessary
that your points be small. And in the middle of the gate &amp; of its
points, make there some openings in order to prevent the fury of the
<m>metal</m> &amp; make it run gently. One also needs to
<del><fr>c</fr></del> conjoin the folded parts of the animal with little
notched lines, <del><fr>a</fr></del> especially the end of the tail or
other delicate part, in order that the <m>metal</m> flows everywhere
&amp; carries itself from <del><fr>e l</fr></del> one part to the
other.</ab>

<ab>

Do not forget to make a gate of <m>wax</m> for the feet of <al><oc>sand
lizards</oc></al> &amp; delicate things like this.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

When you <add>have</add> molded an animal in the first part of the
<tl>mold</tl>, do not let this part dry before you have taken away the
said animal, for the <tl>mold</tl>, in drying, contracts and would also
make the animal contract. Keep it therefore in some <env>moist &amp;
humid place</env> until you have done it.</ab>

<figure>

<id>fig_p135r_1</id>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

<link>https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5U3BqOGxwTHNPeVk</link>

</figure>

</div>

<div>
<id>p135r_3</id>
<head><pa>Vine</pa> leaf and <al>small frog</al></head>

<ab>

Take <pa>vine</pa> leaves to mold, as they are in growth, likewise with
all plants &amp; flowers or a young <pa>vine</pa> growing again after
having been cut, or when they rebud <tmp>in autumn</tmp>, because the
new leaves are more lumpy &amp; have more apparent lineation. On the
contrary old leaves are smooth on the inside &amp; pierced in several
places. Therefore place your leaf bottom down on the <tl><m>clay</m>
slab</tl>, and secure it with <tl>small points</tl>, nevertheless
leaving it its natural curve. And make a notch <add>in the
<m>clay</m></add> to hide the stem at the first gate, which, once made
&amp; dry, you will take away the stem from the leaf &amp; clean with it
well with <tl>small bristle brushes</tl> &amp; fix it with a small mount
of <m>clay</m>. Next, make several gates around the leaf with <m>wax</m>
as you know &amp; <del><fr>gec</fr></del> make the gate thin &amp; with
several lines &amp; lumpy.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>

The <pa>vine</pa> leaf is painted with green made of <m>stil de grain
yellow</m> &amp; <m><fr>verd de terre</fr></m>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>

You can cast on the leaf a <al>spider</al> or <al>frog</al> &amp;
whatever you like.</ab>

</div>
</root>
