<root>
<page>041r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f87.image</image>

<div>

<id>p041r_1</id>

<head><m>Earth for casting, for <pro>founders</pro></m></head>

<ab>It renders itself fat once beaten and also mixed with
<m><al>horse</al> dung</m>. <m><pro>Potter</pro>'s earth</m> would be
too fat and would crack &amp; would not hold in the fire, but one needs
to mix it with <ms>half the quantity</ms> of sand and a <ms>quarter</ms>
or a <ms>fifth</ms> of <m><add><al>horse</al></add> dung</m>. And leave
it to dry, then turn it to powder, then <tl>sift</tl> it to render it fine &amp;
purged of gravel, which would prevent it from casting neatly. The <m>dung</m>
renders the <m>earth</m> more amenable &amp; easier to deal with, but it
is necessary that it be well free of <m>straw</m> &amp; other things.
And when the <m>earth</m> is very fat, one needs to give it more sand
&amp; more <m>dung</m>. But one does find fat varieties of <m>earth</m>,
themselves mixed with sand. If they are not, make them so artificially.
One always needs to reheat the <m>earths</m> before casting.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p041r_02</id>

<head><pa>Garden lilly</pa></head>

<ab>If one breaks it at its first blossom &amp; it will bud &amp; bloom
only <tmp><ms>in the following year</ms></tmp>, &amp; know the
<pa>bulbous plants</pa> do thus.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p041r_03</id>

<head>Sand</head>

<ab>The sand chosen <del>cast</del> for casting should be neither so
lean that it has no stickiness, nor too fat. And even if it is found
<env><m>in nature</m></env>, however, it is not everywhere. And if you
are in a place where it is not found, you can make it, but not with
<m>fat earth</m>, for the sand does not want any of that, for it makes
it very porous. But you can make it bindable with <m>brick well
ground</m> on <tl><m>marble</m></tl>, or <m>plaster</m> or <m>calcinated
alabaster</m> or something similar, or the <m>burned marrow of
<al>ox</al> horn</m> or <m>burned asphalt</m>. If you grind it quite
finely on <tl><m>porphyry</m></tl>, it <del><fr>s</fr></del> acquires
stickiness better &amp; then you can burn it with <m>asphalt</m> or mix
it with a <ms>quarter part</ms> of <m>tripoli</m>. Guard against
<m>bread</m> falling into your sand because it makes it very
porous.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

Try mixing in <m>soot black</m>.</ab></div>

<div>

<id>p041r_04</id>

<head><al>Ducks</al></head>

<ab>Young domestic ones do not grow for a <ms><tmp>month</tmp></ms>
after they are hatched, but remain in this state. But after that they grow quickly, similarly if they go into the water. One feeds them with <m>boiled
<pa><fr>millet</fr></pa> grains</m>, crumbling them among <m>bread</m>
and spreading in <m>well chopped <pa>lettuces</pa></m>.</ab></div>
</root>
