<root>
<page>018v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f42.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p017r_1</id>

<ab>

The average weighs 18 <fr><ms>quintals</ms></fr> &amp;
measures<comment>c_018v_01</comment> xii <fr><ms>pans</ms></fr> long.
Its ball weighs eight or 9 <ms>lb</ms> &amp; its charge is six
<ms>pounds</ms> of <m>powder</m>. <del>And for</del> At the breech it
carries a <ms>thickness of three balls</ms>, &amp; in front, two. It is
more appropriate for the defense of a <env>city</env> than for battery.
However, one takes it sometimes either to break a <env>barricade</env>
or to support the battery after the cannons have fired, in order to
prevent the assailed from re-fortifying after the cannons have played or
fired. Four <al>horses</al> can draw it. It shoots at point blank eight
or nine hundred <ms><fr>pas</fr></ms> &amp; almost as much as the
<fr>bastarde</fr>.</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

To cannons &amp; large pieces one gives<del><fr>n</fr></del> as much
<m>powder</m> as is the <ms>diameter of a ball &amp; a half</ms>, to
which dimension the escutcheon<comment>c_018v_02</comment> comes. To medium pieces, such as
field pieces, &amp; smaller ones, one gives them powder the
<ms>thickness of two balls</ms>. To the passe-volant &amp; other smaller
ones, one gives them <m>powder</m> the <ms>thickness of three
balls</ms>. In general, one charges all pieces <ms>up to the
escutcheon</ms>. One charges with the <tl>ladle</tl> all
pieces from the cannon to the piece of four <ms>quintals</ms>
<del><fr>de char</fr></del>, and one gives to them two
<tl><ms>ladles</ms></tl> of <m>cannon powder</m> or one &amp; a half
of <m>arquebus powder</m>. To smaller ones, one only gives one
<tl><ms>ladle</ms></tl>, &amp; those of one <ms>quintal</ms> are
charged with a small charge.</ab>

<ab>

A field piece weighs ten or twelve <ms>quintals</ms> &amp; is ten
<fr><ms>pan</ms></fr> long or 12. Its ball weighs vi or vii <ms>lb</ms>
&amp; its charge is 4 <ms>lb</ms> of <m>powder</m>. At the breech it has
three balls &amp; two in front, as do all pieces that are smaller than
the average. One gives them more of a breech because one makes them
longer in proportion, and also because in a <env>house or
elsewhere</env> one fires them more frequently than the large pieces.
Their <ms>caliber</ms> is also small, which makes the breech 3 balls
thick. They are used for following a camp promptly &amp; for the defense
of <env>cities</env> &amp; <env>houses</env>, putting them on the
<env>walls</env> or on a <env>tower</env>. One needs three <al>good
horses</al> for drawing it.</ab>

<ab>

The passe-volant weighs vi <ms>quintal</ms>, is eight or nine
<fr><ms>pans</ms></fr> long. Its ball weighs two <ms>lb</ms>, &amp;, for
its charge, a <ms>lb</ms> &amp; a half of <m>powder</m>. At the breech
it has three balls &amp; two in the front. Two <al>horses</al> can move
it, for a single <al>horse</al> does not begin to move a piece. It is
used for the defense of <env>houses</env>, or for taking among the
<pro>infantry</pro> to break a rank of <pro>cavalry</pro>.</ab>

<ab>

The <fr>faulconneau</fr> weighs 4 <ms>quintals</ms>, is x
<fr><ms>pans</ms></fr> long. Its ball weighs one <ms>lb</ms> &amp; a
quarter, its charge is half a <ms>lb</ms> of <m>powder</m>. At the
breech three balls, at the front, two. To move it, two <al>horses</al>,
although such pieces are hardly moved insofar as they only serve to
defend <env>houses</env>. The ones which are carted around either for
battery or for siege combat, are cannons, culverins, medium-sized
<fr>bastardes</fr> &amp; field pieces</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
