<root>
<page>148v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f302.image</image>

<div>

<id>p148v_1</id>

<head>Molding <al>turtles</al></head>

<ab>Next, reassemble the parts of your <tl>mold</tl> and <tl>clamp</tl>
carefully all the joints, as much as above &amp; below as on the sides,
having not forgotten to notch the joints of the <tl>molds</tl>, as with
others. Having <tl>clamped</tl> it all, undo the <tl>clamps</tl> on the
side &amp; not the others. And thus, your <tl>mold</tl> of several
pieces <del><fr>sem</fr></del> will open as if it were only in two
halves. If you want to mold hollow, make in the middle of the <del>of
the part</del> <tl>mold</tl> of the belly a hole, from side to side,
which, inside, is <ms>of such capacity that the end of a <bp>little
finger</bp> can almost enter it</ms>, widening like a <fr>clervoise</fr>
the outside of the hole. This is to cast the <fr>noyau</fr>. But, note
that <corr>all</corr> these difficulties would be nothing if you wanted
to mold hollow because you could mold your <al>turtle</al> in two pieces
<del><ill/></del> and burn it inside, as with other animals, and it
would be done quickly. But since the <al>turtle</al> is massive &amp;
that it is weighty, without being hollow, one considers better molded in
this way, <add>hollow</add>, and in <del><fr>cha</fr></del> this fashion, to
make well a <tl>mold</tl>, one really needs <tmp>three
<ms>days</ms></tmp>. Take heed, for hollow &amp; fanciful
<tl>molds</tl>, to have some <m>strong plaster</m>, which endures the
fire without bursting, if it is possible. But, if you cannot have any
such, mix a little more <m><fr>alum de plume</fr></m> &amp; add to it
also some <m><la>crocum</la></m>, which fortifies it &amp; makes so the
flashing, if there is any, comes out so finely that it is easily undone.
Also do not forget to tighten well, with a <tl>press</tl>, your
<tl>molds</tl>, to avoid flashing which is made either when the
<tl>mold</tl> is not well joined or when it bursts. To repair, if the
features are not apparent enough, retrace them lightly with a
<tl>burin</tl>, then soften them with a <tl>small chisel</tl>. The flashing
is removed with the <df><tl><fr>chaple</fr></tl></df>, a type of
<tl>burin</tl>. For the lumps &amp; scales, they are made either with a
<tl>little gouge</tl> or a <tl>little round cutting-punch</tl>, or with
the <tl>point of a small chisel</tl>, not tempered &amp; struck on a
<tl>small file</tl>. </ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Make this hole before <del>molding</del>
joining your <tl>molds</tl>.</ab></div>
</root>
