<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="065v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f136.image">




<div id="p065v_1" categories="painting">



<head>Semi-lively colors</head>

<ab>When colors <del><fr>a</fr></del>absorb into the <m>canvas</m>, it
means that it has been given imprimatura only once, &amp; for this reason they
become matte rather than <add>being</add> shiny. But this is the best,
as long as you re-coat it twice, for in this manner, the colors, having
more body, do not die &amp; are all the more beautiful for it,
especially <m>azure</m>, <m>lake</m>, &amp; those do not have body. But
those who want to rush their painting apply imprimatura twice on the first go, to be
done with it. Thus the colors do not absorb, also they will not last as
long. The second layer of these does not absorb &amp; remains
shiny.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p065v_6" categories="painting">
        

        
<head>From nature</head>
        
<ab margin="left-top" render="tall">
There are some who paint from nature on <m>oiled paper</m>, &amp;
if they do not finish in one go, they put their <m>paper</m> &amp;
unfinished picture in <m>water</m> so that it shall not dry.</ab>
        
<ab margin="left-top" render="tall">


<pro>Illuminators</pro> painting on <m>paper</m> temper their colors
with <m>gum</m> &amp; mix in a little <m>soap</m> to make them run
better.</ab>
        
<ab margin="left-top" render="tall">

           
<pro>Painters</pro> must all learn how to depict after nature, for to them
it is travel provisions &amp; revenue &amp; sure means of earning their
passage when travelling across the lands with only their
<m><fr>cocon</fr>.</m><comment rid="c_065v_03"/></ab>
        
</div>
    
<div id="p065v_2" categories="painting">



<head>Painting large figures</head>

<ab>You need to put your <m>charcoal</m> at the tip of a <tl>stick</tl>
such that you make your first drawing from a distance because up close,
you would not be able to judge proportions as well as from a certain
&amp; sufficient distance. Also, when you paint up close, hold your
<m>charcoal</m> at the farthest end, &amp; practically with your
<bp>fingertips</bp>. For in this way you will acquire an<pro>
artist</pro>’s <del>l</del> stroke &amp; will render your <bp>hand</bp>
nimble.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p065v_3" categories="painting">



<head>Glazing</head>

<ab>One commonly glazes with colors that do not have body, such as
<m>lake</m> &amp; <m>verdigris</m>. However, to use other colors, one
mixes in a quantity of <m>calcined &amp; ground <fr>cristallin</fr></m>, which also
has no body &amp; <del>makes</del> lightens the density of the others.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p065v_4" categories="painting">



<head>White and black</head>

<ab>It is good that an <pro>apprentice</pro> should work with white
&amp; black for two or three <tmp>years</tmp> to become an
<pro>artist</pro>.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p065v_5" categories="painting">



<head><m>Lead white</m></head>

<ab>It does not die &amp; has a lot of body.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p065v_7" categories="painting">



<head margin="left-middle">Imprimatura</head>

<ab margin="left-top" render="tall">

One needs to be quite careful about this, &amp; not make it, as some
will, with gold color which is made with the <m>washings of
<tl><m>oil</m> paintbrushes</tl></m>, because <m>verdigris</m> &amp;
other corrosive colors which are in it will in the end will make
the colors die that are <del><fr>meu</fr></del> layered on next. It is
good to do it<comment rid="c_065v_02"/></ab>

<ab>
<comment rid="c_065v_04"/>with <m>ceruse</m>, <m><del>&amp; a bit of </del>yellow ocher</m>, &amp;
a little <m>massicot</m>, &amp; make it not very thick in order that it does
not crack.</ab>

</div>
</root>
