<root>
<page>119v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f244.image</image>

<div>

<id>p119v_1</id>

<head>Fashion of preparing <del><fr>aspalt</fr></del>
<add>spat</add><comment>c_119v_04</comment></head>

<ab>It is found in earth in <pl>Germany</pl>, the color of <m>cooked
plaster</m>, made of long filaments, very soft to handle. And because it
is mixed with <m>earth</m> and <m>filth</m>, one pestles it coarsely
&amp;one makes little balls, having, for this purpose, soaked it in
<m>sal ammoniac water</m> of such a composition that you were told
above. One places these balls to reheat in the fire of the <tl>furnace
of the <pro>potters</pro></tl>, then one soaks it again in the same
<m>water</m>. The <m>earth</m> and <add>the</add> coarseness and
<m>filth</m> go to the bottom, and the <m><fr>pure aspalt</fr></m>,
which is light &amp; soft and handleable as <m>wet flour</m>, adheres
with the <m>water</m> and goes to the surface, clouding the
<m>water</m>, empty that cloudy part in a separate <tl>vase</tl>.
Having sat, one, one empties the <m>water</m> by tilting, or by taking
it away with a <tl>sponge</tl>, and the<m><fr>pure aspalt</fr></m>
remains at the bottom. Dry it &amp; employ it in a <tl>frame</tl>, having
been moistened with <m>sal ammoniac water</m>. And try it in the
<tl>frame</tl>, in which it shrinks when reheated or dried, that is to
say that one needs to reheat it again on a good fire and redden it.
Thus, for medals and flat things, you should use this one, because it is
the most perfect of all for <m>gold</m>, <m>silver</m>, <m>copper</m>,
<m>lead</m>, <m>latten</m>, &amp; <m>tin</m>, for it withstands the fire
&amp; reddens whenever need be, without corrupting. The more it is used,
the <del>b</del> better it is, &amp; it does not spoil. At the beginning
it is white, &amp; being used it becomes grey. However make sure to put
aside the one that served for casting <m>lead</m> &amp; <m>tin</m> &amp;
<m>latten</m>, for <m>gold</m> would sour in it, &amp; would not come
out of it well. And to do this better, you could put it aside to be used
for each <m>metal</m>. </ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

See <la><pn>Gesnerus</pn>, De lapidibus</la>

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-top</margin>

It endures ten or twelve castings without corrupting, it withstands the
fire &amp; reddens, it is suitable for all <m>metals</m>. It is so
tenacious that should the <tl>frame</tl> be straked, it holds.

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

The <m>spat</m> almost does not set, even though it is reheated &amp; is
a kind of <m>plaster</m>. Raw, it breaks easily with the
<tl><bp>fingers</bp></tl>.</ab>

</div>

<div>

<id>p119v_2</id>

<head>Excellent secret for molding hollow and very delicately in<m>fine
gold</m></head>

<ab>Cast with your aforementioned sand your animal and <al>lizard</al>
or other thing with <m>billon silver</m> &amp; it will come out very
neat. <del>E</del> But take heed to mold it hollow, or at least leave a
small hole, in its <corr>mouth</corr> or in another place. Next,
<m>gild</m> it with <m>fine gold</m>, as uniform as it will be possible
for you, three or four or five times, &amp; until your <m>gold</m> has
the <ms>thickness of a piece of <m>paper</m></ms> or something similar,
&amp; all the scales will always show equally. Next, put it in good
<m>aquafortis</m>, which, by this hole, will corrode the <m>billon</m>
&amp; the <m>gold</m> will remain hollow &amp; light &amp;
wonderful.</ab>

</div>
</root>
