<root>
<page>053v</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f112.image</image>

<div>

<id>p053v_1</id>

<head><al>Silkworms</al></head>

<ab>They are produced from seed, that is to say eggs, that which is sold
by the <ms>ounce</ms>, which is commonly sold in <pl>Languedoc</pl> iii
<ms>lb</ms> v <cn>s</cn>. The one from <pl>Spain</pl> that
<pro>merchants</pro> bring there is considered the best because the
<al>worms</al> which come from there are not so subject to illnesses
&amp; make more <m>silk</m>. In <pl>Spain</pl>, one <ms>ounce</ms> of
<del><m>silk</m></del> seed, they produce there <al>worms</al> which
commonly yield <del><fr>ord</fr></del> xv <ms>lb</ms> of <m>silk</m>.
But <del><fr>l’<ms>once</ms></fr></del> from one <ms>ounce</ms> of seed
produced in <pl>France</pl>, they only return x or xii. Three
<ms>ounces</ms> of seed are for producing such a quantity of
<al>worms</al>, that with them you will be able to furnish a <env>room
accomodated with three or 4 shelves of large shelves</env>. Willingly
they begin to unskin themselves <tmp>around holy week</tmp>. And to do
this, one puts them in a <tl><pa>fir</pa> box</tl>, like those where one
puts <fr>dragée</fr>, warmly among <tl>feather cushions</tl>. And at the
beginning, they unskin themselves like <del><fr>f</fr></del> little
<pl>black ants</pl>, &amp; as soon as there are two or three unskinned,
one needs to give them <m><pa>white mulberry</pa> leaves</m>, and then
arrange them on the <tl>shelves</tl>. And three <ms>times <tmp>per
day</tmp></ms>, one needs to exchange <m>fresh leaves</m>. And if
<tmp>during the day</tmp> there is some <env>thunder <add>or rainy
weather, cloud-covered &amp; cool</add></env>, one needs to keep in the
<env>room</env> three or 4 <tl>chafing dishes <del>&amp;</del> with
glowing charcoal</tl>, &amp; put in <m>incense</m> until all the
<env>room</env> would be filled with <m>smoke</m>. And when the
<env>weather is warm &amp;<fr>serain</fr></env>, the <m>silk</m> abounds
more &amp; and then it is better. Some <al>worms</al> make it whiter,
others more yellowish. And even if it may be white, it yellows when one
draws it through <tl><m>hot water</m></tl> <del><fr>despuys</fr></del>.
The <al>worms</al>, <tmp>from their birth until the <del>their</del>
time when they make their cocoons &amp; their prisons</tmp>, sleep &amp;
rest 4 times, &amp; each time remain 4 or five <ms><tmp>days</tmp></ms>
resting without eating, as if they were dying for rebirth another time,
for each time they change skin &amp; begin by unskinning the head then
consequently, on different <tmp>days</tmp>, the <del><fr>s</fr></del>
rest of the body, &amp; from white turn grayish, &amp; from grayish to
white <del><fr>en fin</fr></del>. And if one of them has some illness
who does not have the strength to unskin, one needs to help it &amp;
prevent puncturing it, for at that time rendering a yellow liquor, it is
no longer worth anything. And further they scarcely profit after one has
handled it with the <tl><bp>hand</bp></tl>. <tmp>Around Pentecost</tmp>,
they begin to want to climb on the dry branches of <pa>heath</pa> or
<pa>heather</pa> that one prepares for them <del><fr>en</fr></del> &amp;
attaches</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

See <pn>Marco<comment>c_053v_01</comment> Girolamo Vida,
<add>Bishop</add> <del><la>de b</la></del> of <pl>Alba</pl> and
<pl>Cremona</pl></pn>, wrote a poem on the nature of <al>silkworms</al>.

</ab>

<ab>

<margin>left-middle</margin>

How one moves them

</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
