<root>
<page>005r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f15.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p004v_3</id>

<ab>or <m><pa>linen</pa></m> &amp; leave it thus for xx4
<ms><tmp>hours</tmp></ms> &amp; it will be etched. But if you should
want to etch promptly, varnish all your work &amp; boil it in the
aforesaid liquor, and it will promptly etch.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p005r_1</id>
<head><m>Steel</m> mirrors</head>

<ab><mark>+</mark>They are called of <m>steel</m> because in the
past they were commonly made of <m>steel</m> polished with
<m><fr>potée</fr> of emery</m>. But more easily, various kinds are made
of <m><fr>cuivre franc</fr></m>, which is <m>rosette</m>, and
<m>tin</m>, because this can be cast in a <tl>mold</tl> &amp; made
round, concave, convex &amp; however you like, to produce various
forms.</ab>

<ab>So take <ms>half</ms> of <m>rosette copper</m> &amp; <ms>half</ms>
of <m>doux tin</m>, that is to say fine, which has not yet been used.
Put them in a <tl>crucible</tl>, &amp; first melt the <m>copper</m>
well. And once it is well melted, put in the <m>tin</m> and mix
together. Then cast in the <tl>mold, of <m>white stone</m> with no
eyelets</tl>, &amp; anoint the <tl>mold</tl> with <m>oil</m>, &amp; let
it be moderately warm. Then, having
<tl>molded</tl> your mirror, you can polish it in this manner.</ab>

<ab>Set one of these in <m>plaster</m> in order that it holds firmly,
&amp; then put the other one over it with <m>thin sand</m> in between,
&amp; rub one against the other, whether hollow or flat, &amp; thus you
will polish two at once. And if you want to polish them on both sides,
you only need to switch them, which means putting the one that was
polishing into the <m>plaster</m> &amp; using the one that was in the
<m>plaster</m> to polish. After having polished them with the
<tl><m><fr>arene</fr></m></tl> you can soften them with <tl><m>tripoli
of <pl>Venice</pl></m></tl>, which should not be sandy, &amp; next with
<tl><m><fr>potée</fr></m></tl>. You polish with
<tl><m><fr>arene</fr></m></tl> using <m>water</m>, but polishing with
<tl><m>tripoli</m></tl> &amp; <tl><m><fr>potée</fr></m></tl> is done
dry. Once polished, you can set it.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p005r_2</id>
<head>Concave mirrors</head>

<ab>The concave mirror composed in the aforesaid form produces an
endless number of pretty conceits which seem magic. If someone wants to see
oneself from behind, it is necessary to place the <tl>concave
mirror</tl> on the ground on its foot, &amp; let it be at a slant;
next, <sn><add>look</add></sn> at it one <ms>step</ms> away. But if you
<sn>look</sn> at it closer up, it will show you the right way up but
with your <bp>face</bp> quite large &amp; the <sn>hairs of your
beard</sn> as thick as</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
