<root>
<page>070r</page>

<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b20500001g/f145.image</image>

<div>

<cont/>

<id>p069r_2</id>

<ab>When you have molded, it is good to reheat your mold on the smoke of
the substance you are melting, because the cast absorbs the quality
o<del><fr>e</fr></del><add>f</add> the <m>metal</m>, which afterwards runs more easily in something that comes from it.</ab>

<ab> <m><al>Human</al> bones</m> are the best for casting once
calcined.</ab>

<ab>To cast neatly, it is necessary that your substance be quite hot
&amp; to achieve this, when your substance is melted, throw in some
<m>iron scales</m>, or in powder or otherwise <del><fr>E</fr></del>, for
it heats <m>copper</m> a lot &amp; cleanses it of its <m>fat</m>. At the
end, when you want to cast, add some <m>saltpeter</m>, by folding your
additions in a <tl><m>paper</m></tl> in order that everyone may not know what you
are adding.</ab>

<ab><m><al>Sheep</al> foot bones</m> are even better than <m><al>ox</al>
foot bones</m>.</ab>

<ab><m>Oil</m> &amp; <m>tallow</m> make it really porous &amp;
<m><tl>pestled</tl> glass</m> &amp; <m>copper</m> alone.</ab>

<ab><m><fr>Cendrée</fr> earth</m> molds very neatly.</ab>

<ab><m>Ashes</m> do not have enough body to withstand
<m>copper</m>.</ab>

<ab>It is best not to mix the sands, but fill the <tl>frame</tl> with
one only.</ab>

<ab><m>Latten</m> is always fat, &amp; does not mold neatly. One finds
that it comes out better alloyed with a <ms>quarter</ms> of
<m>copper</m>, but it needs to be cast very hot.</ab>

<ab><m>Copper</m> comes out well with a bit of <m>metal</m>. If you mix
in <m>metal</m> within <m>latten</m>, it will be more brittle &amp; more
troublesome.</ab>

<ab>A slightly coarser sand has more body.</ab>

<ab><m>Sand from <del><fr>corp</fr></del> rock</m> is always better,
which seems like <m><fr>tuf</fr></m> in lumps, which has a beautiful
&amp; very fine grain, &amp; a little fat. One pestles it, then one
dries it in a <tl>skillet</tl> on the fire, until it <del>is</del> stops
smoking, then one passes it through through a <tl>double sieve</tl>
&amp; fine, &amp; one molds with it.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<m>Copper</m> or <m>latten</m> cannot come out well if the medal does
not sufficient thickness, &amp; if it does not have it, give it some
with some <m>wax</m>.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Some cast through a hole made in the middle of the reverse side of the
medal.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Some wanting to cast large works in <m>latten</m> <del><fr>y</fr></del>
mix in the sand some <m><tl>pestled</tl> glass</m> to give the <m>earth</m> some
bond. But it makes it porous, and needs to be repaired.</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
One puts in <m>lead</m> for a large work to make it run, but not
<del>not<lb/>

for</del> in a small one because it would leave <m>filth</m> all around
the work.</ab>

<cont/>

</div>
</root>
