<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="021r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f47.image">




<div id="p021r_1">



<head><pro>Cannoneer</pro></head>

<ab>As for small cannons that are not loaded with a linstock, one loads
them with <m>powder</m> all the way up to the touch hole, which is
placed at a point on the cannon that indicates the appropriate
measure.</ab>

<ab>To point a cannon, that is to say to fix the target, one needs to
set the sights, in other words, take aim, from the sides rather than the
top, that is to say the top of the cannon. By taking aim from the top,
you can find the line of fire that leads to your target, but you will
not find out if the cannon leans more to one side or the other. Then
take your sights first from one side and then from the other and adjust
your cannon to point at your intended target. Then set your sights from
the top of the breech, which will be quickly done. Next, use your
discretion to lower the cannon a little if you are within firing range,
because the force of the <m>powder</m> blast usually raises the barrel.
If you are outside of the range in which the cannon can fire in a direct
line, you should consider that the weight of the cannonball will lower
the barrel.</ab></div>

<div id="p021r_2" continued="yes">



<head>Shooting a cannon at night</head>

<ab>Some keep their cannons loaded <del>and</del>in the daylight hours.
Then, so that the <pro>cannoneer</pro> can shoot into the breach where
the besieged are perhaps reparing <x>the breach</x>, the assailants
raise a false alarm so that the besieged throw torches or <m>artificial
fire</m> into the moats or around the breach, light by which the
<pro>cannoneer</pro> can take aim. Sometimes by using the reflection off
<tl>mirrors</tl> or <tl>jars</tl> full of <m>water</m>, the assailants
can redirect the light onto the breach. The method that you know, using
a sundial and <m>lead</m> line, is also very good. Others use strong
<m>iron</m> pegs to fix two or three planks onto a platform of
<m>wood</m> made to carry a battery of cannon, and leave some notches
empty where the cannon wheels can pass perfectly. And with this method
you will always put the cannon in such a position so that it doesn't
tilt to the right or the left. And so that it isn't too high or low when
you fire the following day, you place a marker that is well fixed in the
ground, that just touches the bottom edge of the canon after it has been
aimed and adjusted for firing.</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">If the platform, the wheels or wedge
parts break or come loose, this invention holds no advantage.</ab>



</div>
</root>