<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="082r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f169.image">




<div id="p082r_a1">

<head> Heat of <m>copper</m></head>

<ab>It is hot enough when you see it neat &amp; even on top, without
<m>filth</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p082r_a2">

<head>Frame</head>

<ab><m>Iron</m> &amp; <m>copper</m> make it porous if the <m>metal</m>
touches it, &amp; the <m>wood</m> warps. Thus, make a mold of
<m>wood</m>, &amp; have frames of <m>bricks</m> made inside this mold of
whatever thickness that you want.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p082r_a3">

<head><m>Glair of eggs</m></head>

<ab><m>Glair of eggs</m> gives strength to sand to make several
casts.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p082r_a4">

<head><pro>Watchmakers</pro></head>

<ab>To divide the teeth of their cogwheels proportionately, they do not
use a compass, for there is none so fine that it can compass distances
as small as those of the small cogwheels. But they make a
<fr>platteforme</fr> (as they call it) of <m>latten</m> divided into
several circles, &amp; each circle is divided into equal distances
marked by a point, and each circle has a certain number of them, for
example one 30, another 36, another 40, &amp;c. Then, on the pierced
center of the <fr>platteforme</fr>, they set the small cogwheel there,
and on the center of the cogwheel a flat line or alidade which is moved
to the circle with the number that you want to mark on your cogwheel.
Then they draw a line on the cogwheel with a prick, then move the
alidade to the following point, &amp; continue to mark thus. And to mark
the points on the circles of their <fr>platteforme</fr>, they divide the
circle into three &amp; then divide this third part into as many
distances as is necessary with regard to the total division of the
circle, &amp; make in this manner their division &amp; distribution of
the teeth as fine as they please.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p082r_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5MG1jZS1LOUE2QWs">





</figure>

</div>
</root>