<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="126v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f258.image">




<div id="p126v_1">



<head><m>Crocum ferri</m></head>

<ab>It is best made rather with <m>iron rust</m> than with
<m>filings</m>. For if the vinegar is good, you will see it boil with
large bubbles <del>as if it</del> on the rust, as it it were on the
fire, on the fillings, it does not boil unless it is put on the fire or
hot ashes. However, when the fillings are passed through vinegar &amp;
you have made it evaporate &amp; heat up &amp; it is very red, if you do
this again for a second time, the vinegar will have much more strength,
&amp; the crocum will only be finer for it &amp; redder. Those who use
it to cast in <m>gold</m> <del>ven</del> buy the ounce for forty or
fifty sols.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">It does not harden the molds, and, in
scraping, one cannot tell that they are harder from it. But it makes the
mold less dense, and it drinks in and attracts the <m>gold</m>
better.</ab></div>

<div id="p126v_2">



<head><m>Plaster</m></head>

<ab>You can mold with it as large a piece as you please. But if you take
your molds from large works &amp; pieces of <m>wood</m>, it will not
release well, unless you <del>boil</del> make your wood drink up very
hot wax. For the wood absorbs &amp; drinks &amp; in this way attracts
the plaster. You can assume the same thing for any other large piece of
work. But the cure is to <del>l’ab</del> soak <del>l’ouvra</del> with
very hot wax, the work on which you want to cast your plaster. For, by
this means, it will not drink it up &amp; will release very neatly.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

If the <m>plaster</m> shrinks, it will always make flaws. Find some hard
ones and <del>it</del> place your molds well pressed together before
casting.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">It is not good when it
shrinks.</ab></div>

<div id="p126v_3" continued="yes">



<head>Plants difficult to burn in the <fr>noyau</fr></head>

<ab>Any plant which has a hard stem &amp; like <m>wood</m> is very
difficult to burn in the <fr>noyau</fr>, such as asparagus, thyme, &amp;
similar things, because they stay as <m>coal</m> in the small conduits,
&amp; if they do not reduce well into ashes, it is not possible to empty
them from the mold. Some reheat them, to this effect, two or
<del>d</del> three times. Others, putting several plants together in the
mold, pass through <del>threads</del> the plants &amp; the circle of
earth, which is to receive the wet sand,<del>plusi</del></ab>

<ab>This does proceed from plants that have a stem with lines, because
rosemary burns well, but it is in the nature of certain plants.</ab>



</div>
</root>