<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="148v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f302.image">




<div id="p148v_1">



<head>Molding <al>turtles</al></head>

<ab>Join the parts of your mold and fix very carefully clamps on all
joints, which are on the top, the bottom and the sides of the mold; do
not forget to notch the joints as you did with the other moulds. Once
you have fixed all the clamps, remove the sides ones, not the others.
Thus your mold, made of several pieces, will open as if it was only made
of two parts. If you want to mould hollow, pierce a hole big enough to
thread the end of your little finger in the middle of your mold's belly.
Widen the outside of the hole, like clervois, in order to cast the core.
You could avoid all these difficulties if you didn't mold hollow; you
could then mold your <al>turtle</al> in two pieces, more quickly, and
burn it inside of the mold like other animals. But a <al>turtle</al> is
weighty, and would be heavy if not molded hollow. This is why it is
considered better to mold it that way. It takes three days to make the
proper <sup>hollow</sup> mould. To mold hollow and fantastic
<sup>forms</sup>, you need very strong <m>plaster</m> which can
withstand fire without bursting. But if you can't get this kind of
<m>plaster</m>, add to it a little more <m>stone alum</m>, and also add
<m>crocum</m>, which fortifies it <sup>the <m>plaster</m></sup> and
makes the flaws -- if there are any -- so fine that they can be easily
removed. Do not forget to tighten your mould with a press in order to
avoid flaws that happen when your mold is not tight enough, or when it
bursts. To repair it, if the lines are not apparent enough retrace with
a burin, then soften the lines with a ciselet. You can remove the flaws
with a chaple, a kind of burin. For the lumps and crumbly bits, they can
be made with a gadet or a small carving tool which isn't hammered, and
hitting with a small file.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">Make this hole before joining the
mould.</ab></div>
</root>