<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="144v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f294.image">




<div continues="yes" id="p144r_1">





<ab>having been thusly arranged and well cleaned with brushes, put the
circle of <m>clay</m> around the base. Then, with a roll of <m>clay</m>
placed on the middle of the back of the <al>turtle</al>, as you can see,
and at the widest place, divide your mold. Next, <m>oil</m> with your
<m>oiling</m> brush half the half of the shell you want to mold. If you
sand is a bit thick, temper your sand with <m>warm water</m>, so that
without burning yourself you can put your finger in it without burning
it. And before casting it, rub the shell with <m>spirits</m>. And then
cast your sand and let it take hold. And note that all things that have
shells, or that are hard, or do not yield as <al>snakes</al> and
<al>lizards</al> do, must be <m>oiled</m> to come out cleanly. The
things that yield do not need this. <m>Warm water</m> means that the
tempered sand sits better on the <m>oil</m>, which otherwise would not
work. With the half <al>turtle</al> having been thusly molded, separate
it with its mold from its <m>clay</m> base, which you will put aside to
use when needed. Then clean your half-mold, join it and flatten it like
for the others. But because there will be the roll of <m>clay</m>, the
half mold will have more than just half the <al>turtle</al> in it, cut
and crop cleanly the excess <sup>clay</sup> and clean everything well
with the brushes. Then at the top of the edge of the mold on the side
where it is cut, at the halfway mark, make two notches as you have done
with other molds. And flip the <al>turtle</al> on its base, as it was,
and secure the two legs that are not molded with <m>iron</m> pins and
fill the empty areas around it, up to the edge of the top shell with
some <m>clay</m>. Then place the circle around it and place a roll of
<m>clay</m> on the first mold, a bit above the notches. And having
<m>oiled</m> the first half-mold and its notches and the shell of the
<al>turtle</al>, and having also sprinkled it with <m>spirits</m>, warm
your <m>water</m>, temper your sand with a bit of <m>salt water</m>,
<m>ammoniac</m>, and the aforesaid <m>hot water</m>, make your cast.
Having taken hold, keep the sides of the two molds neatly together, and
for each side secure the joints, which are not prone to do so naturally,
with two clamps, so that when you uncover the bottom of the
<al>turtle</al> the top joint does not open. Then open the side with the
belly and the throat, in the same manner that you would open a
<al>crayfish</al>, which is the hardest animal to mold of all animals
that are molded in two parts.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p144v_1" margin="left-top" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5ZGhySWFITlRSaG8">







</figure>

<figure id="fig_p144v_2" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SlhGM2FYLUUteXc">







</figure>

<ab margin="left-bottom">You can also mold your <al>turtle</al>
in one piece for each side, but you will need to burn it. And then to
make the hollow, the recooked mold cannot be well-<m>oiled</m> because
it absorbs the <m>oil</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom"><mark/>+

If there is <m>crocum</m> in your sand, the joints of the molds will not
join well together. </ab>

<ab margin="bottom">

Turn to the second leaf.</ab>

</div>
</root>