<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="127v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f260.image">




<div id="p127v_a1">

<head>Founder's earth</head>

<ab>It is <m><fr>terre bolbene</fr></m> mixed with dung or cloth waste,
which withstand fire, which you need to always have provision of, to
lute your molds which must be used to cast silver &amp; that you need to
reheat. Those, where one needs to burn some flower or animal, should not
be luted, until they have been reheated once and they have been cleaned
from bones &amp; ashes remaining inside, and having removed the clamps,
you have opened the two halves to see if they have any cracks. For there
is some plaster that is not so hard in the fire, the one as much as the
other. Moreover, there is some which makes crusty the things which stay
burning inside. And these are imperfections that one needs to avoid,
either <del>by</del> by bathing well with eau-de-vie the animal before
casting in the wet sand, or mixing in more or less brick, or alum, or
reheating the brick more, or in place of the brick, mixing in crucible
bottoms &amp; similar things which resist well in the fire. Having
therefore reheated your mold to burn it inside, leave to cool well. And
if it is neat &amp; not cracked, reput the clamps &amp; lute with this
above mentioned founder’s earth &amp; sprinkle a little sifted ash &amp;
let dry a little. But keep yourself from luting <del>that they are
not</del> until the molds are colde. Those for casting silver, where
there is nothing to burn inside, only need, except when the gate &amp;
vents are made, luting &amp; reheating once. Do not lute the end of the
mold where you want to make your gate, rather leave it uncovered &amp;
the exit of the vent as well. </ab>

<ab>If the molds <del>that</del> were <del>do</del> to crack, it is
<del>make thus</del> at the first reheating, for at the second, they no
longer crack.</ab>

<ab>The smallest molds are reheated more quickly. Take <del>the</del>
therefore the first ones reheated when you cast, for you can put several
of them to reheat. .</ab>

<ab>Light the charcoals, firstly in the forge, or in some other place
nearby, &amp; having placed your molds on a layer of good embers, not
burning too much, to have a slow fire at the beginning, put there &amp;
adjust a little the half lit charcoals in the forge.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">

The earth that founders use to braze or solder, which is sandy clay
earth, or else clay mixed with sand, after having dried &amp; sieved
&amp; then composed it, is good for luting your molds, because this
earth melts rather than cracks. And any earth that melts <del>is</del>
cannot be lacking in this.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">

Iron wire to give it bond.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p127v_1" margin="left-top" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5S2VzRmhYUWpfbmc">







</figure>

<ab margin="left-middle">

Lute thickly your molds, &amp; if they are small, you can reheat them
immediately in a good fire, especially those of crocum.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

If the earth is good, &amp; <del>l</del> does not crack while reheating,
&amp; does not separate from the mold, the molds will also not crack
&amp; will not make flaws at the casting. Reheat with slow ease in a
closed fire &amp; do not expose them hot to the air.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

Lute rather thickly in two or three layers, especially right in the
joints, in order that the silver does not come out of the mold. </ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">

Reheat in a <fr>four de reverberation</fr>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">

To test if your earth is good, before putting it on your mold, lute at
the place of the wall of the forge which is around the <fr>tuelle</fr>
&amp; barrel of the bellow, &amp; light the fire and if it withstands
this without cracking, it will be good.</ab>

</div>
</root>