<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="163v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f332.image">




<div id="p163v_1">



<head><al>Crayfish</al></head>

<ab>The hairy little horns that it <sup>the <al>crayfish</al></sup> has
under its snout tend to come out lumpy and unclear because, after they
are burnt, it is difficult to remove and clean away their ash, which,
staying in the mold, prevents the <m>metal</m> from running well. And
for this reason, one makes a small gate of <m>wax</m> thread at the tips
of them, in order both to hold them up and to blow away the cumbersome
ashes from inside.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">Do not spare any pins, placing them not
only in the middle of the body, but also on the big legs, and two or
three on the tail, according to the positioning that you want to give
it.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p163v_2">



<head><m>Crocum</m></head>

<ab>That which has become rusty by itself, having been doused with
<m>water</m>, <m>salt</m>, and either <m>vinegar</m> or <m>urine</m>,
and then well-dried and reddened by heating, is deep red when crushed on
<m>porphyry</m> and is of the color of <m>bol de levant</m>, almost like
<m>minium</m>. But that which is doused with <m>urine</m> and dried
acquires a deeper color and almost like crushed <m>aes ustum</m> or like
<m>vermillion</m>. But the first one, finely crushed, acquires a bright
red color like <m>cinnabar</m> when placed in <m>spirits</m>. And the
one and the other, when prepared as said above, finely ground and made
very hot, produce a red smoke like an acid vapor if, being thus hot and
fine, one throws <m>vinegar</m>, <m>urine</m> or <m>spirits</m> on top.
The <m>urine</m> makes a lot of color and the <m>spirits</m> as
well.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p163v_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5anJvd0FQQ3BkRFE">





</figure>

</div>

<div id="p163v_3">



<head>Repairing</head>

<ab>It is much better to only lightly repair your work with a burin
called an <fr>onglet</fr> or the one called <fr>chaple</fr> or with a
small file. Above all, avoid touching your work, but touch only the burr
or lumpy parts that will have occurred during the casting. While
reworking, moisten and rub your work with a small <m>bristle</m>
brush.</ab>

</div>
</root>