<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="157v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f320.image">




<div id="p157v_1">



<head>Ashes in the moulds</head>

<ab>You must let the mold cool down rather than blow into it to try to
get the ashes out. Because when the mold is hot, the ashes stick to it,
and when it cold, they separate from it more easily, and will exit by
blowing with le vent a vapeur.</ab></div>

<div id="p157v_2">



<head>Moulding a <al>bird</al></head>

<ab>You must give it its pose. And to do so, place it on its side on a
<m>clay</m> base and hide it in the aforesaid <m>clay</m> base and sink
half the aforesaid <al>bird</al> in it, so that it is only showing one
leg and foot, then you will apply <m>butter</m> to keep the feathers
down and then apply some <m>spirits</m>. Then cast it. And having taken
hold, clean and uncover what needs to be uncovered. Because the feet are
made of bones which are hard to burn, and which will not be able to be
cleaned neither with <m>quicksilver</m>, nor by any other means, if the
mold does not open, uncover the bottom of the foot and the toe, or the
nail of the claw, and mold <sup>it with</sup>a separate piece. Make a
second cooking and open your mold and clean the bones. Feet generally
remain <sup>too</sup> weak to support the a heavy <al>bird</al>. Because
of this one adapts an <m>iron</m> thread in the foot mold which goes
through the body before you cast. In this way they are reinforced. Some
mold the wings in a frame. Some mold the head and the aforesaid wings
separately en noyau, then reattach and repair them to start shaping
<sup><al>the bird</al></sup>, which will firstly have a rigid shape and
support the tempered sand.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">They are skinned and filled with
<m>cotton cloth</m>. And for the best result, you must prepare it in the
way that <pro>leather-workers</pro> do, so that they do not lose their
comely feathers. The preparation is made of <m>alum</m> and <m>flour
paste</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p157v_3">



<head>Po<exp>ur</exp> f<exp>air</exp>e h<exp>…</exp> vin f<exp>…</exp>rs
<x>?</x></head>

<ab>Prenez un chausson du pied droid <add>t</add> qui ait este porte et
le faictes<lb/>

tremper en <m>eau</m> et de l<m>eau</m> q<exp>u</exp>i en sortira la
f<exp>air</exp>e boyre au mesme<lb/>

ou autre et v<exp>er</exp>rez merveilles</ab>

</div>
</root>