<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="118r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f241.image">




<div id="p118r_a1">

<head><al>Snails</al></head>

<ab>Those which are found in the <env>sea</env> &amp; similarly those in
which certain small crabs dwell are very beautiful for grottoes, if they
are stripped of the first crust of their shell with <m><la>aqua
fortis</la></m>, for they truly appear to be made of
<m>mother-of-pearl</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p118r_a2">

<head>For removing flaws and flashing from things <tl>molded</tl> <fr>en
noyau</fr></head>

<ab>If your <tl>molds</tl> are of good <m>plaster</m> which withstands
well the fire<del>&amp;</del>, they will not crack at all, especially
if, with presses, they are well squeezed well between two tablets or in
a <tl>vessel</tl> filled with <m>ashes</m> or sand, &amp; in this way
they will make any flaws. But if they do make some, you can remove them
with a <tl>burin</tl> that one calls <fr><tl>chaple</tl></fr>, which has
a tip like a small <tl>chisel</tl>.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p118r_a3">

<head>For <env>grottoes</env></head>

<ab margin="left-middle">

The <m>old <pa>vine</pa> stocks</m></ab>

<ab><m>Stones made from water</m> called <m><df>stuf</df></m>;
<m>charcoal</m>; the compound of <m>tin</m> &amp; <m>fine latten</m>;
<m>paper pestled</m> &amp; mixed with <m>pestled glass</m>; <m>cork</m>;
<m>heated parchment</m>; <m>white coral</m> are appropriate for making
<env>grottoes</env>. But <m>fantastical pieces of wood</m> which are
found in the <env>forests</env> &amp; <m><pa>mushrooms</pa></m> and
<m><fr><pa>potirons</pa></fr></m> of trees, once dry, are better than
all because they are light. One mixes in small pieces of
<m>looking-glass tin</m> which has a shiny luster. One finely pestles in
a different kind of <m>marcasite</m> which one washes to cleanse them of
<m>earth</m>, &amp;one dusts the work with it, which is very beautiful.
If there is no fountain in the <env>grotto</env>, one glues all
<del><fr>al</fr></del> of this with <m>colle forte</m>, <del>which</del>
and it is soon done. <add>Have examples of all kinds of <m>mines</m>.
The <m>sulfurous marcasites</m> which do not have a grain but are even
like <m>looking-glass tin</m> are very beautiful.</add></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<m><fr>Rosette</fr></m> is found sometimes mixed with certain brittle
lumps which are pulverized under the <tl>hammer</tl>, which are very
beautiful pulverized on <env>grottoes</env>.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p118r_a4">

<head><m>Looking-glass tin</m></head>

<ab>It whitens and renders firm fine <m>tin</m> if <del><fr>en
on</fr></del> one puts <del>in</del> in one ounce of it, that is to say,
i <mark/>℥ of <m>looking-glass tin</m> in one <ms>lb</ms> of
fine <m>tin</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p118r_a5">

<head><m>Sal ammoniac</m></head>

<ab><del>It</del><m>Sal ammoniac water</m> is very natural for
<tl>casting</tl> in <m>gold</m> and in <m>silver</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>