<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="121v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f248.item.r=">




<div id="p121v_a1">

<head>For casting in <m>silver</m></head>

<ab>You need to arrange your animals as said, and compose the same sand
<del>two parts of</del> out of <ms>4 parts</ms> of <m>plaster</m>, of
<ms>two parts</ms> reheated <m>brick</m>, &amp; <ms>one part</ms>
<m>alum de plume</m> reheated, and mix it well. Then, having been
prepared thus, and you wishing to mold it, take the <ms>three parts</ms>
of an earthenware <tl>bowl</tl>, from which the peasants eat their soup,
of the aforementioned sand, &amp; add to it pure <m>alum de plume</m>,
reheated &amp; pulverized in the <m>mortar</m>, as much as you can grab
with <ms>4 <bp>fingers</bp> and the <bp>thumb</bp></ms>, or a <ms>small
double handful</ms>. Then, mix mix well &amp; wet with a little <m>sal
ammoniac</m> &amp; the rest of the <m>common water</m><mark/>+
&amp; stir it with your <tl>pallet</tl>, so that it all becomes like a
thick sauce or light <m>mustard</m>. &amp; having rubbed, with the
<fr>pinceau</fr>, the animal with <fr>eau de vye</fr>, cast &amp; blow,
and beat the table to shake the <tl>mold</tl> &amp; do as with others.

<add>Do not forget to put in it <m>crocum</m>, for it prevents the
<tl>molds</tl> from cracking, &amp; is appropriate for all
<m>metals</m>.</add></ab>

<ab margin="left-top">

Alloyed <m>silver</m> is better for casting than the fine one, provided
that it is <fr>doulx</fr>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">

One needs for the <m>alum de plume</m> to be well pulverized and well
mixed.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">

<m>Sal ammoniac</m> is a friend of <m>gold</m> and of
<m>silver</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">



<add>Which needs to be placed before the sand in the <tl>dish</tl>,
which is put in the <m>water</m>, &amp; not the <m>water</m> in the
sand</add></ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

<m>Latten</m> is the ennemy of<m>gold</m> &amp; the friend of
<m>silver</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p121v_a2">

<head><m>Silver</m> for casting</head>

<ab>It is not fine <m>silver</m> but alloyed, &amp; which does not
become perfectly white on the fire, they put it to whiten after the
fusion to also clean it of the solder. <del>or of the</del> When you
need to attach some <del>leg</del> animal against another or to repair,
it is commonly <fr>teston</fr> <m>silver</m>. And, all alloyed
<m>silver</m>, as long as it is <fr>douls</fr>, is good.</ab>

<ab>Before starting to cast in <m>silver</m>, one needs to have earth
<del>of which</del> which withstands the fire, like the sandy earth
<del>de qu</del> mixed with <m>cloth waste</m> which <pro>founders</pro>
use to cast their canons, or any good <m>lute</m> which withstand fire,
in order to surround your <tl>molds</tl> &amp; fortify them, for one
needs for them to be red. One needs to also tie them with
<tl><m>iron</m> wire</tl>.</ab>

<ab>That before <del>casting sil</del> reheating the <tl>molds</tl>, you
have the mixture one needs to make the <m>silver</m> run.</ab>

<ab>If the <pro>goldsmiths</pro> knew knew the substance to make
<m>silver</m> run in their works, they would buy a lot. Some buy it five
sols for a denier.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

I have used <m>silver</m> from the capital.</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">

Before <del>binding</del> luting &amp; strengthening your <tl>molds</tl>
for <m>gold</m> &amp; <m>silver</m> with the said <m>earth</m>, one
needs for the cast to be made &amp; the vents, &amp; the <tl>molds</tl>
to have been reheated <del>of</del> very red, to burn the animals,
flowers and plants that are inside, &amp; to clean them well of the
ashes. Once well clean &amp; prepared, lute them &amp; bind them with
<tl><m>iron</m> wire</tl>, &amp; reheat them again until they will be
well red.</ab>

</div>
</root>