<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="095r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f195.image">




<div continues="yes" id="p094r_a1" continued="yes">





<ab>The <pro>furbisher</pro> buys his blades by the dozen which are not
finished, <x>but ready</x> to be pulled from <x>their</x> sheaths since
he does this himself in order to add them well at the pommels and
guards.</ab>

<ab>Spanish swords are esteemed to be better for they are of better
<m>steel</m> and <m>iron</m> but they are not as well-forged as swords
from Vienne in Dauphiné. The Spanish ones are not as well sharpened from
the forge since they sharpen them with their feet and this is what makes
them wavy.</ab>

<ab>Blades from Vienne commonly cost xviii or 19 lb.</ab>

<ab>The first thing the <pro>furbisher</pro> does to his new blades is
to draw them out from the sheath, which he does himself or has it done
by <pro>locksmiths</pro> or <pro>blacksmiths</pro> to whom he gives some
liart for their <m>charcoal</m>. Afterwards they pass it over a
grindstone to cut it down. Then they lay it down on the chameau<m>,</m>
and with some powdered <m>emery</m>, fine and soft as flour, and soaked
with <m>oil</m> to make it take, they polish the sword with the stick
used to take off the tracks left by the grindstone and then they clean
the blade well with the <m>emery</m>. And they add a drop or two of
<m>oil</m> spread with the finger to give it luster. Once the <m>oil</m>
is applied, they polish it again on the chameau with the "felin" which
is a thunderstone mounted on the middle of a stick like the "fustée."
And this stick is called the "felindel" stick. Once they used the
"felin," they polish it again with some <m>chalk</m> and the <m>oil</m>
<x>already</x> on the sword. After they follow this and going over it
again, they polish it with dry <m>chalk</m>. Finally when they are
finished with mounting <x>of the pommel and guard</x>, they give it a
sharp edge with a file. They then dry it and sharpen it and furbish it
again with some dry <m>chalk</m>. At the end when they are completed and
mounted, they give it <x>the blade</x> a sharp edge with a grater.</ab>

<ab>They are polished on a false mounting with the guards which are
present in order to find out if they work well together. And employing a
blade of the sort of which all the sizes should be made in the hand, one
conjectures whether it will be as strong when mounted.</ab>

<ab>One puts the blade in a vice between two pieces of <m>wood</m>, then
with a file, they enlarge <x>it</x> if needed for attaching the guard.
Then to clench it, one positions the place to be riveted and the pommel
on a piece of <m>wood</m>. And with a hammer, one beats on the top to
make it very level and to secure the pommel. Then with the hammer, one
finishes the rivet when the hammer is well secured and does not shake.
The <m>wood</m> is placed so as not to put gashes in the pommel.
Afterwards one makes a place for the rivet with a file or chisel. And
some make the rivet <x>or attachment</x> in a diamond-shape but this is
not as good as a round <x>topped one</x> because one cuts oneself on the
corner of the rivet.</ab>



</div>
</root>