<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="151v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f308.image">




<div continues="yes" id="p150v_1">





<ab>However, do not remove it before you have prepared the whole
<al>turtle</al>, because you will use this <m>earth</m> as
<m>cement</m>, should you need embed something or make repairs with a
chisel. If you have some metal overflow at the joints of your mold, you
will remove it, either with a burin, called a chaple, or with a very
sharp pen-knife, or with a small file followed by the chisel. Always
keeping in front of you the real thing to do as best you can. You can
curl on a file a chisel point, which is not at all moistened, to make
something lumpy. For these <al>turtles</al> and any other hollow things
which you can assume are quite big, create a <m>ligue</m> of half
<m>lead</m> and half <m>refined tin</m>. There is more to do when
molding a <al>turtle</al> than when molding a dozen flowers. If there is
<m>crocum</m> in your sand, there will be no metal overflow and if you
are unfortunate enough that there should be some on the sides, these
will be as thin as <m>paper</m>, as long as your mold is very tightly
pressed together. And to make the scales of <al>turtles</al> and other
animals, you can make little chisel marks in the shape of round punch
cutters, others in the shape of a gouge, or shaped like a <al>snake</al>
or <al>lizard</al> scale, and other using a file used to make twisty
bits and lumps. <al>Turtles</al> that do not need to be molded hollow
are not as much work, because they are molded in two pieces and repair
them with little chisels <sup>that make</sup> punch cutters, little
couge, and serrated chisels.

<figure id="fig_p151v_1" margin="left-middle" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bk1US2QxRTVwa2s">







</figure>

</ab>

</div>

<div id="p151v_1">



<head><m>Wheat oil</m></head>

<ab>You must make it between two empty <m>iron</m> blades, the bottom
one in particular will be slanted downwards and on this one you will put
an even and equal <sup>layer</sup> of <m>wheat</m>. Then you will place
on it the other <sup>blade</sup>, which is very hot, and you will press
it down until you see the black <m>oil</m> drip. Remove the top blade
when you have enough. This <m>oil</m> dries very quickly. It gilds
<m>silver</m> and varnished things, deepens the color of gilded things,
<sup>can be used</sup> as a <m>varnish</m> on <m>iron</m> before you
engrave it, and to varnish the tanned <sup><m>leather</m> parts</sup> of
sword hilts. And it could also be used by <pro>those who make gilded
<m>leather</m></pro>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">You must use this, as has been done
recently. And for things you need to mold, it must not be as thick as
for dyeing.

</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">You cannot use this to oil hairy
animals, because it is too strong and rigid, but it is good to apply to
the foot of a little animal, like a <al>fly</al> and other similar
things. It is also excellent to dye white stones <ill/></ab></div>
</root>