<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="025r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f55.item">




<div continues="yes" id="p024v_1">





<ab>a hundred feet away from the battery and should be surrounded with
barricades or trenches. And this is where they go and get <m>powder</m>
in bags or baskets. And each piece has its own basket to it three or
four times. Then, when the cannon is placed on the platform, one puts an
arquebus bulletproof board between two gabions. Then, with a lantern, a
<pro>gunner</pro> reloads it, and with the ramer which is at the other
end of the lantern, two men press as hard as they can, nine of ten
pushes, until the <m>powder</m> is dense Then another one adds some
<m>hay</m> or <m>straw</m> and the others ram for a while. Another one
loads the cannon ball. And the one with the <m>hay</m> adds the same
amount and presses again. Another one adds a <m>wood</m> hung but this
might damage the piece. And if one has to shoot a lot, one would need
many hungs which are heavy to bring. When the cannon is loaded, xx or
xxv <pro>workers</pro> push it forward with the sticks by the side,
behind the gabions without taking off the board until the cannon reaches
it. Once the cannon is forward, the <pro>gunner</pro> adjusts it with
the hooks at the back, pointing at the target on each side and then in
the middle.Then another one nearby sets fire. Each <pro>gunner</pro>
needs 3 <pro>cannoners</pro>: one to load, one to point at the target
and one to set fire. Sometimes, against a camp where breaches are made,
one shoots a cartridges, as you find elsewhere, or one may use a basket
full of <m>stones</m>, <m>cars' nails</m> or similar things. A cannon
must not be carried unless it is with two <m>wood</m> or <m>iron</m>
carriages. And you need seven quintals and a half of <m>iron</m> to fill
the cannon's wheels, flasques and other equipage. The best battery is,
according to some people, made as a curtain which sideways, because by
doing so you unsettle more stones.</ab>

<mark/>----------------------------------------

<ab margin="bottom">



Some add small wheels to a piece and a thick board to the end of the
piece so it can be moved quicker and without noise. Others add some
leather around the wheels and also add soles or leather shoes to the
horses' hooves so they cannot be heard.</ab></div>
</root>