<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="142v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f290.image">




<div id="p142v_1">



<head>Molding <al>grasshoppers</al> and things too thin</head>

<ab>If you have to mold a piece of written-on <m>paper</m> that is too
thin, after you have done the first cast and it has set, give a little
thickness to the reverse of your <m>paper</m> with melted <m>butter</m>,
which is the most appropriate means there is, &amp; for strengthening
the wings of either a <al>butterfly</al> or a <al>grasshopper</al>, or
any delicate part of an animal to which you need to give thickness. But
take heed to apply this melted <m>butter</m> under the wing or in
whichever place it will not be seen. For giving thickness to a pansy or
other flowers, <m>butter</m> is not good, but rather <m>wheat oil</m>,
which is soon dry &amp; holds firm. <m>Wax</m> would not be appropriate
here for it is too hot once melted, and it makes the thing to which it
is applied contract. But <m>butter</m> is amiable and handleable.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">If you write on <m>paper</m> or on common
<m>carton</m> and your letters are made with <m>gum</m>, the moisture of
the <m>clay</m> plate (?) or the wet (?) sand for a noyau will moisten
your letters <sup>and</sup> undo them. Write therefore with
<m>cinnabar</m> mixed with <m>oil</m>, on oiled &amp; stamped (?)
<m>paper</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle"><mark/>+Reheat your molds with
<m>charcoal</m> firstly lit in the forge, so that the fire is not too
hot and does not break the molds. And do not fire as strongly where the
mold is thin as where it is thick.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p142v_2">



<head>Molds</head>

<ab>Make some notches in them <sup>the molds</sup> that enter more into
the inside of the mold than the outside because in this way, they have
more strength. Take care to keep from reheating them suddenly in a
burning hot fire, because this will make them break.</ab>

<ab margin="right-middle">Do not keep them <sup>molds</sup> in a
humid place, nor an enclosed place if they are not well dry, because
they will mold. The same with dried animals.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">It is not at all necessary to reheat the
molds two times when the animal can pull away without burning, as do
<al>toads</al>, which can very well be molded hollow like all thick
animals. However, it is always good to redden the mold once.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p142v_3">



<head><m>Lute</m> for <m>luting</m> your molds</head>

<ab>I have not found a <sup>lute</sup> that is made more quickly than
this one, nor a better one. Take some of the lean <m>earth</m> that
<pro>artillery founders</pro> and <pro>bell founders</pro> use to make
their trusseaulx and molds, which is lean and sandy. Soak it moderately
like a very thick <m>mortar</m>. Mix into it about one half of <m>horse
manure</m> and then beat it well. Afterwards mix in one third of
<m>cloth waste</m> or <m>cloth shavings</m> and beat it again quite
strongly. You can reheat your mold as soon as the <m>lute</m> is
ready.</ab>

</div>
</root>