<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="044r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f93.image">




<div id="p044r_a1">

<head>The range of an arquebus</head>

<ab>The proportion of a hunting arquebus is a length of 4 king's feet
and a bullet of xviii pennyweight, a chasse of vi pennyweight of
<m>powder</m>, its range iiii-by-xx pans and 3 and a half feet and two
thumbs and a few lines, which is the Paris aulne. The medium arquebus,
which is the usual one and the easiest, has xv pennyweight of
<m>bullet</m>, v pennyweight of <m>powder</m> &amp; a range of lx
paces.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p044r_a2">

<head><pro>Pewterer</pro></head>

<ab>They mix viii <ms>lb</ms> <add>or ten</add> of <m>lead</m>, per
<ms>quintal</ms> of <m>tin</m> in <env>cities where they are <pro>sworn
masters</pro></env>. But elsewhere, they add as much as they can. One
also uses ii <ms>lb</ms> of <m>looking glass tin</m> to bind it &amp;
three <ms>lb</ms> of <m>debris</m>, that is to say the <m>copper shards
that <pro>coppersmiths</pro> make</m>. This makes the vessel more
<sn>sonorous</sn> and it is not as breakable.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

This <m>tin</m> is called <m>common tin</m>.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p044r_a3">

<head>Arquebuse</head>

<ab>To keep it from backfiring, clean your arquebuse every eight days,
and rub it with <m>oil</m>, and when you draw out, wet some <m>linen</m>
in <m>oil</m> &amp; put it in instead of <m>paper</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p044r_a4">

<head><m>Lake</m></head>

<ab>To test it, soak it &amp; apply it to <m>paper</m>, &amp; if one or
two <ms><tmp>hours</tmp></ms> later it does not die there, it is fine
and good.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p044r_a5">

<head><m>Dyes from flowers</m></head>

<ab>The <m><pa>red poppy</pa></m>, which grows amongst <pa>grains</pa>,
makes a very beautiful columbine on <m>white leather</m>. The
<m><pa>cornflower</pa></m> makes a very beautiful blue. A <m>plant which
grows in hedges, which has a stem similar to <pa>flax</pa>, a long &amp;
broad leaf like small <pa>bugloss</pa>, which has a violet flower
verging on blue &amp; is shaped like the <pa>lily flower</pa></m>, makes
a very beautiful turquin, surpassing azure. Another flower, the
<m><pa>columbine</pa></m>, of the shape &amp; size of the
<m><pa>bugloss</pa> flower</m>, which has a petal like that of the
<m><pa>pansy</pa></m>, also makes a very beautiful turquin. It grows
amongst <pa>grains</pa>, in light soils.</ab>

</div>
</root>