<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="143r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f291.image">




<div id="p143r_1">



<head>Moulding <al>turtles</al> and <al>tortoises</al></head>

<ab>The <al>turtle</al> <sup>the one that lives in water</sup> is more
beautiful to mold because it has prettier scales and straight legs. And
the <al>tortoises</al> have crooked ones. They eat a lot. To get ready
to kill them, open their mouth and pass a long penknife through all the
intestines. And then make it swallow some <m>vinegar</m> mixed with
<m>spirits</m> or <m>urine</m>, as one does for snakes. It is necessary
to mould them in several pieces, and even the back sometimes because the
sides of certain ones are narrower than others and in this instance do
not release <sup>from the cast</sup>. To make them die, you must not
boil them, because they come apart, even the shell, in the hot
<m>water</m>. They <sup>the shells</sup> come out better <sup>when</sup>
hollowed because their great thickness spoils the mold. <al>Turtles</al>
are more lively. The <al>tortoises</al> are leaner, slower, and more
sleepy. If you scratch <al>turtles</al> on their shells, no matter how
sleepy they are, they move; <al>tortoises</al> do not.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">They <sup><al>turtles/tortoises</al></sup>
die rather quickly in <m>vinegar</m> mixed with a little <m>spirits</m>
or <m>urine</m>, as with all other animals.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">They <sup><al>turtles/tortoises</al></sup>
keep their eyes closed in the winter, and appear as dead, having been
numbed by the cold. They hide in the earth or under balls of grain or
warm manure, and survive only on the dampness of the <m>earth</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">You must not mold them too soon after
they die because they are still stiff. But on the day after, you will be
able to manipulate them and bend their legs as you wish.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p143r_2">



<head><pro>Moulders</pro> from <pl>Foix</pl></head>

<ab>Those who mould from across <sup>the way</sup> make their sand from
<m>crocum</m> ferri and <m>calcinated slate</m>, but <m>slate</m> always
retains its bumpiness and swells because it is a fatty. In the noyau, it
is not good; in sand, it can be put to use. They <sup>the moulders from
<pl>Foix</pl></sup> sieve their sand, grind it on <m>porphyry</m>, and
soak it in <m>water</m>, and they keep the finest bits which are on the
top, then they reheat it.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p143r_3" continued="yes">



<head><al>Toad</al></head>

<ab>Having been molded, you can take it out it without burning it,
because it releases <sup>easily</sup>from the mold. Choose the biggest
and the lumpiest <sup><al>toads</al></sup>. Because they contain a lot
of metal, it is best to mold them hollow, since they turn out better.
You could make your cast in one great piece, but it would be troublesome
to cut. It is best to do it in three or 4 parts, which will be thicker
close to the animal, and include the most amount of edge that is close
to the cast/mold. Make as well some casting conduits all the way from
the end <sup>of the cast</sup>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">

<figure id="fig_p143r_1" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5cnJFVXFaRURaY3c">





</figure>

Let the mold cool rather than opening it, even for thick things.</ab>



</div>
</root>