<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="132v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f270.item.r=">




<div continues="yes" id="p132r_2">





<ab>dry by itself. When your mold starts to redden, it will soon be
become completely red-hot. But make sure that its bottom is red-hot too,
without any black spot.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p132v_1">

<head> Common quarry <m>sand</m></head>

<ab>In a frame, If you cast it hot, <m>sand</m> will bubble; thus you
have to just dry it.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">

I have tried to prevent molds blended with <m>sand</m> from cracking
when annealed, and thus not get any with flaws that crack.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p132v_2">

<head><m>Crocum ferry</m></head>

<ab>After I processed it with <m>vinegar</m> and reddened under heat, I
had it ground very finely on the <m>porphyry</m>, until there could be
no ruggedness felt under the nails. Then I soaked it in very good
<m>vinegar</m> for 2 or 3 days, stirring the mixture several times a
day. Then I boiled it and made it red-hot in a pot, and put the whole
thing into an air furnace. I obtained a mass full of eyes, but that
crumbled finely between the fingers. I mixed half as much as <m>stone
alum</m> in the sand. I diluted the sand very thinly, and molded a very
small lizard, which molded very cleanly and finely. <m>Crocum ferry</m>
does not make the mold harder, but makes it firmer. When your mold is
soft and fat under your nail, it means that the <m>crocum</m> is good,
very fine and well prepared. You can add any quantity of <m>crocum</m>,
your mold will not be damaged because it is a friend of gold. I think it
would be the same with <m>silver</m>. And in order that molds made with
it do not crack, make it with needle filings.</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">

<m>Sand</m> is better made with <m>distilled vinegar</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">

You can add this <m>sand</m> to the molds you want to use to cast
<m>silver</m>, because it make molds firmer, and when you scratch it,
you will find it a bit rougher than the other molds not made from this
<m>sand</m>. You mold very clean with this <m>sand</m>.</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">

You can use this one for all molds, because it prevents them from
cracking and bursting when heated. This <m>sand</m> withstands several
casts for molding flat medals. Sand from <m>steel</m> or <m>needle
filings</m> is redder and better.</ab>

</div>
<div id="p132v_3">

<head>Gilding animals casted with <m>silver</m></head>

<ab>You can gild them with an amalgam, the lines won't be damaged if
they are made from <m>silver</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>