<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="097r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f199.image">




<div id="p097r_1">



<head><m>Black varnish</m></head>

<ab>It is said, at the beginning of the book where you can see it, that
it is made with <m>galipot</m>.

</ab>

</div>

<div id="p097r_2">



<head>Gilding</head>

<ab>One prepares the guards thoroughly with a soft, very <tl>soft
file</tl> such that there is nothing black left on any of the guards,
and next heat them, &amp; pass them as said. But to gild &amp; gild with
<m>silver</m>, they ought not to pass, except maybe a little towards
blue. Then while the guards are hot, one attaches them to a wood block
&amp; with some <tl>tweezers</tl> one layers the <m>gold</m> &amp; one
makes it sit with <m>bloodstone</m>,which is quite clean &amp; rubbed
with <m><fr>pottée</fr></m>. And when the guards are cold, one reheats
them, then one layers the <m>gold</m> as above. And first one gives
<del><fr>de</fr></del> two layers, until the entire guard is
well-adorned. And next one reheats as at the beginning, &amp; one gives
the third covering of <m>gold</m>. Then one burnishes very thoroughly
and with great force with a large <m>bloodstone</m>. <del>And</del> But
note that <add>to</add> burnish well, the guard always needs to be warm.
And to know this, <sn>one smells it &amp; brings it close to the
<bp>nose</bp></sn>. For one ought not to touch with the
<bp>fingers</bp>, but one <del>grasps</del> picks it up from on top of
the warm <m>ashes</m> with a small <tl><m>iron</m> rod</tl>, which has
been purposely made to go into the eye of the guard. And when it is
entirely well-polished, one rubs it very well with a <tl><m>white
linen</m></tl>, and the <m>gold</m> needs to be thicker &amp; stronger
than for <pro>painters</pro>. A <ms>quarter</ms> is worth fifty or LX
<cn>s<exp>ols</exp></cn>.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p097r_3">



<head>Gilding with <m>silver</m></head>

<ab>One needs to prepare the guards &amp; whiten them with a
<del><fr>lince </fr></del> <tl>file</tl>, a little coarser
<del>for</del> than for <m>gold</m>. And one makes them pass to grey, as
for gilding. And when they are warm, one needs to double the <m>leaf of
silver</m>, then divide it with a <tl>knife</tl>, next cover the guard
with it, with <del><fr>un petit</fr></del> <tl>tweezers</tl> &amp; a
small <tl>burnisher</tl>. And then reheat &amp; apply them, until they
are all gilded in <m>silver</m>. Next one needs to cover them for the
third time, with the <m>leaf</m> doubled as has been said, then burnish
them very strongly &amp; with good strength, not with the
<m>bloodstone</m>, but with a strong <tl>burnisher</tl>, just as the
<tl>burnisher</tl> ought not to burnish <m>gold</m>.</ab>

</div>
</root>