<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="169v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f344.image">




<div id="p169v_1">



<head>Molding very thin like<pro>bimbalotiers</pro> do</head>

<ab>They mould in <m>paper</m> or <m>cardboard</m>, because neither
sandy <m>earth</m> nor <m>metal</m> would mold so neatly and would not
receive. Or they engrave with <m>stone</m> from <pl>Istre</pl>, for the
main side, and the reverse is in <m>paper</m> or <m>cardboard</m>.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p169v_2" continued="yes">



<head>Reducing a round form into a hollow one</head>

<ab>You must firstly mold it with <m>plaster</m> as has been said
before, and in the <m>plaster</m> throw in some <m>wax</m> from which
will come a relief that you will repair very neatly, and will shape at
your pleasure. Then you will mold this <m>wax</m> relief once more in
<m>plaster</m>, or even better with your tempered sand,
<mark/>#, as if for a noyau. And in the latter throw in some
<m>lead</m> and from this you will have a very neat relief, and if it is
not, repair it on <m>cement</m> or a similar material, and beware that
it should always release well. And this one will always serve you as a
model for making as many hollow molds as you would like. In this way,
place half of your <m>lead</m> figure which you have <m>oiled</m>, and
moisten it with <m>spirits</m> as we have seen above, on your
<m>clay</m> base, then mold this half with a <m>white plaster</m>.
Having taken hold, and having smoothed and flattened the <m>plaster</m>,
take your <m>black wax</m> mixed with <m>sulphur</m> as we have seen
before, because it leaves nothing in the mold and melts quicker. Dip it
in hot <m>urine</m>, and once it is softened enough, make an imprint
with it on your half figure in <m>lead</m>. And you will have a very
neat hollow mold. Then adapt your <m>wax</m> hollow mold into a square
shape, as it pleases you, as long as you have sufficient thickness, and
make sure it is well even on all sides, and then mold this hollow
<m>wax</m>; and having it imprinted on one side, and having it flat and
even on the other, in the same way that you would mold a flat medal in
<m>wax</m> or <m>metal</m> in a noyau. And the noyau mold will give you,
whether in <m>silver</m> or any other metal you wish, a figure similar
to the <m>wax</m> one, which is to say, flat and even on one side, and
hollow on the other. And having cleaned this hollow, and having put it
in the <m>bleach</m>, if it is made of <m>silver</m>, you can put into
it some <m>sugar</m> work</ab>

<ab margin="left-top">Having made a hole in your <m>clay</m> base
and having placed there your half figure in <m>wax</m>, <m>oil</m> it a
bit so that it comes out more easily.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">Transparent <m>wax</m> is not good as
opposed to one that has body, for making good imprints.</ab>

<figure id="fig_p169v_3" margin="left-bottom" link="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5MGtBY2MyYTNKTUE">







</figure>

<ab margin="left-bottom">Because you have molded one of your
halves with <m>plaster</m> and <m>wax</m>, you can do the same thing to
the other half.</ab>



</div>
</root>