<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="096r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f197.image">




<div continues="yes" id="094r_1">





<ab>

round <tl>plane</tl>, also two-handed, and then with a small narrow
<tl>plane</tl>, it is gutted and scoured for half a foot towards the end
of the heel. And a shorter scouring is better so that the sword does not
always cut the scabbard.</ab>

<ab>

The opening of the scabbard is called the mouth and on top of it is the
shape of the knife.</ab>

<ab>

The stitch which is a <m>leather</m> rim set on the edge of the knife
shape is made to stop the sword frogs.</ab>

<ab>

When the small planks are well flattened, the sword is laid down on them
and with a <tl>black stone</tl> one marks the width and length of the
blade. Then with a <tl>chisel</tl> the excess is cut. And a
<tl>plane</tl> is used to even properly following the marks.</ab>

<ab>

Then the two small planks are stuck edge to edge <add>and all
around</add> only following the knife shape and not elsewhere. And this
is to make the scabbard <m>velvet leather</m> hold.</ab>

<ab>

Then the sword is put in the small planks and it is set in the scabbard
which is sewed. And they rub what is glued directly on the knife shape
with some <m>tallow</m> to run into the scabbard.</ab>

<ab>

The scabbard is made of <al>calf</al> or <al>sheep</al> <m>leather</m>,
the <al>calf</al> ones are in all one piece, but not the <al>sheep</al>
ones. When swords are long, they are made of several patches sewn
between <m>leather</m> and <m>flesh</m> and then they rub firmly the
stitching with a <m>boxwood</m> piece to cover and even it. From a good
<al>calf</al> <m>skin</m>, 8 or 9 or 10 scabbards can be made. A
<pro>workman</pro> can easily make 6 a day. If they are too thick, they
are lightly thinned out with a plane. If the <m>skin</m> is too hard, it
is lightly dipped in some lukewarm <m>water</m> but not for long. Next,
the same worker who worked <m>wood</m> piece has to adjust the scabbard
in order for it to be well done. It is true that for common people,
there are some good already all made, but they never fit perfectly. When
the scabbard is made and sewed with black <m>thread</m>, it is rubbed
with a <m>boxwood</m> piece or a slightly <m>oiled</m> cloth . The good
<al>cow</al> <m>leather</m> scabbard is the best of all and costs also
more than all except the <m>velvet</m> ones. Under the <m>velvet</m> one
usually put plain <m>canvas</m> or a <al>sheep</al> <m>skin</m> scabbard
or a <m>parchment</m> layer. But the best scabbard is a waxed scabbard
covered with either <m>velvet</m> or <al>calf</al> <m>skin</m>. One
covers the wood with thin canvas, which one then waxes, and covers in
<m>velour</m> or <al>calf</al> <m>skin</m>. A <m>waxed</m> scabbard is
worth at least 30 cents, a <al>cow</al> leather one, 20 cents. </ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">



From a <al>sheep</al> <m>skin</m>, v or vi.</ab>

</div>
</root>