<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="149v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f304.image">




<div id="p149v_1">



<head>Molding vases in several pieces</head>

<ab><pro>Goldsmiths</pro> who make large works and crockery use a
turning lathe to get the model they wish in wood. Then with some
<m>wax</m>, <sup><pro>the goldsmiths</pro></sup>model on top of this the
masks, festoons, or anything that they wish. Then they mould the model
in three, four, or several pieces.</ab>

</div>

<div id="p149v_2">



<head><m>Gold</m> solder</head>

<ab>They take on a <m>gold</m> penny a small pinch of refined
<m>aloc</m>, as you would find in old sous. </ab>

</div>

<div id="p149v_3">



<head>Molding <al>flies</al></head>

<ab>Large <al>flies</al> can be molded &amp; cast. But you must apply
underneath their wings some <m>wheat oil</m>, which dries quickly and
firms them up &amp; gives them a little thickness. The same thing can be
done with <al>butterflies</al>, <al>cicadas</al>, <al>grasshoppers</al>
&amp; similar things. But to cast them more easily, you must set them on
some leaf or bouquet. The others should be placed by hand on a very
slender <m>silver</m> blade. You cannot keep your insects when they are
dead, since they will dry out and their legs will break.</ab>

<ab margin="left-bottom">

<m>Wheat oil</m> should be put underneath delicate things to make them
more rigid &amp; firm, &amp; to make them hold their natural posture,
since being weak &amp; delicate, the tempered sand, adding weight to
them, would change their form.</ab></div>

<div id="p149v_4">



<head><al>Bats</al></head>

<ab>They have very thin wings and if they are large &amp; dry and the
wings are extended, you need a very big mold &amp; it is not certain
that the <m>metal</m> will run sufficiently; thus, when you want to mold
some, choose the medium-sized ones &amp; and arrange them so that they
have their wings are half folded, since in this way they will come out
better. But be sure to apply, as you known, some <m>wax</m> on the side
of the wings, so that the cast flows well.</ab>

</div>
</root>