<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="167v" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f340.image">




<div continues="yes" id="p167r_1" continued="yes">





<ab>

The ones weighing about 27 lb. are ix pousses long and the mouth is 6
<x>pousses</x> in diameter. At their bottom, they are 6 lignes thick,
and 3 for the mouth. The ones weighing 17 lb are 8 poulsses long and the
mouth is five <x>poulsses</x>. They are all covered together, all the
forks, rods, and tools which one uses, with a big canvas or big cloth so
that they do not make any noise. It is good that they sit loaded for a
while. After the <m>powder</m> has been put in, it is grinded very hard
and then tightly pressed <m>paper</m> is put in, then a cake of well
pressed <m>wax</m> and, on the <m>wax</m>, another slab of <m>cork</m>
that fits in very snugly and that you have to force in. In this way, the
<m>powder</m> remains well packed and gives much greater force, and if
you wish, you can put on the <m>cork</m> slab one of wood pierced in the
middle, if the mortar has a pierced bottom, which is believed to be the
easiest and which makes a greater hole because it cannot recoil. And for
these that have a pierced bottom, one must have a good gimlet to first
make the hole so that the rod, which is made by the point of the gimlet,
has before and without noise attached the mortar. And for these, one
must cover the button, which is quite sharply filed, with <m>waxed
canvas</m>, or add <m>wax</m> to it so that it completely plugs the hole
in the bottom. But because the doors are sometimes iron and the iron
rods cannot pierce it, an iron fork made like pincers and another iron
stick made with three claws, like you see painted, are use. And in this
way, the mortar stays in place well and is immediately steadied. The
iron rods must come out of the mortar from every point made by the
gimlet, namely by three or 4 finger lengths, which all enter in the
door. When the mortars are placed, the touch-hole is filled with good
<m>powder</m> and inserted in it is a <m>feather shaft</m> filled with
tightly pressed <m>powder</m> and moistened with <m>vinegar</m>, or if
needed, the powder is firmly pressed with the palms of the hands and,
having wet it with some <m>saliva</m>, you shape it like a cocoon
or</ab>



</div>
</root>