<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root page="021r" image="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f47.image">




<div id="p021r_1">



<head><pro>Gunner</pro></head>

<ab>As for small <wp>cannons</wp> which are not loaded with a <tl>ladle</tl>,
    one charges them with <m>powder</m> <ms>up to the escutcheon</ms>,<comment rid="c_018v_02"/> which
is placed on the <wp>piece</wp> with due proportion.</ab>

<ab>To point a <wp>cannon</wp>, that is to say to take its aim, one needs to take
the sight, that is to say aim, from the sides before the top, that is to
say above the <wp>cannon</wp>. For by aiming along the top, you will be better
able to find the line tending to your target, but you would not find out
if the <wp>cannon</wp> tends more to one side than the other. Therefore take your
sight on one side, then on the other &amp; adjust your <wp>piece</wp> to the
point at which you aim. Then take your sight from the top of the breech,
which will soon be done. Next, lower your <wp>piece</wp> a little at your
discretion if you are within true range, because the force of the
<m>powder</m> usually makes it rise. But if you were farther away than
your <wp>piece</wp> shoots at point blank, you would need to consider that the
weight of the ball would make it lower.</ab></div>

<div id="p021r_2" continued="yes">



<head>For firing a <wp>cannon</wp> at night</head>

<ab>Some keep their <wp>pieces</wp> loaded <del>and</del> from the day. Then, in
order that the <pro>gunner</pro> can fire into the breach where the
assailed are perhaps making repairs, the besiegers raise a false alarm
in order that the besieged throw torches &amp; artificial
fire into the moats or around the breach, at which the
<pro>gunner</pro> aims. Sometimes, by using the reflection of
<tl>mirrors</tl> or <tl>flasks</tl> full of <m>water</m>, the assailants
light up the breach. The method you know, with a <tl>quadrant</tl> &amp;
<tl><m>plumb</m> line</tl>, is very good. Others nail two or three rows
of boards with <m>strong iron pegs</m> on the <m>wooden</m> platform
made for mounting the <wp>cannon</wp>, and leave empty notches into which the
wheels of the <wp>cannon</wp> can just fit. And by such means you will always
<del><fr>te</fr></del> place it at a similar <del><fr>q</fr></del>
point, that it will not incline more to the right than to the left. And
in order that it be neither too high nor too low, when you fire during
the day, you place a <tl>ruler</tl> fixed well in the ground, which
comes just to touch the the bottom of the edge of the <wp>cannon</wp> after it
has been pointed &amp; adjusted for firing.</ab>

<ab margin="left-middle">If the
platform<comment rid="c_021r_01"/>, the wheels, or the
wedges<comment rid="c_021r_01"/> break or are disturbed, this
invention is of no profit.</ab>



</div>
</root>